{ 
"horse-bowl": [
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"506 easy CAHA8/HIH230-2 ","question":"How many ribs does a Percheron have? ","answer":"36 or 18 pairs 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"508 easy HIH505-1/DET293","question":"What part of the foot is between the wall and the frog? ","answer":"Sole	 (also accept white line, bars, and commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves)
(Addtl info - White line is junction of the sole & wall ï¿½ where the sensitive & insensitive laminae meet)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"509 easy HIH525-1 ","question":"What is the name for the soft, spongy part of the horse's foot? ","answer":"Frog  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"510 easy HIH505-1 ","question":"What is the term for the outside part of the hoof? ","answer":"Wall  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"511 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"The elbow, knee, and fetlock are all joints on which leg? ","answer":"Front  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"512 easy HIH202-3 ","question":"The stifle, hock, and fetlock are all joints on which leg? ","answer":"Rear  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"513 easy TH693/HIH505-1 ","question":"What part of the foot separates the wall and the sole? ","answer":"White line    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"514 easy HIH220-6 ","question":"What joint is located between the fetlock and the stifle? ","answer":"Hock 	(tarsus)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"515 easy CAHA24/HIH505-1 ","question":"Where is the white line located? ","answer":"Between the wall and the sole  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"516 easy CAHA4/HH39 ","question":"What is the proper name for the lock of hair falling forward over the horse's face? ","answer":"Forelock  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"517 easy TH81/HH7/HIH465-1 ","question":"What is the usual color of the horse's eye? ","answer":"Brown  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"518 easy CAHA1/HIH220-3 ","question":"What part of the horse lies between the knee and the fetlock? ","answer":"Cannon  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"519 easy CAHA1/H2-35/DET262 ","question":"What is the term for the base of a horse's tail? ","answer":"Dock or tail head      (accept either) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"520 easy CAHA4/HH9 ","question":"What is the term for the horny growth found at the back of the fetlock? ","answer":"Ergot  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"521 easy TH12/BEG119-1L ","question":"Which structures carry blood away from the heart? ","answer":"Arteries  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"522 easy CAHA1/HH8 ","question":"What part of the horse is located directly above the stifle? ","answer":"Thigh  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"523 easy TH142/HH8 ","question":"What is the part of the horse located between the rump and the quarter? ","answer":"Buttocks  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"524 easy HIH230-6 ","question":"2 part question:  How many pasterns does a horse have and what is the best angle? ","answer":"4 pasterns; 45 - 50 degrees "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"525 easy HH37 ","question":"What part of the horse is located between the coronet and the ground?  ","answer":"The hoof   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"526 easy TH98/HS9 ","question":"The muscles that control leg movement end where? ","answer":"At the knees and hocks"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"527 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is located between the elbow and the knee? ","answer":"The forearm  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"528 easy HIH220-6 ","question":"What is the term for the area between the last rib and the croup? ","answer":"Loin or coupling (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"529 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is another name for the fetlock joint? ","answer":"Ankle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"530 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"On the front leg of a horse, which should be longer - the forearm or the cannon? ","answer":"The forearm  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"531 easy TH154/HH8 ","question":"Give 2 names for the area of the horse between the loin and the buttock ","answer":"Croup and rump"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"532 easy TH49/HH49 ","question":"What part of the foot is located between the plantar cushion and the insensitive frog? ","answer":"Sensitive frog  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"533 easy TH98/HS9, H2-27 ","question":"Why is it difficult for cuts and bruises to heal below the knees or hocks? ","answer":"There are no muscles below the knees and hocks; therefore the blood supply is limited"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"534 easy HIH830-1 ","question":"What is the main purpose of the red blood cells? ","answer":"To transport oxygen to the tissues and organs"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"535 easy HIH830-1 ","question":"What is the easiest way to determine if the cardiovascular system is working? ","answer":"Heart rate or pulse  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"536 easy HIH840-1 ","question":"When a horse's muscle shortens, is the muscle contracting or relaxing? ","answer":"Contracting  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"537 easy HIH840-1 ","question":"When a horse's muscle lengthens, is the muscle contracting or relaxing? ","answer":"Relaxing   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"538 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"The gaskin is located between which 2 joints of the horse's hind leg? ","answer":"Stifle and hock  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"539 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is the name of the muscular part of the hind leg above the hock? ","answer":"Gaskin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"540 easy HIH1100-8/HH12/TH150,179 ","question":"The set of the feet and legs affects what? ","answer":"The action       (how the horse moves) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"541 easy TH150,179/HIH220-3 ","question":"What do you call the curved covering of horn over the foot? ","answer":"Hoof  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"542 easy HIH220-3/TH696 ","question":"What is the purpose of the deep flexor tendon? ","answer":"Flexes (or bends) the hoof and leg"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"543 easy TH696/HIH220-3 ","question":"What is the purpose of the extensor tendon? ","answer":"Extends (or straightens) the hoof and leg  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"544 easy HIH220-6 ","question":"What is the ideal slope of the shoulder? ","answer":"45 - 50 degrees 	(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"545 easy HIH220-6 ","question":"What is another name for the loin? ","answer":"Coupling  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"546 easy TH80/HH8 ","question":"What is another name for the chestnuts on a horse's leg? ","answer":"Night eyes  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"547 easy TH151/HIH220-3 ","question":"What is the name for the part of the horse located at the junction of the neck and the back? ","answer":"Withers                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"548 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What do you call the measurement around the horse's body just back of the withers? ","answer":"Girth or heart girth 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"549 easy FCH120/HIH230-2/HH8/CAHA1 ","question":"What part of the horse lies between the withers and the point of the shoulder? ","answer":"Shoulder 	(also accept thorax or scapula)   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"550 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"Where is the gaskin located? ","answer":"Below the stifle OR above the hock OR between the hock and the stifle"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"552 easy CAHA68/H3-6 ","question":"Where is urine stored in the horse? ","answer":"Bladder  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"553 easy HIH505-5 ","question":"What bone is located between the cannon bone and the short pastern? ","answer":"Long pastern    	(also accept 1st or proximal phalanx) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"554 easy TH126/HS4 ","question":"What is the purpose of the 3rd eyelid? ","answer":"Prevents foreign bodies from getting into the eye OR cleans or removes foreign bodies from eye
(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"555 easy TH121/HIH1220-2 ","question":"Who has better hearing, you or your horse? ","answer":"Your horse  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"556 easy HIH505-5 ","question":"What bone is located at the lowest point in the hoof? ","answer":"Coffin bone 		(also accept pedal bone, distal phalanx, or 3rd phalanx)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"557 easy CAHA1/HH8 ","question":"The forearm of the horse lies between what 2 parts? ","answer":"Arm and knee OR elbow and knee"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"558 easy CAHA58/HIH830-1 ","question":"How many chambers are in a horse's heart? ","answer":"4 (four)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"559 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is the name of the joint above the pastern? ","answer":"Fetlock or ankle 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"560 easy CAHA6/H2-7 ","question":"What is the name of the structure that protects the vital organs? ","answer":"Skeleton  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"561 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is the cannon? ","answer":"Lower leg (bone) between the knee or hock and the fetlock or ankle"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"562 easy HIH220-6 ","question":"Sharp, prominent, and well defined describes what part of the horse? ","answer":"Withers  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"563 easy HIH505-5 ","question":"Name 2 of the bones in the fetlock joint.","answer":"Cannon, long pastern, proximal sesamoids"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"564 easy HH9/TH142/CAHA1 ","question":"What do you call the upper curved part of the neck? ","answer":"Crest  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"565 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"Where is the croup? ","answer":"Just in front of the tail OR between the loin and the tail or dock "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"566 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"The top of a horse's head just back of the ears is called what? ","answer":"Poll  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"567 easy HS4/TH126/HIH465-1 ","question":"A third eyelid or membrane in front of the eye which removes foreign bodies from the eye is called what? ","answer":"Haw or nictitating membrane	 (accept either)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"568 easy HH9 ","question":"What is an ergot? ","answer":"A horny growth behind the fetlock joint  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"569 easy HH8/CAHA4/TH128 ","question":"The horny growths on the insides of a horseï¿½s legs are called what? ","answer":"Chestnuts or night eyes 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"570 easy HIH505-6/CAHA24 ","question":"What is the varnish-like layer of the hoof called? ","answer":"Periople  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"571 easy HIH220-3   DET205","question":"Where is the pastern found? ","answer":"Between the coronet band and the fetlock "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"572 easy HIH220-3/DET69 ","question":"Where is the coronet band located? ","answer":"Hairline above the hoof OR a band around the top of the hoof from which the hoof wall grows"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"573 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is the band directly above the hoof called? ","answer":"Coronet, coronet band, or coronary band 	(accept any)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"574 easy HH9/TH142/CAHA1 ","question":"Where is the crest? ","answer":"Part of the neck under the mane OR the top line of the neck OR the curved upper part of the neck 
(accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"575 easy HS4/TH126 ","question":"In connection with the eye, what does the term "haw" mean? ","answer":"Third eyelid or nictitating membrane 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"576 easy HIH220-6    ","question":"What part of the top line has no bone structure for support other than the lumbar vertebrae? ","answer":"Loin or coupling 	(accept either)    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"577 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is another term for the trunk area of the horse? ","answer":"Barrel  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"578 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What do you call the area at the end of the head, which includes the lips and the nostrils? ","answer":"Muzzle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"579 easy HIH830-1 ","question":"What is the largest muscular organ of the cardiovascular system? ","answer":"Heart  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"580 easy HIH830-2 ","question":"What could cause the heart rate to increase? ","answer":"Increased activity/exercise, anxiety/stress, illness, fever 	(accept any)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"581 easy HIH840-1 ","question":"What is the largest tissue mass in a horse's body? ","answer":"Muscles  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"582 easy HIH100-3 ","question":"Define the exact area of your horse's heart girth. ","answer":"Belly area directly behind the front legs OR measurement around the body just back of the withers "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"583 easy HH8 ","question":"Where is the horse known for being ticklish? ","answer":"Flank  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"584 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"Where is the throatlatch on a horse located? ","answer":"Where the jawbone and neck connect OR space between the jawbone and neck"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"585 easy HIH220-3,6 ","question":"What is located between the back and the croup? ","answer":"Loin or coupling	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"586 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What joint is located between the hock and the hip? ","answer":"Stifle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"587 easy HIH220-3/HH8 ","question":"Name the part of the horse's topline just in front of the tail. ","answer":"Croup or rump 	(accept either)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"588 easy HIH505-5 ","question":"Where is the coffin bone? ","answer":"In the foot OR lowest bone in the foot "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"589 easy HH8/CAHA4/TH128 ","question":"What are chestnuts? ","answer":"Horny growths on the inside of a horse's legs
(additional info - above the knees and at the lower part of the hocks)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"590 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What is located between the forehead and the muzzle? ","answer":"Face  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"591 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What joint is located between the shoulder and the knee? ","answer":"Elbow  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"592 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"What joint is located between the elbow and the fetlock? ","answer":"Knee  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"593 easy HIH220-3 ","question":"The part of the horse between the withers and the loin is called what? ","answer":"Back  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"594 easy HIH220-6/TH152  ","question":"What is the main role of the hindquarters? ","answer":"Propulsion  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"595 easy HH39/TH129 ","question":"What is the purpose of the long ï¿½feelerï¿½ hairs around the muzzle? ","answer":"Help the horse make contact with its surroundings especially in the dark"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"596 easy HH4,8/TH80 ","question":"What is a common name for a horny growth on the inside of the legs sometimes referred to as night eyes?  It's also a term used to describe a coat color ","answer":"Chestnut  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"597 easy HIH220-6 ","question":"What part of the horse is important in keeping the saddle in place? ","answer":"Withers  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"598 easy HIH465-1 ","question":"The cornea, sclera, choroid, iris, and retina are all parts of what? ","answer":"The eye  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"599 easy BEG119 ","question":"To which side of the heart does blood return from the body? ","answer":"Right  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"600 easy H1-34 ","question":"Cowlicks commonly occur on what part of the horse? ","answer":"Head, neck, throatlatch, or flank 	(accept any)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"601 easy ADV321-2 ","question":"The sole of the hoof is flatter on which pair of feet, the front or the rear? ","answer":"Front  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"602 easy ADV325-2 ","question":"Which system in the horse consists of the blood, blood vessels, and heart? ","answer":"Cardiovascular or circulatory  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"603 easy HIH810 ","question":"The term "respiration rate" refers to what? ","answer":"Number of breaths taken per minute  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"604 easy HH48 picture/TH695 ","question":"The wall of a horse's hoof will be thickest in which area? ","answer":"Toe  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"605 easy HIH505-7 ","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the greatest amount of moisture? ","answer":"Frog  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"606 easy HH8 ","question":"Night eyes are another name for what structures on the horse?   ","answer":"Chestnuts  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"607 easy HIH465-1 ","question":"What is the term for the opening in the iris of a horse's eye? ","answer":"Pupil  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"608 easy HIH230-2 ","question":"Where are the cervical vertebrae located? ","answer":"Neck  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"609 easy HIH230-2/TH96 ","question":"How many cervical vertebrae does a horse have? ","answer":"7   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"610 easy HIH465-2/CAHA4-5 ","question":"The horse's eye is lubricated by what fluid? ","answer":"Tears or lacrimal fluid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"611 easy HIH465-1 ","question":"What structure is the first protection for the horse's eye? ","answer":"Eyelid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"612 easy HIH505-7 ","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the least amount of moisture? ","answer":"The wall  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"613 easy HIH810-1 ","question":"When breathing, what is the main gas that's exhaled? ","answer":"Carbon dioxide  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"614 easy HIH230-2 H2-35 ","question":"What is another name for the horse's shoulder blade? ","answer":"Scapula  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"615 easy HIH230-2/H2-35 ","question":"What is another name for the scapula? ","answer":"Shoulder blade    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"616 easy CAHA41/H2-6 ","question":"What is the correct term for the lower jawbone? ","answer":"Mandible  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"617 easy CAHA41/H2-6 ","question":"What is the mandible? ","answer":"Lower jawbone  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"618 easy HIH230-1 ","question":"The durability of a horse to do work depends on what? ","answer":"On his action or his feet and legs	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"619 easy CAHA4 ","question":"What are tactile hairs? ","answer":"The coarse, ï¿½feelerï¿½ hairs around the muzzle and eyes 	(also accept whiskers)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"620 easy TH98 ","question":"Do the front legs or hind legs have the most joints? ","answer":"Hind		 (additional info:  hind legs have 7 joints and front legs have 6 joints)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"621 easy CAHA8 ","question":"How many bones are in the sternum? ","answer":"1 (one) 	(additional info:  manubrium and xyphoid are cartilaginous attachments)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"622 easy TH145 ","question":"The spring-like action which absorbs concussion during movement is called what? ","answer":"Shock absorption  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"623 easy TH104 ","question":"Why is it important for a horse to have large nostrils? ","answer":"To allow for maximum air intake 	(also accept:  so it can breathe better))"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"624 easy TH129 ","question":"Name 2 areas of hair on the horse that do not shed. ","answer":"Mane, tail, eyelashes, tactile hairs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"625 easy TH90/CAHA8 ","question":"How many bones are in the horse's body? ","answer":"205                                "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"626 easy TH82 ","question":"What color are a horse's hooves at birth? ","answer":"Usually white  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"627 easy TH96/HS8 ","question":"What is the most flexible portion of the spine? ","answer":"Cervical 	(neck area) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"628 easy TH99 ","question":"Are skeletal muscles voluntary or involuntary? ","answer":"Voluntary  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"629 easy TH129 ","question":"Where on the horse are there no sweat glands? ","answer":"Legs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"630 easy HIH655","question":"Together the withers, back, loin & croup create what?","answer":"Topline               "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"631 easy TH91/HIH230-2 ","question":"What is the largest bone in the horse's head? ","answer":"Mandible	 (lower jaw)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"632 easy HIH525-1 ","question":"What part of a horse's foot provides traction and absorbs shock? ","answer":"Frog    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"633 easy TH683/HS6 ","question":"How are the front legs attached to the main skeleton? ","answer":"By muscles	 (also accept by tendons and ligaments)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"easy","number":"634 easy CAHA8/HIH230-2 ","question":"How many PAIRS of ribs does a horse have? ","answer":"18  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"635 medium CAHA6,1 ","question":"What is the main bone between the stifle and the hock? ","answer":"Tibia  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"636 medium TH90 ","question":"In the skull, what is protected by the orbital cavity? ","answer":"Eyes  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"637 medium CAHA57 ","question":"What is the name of the primary vessel that carries blood from the heart to the rest of the body? ","answer":"Aorta  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"638 medium TH126 ","question":"How does a hormone get to a distant part of the body? ","answer":"Through the bloodstream 	(circulatory system) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"639 medium BEG106-3 ","question":"What is the name of the bone that's shaped like a miniature hood? ","answer":"Coffin bone 		(also accept pedal bone, 3rd phalanx, or distal phalanx) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"640 medium CAHA58 ","question":"Name one of the functions of the heart that make the sounds you can hear with a stethoscope?  ","answer":"Rush of blood; closing of heart valves	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"641 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"In what units is respiration measured? ","answer":"Breaths per minute (BPM)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"642 medium TH141 ","question":"A horse uses what 2 parts of its body to aid in stability and balance? ","answer":"Head and neck"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"643 medium CAHA10 ","question":"The radius and ulna comprise what structure of the horse? ","answer":"Forearm  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"644 medium ADV323 ","question":"What is measured from the chest floor to the top of the withers? ","answer":"Depth of heart    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"645 medium CAHA41 ","question":"What is the orbital cavity? ","answer":"Bony socket that surrounds and protects the eye"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"646 medium TH117 ","question":"Where is a large supply of the horse's red blood cells stored? ","answer":"Spleen  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"647 medium FCH188 ","question":"2 part question:  For a horse, what is the first line of defense against the cold and what is the second line of defense? ","answer":"Firstï¿½hair coat; secondï¿½fat      (provides insulation)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"648 medium CAHA63 ","question":"Where does formation of red blood cells occur? ","answer":"Bone marrow  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"649 medium CAHA45 ","question":"What part of the eyeball allows light to pass through to the lens? ","answer":"Cornea      (also accept pupil)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"650 medium TH98 ","question":"What controls cannon, pastern, and foot actions? ","answer":"Ligaments and tendons  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"651 medium TH322 ","question":"In reference to a mareï¿½s udder, how many teats does a mare have? ","answer":"2 (two)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"652 medium ES160 ","question":"In regards to anatomy, why is it best to listen to the heartbeat from the left side of the horse's body? ","answer":"Heart is closer to left side"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"653 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"Why can't a horse breathe through its mouth? ","answer":"Blocking action of the soft palate  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"654 medium ES60 ","question":"Research indicates that horses do see in color.  However, they may have more difficulty seeing which color? ","answer":"Red  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"655 medium TH90 ","question":"Muscles are attached to bones by what? ","answer":"Tendons  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"656 medium HIH1100-8 ","question":"What is another name given to the chin area of your horse? ","answer":"Curb groove or chin groove 		(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"657 medium CAHA77/HIH910-5 ","question":"Where is the hypothalamus located? ","answer":"Base of the brain  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"658 medium HIH220-6 ","question":"Name the 4 parts of the topline. ","answer":"Withers, back, loin or coupling, croup or rump  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"659 medium TH89 ","question":"What is the name of the science that studies the structure of the animal and the relationship of its parts? ","answer":"Anatomy  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"660 medium DET67/TH126 ","question":"What is the common name for the membrane of the eye that helps remove foreign materials from the eye?  It's also called the third eyelid or nictitating membrane? ","answer":"Haw   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"661 medium HIH425-1,535-2 ","question":"Two grooves separate the sole from the frog.  These are called what? ","answer":"Collateral grooves, commissures, or sulci	 (accept any)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"662 medium CAHA23 ","question":"The blood supply to the foot is furnished by what 2 digital arteries? ","answer":"Medial and lateral"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"663 medium CAHA4 ","question":"Being specific, where are chestnuts located on a horse? ","answer":"Front legs - inside surface above the knees;
hind legs - inside surface at the bottom of the hocks"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"664 medium TH691 ","question":"What is the largest joint in the horse? ","answer":"Stifle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"665 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"What is another name for the trachea?   ","answer":"Windpipe  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"666 medium TH117    ","question":"Name the 2 major components of blood. ","answer":"Plasma and cells  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"667 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"What is the medical name for the windpipe? ","answer":"Trachea  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"668 medium CAHA77 ","question":"Where is the pituitary gland located? ","answer":"Base of the brain  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"669 medium DET55 ","question":"What is the chin groove? ","answer":"Small indentation between the chin and the jaw"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"670 medium CAHA4 ","question":"Name 2 locations on the horse where you would find tactile hairs. ","answer":"Around the eyes, nostrils, lips, muzzle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"671 medium DET72 ","question":"What part of the horseï¿½s body does the term ï¿½cranialï¿½ refer to?  ","answer":"The skull or head OR the end of the body towards the head   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"672 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"If the horse increases its movement, does the minute volume go up or down? ","answer":"Up (additional info:  minute volume is the tidal volume times the respiratory rate)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"673 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"What is another name for the respiration rate? ","answer":"Respiratory frequency  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"674 medium HIH505-5 ","question":"What arteries provide blood to the sensitive structures of the foot? ","answer":"Digital arteries       (medial and lateral digital arteries)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"675 medium HIH810-1 ","question":"What is the term for the amount of air inspired in one minute? ","answer":"Minute volume  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"676 medium TH688 ","question":"What part of the horse has a distinctive pattern that can be used to positively identify a particular horse? ","answer":"Chestnuts  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"677 medium TH89 ","question":"The sciences that study the relationship of form to function are called what? ","answer":"Anatomy and physiology"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"678 medium TH90 ","question":"What is the difference between ligaments and tendons? ","answer":"Ligaments attach bones to bones; tendons attach muscle to bone  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"679 medium CAHA12/DET188 ","question":"What is another name for the distal sesamoid bone? ","answer":"Navicular bone   (also accept shuttle bone)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"680 medium TH96 ","question":"What term refers to the upper surface of the vertebrae? ","answer":"Spinous process   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"681 medium HIH505-4 ","question":"What is the PRIMARY purpose of the digital cushion? ","answer":"Shock absorption	 (additional info:  also assists in blood circulation)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"682 medium HIH505-4 ","question":"What is the shape of the digital cushion? ","answer":"Wedge shaped  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"683 medium TH154 ","question":"What is the hardest working joint in the horse's legs? ","answer":"Hock  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"684 medium HIH505-5 ","question":"Where are the lateral cartilages located? ","answer":"On the sides or wings of the coffin bone  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"685 medium TH98 ","question":"Which bone in the horse is similar to the human kneecap? ","answer":"Patella of the stifle joint"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"686 medium ADV323 ","question":"What is depth of heart? ","answer":"Measurement from the top of the withers to the chest floor"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"688 medium TH97 ","question":"What is the main bone of the forearm called? ","answer":"Radius  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"689 medium TH97 ","question":"What is the heaviest and strongest bone in the horse's body? ","answer":"Femur  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"690 medium TH98 ","question":"Why do injuries to ligaments heal slowly? ","answer":"They have a limited blood supply  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"691 medium CAHA7 ","question":"What is the name of the first cervical vertebrae? ","answer":"Atlas  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"692 medium TH104 ","question":"What is the primary purpose of the respiratory system? ","answer":"Oxygenate blood   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"693 medium TH708 ","question":"Why can a horse rest standing up? ","answer":"Legs have a locking mechanism 	(stay apparatus)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"694 medium CAHA27 ","question":"The digital cushion fills the area between the frog and what tendon? ","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon	 (also accept deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"695 medium CAHA61 ","question":"What artery is the main blood supply to the head? ","answer":"Carotid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"696 medium TH322 ","question":"What is another name for the mare's mammary gland? ","answer":"Udder  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"697 medium CAHA8 ","question":"Where on the horse would you find the sternum? ","answer":"Chest	 (front part of the chest attached to the ribs)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"698 medium CAHA2 ","question":"2 part question:  What directional term refers to a structure thatï¿½s located closer to the head and what term refers to a structure thatï¿½s closer to the tail? ","answer":"Cranial is closer to the head; caudal is closer to the tail "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"699 medium CAHA4/TH126 ","question":"What system produces chemical substances called hormones? ","answer":"Endocrine system  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"700 medium DET211 ","question":"What is physiology? ","answer":"Study of the function of the body systems"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"701 medium CAHA5 ","question":"What type of nerve brings sensations of pressure, pain, heat, and cold from the nerve endings? ","answer":"Sensory  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"702 medium INT229-1-3 ","question":"Where is the horse's counterpart to the human knee?   ","answer":"Stifle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"703 medium CAHA21 ","question":"The stay apparatus is a mechanism that enables the horse to do what? ","answer":"Sleep standing up	 (addtl info:  it locks the legs, prevents overextension, and reduces concussion)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"704 medium CAHA6 ","question":"What 2 areas of the horse each contain 40 bones? ","answer":"Front and hind legs"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"705 medium CAHA7 ","question":"Where in the spinal column would one find the coccygeal vertebrae?","answer":"Tail  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"706 medium TH90 ","question":"What is the proper name for the bony socket that surrounds and protects the eye? ","answer":"Orbital cavity  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"707 medium HIH320-4","question":"What is the diameter of an average adult light horseï¿½s foot?				","answer":"4-6ï¿½     (accept any answer in range)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"708 medium CAHA57 ","question":"Which artery carries oxygen poor blood from the heart to the lungs? ","answer":"Pulmonary artery"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"709 medium CAHA23 ","question":"The medial and lateral digital arteries furnish blood to what part of the horse? ","answer":"Foot  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"710 medium CAHA4 ","question":"The coarse ï¿½feelerï¿½ hairs that protrude from around the nostrils, lips, and eyelids are called what? ","answer":"Tactile hairs    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"711 medium TH111 ","question":"You do the mathï¿½ Your horseï¿½s resting heart rate is 32 beats per minute.  The stroke volume or amount of blood pumped during each heart contraction is approximately 1 liter.   What is the cardiac output for this horse? ","answer":"32 liters per minute 
(additional info:  cardiac output equals stroke volume times heart rate)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"712 medium ADV325-2 ","question":"What is cardiac output? ","answer":"How much blood the heart can pump in one minute 
(additional info:  cardiac output equals stroke volume times heart rate)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"713 medium TH594 ","question":"What artery is located under the jaw bone at the last cheek tooth and can be used to take a pulse? ","answer":"Facial artery  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"714 medium CAHA57 ","question":"Which are the smallest blood vessels? ","answer":"Capillaries  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"715 medium HIH895-1 ","question":"What is the definition of respiratory frequency? ","answer":"Number of breaths taken per minute"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"716 medium TH695 ","question":"What term describes the point of the frog towards the toe? ","answer":"Apex  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"717 medium DET104 ","question":"What is the general term for the last 10 pairs of ribs, those not connected to the sternum? ","answer":"False ribs or floating ribs 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"718 medium TH89 ","question":"What system in the horse's body includes the brain, spinal cord, and associated nerves and special sensors? ","answer":"Nervous system    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"719 medium TH96 ","question":"What joint is commonly referred to as the "yes-no" joint? ","answer":"Atlas-axis joint OR joint between the 1st and 2nd cervical vertebrae OR atlantoaxial joint     (accept any)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"720 medium ES21 ","question":"2 part question:  How many chestnuts do asses and donkeys have and where are they located? ","answer":"2 (two);          on the insides of the front legs only"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"721 medium FCH199 ","question":"During exercise, body heat is primarily produced by what system? ","answer":"Muscular system"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"722 medium HIH705-1 ","question":"What is an obligate nasal breather? ","answer":"Animal that breathes only through the nose      (can't breathe through the mouth)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"723 medium CAHA8 ","question":"Which pairs of ribs are fastened to the sternum by cartilage and are called ï¿½true ribsï¿½? ","answer":"First 8 pairs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"724 medium DET778 ","question":"Name the tendon connecting the deep muscles of the back of the leg to the coffin bone. ","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon           (also accept deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"725 medium TH90 ","question":"Name the 2 components of the skeletal system. ","answer":"Bones and ligaments"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"726 medium HIH830-1 ","question":"Which blood cells aid in clotting?   ","answer":"Platelets     (thrombocytes)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"727 medium BEG106-1 ","question":"Describe the difference between sensitive and insensitive structures of the hoof. ","answer":"Sensitive structures contain blood vessels and nerves;
Insensitive structures have no blood vessels or nerves"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"728 medium CAHA7/TH90 ","question":"What body SYSTEM do irregular bones protect? ","answer":"Nervous system      (spinal cord of the nervous system)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"729 medium TH9 ","question":"In the horse's body, what connects bones to bones? ","answer":"Ligaments  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"730 medium DET214 ","question":"What is the name of the clear, yellowish, fluid portion of the blood in which various blood cells are suspended? ","answer":"Plasma  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"731 medium TH90 ","question":"What is the purpose of synovial fluid? ","answer":"To lubricate joints  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"732 medium CAHA5/DET97 ","question":"What is the purpose of the epiglottis?","answer":"Prevents food from entering the larynx or trachea when swallowing"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"733 medium DET80 ","question":"What is the name of the muscle that separates the abdominal and the thoracic cavities? ","answer":"Diaphragm  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"734 medium TH119 ","question":"What organ provides a blood filtering system that is responsible for the excretion of many waste products from the body? ","answer":"Kidney  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"735 medium DET242 ","question":"Where are the proximal sesamoid bones located? ","answer":"At the rear of the fetlock joint            (additional info:  distal sesamoid or navicular is in the hoof)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"736 medium TH696 ","question":"Name the fibro-elastic, fatty cushion in the foot that acts as a shock absorber. ","answer":"Digital cushion  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"737 medium TH80 ","question":"What do a horse's chestnuts and a human's fingerprints have in common? ","answer":"Both have unique patterns that can be used to identify individuals"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"738 medium CAHA8 ","question":"The head of each rib of a horse is attached to what structure? ","answer":"Vertebrae       (thoracic vertebrae)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"739 medium TH127 ","question":"What gland controls the metabolic rate? ","answer":"Thyroid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"740 medium TH706 ","question":"Where is the femoral artery? ","answer":"Hind leg  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"741 medium HIH810 ","question":"What is the name of the tiny air sacs in the lungs where oxygen and carbon dioxide are exchanged? ","answer":"Alveoli           (al-VEE-oh-lie)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"742 medium DET144 ","question":"Name the bone that extends from the shoulder to the elbow. ","answer":"Humerus   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"743 medium DET158 ","question":"What is the name of the place of union or junction between two or more bones of the skeleton? ","answer":"Joint  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"744 medium CAHA57 ","question":"Which chamber of the heart is the primary pumping chamber for moving oxygenated blood to the body? ","answer":"Left ventricle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"745 medium DET70  ","question":"The coupling is the pivot point of the horse's back and is supported by which section of the horse's vertebrae? ","answer":"Lumbar  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"746 medium DET167 ","question":"The lens focuses light rays to form an image on what structure?   ","answer":"Retina  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"747 medium TH127 ","question":"What is the major function of the thyroid gland? ","answer":"Controls metabolic rate   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"748 medium DET258 ","question":"Define the term "stroke volume". ","answer":"Amount of blood the heart pumps with each beat"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"749 medium DET92 ","question":"Which body system has glands that produce hormones to regulate growth, reproduction, metabolism, and digestion? ","answer":"Endocrine"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"750 medium TH120 ","question":"What part of the brain controls respiration and blood pressure? ","answer":"Brainstem  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"751 medium CAHA43 ","question":"What is the external part of the ear called? ","answer":"Auricle    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"752 medium TH123/DET69 ","question":"What is the first structure that light entering the horse's eye would pass through? ","answer":"Cornea   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"753 medium TH82 ","question":"In a wall eyed horse, which specific structure of the eye is light blue or hazel in color? ","answer":"Iris  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"754 medium DET47 ","question":"2 part question:  Which are the smallest blood vessels and what do they connect? ","answer":"Capillaries;      connect arteries with veins  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"755 medium CAHA21, 36 ","question":"2 part question:  What is the stay mechanism and what is its purpose? ","answer":"Joints of the legs are locked in position by muscles and ligaments;       it allows the horse to sleep standing up (additional reference TH708)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"756 medium TH114 ","question":"Which muscle has the largest increase in blood flow during exercise? ","answer":"Diaphragm  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"757 medium DET42/CAHA24","question":"The soft, fleshy part of a horse's heel is called what? ","answer":"Bulb  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"758 medium CAHA28/DET156 ","question":"The ilium and ischium are 2 of the bones that make up what structure of the horse? ","answer":"Pelvis  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"759 medium DET75 ","question":"What is the name of the area on the horse's head where the curb chain should rest? ","answer":"Curb groove or chin groove		 (accept either)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"760 medium HIH830-1 ","question":"In what part of the vascular system does the majority of exchange of substances in and out of the blood occur? ","answer":"Capillaries  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"761 medium TH90 ","question":"What is the primary function of the short bones? ","answer":"Absorb concussion         (shock absorbers)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"762 medium CAHA68 ","question":"In the horse's renal system, what structure connects the kidney to the bladder? ","answer":"Ureter  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"763 medium FCH395H2-35 ","question":"What is the name of the upper jaw bone? ","answer":"Maxilla  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"764 medium DET110 ","question":"When fluorescein dye is applied to the surface of the eye, it will indicate any damaged areas of what structure of the eye? ","answer":"Cornea  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"765 medium TH689 ","question":"What is the least moveable joint in the horse's leg? ","answer":"Pastern  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"766 medium CAHA19 ","question":"The forces exerted by muscles in the foreleg are transmitted by tendons.  Generally muscles are not found below what joint of the foreleg? ","answer":"Knee      (carpus)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"767 medium CAHA58 ","question":"The coronary arteries are the first branches off the aorta and carry blood to what structure? ","answer":"Heart  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"768 medium TH123/DET102","question":"Name 2 clear or translucent structures that light must pass through to reach the retina in the horse's eye.","answer":"Cornea and lens "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"769 medium CAHA77 ","question":"Name one of the two endocrine glands that are attached to the brain. ","answer":"Pituitary gland; pineal gland  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"770 medium TH695/CAHA24/DET62 ","question":"The frog is a wedge-shaped mass that occupies the area between what structures at the heel of the foot? ","answer":"Bars            (also accept commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"771 medium TH126 ","question":"What structure in the brain controls the release of hormones by the pituitary gland? ","answer":"Hypothalamus  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"772 medium DET194 ","question":"Where is the horse's occipital crest located? ","answer":"Top of the head between the ears or the poll            (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"773 medium CAHA50 ","question":"What is the common term for the vallate, foliate, and fungiform papillae that are found on the tongue? ","answer":"Taste buds  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"774 medium CAHA50 ","question":"What bony structure in the oral cavity separates it from the nasal cavity? ","answer":"Hard palate     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"775 medium TH689/DET48 ","question":"What is another name for the horseï¿½s knee?    ","answer":"Carpus    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"776 medium CAHA16/DET176 ","question":"2 part question:  Name and give the function of the large muscle located on either side of the face.  It sits beneath the ear and covers the mandible. ","answer":"Masseter muscle;                    purpose - chewing    (opens and closes jaw)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"777 medium TH696 ","question":"Muscles that work together to accomplish a movement are called synergists.  What is the term for muscles that oppose each other and limit movement? ","answer":"Antagonists  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"778 medium DET37 ","question":"What part of the brain controls basic body functions such as respiration and heart rate? ","answer":"Brainstem       (specifically medulla oblongata) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"779 medium HIH220-6/DET216 ","question":"What is the term for the pivot point of the back that is located at the area between the last rib and the croup? ","answer":"Loin or coupling              (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"780 medium CAHA78 ","question":"What is the proper name for the cranial nerve that provides the horse with a sense of smell? ","answer":"Olfactory nerve  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"781 medium TH686/CAHA12/DET60 ","question":"Which bone of the horse am I describing?  The bone is very porous.  Blood vessels pass in and out of the pores.  Lateral cartilages are attached to the wings of this bone. ","answer":"Coffin bone, third phalanx, distal phalanx, or pedal bone                   (accept any)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"782 medium HIH465-1 ","question":"Give 2 purposes of the nictitating membrane. ","answer":"Removes foreign bodies from the eye, protects the eye from trauma, and smooths tear film over the eye  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"783 medium CAHA15 ","question":"What is the proper name for the layers of loose, dense fibrous connective tissue that are found superficially under the skin and deep covering the muscles? ","answer":"Fascia"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"784 medium DET97    ","question":"What is the outermost layer of skin?    ","answer":"Epidermis     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"785 medium HIH465-1 ","question":"In the horse's eye, there are cells known as rods and cones.  Which one of these is responsible for low light vision and motion detection? ","answer":"Rods     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"786 medium HIH465-1 ","question":"In the horse's eye, there are cells known as rods and cones.  Which one of these is responsible for day and color vision? ","answer":"Cones  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"787 medium CAHA59 ","question":"What vein in the horse's neck is commonly used to draw blood samples? ","answer":"Jugular vein  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"788 medium CAHA50 ","question":"Through which body cavity does the esophagus travel on its way to emptying into the stomach? ","answer":"Thoracic cavity    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"789 medium CAHA7 ","question":"The terms transverse process, spinous process, foramen, and arch are used to describe which bones? ","answer":"Vertebrae or spinal bones              (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"790 medium DET102 ","question":"What is the name for the outer protective layer of the horse's eye? ","answer":"Cornea  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"791 medium CAHA6 ","question":"The first phalanx is just below what long bone? ","answer":"Cannon or 3rd metacarpal
(additional info:  1st phalanx is long pastern, 2nd is short pastern, and 3rd is coffin)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"792 medium CAHA57 ","question":"The blood leaving the right ventricle of the heart by the pulmonary artery flows into what organ? ","answer":"Lungs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"793 medium DET167/CAHA78  	 ","question":"In the horse's eye, focused light rays which form the image on the retina are transmitted to the brain by what nerve? ","answer":"Optic nerve  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"795 medium CAHA43 ","question":"What is the horse's auricle? ","answer":"External or outer ear"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"796 medium CAHA7 ","question":"What are the first 2 cervical vertebrae called? ","answer":"Atlas and axis   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"797 medium TH119 ","question":"What system is responsible for collecting and removing the fluid waste materials from the body? ","answer":"Urinary system"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"798 medium TH111 ","question":"Simultaneously, blood enters the right atrium from the body and the left atrium from where? ","answer":"Lungs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"799 medium CAHA60","question":"What organ receives oxygenated blood from the renal artery?","answer":"Kidney                                                                            "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"800 medium CAHA12","question":"In the hind legs, what is the anatomical term for the short pastern bones?","answer":"Middle phalanx or second phalanx                 "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"801 medium TH687","question":"What is the common term for the tuber coxae?","answer":"Hip                    TH687"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"medium","number":"802 medium CAHA57 ","question":"Explain the FUNCTIONAL difference between arteries and veins. ","answer":"Arteries carry blood away from the heart to the body; veins carry blood from the body back to the heart "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"803 hard TH227 ","question":"Osteoblasts form a protein matrix that ultimately forms what tissue? ","answer":"Bone  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"804 hard HIH505-1 ","question":"What structure transfers the horseï¿½s weight from the bony structure to the hoof wall? ","answer":"Laminae  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"805 hard HIH810-1 ","question":"What is the term for the total amount of inspired air inspired in one breath?   ","answer":"Tidal volume  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"806 hard HIH810-2    ","question":"What is the term for low oxygen saturation in the blood?   ","answer":"Arterial hypoxemia or hypoxemia	 (accept either)     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"807 hard CAHA12 ","question":"What common name is given to the 3rd phalanx bone of the foot? ","answer":"Coffin bone or pedal bone 	(accept either) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"809 hard HIH505-2 ","question":"Why are the sensitive structures of the horse's feet called sensitive? ","answer":"Because they contain many blood vessels and nerve endings 
(Addtl info:  injury to them causes bleeding and pain)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"810 hard DET53 ","question":"Which part of the brain controls the coordination of movement? ","answer":"Cerebellum     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"811 hard TH97/CAHA8","question":"What is the difference between true ribs and false ribs? ","answer":"True ribs attach directly to the sternum          (Addtl info: they attach by cartilage).  
False ribs do not attach directly to the sternum.  (Addtl info:  False ribs connect to each other by cartilage and then attach to the sternum.)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"813 hard CAHA9 ","question":"What is the name of the membrane that covers the non-articulating surfaces of bone? ","answer":"Periosteum  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"814 hard HIH230-2 picture ","question":"Which vertebrae of a horse is the most upright member of the spinal column? ","answer":"15th       (also accept thoracic)    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"815 hard HIH1100-8 ","question":"2 part question:  Explain where the gaskin is and what it ties into. ","answer":"Gaskin is the muscle between the hock and the stifle; it ties into the thigh"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"816 hard TH154 ","question":"What does the gaskin muscle have to do with the horse's stride? ","answer":"Pulls the leg forward      (Addtl info:  It enables propulsion)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"817 hard TH123/HIH220-4 ","question":"What is a horse's degree of vision? ","answer":"300 degrees OR 215 degrees in each eye         (additional info:  binocular vision is 65 degrees)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"818 hard HIH840-1 ","question":"What is the basic contractile unit of skeletal muscles? ","answer":"Sacromere  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"819 hard HIH850-1 ","question":"Which type skeletal muscle is used for long-term, non-strenuous work and also provides endurance? ","answer":"Type 1  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"820 hard HIH850-1 ","question":"Type 2B muscles are used for what? ","answer":"Quick bursts of speed for short distances"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"821 hard HIH850-1 ","question":"Which breed has the largest number of Type 2A muscles? ","answer":"Thoroughbred  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"822 hard HIH830-1 ","question":"What are erythrocytes? ","answer":"Red blood cells  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"823 hard HIH830-1 ","question":"What are leukocytes? ","answer":"White blood cells  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"824 hard HIH810-2 ","question":"At a gallop, respiration rate and stride rate are almost always coupled in what ratio? ","answer":"1 to 1  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"825 hard HIH810-2 ","question":"In the gallop, when does the horse exhale? ","answer":"When the front legs make contact with the ground  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"826 hard TH689 ","question":"2 part question:  Which leg joint is subjected to the greatest strain and why? ","answer":"Fetlock; it may support the full weight of the horse during certain gaits or movements such as jumping (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"827 hard TH90 ","question":"What is one purpose of the long bones in the horse's body? ","answer":"Act as levers, support weight, locomotion, store minerals  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"828 hard TH90 ","question":"2 part question:  Where are the short bones located and what is their main purpose? ","answer":"In complex joints such as the knee and hock; absorb concussion   (shock absorption)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"829 hard CAHA6 ","question":"How many bones form the basis of locomotion in the horse? ","answer":"80     (20 in each leg)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"830 hard TH90 ","question":"Which type bones enclose the body cavities containing vital organs and also provide large areas for muscle attachment? ","answer":"Flat bones  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"831 hard TH90 ","question":"2 part question:  Where are the irregular bones located in the horse's skeleton and what is their purpose? ","answer":"Spinal column (vertebrae);  they protect the spinal cord  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"832 hard TH99 ","question":"Which muscle type is fast twitch and fatigues easily? ","answer":"Type 2  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"833 hard TH101 ","question":"What provides the energy for muscle contraction? ","answer":"ATP     (adenosine triphosphate)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"834 hard TH104 ","question":"What is a secondary purpose of the respiratory system? ","answer":"Temperature regulation      (also accept phonation or vocalization)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"836 hard CAHA8 ","question":"What is the term for the ribs that do not connect directly to the sternum?   ","answer":"Floating ribs    (also accepted:  false ribs)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"837 hard CAHA5 ","question":"In the horse, which gland secretes tears? ","answer":"Lacrimal gland  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"838 hard CAHA5 ","question":"The horse's skin is composed of 2 layers.  What are they? ","answer":"Epidermis and dermis  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"839 hard CAHA5 ","question":"What is the common name for the apocrine tubular glands of the horse? ","answer":"Sweat glands  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"840 hard CAHA9 ","question":"Where on a bone would you NOT find the periosteum? ","answer":"At the ends of long bones OR epiphyses OR points of articulation     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"841 hard TH129 ","question":"What is the name for the long, individual hairs that often mix with the dense undercoat of the horse especially under the belly? ","answer":"Guard hairs or cat hairs         (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"842 hard CAHA7/TH96 ","question":"The increased height of the 3rd, 4th, and 5th thoracic vertebrae make up what part of the horse? ","answer":"Withers  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"843 hard CAHA6 ","question":"What is the triangular sesamoid bone that's situated at the front of the stifle? ","answer":"Patella   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"844 hard CAHA27 ","question":"The navicular bone and bursa are associated with which tendon? ","answer":"Deep digital flexor tendon      (also accept deep flexor tendon)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"845 hard CAHA29 ","question":"What is the track-like structure on which the patella rides? ","answer":"Trochlea  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"846 hard CAHA55   ","question":"Name the organ in the abdominal cavity that stores blood, filters blood, and removes old blood cells. ","answer":"Spleen   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"847 hard TH90 ","question":"What is the name of the fluid that fills the sheaths around tendons and lines the inside of joints? ","answer":"Synovial fluid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"848 hard TH122 ","question":"What is the name of the substance contained in the anterior chamber of the eye? ","answer":"Aqueous humor  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"849 hard CAHA68 ","question":"What substance produced by the horse contains nitrogen, sulfur, inorganic salts, and pigments? ","answer":"Urine  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"850 hard CAHA16 ","question":"What is the name of the longest and widest muscle in the horse's body? ","answer":"Latissimus dorsi  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"851 hard CAHA50 ","question":"What is the name of the flap that covers the opening into the windpipe during swallowing? ","answer":"Epiglottis  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"852 hard CAHA10 ","question":"What does "interosseous"  (in-ter-AH-see-us) mean? ","answer":"Between bones  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"853 hard CAHA36 ","question":"Which 2 joints in the rear leg have reciprocal action? ","answer":"Hock and stifle  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"854 hard CAHA56 ","question":"What is the lining of the abdominal wall called? ","answer":"Peritoneum  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"855 hard CAHA8 ","question":"What is the largest ligament in the leg? ","answer":"Suspensory ligament  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"856 hard CAHA8 ","question":"Where are the intercostal muscles located? ","answer":"Between the ribs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"857 hard TH687 ","question":"The os coxae  (ahs COX-ee) of a horse is also known as what? ","answer":"Pelvis or pelvic girdle   (accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"858 hard TH59 ","question":"How many flat bones make up the skull? ","answer":"34   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"859 hard CAHA11 ","question":"What is the fluid-filled space between the iris and cornea called? ","answer":"Anterior chamber 	(additional info:  contains aqueous humor)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"860 hard TH105 ","question":"How many turbinates are in each nasal cavity? ","answer":"2 (two)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"861 hard HIH505-4 ","question":"What are 2 purposes of the digital cushion? ","answer":"Helps absorb shock and helps circulation of blood"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"862 hard CAHA68 ","question":"When the bladder is full, urine is discharged through what? ","answer":"Urethra  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"863 hard TH154/HS9 ","question":"Which muscle helps to pull the hind leg forward and enable propulsion, giving the horse a long, powerful stride? ","answer":"Gaskin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"864 hard CAHA12 ","question":"Which bone of the horse's foot serves as a pulley for the deep flexor tendon? ","answer":"Navicular bone or distal sesamoid 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"865 hard TH713 ","question":"Name the tendon responsible for the extension of the horse's toe and hoof. ","answer":"Digital extensor tendon  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"866 hard CAHA25 ","question":"Specifically, what part of the foot produces the periople? ","answer":"Perioplic corium  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"867 hard TH98  ","question":"Describe one function of the distal sesamoid or navicular bone. ","answer":"Protects coffin joint, provides bearing surface or support for the deep digital flexor tendon"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"868 hard CAHA43,65 ","question":"What is the structural basis for the ears and nostrils? ","answer":"Cartilage  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"869 hard TH684 ","question":"What is unique about the horse's ulna? ","answer":"No bone marrow cavity  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"870 hard CAHA14 ","question":"What 4 bones make up the fetlock joint? ","answer":"Cannon, long pastern, and 2 proximal sesamoid bones"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"871 hard CAHA57 ","question":"What is the anatomical name of the tubular tissue that generally carries oxygenated blood under high pressure? ","answer":"Artery  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"872 hard CAHA57-58 ","question":"2 part question:  The heart is composed of how many chambers and what are their names? ","answer":"4 (four);    left ventricle, right ventricle, left atrium, right atrium  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"873 hard CAHA10 ","question":"2 part question:  How many bones comprise the forearm and what are their names? ","answer":"2 (two);    radius and ulna"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"874 hard CAHA2 ","question":"2 part question:  Explain proximal and distal. ","answer":"Proximal - closer to the body;    distal - furthest from the body"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"875 hard CAHA16 ","question":"Where is the trapezius muscle located in the horse? ","answer":"On each side of the withers  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"876 hard CAHA5 ","question":"What is collagen? ","answer":"Fibrous network that forms the basic framework of body tissue  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"877 hard CAHA5,80 ","question":"Where in the horse's body is epinephrine produced? ","answer":"Adrenal gland  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"878 hard TH96 ","question":"2 part question:  What is the name and function of the first and second vertebrae of the horse's spinal column? ","answer":"Atlas - up and down/flexion and extension of the neck; 
Axis - lateral/left and right movements of the neck"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"879 hard TH128 ","question":"The integumentary system refers to what body part? ","answer":"Skin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"880 hard TH117 ","question":"What is the function of the horse's spleen? ","answer":"Stores red blood cells  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"881 hard TH97  ","question":"What is the name of the largest metacarpal? ","answer":"Cannon bone or 3rd metacarpal (accept either) (additional info:  splint bones are the 2nd and 4th metacarpals)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"882 hard TH97 ","question":"Over which section of the vertebral column does most of the saddle sit? ","answer":"Thoracic  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"883 hard TH429 ","question":"What type of white blood cells is found in the spleen and lymph nodes and is important in fighting infection? ","answer":"Lymphocytes    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"884 hard HIH910-5 ","question":"What is a hormone? ","answer":"Body-regulating chemical secreted by an endocrine gland into the bloodstream "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"885 hard TH117 ","question":"What is the function of erythrocytes? ","answer":"Transport oxygen in blood"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"886 hard CAHA7 ","question":"How many vertebrae are there?  ","answer":"51 ï¿½ 57    (accept any answer within this range) 
(additional info:  7 cervical, 18 thoracic, 6 lumbar, 5 sacral, and 15-21 coccygeal/caudal)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"887 hard TH688 ","question":"What kind of joint is the horse's elbow? ","answer":"Hinge  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"888 hard TH708 ","question":"What is the primary function of the suspensory ligament? ","answer":"To prevent excessive overextension of the fetlock joint  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"889 hard HIH various ","question":"How much blood does an adult horse's body contain? ","answer":"50 liters OR 13.2 gallons  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"890 hard CAHA14 ","question":"The long pastern, cannon, and sesamoid bones make up what joint of the horse? ","answer":"Fetlock or ankle 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"891 hard CAHA9 ","question":"2 part question:  What is the periosteum and what does it do? ","answer":"Bone producing membrane that covers bones (except at the ends).  It protects the bone and is a site of healing."},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"892 hard HIH415-1 ","question":"Name the muscle that lies under the horse's skin that enables the skin to twitch and shake flies off the body. ","answer":"Panniculus  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"893 hard TH118 ","question":"In the horse, the nose, ears, and eyes are referred to as what type of organs? ","answer":"Specialized sensory organs  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"894 hard CAHA7 ","question":"What classification type of bone protects the spinal cord? ","answer":"Irregular   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"895 hard HIH895-1 ","question":"What is the name of the muscles located between the ribs that are involved in inspiration? ","answer":"Intercostal muscles  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"896 hard TH196 ","question":"2 part question:  Where is the panniculus muscle and what is its function?   ","answer":"Muscle under the skin;   enables the horse to flick flies off its skin"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"897 hard HIH455-1 ","question":"The tiny, folded, accordion-like, interlocking projections that connect the coffin bone to the hoof wall are called what? ","answer":"Laminae  (sensitive laminae)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"898 hard HIH455-2 ","question":"Where is the navicular bone located? ","answer":"Behind and below the short pastern OR at the back of the coffin bone"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"899 hard HIH505-5 ","question":"What happens when the large venous plexuses within the hoof are compressed? ","answer":"Blood is pumped back up the leg  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"900 hard ES22 ","question":"Describe a tufted tail. ","answer":"Tail that has short hair (somewhat like a cow) towards the top with a tuft of longer hair beginning about halfway down the tail"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"901 hard ES212 ","question":"How many pairs of spinal nerves does a horse have? ","answer":"22  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"902 hard HIH153B-2 ","question":"What is a jibbah? ","answer":"The bulge between the eyes of an Arabian    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"903 hard HIH435a-1 ","question":"What is the mesentery? ","answer":"Loose tissue that connects the small intestines to the abdominal wall"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"904 hard ES212 ","question":"The central nervous system consists of the brain and the spinal cord.  What does the peripheral nervous system consist of? ","answer":"Nerves that branch off the brain and spinal cord     (also accept:  cranial nerves and spinal nerves)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"905 hard DET97 ","question":"What is the function of the epiglottis? ","answer":"Prevents food from entering the larynx and trachea"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"906 hard DET276  ","question":"2 part question:  Where would you find the turbinate bones and what is their purpose? ","answer":"Bones in the nasal passages;  they filter and warm the air that's inhaled "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"907 hard ADV325-1L ","question":"Which 2 muscles expand the chest during breathing? ","answer":"Diaphragm and intercostal muscles"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"908 hard TH237 ","question":"What are osteoblasts? ","answer":"Bone forming cells  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"909 hard TH129 ","question":"2 part question:  What are guard hairs and where are they commonly found? ","answer":"Long, individual hairs that often mix with the dense undercoat of the horse;   usually seen on the underside of the belly, underside of jaw and neck, and between cheeks of buttocks (don't need to give all locations)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"910 hard TH705 ","question":"What is the name of the largest nerve in the horse's body? ","answer":"Sciatic nerve  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"911 hard CAHA57 ","question":"What chamber of the heart does the oxygenated blood from the lungs enter first? ","answer":"Left atrium  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"912 hard ES56 ","question":"2 part question:  How is the shape of the horseï¿½s pupil different in comparison to other mammals and how does the shape of the pupil benefit the horse? ","answer":"Pupil is more horizontal   (additional info:  a cat's pupil is more vertical and a human's pupil is more round); It gives the horse more vision over a wide horizon OR enables the horse to see predators more easily"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"913 hard TH722 ","question":"What is the common name for the epiphyseal (eh-pee-FISS-ee-al) plates?","answer":"Growth plates  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"914 hard TH8 ","question":"In today's modern Equus, vestiges are still present of the two outside toes that disappeared from the prehistoric horse Mesohippus.  What are these vestiges called? ","answer":"Splint bones		 (also accept chestnuts and ergots)    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"915 hard HS24 ","question":"What 2 tracts does the pharynx belong to? ","answer":"Respiratory and digestive  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"916 hard DET100 ","question":"Name the structure that equalizes air pressure in the ear.   ","answer":"Eustachian tube  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"917 hard TH188 ","question":"Which region of the spinal column is joined securely to the hipbone? ","answer":"Sacrum (at the sacroiliac joint)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"918 hard DET62 ","question":"What is the function of the commissure in the hoof? ","answer":"Gives elasticity to the foot  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"919 hard DET69 ","question":"2 part question:  Where is the coronary band and why do you have to be careful with this area? ","answer":"Hairline between the top of the hoof and the bottom of the pastern;   
Hoof growth starts at the coronary band"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"920 hard TH687/CAHA28 ","question":"The ischium and pubis are located where?    ","answer":"Pelvis           "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"921 hard CAHA54 ","question":"Name the largest internal organ of the horse. ","answer":"Liver  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"922 hard TH129 ","question":"2 part question:  Describe the location and the function of the sebaceous glands. ","answer":"Located at base of hair follicles in the dermis;    they produce sebum an oily, waxy substance that protects and insulates the skin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"923 hard TH690","question":"What is parathormone or parathyroid hormone? ","answer":"Hormone secreted by the parathyroid gland that increases calcium in the blood "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"924 hard TH22 ","question":"At what age do the epiphysis plates on the distal end of the cannon close? ","answer":"9 - 12 months	 (accept any number within this range) "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"925 hard DET67 ","question":"What is the term for the membrane that lines the inside of the eyelid? ","answer":"Conjunctiva  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"926 hard CAHA57 ","question":"Which chamber of the heart does blood returning from the body by the cranial and caudal vena cava enter first? ","answer":"Right atrium  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"927 hard HIH505-4 ","question":"The rear third of the coffin bone does not attach directly to the hoof wall.  What elastic structure provides the bridge for this attachment?   ","answer":"Lateral cartilages    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"929 hard TH114/HIH830-2 ","question":"How does the spleen help the race horse increase its level of arterial oxygen and maintain levels of physical exertion? ","answer":"Spleen contracts releasing additional red blood cells to carry oxygen"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"930 hard TH112/CAHA64/DET173 ","question":"What is the proper term for filters found in the horse's body which can remove bacteria, cancer cells, and foreign materials from circulation?  They are connected to the vascular system by the thoracic duct.","answer":"Lymph nodes  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"931 hard CAHA9/DET80 ","question":"The term "diaphysis" (die-AFF-i-sis) refers to what part of a long bone? ","answer":"Shaft  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"932 hard HIH830-1 ","question":"What is the name of the iron-containing protein found in erythrocytes that binds to oxygen? ","answer":"Hemoglobin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"933 hard FCH404 ","question":"What is the name of the organ in the abdominal cavity which serves as a reservoir for red blood cells and assists the body in combating infectious organisms? ","answer":"Spleen  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"934 hard CAHA8 ","question":"The costal cartilages of the first 8 ribs articulate with what bony structure? ","answer":"Sternum  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"935 hard CAHA14/TH158-59/DET154 ","question":"Identify one of two different places in the horse's skeletal structure where youï¿½d find an interosseous ligament. ","answer":"Attachment of radius to ulna 
(additional info:  present only in foals and is later ossified); attachment of cannon to splint bones"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"936 hard CAHA12/DET188 ","question":"What 2 sets of bones serve as pulleys to change the direction of the deep digital flexor tendon? ","answer":"Proximal and distal sesamoid bones  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"937 hard FCH401,03 ","question":"2 part question:  What is the proper name for the fluid that suspends the red blood cells in whole blood and what term is used for the fluid that remains once the red blood cells have clotted? ","answer":"Plasma - fluid in whole blood;      serum - fluid in clotted blood     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"938 hard TH142/CAHA1,12/DET179 	","question":"What is the proper anatomical name for the bones of the horse that are found between the knee and the fetlock joints? ","answer":"Metacarpal bones    (additional info:  cannon is 3rd metacarpal and splint bones are 2nd and 4th metacarpals)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"939 hard CAHA60 ","question":"Veins from the stomach, spleen, intestines, and pancreas all join to form the portal vein which carries blood to an important organ in the abdominal cavity where essential metabolic functions are performed.  What is the name of this organ? ","answer":"Liver  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"940 hard CAHA13 ","question":"In what joint would you find a fibro-cartilage structure called a meniscus that is located between the articulating surfaces of that joint? ","answer":"Stifle       (femur to tibia joint)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"941 hard CAHA12 ","question":"What 2 bones articulate with the distal sesamoid bone? ","answer":"Short pastern and coffin bone  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"942 hard CAHA42/DET146 ","question":"Name one of the structures that the hyoid bone supports. ","answer":"Larynx, base of tongue, guttural pouches, pharynx  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"943 hard CAHA63 ","question":"What organ located in the thorax, produces lymphocytes, is at its largest in the 6-8 week old foal, and decreases in size with age becoming difficult to find in older horses? ","answer":"Thymus  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"944 hard CAHA45/TH125 ","question":"What is the common term for the fluid that's produced by the lacrimal glands, collects in the medial canthus, and flows down the nasolacrimal duct? ","answer":"Tears  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"945 hard HIH505-4 ","question":"Why is the hoof wall harder at the toe than at the quarters? ","answer":"Toe is further from coronary band and is therefore is more keratinized  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"946 hard HIH810-1 ","question":"In measuring respiratory capabilities of the horse, tidal volume and respiratory rate are used to determine what respiratory parameter? ","answer":"Minute volume           (amount of air inspired or expired per minute)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"947 hard DET254/TH709/CAHA21,36 ","question":"The stay apparatus is a system of muscles, ligaments, and tendons whose purpose is commonly thought to lock the legs to allow a horse to rest while standing.  Name one of the other two functions of this apparatus. ","answer":"Helps reduce concussion and prevents overextension"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"948 hard CAHA78 ","question":"To what structure does the 12th cranial nerve, the hypoglossal nerve, provide motor control? ","answer":"Tongue  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"949 hard DET18/CAHA80 ","question":"The autonomic nervous system regulates many of the internal operations of the body and regulates unconscious responses to external stimuli.  What are the 2 divisions of the autonomic nervous system?   ","answer":"Sympathetic and parasympathetic  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"950 hard HIH465-1 ","question":"2 part question:  In the horse's eye, there are 2 main photoreceptor cell types.  What are they called and what type of vision is each used for? ","answer":"Rods - used for low light vision and motion detection;     cones - used for day vision and color vision"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"951 hard HIH465-1 ","question":"The tear film is necessary for the health of the cornea.  What do tears do for the eye? ","answer":"Supply nutrition, moisture, and oxygen to the eye surface  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"952 hard TH694 ","question":"What is the function of the tectorial layer of the horse's foot? ","answer":"Maintains moisture in the hoof wall"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"953 hard HIH810-1 ","question":"To what does oxygen attach on the red blood cells?   ","answer":"Hemoglobin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"954 hard DET1,3 ","question":"Describe the difference between adduction and abduction as it applies to the movement of the horse's limbs. ","answer":"Adduction - movement toward the body;     abduction - movement away from the body  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"955 hard CAHA58 ","question":"Where would you find the Purkinje fibers? ","answer":"In the heart   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"956 hard DET205  ","question":"Located beneath the ear, what is the largest of the horses 3 salivary glands? ","answer":"Parotid   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"957 hard CAHA31 ","question":"What is the common name for the coxofemoral joint? ","answer":"Hip joint  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"958 hard TH91 ","question":"What is the joint between the femur and the tibia? ","answer":"Stifle    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"959 hard CAHA57 ","question":"What is the only vein that carries oxygenated blood? ","answer":"Pulmonary vein  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"960 hard TH126-27/HS23 ","question":"Name a hormone produced by the pituitary gland ","answer":"Prolactin, FSH, LH, growth hormone, oxytocin, TSH, ACTH, vasopressin"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"961 hard HIH910-5 ","question":"What is the study of hormones and their effects called? ","answer":"Endocrinology   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"962 hard TH126 ","question":"What is endocrinology? ","answer":"Study of hormones (and their effects on the body)   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"963 hard CAHA6 ","question":"What structure begins the healing process when a bone fracture occurs? ","answer":"Periosteum  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"964 hard TH99 ","question":"2 part question:  The muscles of a horse's body are classified as smooth, cardiac, and skeletal.  Which are voluntary and which are involuntary? ","answer":"Skeletal muscles are voluntary; smooth and cardiac muscles are involuntary "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"965 hard HS14 ","question":"Define the term "anatomy". 	","answer":"Science of the structure of the animal's body and the relationship of its parts (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"966 hard HIH505-3 ","question":"What is the name of the internal foot structure that serves as a means of attachment for the hoof wall and the coffin bone? ","answer":"Sensitive laminae (also accept laminae)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"967 hard CAHA10 ","question":"2 part question:  If the horse has a fracture of the olecranon, what bone and joint would be involved? ","answer":"Bone ï¿½ulna; joint ï¿½ elbow    "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"968 hard DET113, 275","question":"Fossa and tuberosity are terms used to describe bones.  In general, what do these two terms describe?	","answer":"Fossa ï¿½ hollow or depressed area    		Tuberosity ï¿½  prominence or projection"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"969 hard CAHA12","question":"What is the anatomical term for the hind cannon bone?","answer":"Large metatarsal or 3rd metatarsal           (answers with metacarpal not accepted)     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"970 hard DET111/CAHA41","question":"What is the anatomical name for a natural passageway or opening in the body that blood vessels & nerves pass through?","answer":"Foramen   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"971 hard DET283","question":"In general, what does the term viscera describe?		","answer":"Internal organs"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"972 hard CAHA60","question":"What specific organ receives oxygenated blood from the left gastric artery?				","answer":"Stomach                        "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"973 hard DET267","question":"What is the main physiological function of thrombocytes?				","answer":"Blood clotting"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"975 hard CAHA30","question":"What is the anatomical name for the bone that forms the point of the hock?","answer":"Calcaneous			"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"976 hard DET214","question":"Thrombocytes are commonly referred to as what type of blood cells?","answer":"Platelets				"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"977 hard FCH689","question":"What is the specific location of the metatarsal phalangeal joint?                        ","answer":"Hind fetlock joint  (may also accept hind ankle or hind ankle joint ï¿½ must specify ï¿½hindï¿½ for correct answer)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"978 hard CAHA46","question":"What anatomical structure of the horse is described as a diverticulum of the auditory tube?","answer":"Guttural pouch               "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"979 hard CAHA8","question":"What would be the general location of the manubrium & xiphoid process?","answer":"Sternum                "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"980 hard CAHA51","question":"Which 2 glands empty into the small intestine at the major duodenal papilla?","answer":"Liver  (bile duct) & pancreas  (pancreatic duct)   "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"981 hard CAHA80","question":"Would the parasympathetic or sympathetic nervous system be stimulated with the ï¿½flight or fightï¿½ instinct?","answer":"Sympathetic               "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"hard","number":"982 hard DET204","question":"Which endocrine gland is responsible for the maintenance of calcium levels in the blood?","answer":"Parathyroid  (also accept thyroid due to the hormone calcitonin)     "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"983 bonus TH120 				","question":"Name the 3 primary specialized sensory organs of the horse's nervous system. ","answer":"Eyes, ears, nose  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"984 bonus TH111				 ","question":"What are the 4 parts of the circulatory system? ","answer":"Heart, arteries, veins, capillaries, blood  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"985 bonus CAHA23 ","question":"Name 3 ways that veins differ from arteries. ","answer":"Veins contain a larger volume of blood, veins have thinner walls, veins have valves, veins carry blood to the heart  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"986 bonus TH129 ","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse's skin that are not covered with hair. ","answer":"Underneath tail, inside of thigh, around genitals, udder  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"987 bonus TH129 ","question":"Name 3 areas of the horse's body where it sweats readily ","answer":"Base of ears, chest, neck, flank   (NOT back)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"988 bonus HIH425-2,3 ","question":"Name 4 of the horseï¿½s body fluids.		","answer":"Feces, urine, tears, sweat, saliva, blood  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"989 bonus TH689 ","question":"The elbow joint in the horse is the articulation site of what 3 bones? ","answer":"Ulna, radius, humerus  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"990 bonus TH119 ","question":"The urinary system consists of what 4 parts? ","answer":"Kidneys, ureters, bladder, urethra  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"991 bonus HIH230-2 ","question":"Name 4 of the bones in the horse's hind leg from the stifle joint distally. ","answer":"Tibia, fibula, tarsal bones, cannon, splint bones, long pastern, short pastern, coffin bone, navicular bone or distal sesamoid, proximal sesamoid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"992 bonus TH117 ","question":"Name 3 of the 5 types of leucocytes or white blood cells.","answer":"Eosinophils, basophils, neutrophils, monocytes, lymphocytes  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"993 bonus CAHA28 ","question":"Name 3 of the bones that make up the horse's pelvic girdle. ","answer":"Ilium, pubis, ischium, sacrum, caudal/coccygeal vertebrae"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"994 bonus INT223-2 			","question":"Starting at the poll, name the 6 parts of the horse that comprise the entire topline ","answer":"Poll, crest, withers, back, loin/coupling, croup/rump"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"995 bonus ADV302-1 ","question":"Name the 3 passages of the facial portion of the skull. ","answer":"Orbital, nasal, oral  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"996 bonus TH104 ","question":"The primary function of the respiratory system is to oxygenate the blood.  What are the 2 secondary functions? ","answer":"Temperature regulation and phonation (vocalization)"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"997 bonus TH97 ","question":"What 3 body systems do the true ribs protect? ","answer":"Respiratory, circulatory, digestive  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"998 bonus TH96 Det204, 258, CAHA44 ","question":"Name two of the three pairs of salivary glands in the horse and give their locations. ","answer":"Parotid - below ear,   submaxillary/submandibular - between jaws,   sublingual - beneath tongue  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"999 bonus BEG115-1L ","question":"The mucous membranes are evaluated as part of the vital signs of the horse.  Name 4 places you can find them. ","answer":"Inner surface of eyelids, inside nostrils, inner surface of lips and gums, inner surface of vulva, inner surface of rectum  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1000 bonus TH99 ","question":"Name 3 places in the horse's body where you will find involuntary muscle action. ","answer":"Digestive tract, respiratory tract, circulatory system, urinary system "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1001 bonus TH90 ","question":"Name the 7 joints of the hind leg in order proximal to distal. ","answer":"Sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock, pastern, coffin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1002 bonus TH98 ","question":"From distal to proximal, name the 7 joints of the hind leg. ","answer":"Coffin, pastern, fetlock, hock, stifle, hip, sacroiliac  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1003 bonus TH91/CAHA6 ","question":"What 4 bones form the stifle joint? ","answer":"Femur, patella, tibia, fibula  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1004 bonus TH91/CAHA110-12 ","question":"Name the 6 joints of the foreleg from proximal to distal. ","answer":"Shoulder, elbow, knee/carpus, fetlock/ankle, pastern, coffin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1005 bonus CAHA various ","question":"Where is each of the 3 following serous membranes found in the horse:  pleura, peritoneum, and pericardium? ","answer":"Pleura cover the lungs and line the thoracic cavity; peritoneum lines the abdominal cavity; pericardium surrounds the heart  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1006 bonus ES67 ","question":"The sense of taste in the horse is similar to that of humans.  What 4 tastes is the horse capable of sensing? ","answer":"Bitter, sweet, salt, sour  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1007 bonus HH10/TH152 			","question":"Give 2 reasons why it's important to have a deep heart-girth with well-sprung ribs. ","answer":"Respiratory capacity and digestive capacity  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1008 bonus HIH220-3 			","question":"Name 3 of the parts of a horse's front leg below the knee. ","answer":"Cannon, fetlock or ankle, coronet band, pastern, hoof"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1009 bonus CAHA 6 							","question":"Name 4 bones of the lower leg below the knee or hock. ","answer":"Cannon, splint, long pastern, short pastern, coffin, navicular, sesamoid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1010 bonus CAHA66 ","question":"Name 3 functions of the larynx.   ","answer":"Controls air flow, protects airway, phonation (vocalization)  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1011 bonus TH98 ","question":"From proximal to distal name the 3 joints of the horseï¿½s leg that are common to all 4 legs. ","answer":"Fetlock, pastern, coffin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1012 bonus HIH220-3 			","question":"Name 4 joints on the front leg. ","answer":"Shoulder, elbow, knee, fetlock or ankle, pastern, coffin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1013 bonus HIH535-2 ","question":"Name 4 parts of the horse's foot. 		","answer":"Toe, heel, wall, white line, frog, sole, buttress, quarter, bulb, bar, apex of frog, cleft of frog, frog, periople, seat of corn, commissure/collateral groove/sulci  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1014 bonus TH89 ","question":"What 3 items make up the central nervous system? ","answer":"Brain, brainstem, spinal cord  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1015 bonus HIH220-3 ","question":"Name 4 joints on the hind leg. 		","answer":"Sacroiliac, hip, stifle, hock, fetlock or ankle, pastern, coffin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1016 bonus HS34 ","question":"What are 3 other parts of the body made of protein besides muscles, internal organs, bones, and blood?","answer":"Skin, hair, hooves"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1017 bonus CAHA57 ","question":"Timelineï¿½ Correctly follow the blood flow through the heart and lungs beginning with blood entering the heart via the cranial vena cava.  Organize the following 7 anatomical terms in the correct order to complete this task:  cranial vena cava, left ventricle, pulmonary vein, right atrium, pulmonary artery, lungs, and aorta.     ","answer":"Cranial vena cava, right atrium, pulmonary artery, lungs, pulmonary vein, left ventricle, and aorta  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1018 bonus TH90 ","question":"There are 4 classifications of bones.  Name 3. ","answer":"Long, short, flat, irregular  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1019 bonus TH90 				","question":"Give 3 main purposes of the horse's skeleton. ","answer":"Provides framework, protects internal organs, locomotion, stores minerals, produces blood cells"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1020 bonus TH89 ","question":"The horse's body is made up of 9 systems.  Name 3. ","answer":"Skeletal, muscular, respiratory, circulatory/cardiovascular, digestive, reproductive, nervous, endocrine, integumentary/skin  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1021 bonus HIH830-1 ","question":"Blood is made up of 3 types of cells.  What are they? ","answer":"Red blood cells/erythrocytes, white blood cells/leukocytes, platelets/thrombocytes  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1022 bonus HIH840-3 ","question":"Skeletal muscles are classified into 4 types.  What are they? ","answer":"Type 1, Type 2A, Type 2B, Type 2C  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1023 bonus TH98				 ","question":"What are the 3 main bones of the foot? ","answer":"Coffin, navicular, short pastern  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1024 bonus TH99 ","question":"Give 3 characteristics of Type 1 muscle fibers. ","answer":"Slow twitch, low glycolytic activity, provide endurance "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1025 bonus TH99 ","question":"What are the 3 subtypes of type 2 muscle fibers and their uses? ","answer":"Type 2A - speed at long distances, Type 2B - quick burst of speed for short distances, Type 2C - training can recruit them to either type 2A or type 2B  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1026 bonus CAHA78 ","question":"Name 3 cranial nerves. ","answer":"Olfactory, optic, oculomotor, trochlear, trigeminal, abducens, facial, vestibulocochlear, glossopharyngeal, vagus, accessory, hypoglossal "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1027 bonus TH119 ","question":"Give 3 functions of the horse's kidneys. ","answer":"Remove wastes, control water balance, control pH, control electrolyte levels, regulate blood pressure, hormone production, absorb minerals, regulate red blood cells "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1028 bonus TH126-27 ","question":"Name 3 of the horse's body functions that are controlled by the endocrine system. ","answer":"Growth, reproduction, metabolism, digestion  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1029 bonus CAHA7 ","question":"Name 4 regions of the spinal column and give the number of vertebrae in each of those regions. ","answer":"Cervical 7, thoracic 18, lumbar 6, sacrum 5, coccygeal/caudal 15-21  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1030 bonus TH98/ES203 ","question":"What are the common names of the 3 phalanx bones? ","answer":"Long pastern, short pastern, coffin/pedal bone"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1031 bonus TH90/CAHA42 ","question":"Name 3 bones found in the horseï¿½s head. ","answer":"Premaxilla/incisive, nasal, maxilla, mandible, frontal, temporal, parietal, occipital, zygomatic, pterygoid, presphenoid, vomar, palatine, orbit, hyoid  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1032 bonus CAHA11 ","question":"2 part question:  How many carpal bones are there in the knee and how are they arranged?","answer":"8 carpal bones; arranged in 2 rows"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1033 bonus HIH840-1 ","question":"Name the 3 types of muscles found in a horse's body. ","answer":"Smooth, cardiac, skeletal  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1034 bonus HIH830-1 			","question":"Name 3 functions of the blood. 		","answer":"Transports nutrients, transports gases (oxygen and carbon dioxide), transports hormones, removes wastes, fights infections, regulates pH, clotting, regulates body temperature, regulates blood pressure "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1035 bonus CAHA63 ","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse's body that belong to the immune system. ","answer":"Lymph nodes, lymph vessels, spleen, bone marrow, thymus"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1036 bonus CAHA25 ","question":"Name 3 parts of the hoof which furnish nutrition to the hoof. ","answer":"Perioplic corium, coronary corium, laminar corium, sole corium, frog corium  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1037 bonus CAHA5 ","question":"Name 3 functions of the horse's skin. ","answer":"Protection, sensation, thermoregulation, controls water loss, absorption  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1038 bonus CAHA13 ","question":"Synovial joints are classified on the basis of the type of motion.  Name 3 of these types. ","answer":"Ball and socket, ellipsoid, hinge, pivot, sliding/gliding"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1039 bonus HIH840-1 			","question":"Name 3 systems in the horse's body that use smooth muscles. ","answer":"Digestive, circulatory/cardiovascular, respiratory, urogenital  "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1040 bonus TH152","question":"What three boney structures form the thoracic cavity?		","answer":"Spine (vertebrae), ribs and sternum"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1041 bonus ES61","question":"Identify four ways that horses use their olfactory sense.	","answer":"To locate food		To ensure food/water are acceptable quality
To identify humans		To identify other horses
To identify objects		To smell potential predators or other dangers
To initiate sexual and breeding behavior	To identify marked territory of other horses/herds"},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1042 bonus CAHA5","question":"List 3 physiological functions of the skin that would affect regulation of body temperature","answer":"Changes in blood flow             Erection of hairs                 Sweating          "},
{"category":"ANATOMY","level":"bonus","number":"1043 bonus TH126-127","question":"Identify 3 of the hormones produced by the anterior pituitary","answer":"Growth hormone (GH)			Adrenocortocotropin   (ACTH)
Luteinizing hormone   (LH)			Follicle stimulating hormone   (FSH)
Thyrotropin (thyroid stimulating hormone or TSH)	Prolactin"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1044 easy H1-9/TH137 ","question":"What does it mean if a horse has its ears pricked forward? ","answer":"Interest or suspicion  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1045 easy HH54 ","question":"What does a nervous handler cause? ","answer":"A nervous or unsafe horse  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1046 easy HH54 ","question":"Teasing a horse may cause it to do what? ","answer":"Develop dangerous habits  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1047 easy HIH1220-2 ","question":"What is a barn sour horse? ","answer":"One that doesn't want to leave the barn  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1048 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"When using binocular vision, At what distance must an object be from the front of the horse for it to see the object? ","answer":"4 feet"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1049 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"What is the ability to see separate objects with each eye at the same time? ","answer":"Monocular vision  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1050 easy H1-9 ","question":"When the dominant horse in a group makes a threat, less aggressive horses will do what? ","answer":"Retreat or get away  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1051 easy HH54 ","question":"There are few vicious horses.  What may cause a horse to become vicious? ","answer":"Abuse  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1052 easy HH52 ","question":"What practice may prevent a horse from becoming a halter puller? ","answer":"Untying the lead rope before taking the halter off  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1053 easy HIH425-6 ","question":"Describe the stable vice called weaving. ","answer":"Horse moves head and/or upper body from side to side OR horse rocks side to side or back and forth"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1054 easy HIH1220-2 ","question":"Horses have a very strong desire for the company of what? ","answer":"Other horses  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1055 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"A horse cannot see directly below what part of its body? ","answer":"Head "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1056 easy HIH1220-2 ","question":"Which sense of the horse is better, sight or hearing? ","answer":"Hearing  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1057 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"To judge distance, the horse uses which type of vision? ","answer":"Binocular  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1058 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"How does a horse reposition its head to better visualize objects that are far away?","answer":"Lower its head  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1059 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"What must the horse do to see close objects? ","answer":"Raise its head  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1060 easy HIH320-1 ","question":"Under natural conditions, horses do not spend long periods of time in what general type of area? ","answer":"Enclosed  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1061 easy HS4/TH182 ","question":"What is the general term for a bad habit that may affect a horse's health, usefulness, or dependability? ","answer":"Vice  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1062 easy HIH710-8/TH183 ","question":"What term describes the habit horses have of eating too fast? ","answer":"Bolting their feed  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1063 easy BEG112 ","question":"How does a healthy foal normally sleep? ","answer":"On its side   "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1064 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"What is the term for the type of vision where the horse sees the same scene with both eyes? ","answer":"Binocular  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1065 easy H1-23/FCH153 ","question":"What sound acts as a warning signal between horses? ","answer":"Snort  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1066 easy TH183/HH/HIH/CCS books ","question":"Name 2 vices that are quickly and often copied by other horses. ","answer":"Cribbing, weaving, wood chewing, pawing  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1067 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"What is monocular vision? ","answer":"Ability to see separate objects with each eye at the same time  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1068 easy HS5 ","question":"The modern horse must depend on man for his what? ","answer":"Safety 	(also accept food, water, shelter, or other reasonable answers)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1069 easy HS7 ","question":"Why shouldn't you punish a horse for shying? ","answer":"Because with its power of association, it would blame the object for the punishment and it might develop the habit of shying at every strange object  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1070 easy H3-34 ","question":"What is the soft, welcoming noise made by a content horse? ","answer":"Nicker  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1071 easy H1-9 ","question":"When a horse lowers its head, licks, and makes chewing motions it's showing what? ","answer":"Cooperation or submission      	(accept either)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1072 easy HH4 ","question":"What do you call a horse that refuses to leave a group of other horses? ","answer":"Herd bound  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1073 easy HH4 ","question":"Which vice is characterized by biting or setting the teeth against the fence or some other object while sucking air? ","answer":"Cribbing  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1074 easy H1-9 ","question":"What does the term "body language" mean? ","answer":"The way horses use their bodies to show other horses or people how they feel    "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1075 easy HIH1220-1 ","question":"A horse has a hard time focusing clearly on objects, but they are very good at detecting what? ","answer":"Movement  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1076 easy HIH1220-2/FCH152 ","question":"What is the term for a horse that's being disobedient by repeatedly turning back towards the barn as its being ridden away? ","answer":"Barn sour  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1077 easy HIH320-1/FCH376 ","question":"The horse has 2 choices in response to fear.  What are they? ","answer":"Fight or flight  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1078 easy HIH1120-1 ","question":"Why do horses want to stay together and not leave other horses? ","answer":"Herd instinct     (a group can protect themselves from predators much better than a single horse) "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1079 easy HS4/TH182 ","question":"An acquired habit that's annoying or that may interfere with the horse's usefulness is called what? ","answer":"Vice  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1080 easy HS34 ","question":"What is the name of the vice where the horse constantly paces or circles around its stall? ","answer":"Stall walking    "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1081 easy TH182 ","question":"Describe a cow kick. ","answer":"Horse kicks with a forward and sidewards motion"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1082 easy TH182 ","question":"When a horse kicks with a forward and sideward motion, it is called what? ","answer":"Cow kick  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1083 easy FCH385 ","question":"A horse that objects to being cinched up is referred to as being what? ","answer":"Cinchbound, girthbound, cold-backed, or cinchy	 (accept any)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1084 easy TH678 ","question":"What is the proper term for the "boss mare" or most dominant horse in a herd? ","answer":"Alpha  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1085 easy TH182 ","question":"What behavior is often displayed when two strange horses stand nose to nose? ","answer":"Striking, grunting, or squealing biting, nipping 	(accept any)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1086 easy FCH385 ","question":"What is a cinchbound horse? ","answer":"One that objects to being cinched up  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1087 easy ES56/HIH1220-1 ","question":"Which type of vision is a horse using when he looks at something head on? ","answer":"Binocular  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1089 easy FCH376/HH/CCS/HIH various ","question":"Eyelids wide open, flared nostrils, snorting, tail tucked between legs, balking, shying, and a whinny of distress are all signs of what? ","answer":"Fright  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1090 easy TH121/HIH1220-2 ","question":"Horses have very good hearing.  What do they do with their ears to help localize the source of the sounds they hear? ","answer":"Turn ears toward the direction of the sound  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1091 easy ES64/HIH1220-2 ","question":"Give a reason why horses may react to sounds that people can't hear. ","answer":"Horses can hear sounds that people can't; horses can move their ears and hear in almost any direction"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1092 easy H1-9 ","question":"How does a horse show its dominant position within a herd? ","answer":"Pinning ears, baring teeth, biting, turning rear toward other horse, kicking or threatening to kick, aggression  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1093 easy H1-9 ","question":"How does a horse show that it's willing to cooperate with the trainer? ","answer":"Lowers head, licks lips, and makes chewing motions     (accept any)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1094 easy HIH1240-7 ","question":"In problem solving intelligence tests, does the horse place high, medium, or low? ","answer":"Low  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1095 easy HIH1220-1/HS5/TH124/ES ","question":"Name 2 areas where a horse does not see anything. ","answer":"Directly in front, directly behind, over its head/neck/back, under head, directly downward      (accept any)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1096 easy HIH320-1 ","question":"What is a horse's primary defense? ","answer":"Flight (running away)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1097 easy HS5 ","question":"As far as behavior is concerned, what is the most important feature of the head? ","answer":"Eye  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1098 easy H1-9 ","question":"What is the term for the way horses use their bodies to show other horses or people how they feel? ","answer":"Body language  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1099 easy HS5/TH124 ","question":"The horse can see anything behind him that's not narrower than his what? ","answer":"Body  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1100 easy HIH320-1 ","question":"In natural conditions, horses demonstrate few vices.  What is it about stalls and stabling that promotes the development of these vices? ","answer":"Boredom  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1101 easy HS4/TH183 ","question":"What is a cribber? ","answer":"A horse that bites or sets its teeth against an object while sucking air    "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1102 easy TH183/HS4 ","question":"What is cribbing? ","answer":"Biting or setting teeth against an object while sucking air  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1103 easy HIH320-1 ","question":"The horse's first reaction to strange and frightening objects it to what? ","answer":"Panic and/or run away  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1104 easy TH137/H1-8,9 ","question":"How do you read your horse's intentions as you approach it? ","answer":"By watching its head and ears"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1105 easy HS4 ","question":"What does herd bound mean? ","answer":"A horse who refuses to leave a group of other horses  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1106 easy HS54 ","question":"Why should you never punish your horse when you're angry? ","answer":"Your punishment will be too severe  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1107 easy HH54 ","question":"Why is it important when you have to punish a horse, that you do it immediately? ","answer":"He won't understand why he's being punished if you wait  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1108 easy HH4 ","question":"Describe head shy. ","answer":"Horse that's sensitive about the head or jerks away when touched on the head  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1109 easy HIH320-1 ","question":"What prompts the horse's immediate instinct to kick or run? ","answer":"Fear  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1110 easy HH4 ","question":"How soon should you punish a misbehaving horse? ","answer":"Immediately or within 3 seconds  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1111 easy HH51 ","question":"What does the horse's instinct tell it to do when afraid? ","answer":"Kick or run  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1112 easy TH182/HS4 ","question":"What is the definition of a vice? ","answer":"A bad or annoying habit OR an acquired habit that's annoying or that may interfere with the usefulness of the horse  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"easy","number":"1113 easy H1-9/TH137 ","question":"What does it mean if a horse has its ears pinned back? ","answer":"Anger or aggression  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1114 medium DET189 ","question":"What is the loud, prolonged call of a horse? ","answer":"Neigh  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1115 medium FCH382/DET34 ","question":"In reference to actions of the horse, what are 2 ways the term "bolting" can be used? ","answer":"Gulping food rapidly; charging forward OR running off  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1116 medium HIH1220-1 ","question":"What survival advantage does the horse have because of its monocular vision? ","answer":"Monocular vision allows the horse to detect predators from either side without turning its head    (particularly important while grazing)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1117 medium FCH408 ","question":"Name a vice associated with head nodding. ","answer":"Weaving  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1118 medium DET179 ","question":"What is the menace reflex?  ","answer":"When the horse automatically closes the eye when a hand is moved toward the eye"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1119 medium FCH375/DET68 ","question":"What is coprophagia?","answer":"Eating feces (manure)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1120 medium FCH153/DET253 ","question":"What sound does a horse make in response to anger? ","answer":"Squeal  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1121 medium FCH389/TH387 ","question":"The curling of the upper lip, common behavior by stallions when teasing mares, is called what? ","answer":"Flehmen reflex "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1122 medium TH673 ","question":"What is ï¿½ingestive behaviorï¿½? ","answer":"Eating or drinking     "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1123 medium HS15 ","question":"What has been a prime feature of the horse's ability to survive? ","answer":"Monocular vision OR its ability to see objects on either side at the same time  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1124 medium HS5 ","question":"Give one reason why a horse may shy at unfamiliar objects.  ","answer":"Faulty vision or natural instinct "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1125 medium FCH401 ","question":"What term is used when a horse drops partially chewed food from his mouth?","answer":"Quidding  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1126 medium HIH1220-1 ","question":"2 part question:  Describe where the object is that a horse is focusing on when he raises his head and when he lowers his head. ","answer":"Raises head - focusing on nearby object;       lowers head - focusing on faraway object  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1127 medium FCH371 ","question":"In general, what is the most effective way to stop a vice before it becomes a habit? ","answer":"Determine and remove the cause"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1128 medium FCH401 ","question":"What type of behavior would be exhibited by a gelding that is described as a ï¿½rigï¿½ or ï¿½proud-cutï¿½ horse?  ","answer":"Stallion-like behavior  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1129 medium TH182 ","question":"When is a horse most apt to strike? ","answer":"When in nose to nose contact with another horse  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1130 medium DET211 ","question":"What is indicated by the behavioral term pica? ","answer":"Eating unnatural substances such as dirt, feces, bones, wood, hair, etc. (additional info:  geophagia, coprophagia, osteophagia, lignophagia, trichopagia)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1131 medium FCH374 ","question":"A strap buckled around the neck in a way that will compress the larynx when the head is flexed is a common remedy for what vice? ","answer":"Cribbing  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1132 medium FCH376 ","question":"If a horse is afraid of something and is unable to run away from the source of fear, what 2 options does he have? ","answer":"Fight or submission   "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1133 medium HIH1220-1 ","question":"Explain the difference between monocular and binocular vision. ","answer":"Monocular vision - sees a different object with each eye; 
Binocular vision - looks at the same object with both eyes"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1134 medium FCH392 ","question":"What is head nodding? ","answer":"Vice where the horse rhythmically nods its head     (either up and down or back and forth)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1135 medium FCH390 ","question":"In reference to a horse's behavior, what does ï¿½freezingï¿½ mean? ","answer":"Horse refuses to move     (becomes stiff or immobile)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1136 medium FCH382 ","question":"Explain the difference between bolting and shying. ","answer":"Bolting - horse goes forward;   shying - horse goes to the side "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1137 medium TH182 ","question":"What is the term for the action when a horse lashes out with a front leg when mad? ","answer":"Striking  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1138 medium FCH375 ","question":"What general age horse is usually involved in tail chewing? ","answer":"Foals or young horses	 (accept either)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1140 medium ES64 ","question":"What is the tactile sense? ","answer":"Sense of touch  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1141 medium TH183 ","question":"In reference to vices, what is the term used when a horse consciously squeezes the handler against the stall wall? ","answer":"Crowding  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1142 medium DET71 ","question":"If a horse has the ability needed to work cattle, the horse is said to possess what? ","answer":"Cow sense or cow 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1143 medium FCH372 ","question":"What is the most important thing for you to provide your horse in order to prevent him from stall kicking, cribbing, and wood chewing? ","answer":"Regular exercise 	(also accept plenty of forage)   "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1144 medium HIH405-3 ","question":"What is a horse doing when he is "quidding"? ","answer":"Dropping partially chewed feed from his mouth  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1145 medium FCH382 ","question":"2 part question:  In reference to vices, what is weaving and where is it commonly seen? ","answer":"Rocking body from side to side while standing still; seen in stall or along fence line  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1146 medium TH183 ","question":"Charging is seen most commonly is what sex of horse? ","answer":"Stallion  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1147 medium TH183 ","question":"The placement of several large, round rocks in a horse's feed tub helps to decrease the incidence of what vice? ","answer":"Bolting feed  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"medium","number":"1148 medium DET71 ","question":"What does it mean if a horse is said to have "a lot of cow"? ","answer":"Horse has mental abilities needed to work cattle "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1149 hard DET109 ","question":"Describe the Flehmen response. ","answer":"Horse raises its head and curls its upper lip back"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1150 hard TH676 ","question":"Horses in a group are likely to run simply because another horse is running.  If the running is not in response to fright, what type of behavior is it? ","answer":"Mimicry or allelomimetic behavior 	(accept either)   "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1151 hard TH676 ","question":"In herds, the mimicking of another horse's actions is called what? ","answer":"Mimicry or allelomimetic behavior	 (accept either)       "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1152 hard FCH370 ","question":"2 part question:  What is an ï¿½escape viceï¿½ and give 2 examples? ","answer":"Vice demonstrated when a horse is unhappy in a certain place and would like to escape; examples:  pawing, pacing, trying to jump out of stall or paddock, weaving, head nodding"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1153 hard FCH372,407 ","question":"What is the name for the oral vice in which a horse sticks its tongue out the side of the mouth? ","answer":"Tongue displacement  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1154 hard TH673 ","question":"What is the term for the type of behavior when horses huddle together during inclement weather? ","answer":"Contactual behavior      (also accept herding)"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1155 hard HIH1240 ","question":"How is behavior shaped? ","answer":"By reinforcing each successive step in the desired direction    "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1156 hard TH387 ","question":"2 part question:  What is the common name for the olfactory reflex and describe it? ","answer":"Flehmen;   when the horse smells something and then extends its neck or raises its head upwards while curling the upper lip back "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1157 hard HIH710-5 ","question":"What is the common negative behavioral consequence for failing to provide your horse with adequate roughage? ","answer":"Horse will develop vices "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1158 hard TH675 ","question":"What is the proper name for the behavior that involves giving of care and attention between mare and foal? ","answer":"Epimeletic  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1159 hard FCH248 ","question":"Abnormal maternal aggression towards the foal is commonly caused by what? ","answer":"Painful udder  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1161 hard DET97 ","question":"What is epimeletic behavior? ","answer":"Giving of care and attention between two horses"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"hard","number":"1162 hard ES58 ","question":"What is the range of a horse's binocular vision? ","answer":"About 65 degrees directly in front of its head    "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1163 bonus FCH153 ","question":"Give 3 physical signs that a horse is afraid. ","answer":"Eyelids wide open/showing white of eye, snorting, whinny of distress, nostrils flared, tail tucked between legs, flight, raised/flinging head  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1164 bonus ES58-60 ","question":"Name 3 of the horseï¿½s blind spots. ","answer":"Directly in front of horse's head, directly behind the horse, under head/neck, over head/neck/back"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1165 bonus HIH710-8 ","question":"What are 3 ways to avoid aggressive behavior when group feeding horses? ","answer":"Use separate feeders, ensure open space, space feeders far apart, use extra feeders  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1166 bonus TH182 ","question":"Name the 3 classifications of vices. ","answer":"Dangerous to man, dangerous to horse, nuisance    (also accept oral and escape) "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1168 bonus ES61 ","question":"Name 3 things the horse uses its sense of smell for. ","answer":"Locate food, ensure quality of food or water, identify other horses, identify people, identify objects, smell potential predators or other dangers, identify marked territory of other horses or herds, initiate sexual or breeding behavior  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1169 bonus FCH403 ","question":"Name 3 stimuli that trigger the response of shivering. ","answer":"Cold, fear, excitement, illness, pain, fever  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1170 bonus HIH220-4 ","question":"What 3 things determine the front & rear vision of the horse? ","answer":"Size of eye, position of eye, width of head, width of body  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1171 bonus HIH1220-2/ES65 ","question":"Name 4 sensitive places on a horse. ","answer":"Eyes, ears, nose, muzzle, mouth, feet, legs, neck, shoulders, withers, belly, ribs, flank  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1172 bonus TH37/H1-9 ","question":"Name 3 things that will tell the mood of a horse. ","answer":"Showing white around the eyes, position of the ears, nostrils flaring, mouth/bearing teeth, ears, tense muscles, tail swishing/wringing, licking, chewing      (accept any reasonable answer)  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1173 bonus TH182-83 ","question":"Name 3 vices that are dangerous to man. ","answer":"Biting, nipping, kicking, striking, charging, crowding, rearing, bucking, shying, bolting (running away), halter pulling  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1174 bonus TH182-83 ","question":"Name 3 vices that are dangerous to the horse. ","answer":"Cribbing (aerophagia), wood chewing (lignophagia), mane/tail chewing, eating dirt (geophagia), eating feces (coprophagia), bolting food, fighting, shying, halter pulling  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1175 bonus TH184 ","question":"Name 3 nuisance vices. ","answer":"Weaving, stall walking, head nodding, tongue displacement, pawing, mane/tail rubbing  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1176 bonus TH182 ","question":"Name 3 fight or flight vices of the horse. ","answer":"Lunging, bolting, aggression, biting, nipping, kicking, striking, exaggerated alarm reaction, balking, snapping, shying, startle reaction, crowding, rearing, charging  "},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1178 bonus FCH376-77 ","question":"Aggression is one of the most common behavioral problems in horses.  Name 3 aggressive behaviors. ","answer":"Lunging, biting, kicking, crowding, striking, snapping, rearing, baring teeth, pinned ears, swishing tail"},
{"category":"BEHAVIOR","level":"bonus","number":"1179 bonus ES55","question":"Name 4 of the 5 senses of the horse.                        ","answer":"Sight, smell, hearing, touch and taste "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1180 easy HS21/TH76","question":"What is the term for a male donkey?","answer":"Jack"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1181 easy HS21/TH76","question":"What is a mule?","answer":"Cross between a jack & a mare"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1182 easy HIH158-1,152B-1","question":"What breed was developed by the Nez Perce Indians?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1183 easy TH61/HH59/HIH175B-1","question":"What are the colors of the Welsh Pony?","answer":"Any color except broken/spotted/pinto	 (also accept - all solid colors)  "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1184 easy HIH210-3","question":"Recording an animal from registered parents in the breed association is called what?","answer":"Registration"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1185 easy HH56/TH18/HIH150,153B-1","question":"What is the oldest purebred breed?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1186 easy HH58/TH20/HIH153-1,168B-1","question":"Where did the Quarter Horse originate?","answer":"United States (eastern US)           	(accept either general or specific)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1187 easy HIH712B/HH58/TH40","question":"Where in the US did the Tennessee Walking Horse originate?","answer":"Tennessee"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1188 easy HH59/TH61","question":"What is the primary use of the POA?","answer":"Children's mounts"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1189 easy HH56/TH12/HIH151-2","question":"Name a breed used as a foundation for developing many modern breeds.","answer":"Arabian, Thoroughbred, Morgan (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1190 easy HH9/DET168","question":"What is a light horse?","answer":"Horse used for riding or driving OR saddle horse OR all breeds except draft"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1191 easy HIH150-1,153B-1","question":"Who were the first breeders of Arabians?","answer":"Arabian (Bedouin) tribesmen"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1192 easy HH56/HIH158-1/TH32","question":"Which breed was pictured in cave drawings in Europe & China over 2000 years ago?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1193 easy HH56/HIH158-1,152B-1","question":"What breed has its headquarters in Moscow, Idaho?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1194 easy HH56/HIH150-1,153B-1","question":"Where did the Arabian horse originate?","answer":"Arabia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1195 easy HH56/HIH150-1","question":"What color skin does the Arabian always have?","answer":"Dark"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1196 easy TH68/HH56","question":"Where did the Clydesdale originate?","answer":"Scotland (near river Clyde)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1197 easy TH72/DET105/HH57","question":"What is feathering?","answer":"Long, silky hair on the lower legs"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1198 easy HH/TH/HIH, etc.","question":"Name 2 breeds of pony.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Connemara, POA, Quarter Pony, New Forest, Dales, Exmoor, American Sport Pony, Chincoteague, Dartmoor, Fells, Gotland, Hackney	 (accept any pony breed)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1199 easy HH59/TH58","question":"Where did the Shetland pony originate?","answer":"Shetland Isles 	(Info only -- off the coast of Scotland)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1200 easy TH70/HH57","question":"Which draft breed is famous for being used in multi-horse hitches, especially one advertising a brewery?","answer":"Clydesdale"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1201 easy TH59/HH59","question":"What are the colors of the Shetland pony?","answer":"All colors 	(both solid & broken/spotted/pinto)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1202 easy HH58/HIH156-1,169B-1","question":"Where did the American Saddlebred Horse originate?","answer":"United States 	(Kentucky & surrounding states)			(accept either general or specific)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1203 easy TH59/HH59","question":"What is one of the primary uses of the Shetland pony?","answer":"Children's mounts, driving"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1204 easy TH59/HH59","question":"What is a distinguishing characteristic of the Shetland pony?","answer":"Small size"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1205 easy HIH110-5","question":"What is the term for an animal of unknown breeding or ancestry?","answer":"Grade"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1206 easy HIH151-1","question":"Where did the Morgan originate?","answer":"United States (New England)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1207 easy HIH160B-1/HH56","question":"Which breed was developed from small English & Dutch mine horses?","answer":"Miniature Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1208 easy TH137/HH56","question":"What is the term for a horse whose parents are recorded in the same breed association?","answer":"Purebred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1209 easy HH56/DET144","question":"What do you call a horse of Eastern or Oriental blood?","answer":"Hot blooded"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1210 easy HH56/TH128","question":"What is a pedigree?","answer":"Written record of an animal's ancestry"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1211 easy HH56/TH137","question":"What is the term for a horse that has parents of different breeds?","answer":"Crossbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1212 easy HH40/DET62","question":"What is a combination horse?","answer":"One used for both riding & driving"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1213 easy HH40/DET127","question":"What is the term for a horse ridden to a hunt meet?","answer":"Hack"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1214 easy HH9/DET168","question":"Any horse used primarily for riding - all breeds except draft breeds - is called what?","answer":"Light horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1215 easy HH56/TH69","question":"What do you call a horse with ancestry from the draft breeds?","answer":"Cold blooded"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1216 easy HIH152-1","question":"Which breed nods his head in rhythm with his walk?","answer":"Tennessee Walker"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1217 easy HIH154-1,160B-1","question":"What is the maximum height of the American Miniature Horse?","answer":"34 inches"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1218 easy HH65/HIH210-1","question":"Which breed excels in distance riding?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1219 easy HIH157-1,173B-1","question":"Which breed is represented by the breed association known as the Jockey Club?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1220 easy TH32,61/HH59","question":"Mottled skin, striped hooves, & sclera around the eye are all characteristics of which breed?","answer":"Appaloosa OR POA"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1221 easy HH40/DET127","question":"What is a hack?","answer":"Horse ridden to a hunt meet"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1222 easy TH61/HH59","question":"Which breed of pony is colored similar to an Appaloosa?","answer":"POA"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1223 easy HIH210-1","question":"Which breed is noted for its great endurance?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1224 easy HIH160-1","question":"Which breed is used primarily for harness racing?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1225 easy HIH160-1","question":"Which breed does the US Trotting Association represent?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1226 easy HIH154-1,160B-1","question":"What breed of horse is registered on a temporary basis until they reach 5 years of age?","answer":"Miniature Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1227 easy HIH173B-1/TH22","question":"What is the average height of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"16 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1228 easy HIH173B-1/TH22","question":"What is the average weight of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"1000 pounds"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1229 easy HIH171B-1,TH31","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average height of the Standardbred?","answer":"14.2 - 16.2 hands	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1230 easy TH31","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average weight of the Standardbred?","answer":"850 - 1150 pounds	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1231 easy TH35/HIH151-1,162B-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average height of the Morgan?","answer":"14.1 - 15.1 hands	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1232 easy TH36/HIH151,1,162B-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average weight of the Morgan?","answer":"1000 - 1200 pounds 	(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1233 easy HIH170-1,158B-2/TH61","question":"What is the main use of the Hackney Pony?","answer":"Driving"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1234 easy HIH170-1,158B-2","question":"What is the most common color of the Hackney?","answer":"Bay		"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1235 easy HIH163-1,155B-1","question":"What color is an American Cream Draft?","answer":"Cream color with white mane & tail (and amber eyes)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1236 easy TH76/HS21/HIH156B-1","question":"Explain the difference in parentage of a mule and a hinny.","answer":"Mule is a cross between a jack & a mare; hinny is a cross between a stallion & a jenny/jennet"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1237 easy HIH152,1,172B-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Tennessee Walker?","answer":"14.2 to 17 hands	 (accept any number within this range)    "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1238 easy HIH186-1/TH17","question":"Which breed must have an ancestry of 50% or higher of Arabian blood?","answer":"Half-Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1239 easy HH56/DET38","question":"The owner of the mare at the time of breeding is called what?","answer":"Breeder"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1240 easy TH75/HS21/HIH156B-1","question":"What do you call a female donkey?","answer":"Jenny or jennet"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1241 easy TH75/HS21/HIH156B-1","question":"What do you call a cross between a stallion & a jennet?","answer":"Hinny"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1242 easy TH68/HH58","question":"Where did the Percheron originate?","answer":"France (LaPerche province)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1243 easy TH68/HH59","question":"What are the colors of the Percheron?","answer":"Black & gray"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1244 easy HIH168B-1","question":"What is the most common color of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"Sorrel (also accept chestnut) "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1245 easy HIH156-1,169B-1/TH39","question":"What are the color restrictions of the American Saddlebred Horse?","answer":"No color restrictions"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1246 easy HIH157-1","question":"What do the Darley Arabian, Byerly Turk, & Godolphin Barb/Arabian have in common?","answer":"Foundation sires of the Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1247 easy HIH160-1","question":"Over 60% of Standardbreds are which color?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1248 easy HIH153-1","question":"What is the average height of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"15 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1249 easy HIH157-1","question":"Which breed excels in dressage, polo, jumping & cross-country?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1250 easy HIH150,210-2,153B-1","question":"What is one primary use of the Arabian?","answer":"Endurance, show, pleasure, stock, racing	 (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1251 easy HH56/HIH158-1/TH32","question":"In which country were horses with the colorful characteristics of the Appaloosa first seen?","answer":"China	 (based on Chinese art dating from 500 B.C.)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1252 easy HIH153-1","question":"Which breed is noted for its cow sense?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1253 easy HIH920-5","question":"What is recognized as the universal birthdate for many breeds?","answer":"January 1st"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1254 easy TH16/H1-35","question":"What is generally considered the minimum height for a horse?","answer":"Over 14.2 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1255 easy HIH186-1","question":"What is an Anglo-Arab?","answer":"Horse that's half Arabian & half Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1256 easy HS21/TH76","question":"What is the result of breeding a horse to a donkey?","answer":"A mule (also accept hinny)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1257 easy HIH158-1,152B-1,167B-2","question":"What breed characteristically has vertically striped hooves?","answer":"Appaloosa or POA"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1258 easy TH49/HIH164B-2","question":"The breed description of a Palomino describes the ideal color to be what?","answer":"The color of a newly minted gold coin"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1259 easy TH60/HH58/HIH167B-1","question":"Where did the POA originate?","answer":"Mason City, Iowa"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1260 easy TH58/HH59","question":"What is the height limit for a Shetland pony?","answer":"46 inches (11.2 hands)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1261 easy TH137/HH56","question":"What is the term for a group of horses having common origin & possessing certain traits that are passed on to their offspring?","answer":"Breed"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1262 easy HH56/TH15?hih220","question":"What do you call characteristics of a breed that distinguish it from other breeds?","answer":"Breed characteristics"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1263 easy TH61/HH59/HIH167B-1","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the POA?","answer":"46 - 56 inches (11.2 - 14 hands)		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1264 easy HH56/TH58","question":"What are the disqualifications for registering the Shetland?","answer":"Over 46 inches in height"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1265 easy TH77/HH56","question":"Who was the first breeder of mules in North America?","answer":"George Washington"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1266 easy HIH150-1,153B-2","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Arabian?","answer":"14.1 to 15.1 hands		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1267 easy HIH154-1","question":"How much does an average Miniature Horse foal weigh at birth?","answer":"15 - 30 pounds 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1268 easy HIH154-1","question":"What is the average height for a newborn Miniature Horse?","answer":"18 inches"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1269 easy HIH159-1,163B-1","question":"What is the difference between a Paint & a Pinto?","answer":"Pinto is a spotted horse;   Paint can only have Thoroughbred, Quarter Horse or Paint breeding"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1270 easy TH77/HIH156B-1","question":"What is the main use of the Mammoth Jack?","answer":"Crossbreeding with horses to produce mules  "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1271 easy H1-35/TH58/DET217","question":"An equine that matures at less than 58 inches (14.2 hands) at the withers is called what?","answer":"Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1272 easy TH29/HH59/HIH171B","question":"What is the term for a Standardbred that races with a diagonal gait?","answer":"Trotter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1273 easy TH/HH/HIH, etc","question":"Name a breed developed from the need for a comfortable, ground-covering, smooth-gaited riding & driving horse","answer":"American Saddlebred, Tennessee Walking Horse, Missouri Foxtrotter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1274 easy TH32/HIH158-1,153-1","question":"What is the origination of the name "Appaloosa"?","answer":"A slurring of the words "a Palouse"		 (referring to the Palouse region where it was developed)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1275 easy HIH814-1,175B-1","question":"All horses registered in this breed trace back to horses that roamed free on the hills of Wales before the time of the Romans.  Which breed is it?","answer":"Welsh Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1276 easy HIH174-1,159B-1","question":"Which breed is world famous because of their connection with the Spanish Riding School?","answer":"Lipizzan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1277 easy HIH174-1,159B-1","question":"What is the predominant color of the LIpizzan?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1278 easy HIH174-1,159B-1","question":"Where is the site of the Spanish Riding School?","answer":"Vienna, Austria"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1279 easy HH56-57","question":"Name 2 colors of the Clydesdale.","answer":"Bay, chestnut, black, roan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1280 easy HIH151-1,162B-1","question":"Who was Figure?","answer":"Foundation sire of the Morgan breed     (later called Justin Morgan)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1281 easy HH56/HIH159-3","question":"Where is the American Paint Horse headquarters?","answer":"Fort Worth, Texas"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1282 easy HIH158-1,152B-1","question":"Which Indian tribe is believed to be the first to practice selective breeding?","answer":"Nez Perce"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1283 easy HIH161-1,165B-1","question":"Where did the Paso Fino originate?","answer":"Spain    "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1284 easy HIH169-2","question":"What breed - bred as pack ponies - is native to the upper dales of Yorkshire?","answer":"Dales Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1285 easy HIH151-2,162B-1","question":"Who is the foundation sire of the Morgan breed?","answer":"Figure 	(additional info ï¿½ later known as Justin Morgan)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1286 easy TH17/HIH150-1","question":"What is the average weight of an Arabian?","answer":"800 - 1000 pounds 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1287 easy HIH154B-1/TH28","question":"What marking is required for a grulla or red dun to be eligible for registration by the International Buckskin Horse Association?","answer":"Dorsal stripe"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1288 easy H1-34/DET84","question":"What is the general term for large, heavy-boned work horses that usually weigh around 2000 pounds & stand 17-18 hands tall?","answer":"Draft horses "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1289 easy H4-34/DET144","question":"What is the term for a horse used to chase foxes & jump over fences?","answer":"Hunter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1290 easy HIH154-1","question":"At what age can a Miniature Horse be permanently registered?","answer":"5"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1429 easy H1-34/DET32","question":"Which breed is the term "blood horse" synonymous with?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1430 easy HIH153B-2","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, which breed consistently outlives other breeds?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1431 easy HH59","question":"Which breed is known as the breed of blacks & grays?","answer":"Percheron"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1432 easy HIH154B-1","question":"Name 2 colors registered in the International Buckskin Horse Association.","answer":"Buckskin, dun, grulla, red dun"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1433 easy HIH151B-1","question":"What is the average height of an American Warmblood?","answer":"16 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1434 easy HIH160-1","question":"What are the 2 racing gaits of the Standardbred?","answer":"Trot & pace"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1435 easy H1-34/TH55/FCH405","question":"What is the term for a horse that was domesticated & then became wild?","answer":"Feral"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1436 easy HH7/TH83","question":"What is the term for a horse with a heavy, coarse tail?","answer":"Broomtail or bangtail"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1438 easy TH59/HIH167B-1","question":"Who was Black Hand?","answer":"Foundation sire of the POA"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1439 easy HIH153-1,168B-1","question":"How did the Quarter Horse get its name?","answer":"From its ability to sprint a quarter mile"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1440 easy TH61/HIH175B-1","question":"What is a Welsh Cob?","answer":"Larger version of the Welsh Pony      (addtl info:  over 13.2 hands with no upper height limit)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1441 easy HIH154B-1","question":"What is the minimum height for registering a horse with the International Buckskin Horse Association?","answer":"14 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1442 easy HIH167B-2/BEG110-3L","question":"Identify the pony described by the following characteristics:  Mottled skin around muzzle, eyes & genital area, white sclera encircling the eyes, striped hooves & one of 7 approved coat patterns.","answer":"POA or Pony of the Americas"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1443 easy HIH175B-1/TH61","question":"Name a color pattern that is NOT permitted in the Welsh Pony breed?","answer":"Spotted/broken/pinto "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1444 easy H1-34/TH16","question":"You are looking at a sale poster for a pretty chestnut mare. The information states that the animal is 57 inches tall. Is the mare a horse or pony?","answer":"Pony ï¿½ the dividing line is 58 inches."},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1445 easy HIH153B-1","question":"Who were the Bedouins?","answer":"Arabian tribesmen who were the first breeders of the Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1446 easy HIH168B-2","question":"Where is the Quarter Horse breed association located?","answer":"Amarillo, Texas"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1447 easy TH36/HIH151-1,162B-1","question":"Name 2 colors or patterns that are ineligible for registration in the Morgan breed","answer":"White above hocks except for face markings, spotted patterns, Appaloosa patterns, blue eyes"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1448 easy DET114","question":"What color is the Friesian?","answer":"Black    (solid black with no white marking preferred)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1449 easy TH68","question":"How many major draft breeds are found in the US?","answer":"5 (additional info:  Clydesdale, Shire, Belgian, Percheron, & Suffolk)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1450 easy TH22","question":"What 2 famous Thoroughbred race horses were both known by the nickname "Big Red"?","answer":"Man oï¿½War & Secretariat"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1451 easy TH72","question":"Which draft breed is generally the tallest?","answer":"Shire"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1452 easy TH72","question":"What is the most common color of the Shire?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1453 easy TH78","question":"What is a burro?","answer":"Small feral donkey of the American Southwest OR Spanish term for donkey"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1454 easy TH78","question":"The burro's ancestors came to North America with whom?","answer":"Spanish"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1455 easy TH61","question":"What is the most common color of the Welsh Mountain Pony?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1457 easy TH65","question":"Where did the Connemara originate?","answer":"Ireland    (County Galway)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1458 easy DET58","question":"What breed of horse is always bay?","answer":"Cleveland Bay"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1459 easy DET58","question":"What is the reason for disqualification when registering a Cleveland Bay?","answer":"If it's not bay"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1460 easy HIH179-1,166B-1","question":"Which breed was first imported from Peru in the mid-1960's?","answer":"Peruvian Paso"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1461 easy HIH163-1,155B-1","question":"Which breed is the only draft breed that originated in America?","answer":"American Cream Draft"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1462 easy HIH155-1","question":"Describe the color of the Golden American Saddlebred?","answer":"Body color golden with white or flaxen mane & tail"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1463 easy DET105/HH57","question":"The long hair around a horse's fetlock - common in draft breeds - is referred to as what?","answer":"Feathers or feathering"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1464 easy HIH220-1","question":"What is the basic difference between breeds?","answer":"Amount & location of muscling & fat on the skeleton"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1465 easy HIH184-1,175B-1","question":"What is the upper height limit for a Welsh Cob?","answer":"There is none"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1466 easy HIH158B-1","question":"Which breed was crossed with the Hackney horse to produce the Hackney pony?","answer":"Welsh Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1467 easy HIH163B-1","question":"A horse of Paint breeding who does not meet the color requirement may be registered in the Paint division known as what?","answer":"Breeding Stock"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1468 easy HIH171B-1","question":"Today's Standardbreds are able to trot or pace at what speed?","answer":"30 mph"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1469 easy HIH156-1","question":"Where is the headquarters for the breed organization of the American Saddlebred?","answer":"Lexington, Kentucky   (located at the Kentucky Horse Park)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1470 easy HIH158-1/TH2","question":"One of the characteristics of the Appaloosa is a striped hoof.  Which way do the stripes run on their hooves?","answer":"Vertical or up & down"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1471 easy H1-35/TH58","question":"A type of horse under 14.2 hands is called what?","answer":"Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1472 easy HH7/TH83","question":"What is a broomtail?","answer":"A horse with a heavy, coarse tail OR a Western range horse OR ill-kept horse of inferior quality"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1473 easy HH56/TH137","question":"What is a grade animal?","answer":"Unregistered horse or a horse with unknown ancestry"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1474 easy HH56/DET104","question":"What is the term for a group of animals within a breed that trace directly back to a common ancestor?","answer":"Family"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1475 easy HH56/TH69/DET61","question":"What does cold-blooded mean?","answer":"Draft horse breeding"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1476 easy HIH210-3","question":"What do you call a written record of an animal's ancestry that's issued by the registry association?","answer":"Registration certificate"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1477 easy HH59/TH61","question":"Referring to horse breeds, what do the letters POA mean?","answer":"Pony of the Americas"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1478 easy HH56/TH69","question":"What does hot-blooded mean?","answer":"Horse of Eastern or Oriental blood"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1479 easy HH59/TH61","question":"Where did the Welsh Pony originate?","answer":"Wales"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1480 easy HIH151B-1","question":"What is a Warmblood?","answer":"Horse that's a combination of hotblood & coldblood breeds"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1481 easy HH59/TH58","question":"What horse originated in the Shetland Isles?","answer":"Shetland pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1482 easy HIH157-1","question":"Where did the Thoroughbred originate?","answer":"England"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1483 easy H1-34/TH55","question":"What is a feral horse?","answer":"A wild horse OR horse that was domesticated & then became wild"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1484 easy HH56/TH61","question":"What is a written record of an animal's ancestry?  It may or may not be used to refer to a registration certificate?","answer":"Pedigree"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1485 easy HH56/TH137","question":"What is a crossbred?","answer":"Horse with parents of 2 different breeds"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1486 easy HIH152B-1","question":"What current breed was formerly known as the ï¿½Palouse horseï¿½?","answer":"Appaloosa				"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1487 easy HIH151B-1","question":"What type of horse is described as a combination of any breeds that are not 100% hot-blood or 100% cold-blood?","answer":"Warmblood						"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1488 easy TH36","question":"Two part:  The foundation sire for the Morgan breed was Figure.  Figure was known by what other name & how did he get that name?","answer":"Justin Morgan ï¿½ custom for that time was to give the horse the ownerï¿½s name         "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"easy","number":"1489 easy TH22","question":"What is the name for the famous Thoroughbred horse that was referred to as the original ï¿½Big Redï¿½?","answer":"Man O-War               "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1490 medium TH45","question":"Giving only one number, what is the average weight of the Galiceno?","answer":"600 - 700 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1491 medium TH45","question":"Galicenos have been imported into the US since 1959 from which country?","answer":"Mexico"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1492 medium TH45","question":"What are the colors of the Galiceno?","answer":"All solid colors 	(no pintos)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1493 medium TH53","question":"What was the original name of the American White Horse?","answer":"American Albino"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1494 medium TH56","question":"Why was the Medicine Hat mustang especially favored by the Cheyenne Indians?","answer":"They were thought to have supernatural powers of protection & invincibility"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1495 medium TH55","question":"Which mustang registry was started to collect & preserve the records of horses tracing to those the Indians originally obtained from Spanish herds?","answer":"American Indian Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1496 medium TH57","question":"Where did the American Bashkir Curly originate?","answer":"United States 	(Additional info -- from 3 curly coated feral horses found in Nevada)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1497 medium TH57","question":"Where did the American Bashkir Curly get its name?","answer":"Named for the curly coated horses raised in the Bashkir region of the Ural Mountains of Russia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1498 medium TH58","question":"The Rangerbred or Colorado Ranger Horse is often confused with which breed?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1499 medium TH59/HIH167B-1","question":"Black Hand, the foundation sire of the POA, was the result of a cross between an Appaloosa mare & what type stallion?","answer":"Shetland pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1500 medium DET60","question":"What is a cob?","answer":"A short-legged, horse, built like a heavyweight hunter that is capable of carrying substantial weight"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1501 medium TH61","question":"Which breed is known as the ï¿½Prince of Poniesï¿½?","answer":"Hackney"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1502 medium TH64","question":"What percent of Hackney registrations each year are ponies?","answer":"95%"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1503 medium TH62","question":"Which breed originated in England from Norfolk Trotters & Thoroughbreds?","answer":"Hackney"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1504 medium TH66","question":"When was the Connemara first imported to the US?","answer":"1951"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1505 medium TH66","question":"In Ireland, the Connemara remains pony sized, but in the US, some are now over what height?","answer":"15 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1506 medium TH69","question":"Which draft breed is thought to be the only one with any Arabian or Barb blood?","answer":"Percheron"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1507 medium TH68,73","question":"Which 2 draft breeds do NOT have feathering on their legs?","answer":"Percheron & Suffolk"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1508 medium TH69","question":"Giving only one number, what is the general height of the draft breeds?","answer":"16 - 17 hands 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1509 medium TH69","question":"Giving only one number, what is the general weight for the draft breeds?","answer":"1600 - 2000 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1510 medium Th73","question":"Where did the Suffolk originate?","answer":"Suffolk, England"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1511 medium TH73","question":"What is the color of the Suffolk?","answer":"Chestnut or sorrel"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1512 medium TH74","question":"Where did the Haflinger originate?","answer":"Austria (south Tyrol area)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1513 medium TH74","question":"Name the small, general-purpose mountain horse from Austria that resembles a small Belgian?","answer":"Haflinger"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1514 medium TH74/HIH167-2","question":"When was the Gotland Horse first imported to the US?","answer":"1957"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1515 medium TH74/HIH167-2","question":"Where did the Gotland Horse originate?","answer":"Sweden"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1516 medium TH75/HIH167-2","question":"Which breed served as a mount for the Goths & Vikings & can be traced as far back as the Stone Age?","answer":"Gotland    "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1517 medium TH76","question":"What is the term used for the feral donkeys of the American Southwest?","answer":"Burro"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1518 medium TH76","question":"Where does the name "donkey" come from?","answer":"The English word "dun" - which describes their usual color"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1519 medium TH78","question":"What is the general height of the burro or donkey?","answer":"40 - 50 inches		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1520 medium TH79","question":"Where did the Miniature Donkey originate?","answer":"Mediterranean area   OR  Sicily & Sardinia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1521 medium TH79","question":"What is the legend associated with the cross on the donkey's back?","answer":"That it's a reward for carrying Mary to Bethlehem & Jesus to Jerusalem"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1522 medium TH68","question":"Modern draft horses are descendants of what earlier group of horses?","answer":"The "Great Horse" OR knight's horses of the Middle Ages"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1523 medium TH75","question":"What is the common name for a female of the species Equus asinus?","answer":"Jenny or jennet"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1524 medium TH53","question":"In what state did the American White Horse originate?","answer":"Nebraska"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1525 medium TH55/HIH183-1,170B-1","question":"What is the first & oldest Mustang registry?","answer":"Spanish Mustang Registry"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1526 medium TH55/HIH183-1,170B-1","question":"Who were responsible for spreading the Spanish horses over the West?","answer":"American Indians   (Apaches)			Accept either"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1527 medium TH66","question":"Giving only one number, how tall is the Connemara Pony?","answer":"13 hands to over 15 hands 			(accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1528 medium TH45","question":"What is a Morab?","answer":"Cross between a Morgan & an Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1529 medium TH57","question":"What is the distinguishing characteristic of the Bashkir Curly?","answer":"Curly coat"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1530 medium TH65","question":"Which breed originated in County Galway, Ireland?","answer":"Connemara"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1531 medium TH65","question":"Connemaras are noted for what?","answer":"Jumping ability"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1532 medium HIH174-2,159B-1","question":"Which breed was developed by the Hapsburg family of Austria?","answer":"Lipizzan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1533 medium HIH167-2","question":"Which breed is considered a Swedish national treasure?","answer":"Gotland"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1535 medium HIH174-2","question":"During World War II, the Spanish Riding School was saved by the efforts of whom?","answer":"US Army OR General Patton OR Alois Podhajsky director of the Spanish Riding School"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1537 medium HIH166-1,174B-1","question":"Because of its elegant way of moving, the Trakehner (tra-KAY-ner) excels in what?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1538 medium HIH169-1","question":"Which breed was first recorded in the Doomsday book of 1085?","answer":"Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1539 medium HIH160-1,171B-1","question":"What is the name of the breed association for the Standardbred?","answer":"US Trotting Association OR USTA"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1540 medium HIH153-1,168B-1","question":"Which breed of horse is known for its ability to gain speed in a matter of seconds over short distances?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1541 medium TH55","question":"Name 2 feral breeds of horse or pony native to the US.","answer":"Mustang & Chincoteague Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1542 medium TH72","question":"Name 2 breeds of draft horse that are commonly seen with feathered legs.","answer":"Shire & Clydesdale"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1543 medium TH69/BEG110-1L","question":"Based on registry, which draft breed is the most numerous in the US?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1544 medium TH17","question":"In what area of the world did the Barb originate?","answer":"Northern Africa OR Barbary States"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1545 medium TH137","question":"According to the American Horse Council, what breed of horse is the most popular in the US?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1546 medium HIH156-1","question":"What breed registry is the oldest for an American breed of horse?  It was founded in 1891 in Louisville, Kentucky.","answer":"American Saddlebred Horse Association"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1547 medium TH84/HIH1910-1","question":"Where is the office of the American Horse Council located?","answer":"Washington, DC"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1549 medium TH58","question":"There are 2 types of Shetland pony.  What are they?","answer":"Island/classic & American/ modern"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1550 medium TH75","question":"What is a Spotted Ass?","answer":"Burro-sized ass that has spotted/pinto coat pattern "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1551 medium TH61","question":"What was the principal reason for the development of the POA?","answer":"To develop a medium-sized western-type pony that's small enough for children to ride & big enough for adults to ride & train"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1552 medium TH17","question":"Prior to 1908, the American Jockey Club registered 2 other breeds of horse besides the Thoroughbred.  What were they?","answer":"Arabian & Anglo-Arab"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1553 medium HIH174-2,159B-1","question":"What breed was threatened with extinction during World War II?","answer":"LIpizzan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1554 medium HIH159-1,163B-1","question":"What does APHA stand for?","answer":"American Paint Horse Association"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1555 medium TH73","question":"Cosmetically speaking, how does the Suffolk differ from the other 2 British draft breeds?","answer":"Suffolk doesn't have feathers on its legs"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1556 medium HIH159-2","question":"On which breed of horse could you find a "blue zone"?","answer":"Paint or Pinto"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1557 medium TH27","question":"Who was the first permanently registered Quarter Horse?","answer":"Wimpy"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1558 medium TH18","question":"What is the usual meaning of an asterisk used in front of a horse's registered name?","answer":"That it's an imported horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1559 medium TH74","question":"Name the most numerous light horse breed in Europe.","answer":"Hanoverian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1560 medium HIH174-1","question":"Describe the coloring of the Lipizzan from birth to maturity.","answer":"Born dark, gradually gets lighter until solid white (turns white between 6 & 10 years old)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1561 medium HIH174-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Lipizzan?","answer":"14.2 to 15.2 hands		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1562 medium HIH154-1","question":"Approximately how much does an average mature American Miniature Horse weigh?","answer":"200 - 350 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)		"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1563 medium HIH154-1,160B-1","question":"What does AMHA stand for?","answer":"American Miniature Horse Association"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1564 medium TH20","question":"What breed can match the Thoroughbred at the racing distance of 6 furlongs to 1-1/2 miles?","answer":"There is none"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1566 medium HIH157-1","question":"Name one country - other than the US - whose Thoroughbred foals are registered with the Jockey Club?","answer":"Canada or Puerto Rico"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1567 medium HIH162B-1","question":"Which breed was the first to represent the US in the World Pairs Driving competition?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1568 medium DET10","question":"Which breed of horse would you find in the American Studbook?","answer":"Thoroughbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1569 medium DET16","question":"In which country did the Asiatic Wild Horse originate?","answer":"Mongolia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1570 medium DET41","question":"What is the term for a wild Australian horse?","answer":"Brumby"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1571 medium DET37","question":"What is the term for the vocal sound made by a jack?","answer":"Bray"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1572 medium DET77/HIH169-2","question":"Name the breed of pony who originated in the valleys or "dales" of Great Britain who's solidly built, has good endurance, & has a calm, agreeable nature.","answer":"Dales Pony	"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1573 medium INT223-3","question":"What is the difference between breed & sex characteristics?","answer":"Breed characteristics are unique to a breed    (ex. body type, color pattern, gaits, etc.); 
sex characteristics refer to masculinity in the male & femininity in the female"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1574 medium DET188","question":"What is the name of the breed developed in the US which is a cross between a Saddlebred & an Arabian?","answer":"National Show Horse		"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1575 medium DET114","question":"Where did the Friesian originate?","answer":"Holland      (Netherlands)		Accept either"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1576 medium TH21","question":"What is the measure of performance for the racing Thoroughbred?","answer":"Speed"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1577 medium DET113","question":"What term is used to identify the original horses used in a breeding program?","answer":"Foundation stock"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1578 medium DET8","question":"What breed of horse originated in the Ural Mountains of Russia?  It's especially well adapted to extremely cold weather & is noted for its long curly hair coat.","answer":"Bashkir Curly"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1579 medium DET108","question":"Which modern breed resembles the wild horse of the Middle Ages?","answer":"Fjord"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1580 medium DET19","question":"Which breed of horse originated in Mexico as a result of crossing Andulusian stallions with Quarter Horse mares?","answer":"Azteca"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1581 medium DET108","question":"Describe the coloring of the Fjord.","answer":"Dun with a black & white/silver mane & tail, dorsal stripe & sometimes zebra markings on legs"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1582 medium TH449","question":"What is the scientific name of the Prezwalski's Horse?","answer":"Equus caballus przewalski"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1583 medium TH67","question":"Where did the Falabella originate?","answer":"Argentina"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1584 medium HIH153B-1","question":"The Arabian's Arabic name is Kohl-ani.  Where did it get this name?","answer":"Its skin is the same blue-black color as the kohl that Arabian women wear as eyeliner"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1585 medium TH79","question":"What animal is known for a dorsal stripe that is intersected by the arms of cross at the withers?","answer":"Donkey       "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1586 medium HIH154B-1","question":"Which breed organization was formed in 1971 to preserve the pedigrees & promote the activities of dun & buckskin horses?","answer":"International Buckskin Horse Association"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1587 medium HIH154B-1","question":"2 part question:  Are blue eyes allowed for horses registered with the International Buckskin Horse Association & if so, are there any qualifications?","answer":"Yes -- as long as conformation & body color are acceptable"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1588 medium HIH157B-1","question":"What is the average height of the Exmoor Pony?","answer":"12.2 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1589 medium HIH174B-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Trakehner  (tra-KAY-ner)?","answer":"16 - 17 hands		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1590 medium HIH175B-1","question":"What is another name for the Section A Welsh Pony?","answer":"Welsh Mountain Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1591 medium HIH175B-1","question":"What is the height limit for registering a Section A Welsh Pony?","answer":"12.2 hands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1592 medium TH73","question":"Other than their predominant chestnut color, what other cosmetic feature differentiates the Suffolk from the other British draft breeds?","answer":"Suffolk has no feathers on legs"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1593 medium HIH157-1","question":"The Jockey Club maintains the registry of Thoroughbreds for the United States, Canada & Puerto Rico.  What is the proper name of the register?","answer":"American Studbook"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1594 medium HIH157-1","question":"What organization has responsibility for maintenance of the American Stud Book?","answer":"Jockey Club"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1595 medium TH83	","question":"What are 2 ways the term "broomtail" can be used in describing a horse?","answer":"Horse with a heavy, coarse tail; ill-kept horse of uncertain breed/inferior quality; Western range horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1596 medium TH75","question":"What breed is referred to as ï¿½Skogsrussï¿½ in their homeland?","answer":"Gotland "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1597 medium DET60","question":"What do you call a short-legged horse that's built like a heavyweight hunter & is capable of carrying a substantial weight?","answer":"Cob"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1598 medium TH53","question":"How many types were recognized by the American Albino Club?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1599 medium TH69","question":"What is the main color of the Belgian?","answer":"Sorrel - with flaxen mane & tail"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1600 medium HIH183-1","question":"What breed registry is attempting to maintain the bloodlines of horses brought to the New World by the Spanish?","answer":"Spanish Mustang Registry"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1601 medium TH72/DET59","question":"Which breed of draft horse has extensive white face & leg markings, long strides with extreme flexion of the knees & hocks & long, silky hair on the lower legs?  This breed originated in Scotland.","answer":"Clydesdale"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1602 medium TH53","question":"Where are the headquarters of the American White Horse (formerly the American Albino Club)?","answer":"Naper, Nebraska"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1603 medium DET55","question":"What breed of pony is the descendant of the survivors of a shipwreck off the coast of Virginia?","answer":"Chincoteague"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1604 medium DET115","question":"What breed of horse was developed in Northern Holland as a war horse, has a distinctive flowing trot, no white markings & is described as a black horse with feathering on the legs?","answer":"Friesian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1605 medium ES51","question":"What breed of horse is sometimes called "rat-tailed" because of its characteristic sparse mane & tail?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1608 medium TH66","question":"What colors are ineligible for registration in the Connemara breed?","answer":"Spotted & blue-eyed creams"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1609 medium TH67/DET103","question":"What is the small horse breed from Argentina which is noted for excellent conformation & extremely small size?","answer":"Falabella"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1610 medium TH72","question":"Which draft breed is a descendent of the English Great Horse?","answer":"Shire or Clydesdale"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1611 medium TH68","question":"Which draft breed is a descendent of the Great Horse of Flanders?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1612 medium TH74","question":"The Hanoverian, Trakehner & Holsteiner breeds developed in which country?","answer":"Germany"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1613 medium TH45","question":"What is the name for the breed that resulted from crossing a Morgan & an Arabian?","answer":"Morab"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1614 medium TH41-42/DET181","question":"What breed of horse is known for its distinctive gait in which the horse performs a brisk walk with the front legs & trots with the back legs?  This breed originated in the Ozark Mountains of Missouri & Arkansas.","answer":"Missouri Foxtrotter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1615 medium TH76","question":"What would you call the offspring of a mule & hinny?","answer":"A miracle!; impossible because both are sterile"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1616 medium HH210-2/HH56","question":"Define breed type.","answer":"Characteristics commonly accepted as ideal for a particular breed"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1617 medium TH16","question":"What is a breed standard?","answer":"Standard of excellence set up by an association for its breed"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1618 medium HIH210-3/HH56/TH16","question":"What is a registry association?","answer":"An organization formed for the purpose of keeping records of the ancestry of individuals within a breed and to promote the breed"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1619 medium HIH153B-1","question":"The popularity of Arabians in the US began with the introduction of 45 horses showcased in 1892 at what location?","answer":"Chicago World's Fair"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1620 medium TH77","question":"What is the name of the registry association for mules?","answer":"American Donkey & Mule Society   (also accept:  American Mule Association, NASMA/North American Saddle Mules Assoc.)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1621 medium HIH161B-1/TH41","question":"Which breed was developed from saddle horses by settlers in the Ozarks?","answer":"Missouri Fox Trotter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1622 medium HIH154-1","question":"An American Miniature Horse is registered on a temporary basis until they reach 5 years of age.  What requirement must they meet at that time to be permanently registered?","answer":"Not exceed the 34 inch height requirement"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1623 medium TH59/HH59","question":"Which Pinto breed conformation type would be represented by a horse of Quarter Horse breeding?","answer":"Stock"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1624 medium TH49/HH59","question":"Into which Pinto breed conformation type would a horse of Thoroughbred breeding fit?","answer":"Hunter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1625 medium TH49/HH59","question":"Which Pinto breed conformation type would be represented by a horse of Saddlebred, Hackney or Tennessee Walker breeding?","answer":"Saddle"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1626 medium HH59","question":"Arabian or Morgan type horses would fit into which Pinto breed conformation type?","answer":"Pleasure"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1627 medium TH28/HIH160-1","question":"Which breed was developed in America from horses of Thoroughbred, Norfolk Trotter, Barb, Morgan, & Canadian racing ancestors?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1628 medium TH20","question":"The Thoroughbred exceeds other breeds at racing over what distance?","answer":"6 - 12 furlongs (3/4 - 1 ï¿½ miles)		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1629 medium TH17/HIH150-1","question":"Around 1906, Homer Davenport was responsible for the major expansion of which breed in America?","answer":"Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1630 medium TH17","question":"Before 1908, Arabians & Anglo-Arabians were registered in which breed association?","answer":"Jockey Club"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1631 medium TH23","question":"Legends say that Paul Revere rode which breed of horse?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1632 medium DET103","question":"Which one of the following breeds would NOT be considered a pony breedï¿½Galiceï¿½o, Exmoor, Falabella or Trottingbred?","answer":"Falabella "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1633 medium DET197","question":"Where did the Orlov Trotter originate?","answer":"Russia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1634 medium DET235","question":"Which breed that originated in Eastern Kentucky exhibits a natural ambling 4-beat gait?","answer":"Rocky Mountain Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1635 medium TH45","question":"Where did the Galiceno originate?","answer":"Spain"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1636 medium TH45","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Galiceno?","answer":"12 - 13.2 hands		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1637 medium HH58","question":"What is a studbook?","answer":"Register of all horses foaled for a breed OR record book published by the breed registry association for purebred horses, ponies or jacks"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1638 medium DET82","question":"What term refers to the female side of the pedigree?		","answer":"Distaff side (also accept dam side)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1639 medium DET271","question":"What part of a pedigree is referred to as the top line?                 ","answer":"Stallion side (or direct line of male descendants)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1640 medium TH40	","question":"Identify one of the breeds that the Tennessee Walking Horse was developed from.","answer":"Standardbred, Morgan or Narragansett pacer				"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1641 medium DET19","question":"What 2 breeds were combined in the development of the Azteca?","answer":"Andalusian & Quarter Horse          "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1642 medium DET108","question":"What breed is being describedï¿½Sometimes used as a pack animal; dun color with black and silver mane and tail, eel stripe and zebra markings; resembles the wild horses of the Ice Age; country of origin is Norway.","answer":"Fjord				"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1643 medium DET298","question":"What would be the result of crossing a zebra & a horse?","answer":"Zebrass, zorse or zebroid                   "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1644 medium TH66","question":"Which 2 breeds were crossed to develop the Americana?","answer":"Shetland & Hackney pony          "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"medium","number":"1645 medium DET190","question":"What is the country of origin for the New Forest Pony?","answer":"England                 "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1646 hard HIH157-1","question":"In addition to Wall St. financier James Keene, what other prominent horseman led the development of the Jockey Club?","answer":"August Belmont II (2nd)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1647 hard HIH151-1","question":"What famous foundation sire carried President James Madison on a Muster Day parade ground?","answer":"Justin Morgan/Figure"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1648 hard HIH157-1","question":"The American Stud Book is a register of Thoroughbred horses from what 3 countries?","answer":"US, Canada, Puerto Rico"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1649 hard HIH150-1","question":"In reference to the evolution of the breed, why is it believed that for their body size, Arabian horses have large hooves?","answer":"Enabled them to travel more easily over desert sands"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1650 hard TH26","question":"The King Ranch of Texas developed a line breeding program around one Quarter Horse stallion that they felt fit their ideal of the working cow horse.  Who was this stallion?","answer":"Old Sorrel"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1651 hard TH9","question":"This type of horse never had a breed registry established, but it was the only heavy type of horse developed in the eastern United States.  What was its name?","answer":"Conestoga Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1652 hard TH498/DET191","question":"2 part question:   Name 2 European breeds with the leopard spotting pattern & their countries of origin","answer":"Noriker ï¿½ Austria            Knabstrupper ï¿½ Denmark"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1653 hard TH20","question":"What is the name of the Thoroughbred ridden by General Custer at the Battle of the Little Big Horn?","answer":"Vic"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1654 hard TH7","question":"What group of people was responsible for the development of many of the American horse breeds?","answer":"Early colonists of the East coast"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1655 hard TH69","question":"Which of these 2 breeds does NOT have a long, springy stride with extreme flexion of the knees & hocks - Belgian or Clydesdale?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1656 hard TH28","question":"What was the original name for the Standardbred?","answer":"American Trotting Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1657 hard TH45","question":"Identify the breed from the description:  This breed of horse has a running walk similar to that of the Tennessee Walking Horse & the Pasos.  They have been imported from Mexico since the late 1950s & range in size from 12 - 13.2 hands.  Arabians, pintos & crosses are not eligible for registration.  Which breed is it?","answer":"Galiceno"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1658 hard BEG110-2","question":"What is the phrase commonly used to describe the American Saddlebred?","answer":"Peacock of the show world/ring"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1659 hard TH43","question":"2 part question:  There are 2 distinct types of Paso horses.  Which breed of Paso does NOT register spotted horses & for what characteristic trait of the gait is the breed most known?","answer":"Peruvian Paso; gait - termino  (additional info:ï¿½ outward swinging leg action)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1660 hard TH63","question":"At breed shows, Hackney ponies are divided into 2 types.  What are they?","answer":"Cob tail & long tail"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1661 hard TH28,37","question":"2 part question:  Name 2 American horse breeds that have 2 distinct types based on gait & name the types","answer":"Standardbred ï¿½ trotters & pacers;	 American Saddlebredï¿½3- gaited   & 5-gaited"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1662 hard TH64","question":"2 part question:  What is meant by the term cob-tail & where is it commonly seen?","answer":"Practice of docking horse's tail to 6" length;     seen in Hackney & draft horses"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1663 hard TH58","question":"An influx of which breed can be seen in the American type of Shetland pony?","answer":"Hackney"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1664 hard TH27","question":"What are the names of the 2 famous grandsires of Wimpy?","answer":"Old Sorrel & Peter McCue"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1665 hard HIH159B-1","question":"In order to be eligible for registration, horses of which breed must trace directly without interruption to the recognized male lines & female families of which official European stud farm?","answer":"LIpizzan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1666 hard TH11/DET263","question":"What is currently the only surviving species of wild horse native to Eastern Asia?","answer":"Prezewalski Horse/Takhi/Mongolian Wild Horse 	Accept any listed 	(not Tarpan ï¿½ it is extinct)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1667 hard HIH157-1","question":"2 part question:  The first organized Thoroughbred races are traditionally credited to Gov. Samuel Ogle.  When & where were the first races staged?","answer":"Annapolis, Maryland in 1749"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1668 hard HIH161-1,165B-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the height of the Paso Fino?","answer":"13 - 15.2 hands	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1670 hard DET88","question":"To what famous Thoroughbred - unbeaten in 24 races in 1764 - do 90% of all modern Thoroughbreds trace their ancestry?","answer":"Eclipse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1671 hard HIH163-1","question":"Identify the breed from the following description:  This breed has a mature weight of 1400 - 1800 pounds for females & 1800 - 2000 pounds for males.  They average 15.1 - 16.3 hands at maturity.  As a breed, their numbers are small & they trace their foundation to a mare from Iowa.  They hold the distinction of being the only draft breed that was developed in the US.  They are all cream in color.","answer":"American Cream Draft"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1672 hard HIH153-1","question":"What breed is being described?  The head is short & broad with large nostrils & short, foxy ears.  The muscling is short, compact & powerful which gives it the ability to gain speed quickly.  The disposition is calm.","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1673 hard TH69","question":"What 2 features made the Percheron a popular draft breed?","answer":"Lack of feathers on legs & their speed at the walk  (also accept bold trot)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1674 hard TH36","question":"Identify the breed from the following description.  This breed was essential in the development of the Standardbred, American Saddlebred & Quarter Horse breeds.  The US Dept of Agriculture had a farm in Middlebury, Vermont that was used to preserve & improve this breed.  They are known for their all-purpose ability on the farm or in the show ring & are the only breed named after a single horse.","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1675 hard HIH159B-1","question":"In addition to the stallion lines, how many dominant female families are recognized by the Lipizzan registry?","answer":"35"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1676 hard HIH157B-1","question":"From where did the Exmoor Pony get its name?","answer":"The moorlands known as Exmoor (SW England)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1677 hard HIH153B-1","question":"The first purebred Arabian breeding program in the US is linked to what US President who was given 2 Arabian stallions by the Sultan of Turkey?","answer":"President Ulysses S.  Grant"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1678 hard TH21","question":"What is the name of the horse traditionally regarded as the first Thoroughbred imported to the US in 1730?","answer":"Bulle Rock    (pronounced Bull Rock)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1679 hard TH242","question":"Mares of what draft breed have a gestation length 15 - 20 days longer than other draft mares?","answer":"Belgian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1680 hard HIH154B-1","question":"True buckskin & dun horses originated from which 2 breeds?","answer":"Sorria & Norwegian Dun"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1681 hard HIH160-1,171B-1","question":"What is the origination of the name "Standardbred"?","answer":"One of the first requirements for admission to the studbook was that the horse had to trot or pace a standard mile in 2 min. 30 sec. or better"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1682 hard TH58","question":"Linden Tree, Leopard & Max are the foundation sires for this breed of horse which is often mistaken for an Appaloosa.  Identify this breed.","answer":"Rangerbred/Colorado Ranger Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1683 hard TH67","question":"The Trottingbred is a synthetic pony breed developed for sulky racing.  Similar to Standardbreds, some are trotters & others are pacers.  Standardbreds race a distance of one mile.  How far do Trottingbred ponies race?","answer":"1/2 mile"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1688 hard HIH161-1,165B-1","question":"Who brought the Paso Fino to the New World?","answer":"Columbus   (on his 2nd voyage)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1689 hard TH39","question":"Name the 6-time winner of the $10,000 5-gaited championship at the Kentucky State Fair.","answer":"Wing Commander"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1690 hard TH28-29	","question":"Name the breed that includes the following famous names in its history ï¿½ Messenger, Greyhound, Hambletonian, Dan Patch, and Niatross.","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1691 hard TH26","question":"What current breed of horse was known as Steeldusts in the early 1900ï¿½s? ","answer":"Quarter Horse "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1692 hard TH52","question":"Where did the Tarpan originate?","answer":"Central Europe"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1693 hard TH23","question":"Which state was the center of raising & training Thoroughbreds in colonial America?","answer":"Virginia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1694 hard TH24","question":"Most Quarter Horse foundation sires trace back to which stallion?","answer":"Janus"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1695 hard TH28/HIH173B-1","question":"Messenger - a gray Thoroughbred - is generally considered to be the foundation sire of which breed?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1696 hard TH28-29/HIH171B-1","question":"99% of all Standardbreds trace to which stallion?","answer":"Hambletonian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1697 hard TH36","question":"The dark liver or "black chestnut" color is most common in which breed?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1698 hard TH38/HIH169B-1","question":"The American Saddlebred was originally called by another name.  What is that name?","answer":"Kentucky Saddler or American Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1699 hard TH38/HIH173B-1","question":"Who was the foundation sire of the American Saddlebred Horse?","answer":"Denmark (a Thoroughbred)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1700 hard TH40/HIH162B-1","question":"Black Allen (Allen P-1) is the foundation sire of which breed?","answer":"Tennessee Walker"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1701 hard TH45","question":"The Galiceno may naturally trot and/or exhibit which other intermediate gait?","answer":"Running walk or Paso gait"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1702 hard TH50","question":"Palomino horses in Spain at the time of Queen Isabella were known by what name?","answer":"Golden Isabellas"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1703 hard TH50","question":"What is one version of the origination of the name Palomino?","answer":"Named after the California golden grape called a palomino"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1704 hard TH52/HIH154B-1","question":"What is a Sorria?","answer":"True breeding buckskin/dun breed from Spain"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1705 hard TH53","question":"Why was the name of the American Albino changed to the American White Horse?","answer":"There are no true albino horses 	(solid white horses have brown, blue, or hazel eyes)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1706 hard TH54","question":"Which color horses now registered as "cream" were originally registered as Albino types A & B?","answer":"Cremello & perlino"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1707 hard TH55/DET55","question":"What is the small, short-coupled horse named for an Indian tribe?  This breed was one of the ancestors of the Quarter Horse?","answer":"Chickasaw Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1708 hard TH55/HIH170B-1","question":"Who was the founder of the Spanish Mustang Registry?","answer":"Robert Brislawn"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1709 hard TH58","question":"The name Shetland came from an old Norse word meaning what?","answer":"Highland"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1710 hard TH72","question":"Where did the Shire get its name?","answer":"English Shires    (specifically Lincolnshire & Cambridgeshire)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1711 hard TH73","question":"Because of its rounded or "punched up" appearance, what was the Suffolk originally called?","answer":"Suffolk Punch"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1712 hard TH52","question":"Name a small, dun-colored genuine wild horse that was formerly abundant in southern Russia & central Asia.","answer":"Tarpan or Prezwalski's Horse or Mongolian Wild Horse/Takhi"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1713 hard TH9","question":"Where was the Conestoga Horse bred?","answer":"Southern Pennsylvania"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1714 hard TH50","question":"In the history of Spain during the reign of Queen Isabella, what current breed of horses was known as Golden Isabellas? ","answer":"Palomino"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1715 hard TH36","question":"In 1894, Colonel Battel founded the registry for what breed of horse?","answer":"Morgan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1716 hard TH66","question":"What breed of show pony was produced by crossing Hackney & Shetland ponies?","answer":"Americana"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1717 hard TH72","question":"Robert Bakewell developed many improved breeds of livestock.  Which draft breed is he known for improving?","answer":"Shire"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1718 hard HIH186-1","question":"What organization started the Half-Arabian registry?","answer":"US Calvary    (Remount Service)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1719 hard TH45","question":"Identify the following breed.  This pony-size equine probably originated in Spain as a result of Spanish Jennet and Barb breeding.  It performs four natural gaits that include the walk, trot, canter and running walk. ","answer":"Galiceï¿½o "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1720 hard HIH174-2","question":"Who was responsible for returning the Lipizzan mares to Austria during World War II?","answer":"US Army"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1721 hard HIH167-1","question":"Which breed can be traced through archeological records to England over 60,000 years ago, making it a contemporary of the Prezwalski Horse?","answer":"Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1722 hard HIH167-1,169-1","question":"What is meant by the term "toad eye"?","answer":"The pronounced eyebrow of the Exmoor Pony"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1723 hard HIH167-1","question":"What is the main limitation to the Exmoor Pony Registry?","answer":"Limited to descendants of moor ponies that have not been improved with any other breed additions"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1724 hard HIH167-1","question":"What is the purpose of the American Livestock Breeds Conservancy?","answer":"To promote rare breeds of horses & livestock in the US"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1725 hard TH36/HIH162B-1","question":"The stallion True Britton (who sired Justin Morgan) was also known by another name.  What was it?","answer":"Beautiful Bay"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1726 hard HIH150-1,153B-1","question":"When was the first purebred Arabian breeding program started in the US?","answer":"Late 1800's"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1727 hard DET155","question":"Which breed was developed by crossing the Thoroughbred & Irish Draft breeds?","answer":"Irish Hunter           "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1728 hard TH66","question":"The Tennessee Walking Horse was crossed with what other breed to develop the American Walking Pony?","answer":"Welsh Pony                  "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1729 hard HIH159B-2","question":"What breed was formerly known as the ï¿½Karsterï¿½ horse?			","answer":"Lipizzan    (Lipizzaner)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1730 hard TH23","question":"Who was the foundation sire for the American Albino Horse?","answer":"Old King                  "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1731 hard HIH175B-1","question":"What pony breed has been referred to as the ï¿½Best ride & drive animal in the worldï¿½?","answer":"Welsh Cob                             "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"hard","number":"1732 hard DET6","question":"What breed is being describedï¿½.Noted for its speed & jumping ability although it can be stubborn  Able to withstand the severe weather in its country of origin which is Russia","answer":"Akhal-Teke                       "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1733 bonus TH8","question":"As the colonies developed in the New World, farmers in New York & Pennsylvania had need of heavy horses that could till the soil & haul products to market.  Name 3 breeds imported for this purpose.","answer":"Belgian, Percheron, Clydesdale, Shire"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1734 bonus HIH155-1","question":"Name 3 qualifications for registering a Golden American Saddlebred.","answer":"Must also be registered as an American Saddlebred; must have Palomino coloring; no white spots on body "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1735 bonus HIH157B-1","question":"What are 3 things that are considered signs of impurity & result in denying registration for an Exmoor Pony?","answer":"White markings, white hairs on body/mane/tail, hooves with white soles"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1736 bonus TH38,61,69/HIH158-2,170-1","question":"Identify  3  breeds from the following nicknames:  Peacock of the Horse World, Prince of Ponies, breed of blacks & grays, Palouse horse, Aristocrat of the Show Ring","answer":"Peacock of the Horse World - American Saddlebred;
Prince of Ponies - Hackney Pony;
Breed of blacks & grays ï¿½ Percheron;
Palouse horse ï¿½ Appaloosa;
Aristocrat of the Show Ring - Hackney Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1737 bonus TH570","question":"In reference to Thoroughbred race horses, name the 3 categories that measure performance.","answer":"Earnings, handicaps, time/speed"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1738 bonus TH74","question":"Name 3 German Warmblood breeds. ","answer":"Hanoverian, Holsteiner, Trakehner, Oldenburg"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1739 bonus HIH154B-2","question":"Name 3 disqualifications for registration in the International Buckskin Association.","answer":"Draft horse conformation, ponies, Palominos with dorsal stripes, horses with Albino, Appaloosa, Paint or Pinto characteristics, roan coloring, graying"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1740 bonus DET59,67,127,217,243,289","question":"Name the country of origin for 4 of the following:  Connemara, Clydesdale, Hackney, Standardbred, POA, Welsh Pony.","answer":"Connemara ï¿½ Ireland; 	Clydesdale ï¿½ Scotland; 		Hackney ï¿½ England; 
Standardbred ï¿½ USA;		 POA ï¿½ USA; 			Welsh Pony ï¿½ Wales"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1741 bonus TH72","question":"2 part question:  Explain the difference between harness & flat racing & name 2 breeds that would participate in each.","answer":"Harness racing are driving races/use sulkies;     breeds Standardbred, Trottingbred Pony, Russian Trotter, Orlov; 
Flat races are riding races;     breeds; Thoroughbred, Quarter Horse, Appaloosa, Paint, Arabian"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1742 bonus HIH151B-2","question":"The American Warmblood Society (AWS) is focused on the qualities and/or performance of the sport horse.  What are 3 disciplines that the AWS supports?","answer":"Dressage, eventing/combined training, show jumping, combined driving"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1743 bonus TH45","question":"Name 2 breeds that have a running walk.","answer":"Tennessee Walker, Galiceno"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1744 bonus TH42/HH57","question":"Name 4 colors of the Missouri Foxtrotter.","answer":"Black, bay, brown, chestnut, palomino, black, roan	 (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1745 bonus HH59/HIH152B-1/TH32","question":"What are 3 characteristics of Appaloosas?","answer":"Mottled skin, sclera around eye, striped hooves, approved coat pattern"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1746 bonus HIH151-1,162B-1","question":"Other than conformation, what are 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Morgan?","answer":"Easy keeper, endurance, docility"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1747 bonus HIH151-1,162B-1","question":"What are 3 colors of the Morgan?","answer":"Bay, brown, black, chestnut, palomino, buckskin, gray, cream"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1748 bonus HIH158-1,152B-1","question":"In what 3 western states was the Appaloosa developed?","answer":"Oregon, Washington, Idaho"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1749 bonus HIH150-1,153B-1/HH57","question":"What are 3 colors of the Arabian?","answer":"Bay, black, brown, chestnut, gray, occasional roan, white"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1750 bonus TH58-67","question":"Name 4 breeds of pony.","answer":"Shetland, Welsh, Connemara, POA, Quarter Pony, New Forest, Dales, Fells, American Sport Pony, Chincoteague, Dartmoor, Gotland, Hackney, etc.		 (accept any pony breed)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"Bonus","number":"1752 Bonus TH61","question":"Timelineï¿½ Place the following 4 breeds in the correct order of development.  Begin with the oldest breed & continue with each of the other breeds until all are in the correct timeline:  Thoroughbred, Hackney, Welsh, Arabian","answer":"Arabian, Thoroughbred, Hackney, Welsh"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1753 bonus HIH156-1","question":"Name 5 colors of the American Saddlebred.","answer":"Black, bay, brown, chestnut, gray, palomino, buckskin, roan, pinto   (any color accepted)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1754 bonus TH29","question":"Name 3 things which determine the racing gait of the Standardbred.","answer":"Genetic factors, training, shoeing"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1755 bonus HH56/TH76/HIH156B-1","question":"What are 3 uses of the mule?","answer":"Saddle, packing, draft/farm work, driving, showing, pets"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1756 bonus HH56/TH67/HIH154-1,160B-1","question":"What are 2 uses of the Miniature Horse?","answer":"Companions, driving, circus, in-hand jumping, in-hand obstacles/trail, halter, showmanship"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1757 bonus HIH150-1,153B-1/HH56/TH67","question":"What are 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Arabian?","answer":"Beautiful head, dished face, arching neck, high tail carriage, free way of going, great endurance, short coupling, docility"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1758 bonus HIH1040-3","question":"Name 3 color patterns of the Appaloosa.","answer":"Leopard, blanket, blanket with spots, few spot leopard, snowflake, frost, mottled, varnish roan"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1759 bonus HIH1040-3/TH491","question":"Name 3 color patterns of the Paint or Pinto.","answer":"Tobiano, overo, tovero, calico, splashed white, sabino"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1760 bonus HH59/TH26-27/HIH153-1,168B-1","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Quarter Horse.","answer":"Cow sense, compact muscling, speed at short distance, short/foxy ears, calm disposition"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1761 bonus HH59","question":"The Standardbred is primarily used in what 2 ways?","answer":"Harness racing, driving"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1762 bonus HH57","question":"What are 3 characteristic gaits of the Missouri Foxtrotter?","answer":"Fox trot gait, rapid walk, rocking chair canter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1763 bonus HIH157-1","question":"Who are the 3 foundation sires of the Thoroughbred?","answer":"Darley Arabian, Godolphin Arabian/Barb, Byerly Turk"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1764 bonus HIH159-1,163B-1","question":"What are the 2 basic requirements for registering an American Paint Horse?","answer":"Must have Paint, Thoroughbred, or Quarter Horse breeding &must meet minimum color requirements
(additional info:ï¿½ should also have stock horse conformation)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1765 bonus HH59/TH69","question":"What are 3 characteristics of Percherons?","answer":"Considerable knee action, bold trot, no feathers on legs, speed at the walk"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1766 bonus TH49","question":"What are 2 uses of the Percheron?","answer":"General draft work, driving, crossbred with Thoroughbreds to produce hunters/jumpers"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1767 bonus TH49/HH59","question":"What are 3 conformation types of the Pinto?","answer":"Stock, pleasure, saddle, hunter"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1768 bonus HIH152-2","question":"Which breeds contributed to the development of the Tennessee Walking Horse?","answer":"Standardbred, Thoroughbred, Morgan, American Saddlebred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1769 bonus TH20","question":"Name 3 breeds for which the Thoroughbred provided foundation stock.","answer":"Standardbred, Quarter Horse, Morgan, American Saddlebred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1770 bonus TH21","question":"There are 3 main Thoroughbred stallion lines that trace to the foundation sires.  Who are they?","answer":"Eclipse, Matchem, Herod"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1771 bonus TH40","question":"Name 2 breeds that developed naturally to meet the work needs of their region & not the desires of fanciers.","answer":"Tennessee Walking Horse, Morgan, Saddlebred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1772 bonus TH42","question":"The Missouri Foxtrotter traces its ancestry to what 3 breeds?","answer":"Arabian, Morgan, Plantation horses"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1773 bonus TH43","question":"What is the main difference between a Peruvian Paso & a Paso Fino?","answer":"Peruvian Pasos were developed solely from horses brought to Peru by the conquistadores; 
Paso Finos were developed from horses imported from Puerto Rico & Columbia"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1774 bonus TH53","question":"What are the 3 major color characteristics of the American White Horse?","answer":"White hair, pink skin, & brown, blue or hazel eyes"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1775 bonus TH55-57","question":"Name 3 registries for the Mustang horse.","answer":"Spanish Mustang, American Indian Horse, Chickasaw Horse, Spanish Barb, American Mustang Association, BLM"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1776 bonus TH67","question":"What are the 5 major draft breeds in the US?","answer":"Shire, Percheron, Clydesdale, Belgian, Suffolk"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1777 bonus TH74","question":"Name 3 German warmblood breeds that are usually used for dressage.","answer":"Hanoverian, Holsteiner, Trakehner. Oldenburg"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1778 bonus TH76/HIH156B-1","question":"Name 3 noticeable differences between the horse & the ass.","answer":"Ass has longer ears, sparse mane & tail, smaller hooves, less chestnuts (chestnuts usually only on front legs), brays instead of whinnies, muzzle & underbelly usually a lighter color, gestation period 30 days longer"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1779 bonus TH58","question":"What is the difference in body types between the classic Shetland pony & the modern Shetland pony?","answer":"Classic - short & chunky;		 modern - fine boned, long-necked, high stepping"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1780 bonus HIH184-1,175B-1","question":"Name 3 sections of the Welsh Pony & Cob registry.","answer":"Welsh Mountain Pony (Section A), 		Welsh Pony (Section B),		
Welsh Pony of Cob Type (Section C), 		Welsh Cob (Section D)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1781 bonus HIH183-1,170B-1","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the Spanish Mustang.","answer":"Chestnuts small/smooth in front or missing, big boned, legs join chest in A shape instead of wide, straight or concave forehead, convex or Roman nose, small to medium ears"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1782 bonus HIH174-2,159B-1","question":"Name 3 classic Lipizzan stallion lines.","answer":"Conversano, Favory, Maestoso, Neapolitano, Pluto, Siglavy"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1783 bonus HIH174-1","question":"Name 3 distinguishing characteristics of the Lipizzan.","answer":"Agility, temperament, good character, docility, intelligence"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1784 bonus HIH166-1,174B-2","question":"Name 3 things judged in the Trakehner (tra-KAY-ner) stallion inspection system.","answer":"Type, conformation, bone, size, temperament, way of moving"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1785 bonus HIH163-1,155B-1","question":"Give 3 characteristics of the American Cream Draft Horse.","answer":"Cream color, pink skin, amber eyes"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1786 bonus HIH169-1,157B-1","question":"Give 3 characteristics of the Exmoor Pony.","answer":"Primitive coat pattern (buff  around eye, muzzle, belly & flank), uniformity of appearance, broad forehead, toad eye, low tail set, double layer coat, snow chute/ice tail"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1787 bonus HIH169-1,157B-1","question":"Exmoor ponies have developed characteristics that help them survive harsh winter conditions.  Name 3.","answer":"Double layer coat, heavy brow/toad eye (to keep wind/rain out of eyes), snow chute/ice tail (short hairs at base of tail to keep snow/rain from under tail)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1788 bonus HIH155-1","question":"2 part question:  Golden American Saddlebreds have 2 predominant families.  Name the 2 families & the trait each is known for.","answer":"Peavine - light skin; 	Belvedere - dark skin"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1789 bonus HIH151-2,162B-1","question":"Name 3 breeds of American horses that can trace their foundation back to the Morgan.","answer":"Saddlebred, Tennessee Walker, Standardbred, Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1790 bonus TH-various","question":"Name 3 synthetic breeds & the breeds they derived from.","answer":"Americana Pony - Shetland & Hackney; 	
American Walking Pony - Tennessee Walker & Welsh Pony;
American Quarter Pony - small Quarter Horse;
Walking Pony - small Tennessee Walker;
Ashland Pony - Chincoteague, Shetland & Chickasaw;
Miniature Horse - Shetland & Falabella;
Trottingbred Pony - Standardbred, Shetland, Hackney & Welsh;
Morab - Morgan & Arab;
Thorocheron - Thoroughbred & Percheron;
National Show Horse - Arabian & Saddlebred
(accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1791 bonus TH58","question":"Name 3 breeds that are named after different US states.","answer":"Tennessee Walker, Missouri Fox Trotter, Colorado Ranger Horse/Rangerbred"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1792 bonus HIH151-1","question":"Name the breed associated with 3 of the following horses:  Figure, Hambletonian, Black Hand, Allan F-1, Janus.","answer":"Figure ï¿½ Morgan; 	Hambletonian ï¿½ Standardbred; 		Black Hand ï¿½ POA;	
Allan F-1 -- Tennessee Walker;		 Janus - Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1793 bonus TH43,74/HIH169-1/DET8,25","question":"Identify the country of origin for 3 of the following breeds:  Bashkir Curly, Haflinger, Hanoverian & Exmoor.","answer":"Bashkir Curlyï¿½Russia; 	Haflingerï¿½Austria; 	Hanoverian ï¿½ Germany;		 Exmoorï¿½England  "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1794 bonus HIH161-1,165B-1","question":"Identify 3 of the 4 breeds that the Paso Fino was developed from","answer":"Andalusian, Barb, Spanish jennet & Friesian           "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1795 bonus HIH167B-2","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the POA.","answer":"Mottled skin, sclera around eye, striped hooves, approved coat pattern"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1796 bonus TH80","question":"Besides color, name 3 physical characteristics used by breed registries for identification purposes.","answer":"Lip tattoo, chestnuts, blood type, muscular dimples, cowlicks, scars, brands, freeze markings, coat pattern, markings"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1797 bonus TH58","question":"Identify the 3 foundation sires for the Rangerbred horse","answer":"Max, Leopard & Linden Tree            "},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1798 bonus HIH156B-1","question":"Identify 3 of the 5 classifications of donkeys according to size				","answer":"Miniature		Small Standard		Standard  	Large Standard		Mammoth"},
{"category":"BREEDS & TYPES","level":"bonus","number":"1799 bonus TH28, 38, 40","question":"Identify 3 breeds that originated in the US and were developed from crossing other breeds with Canadian pacers?","answer":"Standardbred, American Saddlebred & Tennessee Walking Horse          "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1800 easy HIH154B-1/TH51","question":"In order to be registered as a dun, a grulla must have what?","answer":"Dorsal stripe"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1801 easy TH80/HH4","question":"When referring to color, what is another name for chestnut?","answer":"Sorrel"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1802 easy HH4 ","question":"Describe the color buckskin.        ","answer":"Body color is some shade of yellow, mane, tail & lower legs (or points) are black  "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1803 easy HH6/DET77","question":"What term describes a circular or ring-shaped pattern on the coat that has 2 slightly different shades of the same color?","answer":"Dappled"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1804 easy HH6/TH51","question":"What is the term meaning a blue tinge to the coat?","answer":"Smokey"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1805 medium ES63","question":"What color skin does a gray horse have?","answer":"Dark"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1806 easy HH6","question":"Define patched.","answer":"Large roan spots on some base color"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1807 easy DET77/ES39/HH6","question":"Define dappled.","answer":"Circular/ring-shaped pattern on the coat - 2 slightly different shades of the same color"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1808 easy HH7/TH83","question":"Which term means a mane or tail that is white with a few black hairs?","answer":"Silver"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1809 easy HIH140-2","question":"Which white face marking has the largest white area?","answer":"Bald face"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1810 easy HIH140-1","question":"What is the dominant color of hair on a dun horse?","answer":"Some shade of yellow     (also accept yellowish gold)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1811 easy HH4/TH81/ES42-43","question":"What color always has black points?","answer":"Bay       (also accept buckskin,  grulla, brown)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1812 easy HIH140-1","question":"What causes a gray horse's coat to lighten with age?","answer":"More white hairs growing into the coat"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1813 easy HH4","question":"Describe the marking "flame".","answer":"A few white hairs in the middle of the forehead"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1814 easy HIH140-2","question":"Describe the coloring of a red dun.","answer":"Body color is reddish orange/reddish yellow; mane & tail are dark red;  has a red dorsal stripe "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1815 easy HIH1040-3","question":"What is the most common pinto pattern?","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1816 easy HIH140-1","question":"Describe a blue roan.","answer":"Roan horse with a mixture of black & white hairs	 (additional info -- darker on head, neck, & lower legs)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1817 easy HIH140-1","question":"Which pinto color pattern has rounded or oval-shaped spots?","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1818 easy HIH140-1","question":"Which pinto color pattern is characterized by jagged edged, splashy, scattered spots?","answer":"Overo"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1819 easy HH4/TH81","question":"What is another name for a bay roan?","answer":"Red roan"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1820 easy HIH140-1/TH81","question":"Name 2 areas that are generally darker or more solid-colored on a roan horse.","answer":"Head, neck, lower legs, mane, tail"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1821 easy HIH140-1","question":"What color horse has a black mane & tail, body color of brown or black with lighter areas at the muzzle, eyes, flank & inside of upper thighs?","answer":"Brown or seal brown"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1822 easy TH81/HH4","question":"What color does the following describe?  The foal's coat will be a solid color, but with each consecutive hair coat, more white hairs are added.","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1823 easy HH4/TH81/DET89","question":"Give 2 terms that mean a dark line running down the back from the mane to tail.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, line-back, eel stripe"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1824 easy HH4","question":"Be specific:  A red dorsal stripe appears with which coat color?","answer":"Red dun, claybank dun, or apricot dun		 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1825 easy TH53/HH4","question":"What color skin does a true white horse have?","answer":"Pink"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1826 easy TH81/HH5","question":"On what coat color is dappling most easy to see?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1827 easy HIH1040-2","question":"Describe the cremello color.","answer":"Body is cream colored; mane & tail are cream/white"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1828 easy TH34/HIH158-1","question":"Describe a leopard Appaloosa.","answer":"White horse with colored spots on the body & Appaloosa characteristics"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1829 easy HIH140-1","question":"Many brown horses are mistakenly called what color?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1830 easy HIH140-1","question":"What color are the muzzle & flanks of a brown horse?","answer":"Brown or tan"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1831 easy HIH140-1","question":"You are looking at 2 horses - both are light golden red.  One has black points & the other does not.  What are the basic colors of these horses?","answer":"Black points ï¿½ bay;   other horse - chestnut or sorrel "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1832 easy HIH140-2/HH7","question":"Describe the marking "bald face".","answer":"White over most of the flat surface of the face (often including the eyes & nostrils)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1833 easy HH7/TH82","question":"Describe "glass eye".","answer":"Eye/iris is clear, white, or blue"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1834 easy HIH140-2/CAHA4/HH7","question":"What do you call a wide, white stripe running down the face to the lips?","answer":"Blaze"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1835 easy H1-34","question":"What do you call an Appaloosa coat pattern where the horse has a solid colored head, neck & shoulders & changes to white on the back or flank?","answer":"Blanket"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1836 easy HIH154B-1","question":"What is a brindle dun?","answer":"Dun horse with stripes or tear drops markings on its barrel (body)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1837 easy HIH154B-1","question":"The unusual markings of a brindle dun can appear as what?","answer":"Teardrops or zebra stripes  "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1838 easy HH7","question":"What is the term for faded out color around the horse's mouth?","answer":"Mealy mouth"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1839 easy HH4/HIH1040-2/TH53","question":"2 part question:  At birth, what color is the coat of a true white horse & what color is its skin?","answer":"White coat, pink skin"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1840 easy TH81/HH4-5","question":"Both gray & roan horses are a mixture of white & colored hairs.  What is the difference between these 2 colors?","answer":"Gray horses get progressively lighter with age.  Roan horses do not change color - the amount of white hair stays the same"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1841 easy HIH140-2","question":"What color eyes does a white horse have?","answer":"Brown, hazel or blue		 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1842 easy HIH1040-1,140-2","question":"Name this color:  The base color is chestnut with a uniform mix of white hairs on the body.  The head, neck, & legs are darker.  Its color does not get lighter with age.","answer":"Strawberry roan or red roan"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1843 easy HIH154B-1","question":"Which color is described as the color of newly tanned deerhide with black points?","answer":"Buckskin"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1844 easy `				HIH140-2","question":"Describe the leg marking "sock".","answer":"White extends from the coronet to & including the fetlock"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1846 easy HIH140-2","question":"What leg marking extends from the coronet to & including the knee?","answer":"Full stocking"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1847 easy HIH140-2/TH82","question":"Describe the face marking "star".","answer":"Patch of white hairs on the forehead"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1848 easy HIH140-1","question":"What do most grulla horses have on their legs & withers?","answer":"Zebra stripes"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1849 easy HIH140-2","question":"What do you call the head marking where white covers most of the flat surface of the face?","answer":"Bald face"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1850 easy HIH140-2","question":"What does the term "flaxen" mean?","answer":"Mane & tail that are colored light yellow to white "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1851 easy TH46/ES47","question":"Describe the color ï¿½piebaldï¿½","answer":"Black with white spotting"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1852 easy TH46","question":"Describe the color ï¿½skewbaldï¿½","answer":"Any color except black with white spotting"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1853 easy HIH140-1","question":"What leg marking is white from the coronet to the middle of the cannon?","answer":"Half stocking"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1854 easy TH78/HIH140-1","question":"What is the term for a dark line over the withers from side to side?","answer":"Cross or transverse stripe"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1855 easy HIH140-1","question":"Referring to horses, what does the term "zebra" mean?","answer":"Dark stripes on the legs and/or withers"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1856 easy HIH140-2","question":"What do you call a long, narrow band of white running from the forehead down towards the muzzle?","answer":"Stripe"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1857 easy HH4,8/TH80,128","question":"What term describes both a horse color & a horny growth found on the inside of a horse's legs?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1858 easy HIH140-1","question":"What is the difference in coloring between a red bay & a chestnut?","answer":"Bays always have black manes & tails.  Chestnuts have red or flaxen manes & tails."},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1859 easy HH4","question":"What is a "line back"?","answer":"Darker line running along the back from mane to tail (dorsal stripe)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1860 easy HIH140-2","question":"What term means dark stripes on the legs and/or withers?","answer":"Zebra stripes"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1861 easy HIH140-1","question":"Describe the color pattern "pinto".","answer":"Combination of white & colored markings in irregular patches or spots"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1863 easy HIH140-2","question":"Name 3 of the 5 leg markings.","answer":"Coronet, pastern, sock/ankle, half stocking, full stocking"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1864 easy HIH140-2","question":"Describe a full stocking.","answer":"White extends from the coronet to & including the knee"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1865 easy HIH140-2","question":"Describe the marking "coronet".","answer":"White covering the coronet band"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1866 easy HIH140-2","question":"What is a half stocking?","answer":"White extends from the coronet to the middle of the cannon"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1867 easy HIH140-2","question":"Describe a roan horse.","answer":"Color is a mixture of white & colored hairs"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1868 easy HIH140-2,164B-2/TH49","question":"Describe the color palomino.","answer":"Golden color with white mane & tail "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1869 easy HIH140-1","question":"What color is the mane & tail on a buckskin?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1870 easy HIH140-1","question":"Describe the color chestnut.","answer":"Body is some shade of red; mane & tail are same color as the body or flaxen"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1871 easy HIH140-2","question":"What is a true white horse?","answer":"One that's born white & dies white	  (also accept: white hair, pink skin, & blue, brown, or hazel eyes)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1872 easy HIH140-2/HH4/TH80","question":"Which color varies from a bright yellowish red to a rich mahogany red with a red or flaxen mane & tail?","answer":"Chestnut  or sorrel     "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1873 easy HIH140-1","question":"What color would you call a black horse that has tan or brown hairs on the muzzle or flank?","answer":"Seal brown     (brown)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1874 easy TH80/HH4","question":"What color is a horse that has a reddish brown body & a black mane & tail?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1875 easy HIH140-1","question":"How can you tell whether a horse is black or seal brown?","answer":"Black horses have no areas of brown; seal brown horses have tan or brown hairs on their muzzle, flank, and/or buttocks"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1876 easy HIH140-2","question":"Describe a snip.","answer":"Small patch of white hairs on the muzzle "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1877 easy TH82/HH7","question":"What do you call a blue or whitish eye?","answer":"Glass eye, watch eye, or wall eye 	(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1878 easy HIH140-2","question":"Name 2 of the 5 major VARIATIONS of coat colors.","answer":"Dun, gray, roan, palomino, pinto"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1879 easy HIH140-1/HH4/TH80","question":"Name 3 of the 5 BASIC coat colors.","answer":"Black, bay, chestnut or sorrel, brown, white    "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1880 easy HIH140-1","question":"What color is the mane & tail on a chestnut?","answer":"Red (reddish brown) or flaxen           "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1881 easy HIH140-2","question":"Red, strawberry & blue are variations of which color?","answer":"Roan"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1882 easy HIH140-1","question":"Where do you find the black points on a horse?","answer":"Mane, tail & legs"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1883 easy HH4/TH80","question":"How many basic coat colors are there?","answer":"5"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1884 easy HH4/TH81","question":"How many major variations of horse coat colors are there?","answer":"5"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1885 easy HIH140-1","question":"Most so-called white horses are really which color?","answer":"Gray"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1886 easy HIH140-2","question":"Describe the facial marking "stripeï¿½.","answer":"Long, narrow band of white from the forehead down towards the muzzle"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1887 easy HH7/CAHA4","question":"What is the term for a patch of white hair between a horse's eyes?","answer":"Star"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1888 easy TH82/HH7","question":"What term refers to both white on the face covering the eye area or to one defective eye?","answer":"Wall eyed"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1889 easy HH7/TH82","question":"What is the term for a horse whose iris is a light color?","answer":"Glass eye, wall eye or watch eye		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1890 easy HH5","question":"The mealy mouthed description is most likely to be found in what color horse?","answer":"Bay or brown"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1891 easy HIH140-2","question":"Name 3 of the 5 white face markings.","answer":"Star, stripe, blaze, snip, bald face"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1892 easy HIH140-1","question":"What is the term for a dun horse whose yellow hairs are mixed with brown or black?","answer":"Grulla"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1893 easy HH4","question":"Describe the markings of a zebra dun.","answer":"Dun horse with black points & zebra stripes on legs and/or withers"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1894 easy HH4/TH485","question":"What is the term used for a gray horse that has a lot of black in his coat?","answer":"Steel gray"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1895 easy TH485/HH5","question":"Define flea-bitten.","answer":"Dark colored flecks on a gray coat color     (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1896 easy HH6","question":"What term means large roan spots on some base color?","answer":"Patched"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1898 easy HH6","question":"What term means a lack of uniformity in color, a dull, dirty tone?","answer":"Ratty"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1899 easy HH6","question":"What term means darker patches, dull finish, or dark overcast?","answer":"Toasted"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1900 easy HIH140-1","question":"A chestnut horse whose mane & tail are lighter in color than the body is called what?","answer":"Flaxen"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1901 easy ES43","question":"The coat color of a dun and grulla are different, however, they   both have what characteristic marking?","answer":"Dorsal stripe (do not accept black points or head is darker than body"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1902 easy DET11, 205, 298","question":"In general, the terms ankle, pastern, zebra stripes & distal spots share what common characteristic?","answer":"Types of leg markings                 "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"easy","number":"1903 easy HH6","question":"What are the 2 most common dorsal stripe colors?","answer":"Red & black"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1904 medium TH46","question":"The word "pinto" is derived from a Spanish word meaning what?","answer":"Painted, paint or spotted  	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1905 medium TH56","question":"The Cheyenne Indians thought Spanish mustangs with what color pattern possessed supernatural powers of protection? ","answer":"Medicine Hat "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1906 medium HIH159-3,163B-1,1040-3","question":"Describe the tovero color pattern.","answer":"Combination of the tobiano & overo patterns - clearly doesn't belong in either one"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1907 medium TH80","question":"In reference to coat colors, what are 2 common names for a very dark chocolate shade of chestnut?","answer":"Liver chestnut or black chestnut"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1908 medium DET6","question":"Why are most white horses not considered albinos?","answer":"The majority have pigmented/colored eyes ï¿½ true albinos have no eye pigment/color"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1909 medium TH47","question":"What pinto pattern has a dark base color with white spots?","answer":"Overo"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1910 medium TH47","question":"Your Paint horse has 2 solid legs & 2 white stockings.  His face has a wide blaze & the white body markings are irregularly spotted.  What type of spotting pattern does this horse have?","answer":"Overo"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1911 medium TH82","question":"To be classified as a blaze, the white must cover the full width of which bones?","answer":"Nasal"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1912 medium HIH177-2,164B-2","question":"Dark hairs in the mane or tail of a palomino must not exceed what percent?","answer":"15%"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1913 medium TH83","question":"What are distal spots?","answer":"Dark spots on a white coronet or pastern"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1914 medium TH46/ES47/DET246","question":"What is the general or slang term that describes the color of a bay & white pinto?","answer":"Skewbald   (addtl info:  skewbald is any color spotting - other than black ï¿½ with white"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1915 medium HIH140-1/DET42,86","question":"Identify the horse color from the following description:  Body color is yellowish or gold.  Mane & tail may be black, brown, red, white or mixed.  Has a dorsal stripe & usually has zebra stripes on legs and transverse stripe over the withers","answer":"Dun	 (buckskins do not have dorsal stripes)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1916 medium HIH159-3/TH48","question":"Which Paint color pattern is being described?  All 4 legs are white below the knees & hocks.  The horse has a star & stripe.  The white body markings are regular, oval-shaped, distinct & extend down the neck & chest.  White crosses the back.","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1917 medium DET178/TH129","question":"What is the name of the pigment that is responsible for the color of the skin, hair & eyes?","answer":"Melanin"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"Medium","number":"1918 Medium ES38","question":"What is the general term for markings such as a dorsal stripe, cobwebbing on the forehead, zebra stripes on the legs and a wither stripe or shadowing?","answer":"Primitive markings    (also accept dun factors)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1919 medium DET84","question":"Describe an eel stripe.","answer":"Continuous black stripe down horse's back from mane to tail"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1920 medium DET6","question":"What do you call the congenital absence of pigment in the skin, hair & eyes of an animal?","answer":"Albino or albinism 	(Addtl info:  there are no true albino horses)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1921 medium DET84","question":"What do you call a body marking that is a continuous black stripe running down the horse's back from mane to tail?","answer":"Dorsal stripe or eel stripe    "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1922 medium TH81","question":"If a horse is called a "rose gray", what is its base color?","answer":"Chestnut or bay"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1923 medium HIH1040-3","question":"What is the rarest pinto pattern?","answer":"Sabino"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1924 medium TH82","question":"Describe the difference between a stripe & a blaze.","answer":"Blaze is wider - covers the width of the nasal bones"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1925 medium HIH140-1/TH51","question":"What color is a horse whose body is smoky or mouse colored with a black mane & tail.  It also usually has a dorsal stripe & black points.","answer":"Grulla"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1926 medium TH82","question":"What does the term "watch eye" mean?","answer":"Another name for glass eye          (iris is clear or blue)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1927 medium HIH140-1","question":"Describe an overo.","answer":"Paint/Pinto that doesn't usually have white across the back.  Spots are irregular/jagged edges.  Often has a bald face.  "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1928 medium TH59/HIH1040-2","question":"Describe the  color "silver dapple" or ï¿½blue silverï¿½.","answer":"Blueish or brown with very light manes, tails & lower legs
(Additional info -- silver dapple gene makes black areas pale & leaves red areas unaffected)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1929 medium TH81","question":"The gray color pattern on a bay or chestnut horse is called what type of gray?","answer":"Rose gray"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1930 medium TH53","question":"What color horse is known as the horse of heroes, history, art & fiction?","answer":"White"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"medium","number":"1931 medium ES45","question":"What term refers to bursts of white on a gray coat color?","answer":"Rosettes        "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1932 hard TH493","question":"Which pinto color pattern can be confused with blotchy roaning?","answer":"Sabino"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1933 hard TH83","question":"A chestnut horse has a hind leg with white that extends to the pastern.  In this white area there are liver-colored spots.  What is the term for these spots?","answer":"Distal spots or ermine spots"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1934 hard TH59","question":"A coat color of dappled chestnut with a silver mane & tail is commonly associated with which breed?","answer":"Shetland pony, Miniature Horse or Rocky Mountain Horse		 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1935 hard BEG110-1L","question":"In general terms, what distinguishes the difference between tovero, overo & tobiano Paint horses?","answer":"Location of color on the horse"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1936 hard TH492","question":"In this type of spotted coat pattern the white rises from the bottom side of the horse and the legs are white with clearly defined edges between the colored and white areas.  There is extensive white on the face.  What is this pattern?","answer":"Splashed white  "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1937 hard TH81","question":"What color is a horse with an ivory coat color & rusty points?","answer":"Perlino"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1938 hard ES39","question":"A dark colored (usually red or brown) splotch on the base coat color is called what?","answer":"Blood mark or handprint  "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1939 hard ES40","question":"Referring to markings, what is an ink spot?","answer":"Small dark-colored spot seen on the white area of a Paint or Pinto"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1940 hard DET58","question":"Describe the color "claybank".","answer":"Very light red dun (light copper color)"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1941 hard DET58","question":"What do you call a variation of the red dun color - body color is light copper with mane & tail a darker shade?","answer":"Claybank"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1942 hard ES47","question":"Small, dark-colored spots on a roan coat are called what?","answer":"Corn spots"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1943 hard ES48","question":"Frame, sabino & splashed white are 3 color patterns within which more general Paint color pattern - overo or tobiano?","answer":"Overo"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1944 hard ES49","question":"What is the term described as a "speckled, flecked & jagged Paint color pattern"?","answer":"Sabino"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1945 hard DET110","question":"What is the name of coat markings or areas of the skin where there is no pigment?","answer":"Flesh marks"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1946 hard TH81","question":"Describe the color perlino.","answer":"Ivory color with rusty points"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1947 hard ES93","question":"2 part question:  The pigment melanin comes in 2 forms.  Name them & the colors they control","answer":"Eumelanin - controls black or brown;                pheomelanin - controls red or yellow"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1948 hard TH82","question":"What is the term used for a horse that is almost entirely white except for colored areas over the ears & perhaps the eyes, chest & base of tail?","answer":"Medicine Hat"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1949 hard ES p. 41 ","question":"When referring to chestnut horses, what is a ruano? ","answer":"A red colored horse with lighter points or a flaxen mane & tail "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1950 hard ES41","question":"When referring to a chestnut horse what does the term ï¿½tostadaï¿½ describe?","answer":"A red colored horse with darker red-colored points"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1951 hard TH489","question":"The Taffy color common to the Australian pony is the same as what color seen in Shetland ponies.","answer":"Silver Dapple"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1952 hard DET209","question":"What color dilution is often referred to as type B albino?","answer":"Perlino				"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1953 hard DET171","question":"Describe a ï¿½coyote dunï¿½?			","answer":"A dun with black points and a black dorsal stripe?"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"hard","number":"1954 hard DET71","question":"What color describes a dun with black points & a black dorsal stripe?","answer":"Coyote dun                "},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1955 bonus HIH154B-1/DET71","question":"Name 3 types of dun besides a yellow dun.","answer":"Zebra dun, grulla, red dun, brindle dun, claybank, apricot dun, coyote dun"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1956 bonus HH4","question":"Name the 5 basic coat colors.","answer":"Black, brown, chestnut, bay, white"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1957 bonus TH82","question":"The term "wall eye" can mean 3 different things.  Name them.","answer":"Light blue or hazel eye, defective eye, white spot over the eye area"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1958 bonus HIH140-1/TH47","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the overo color pattern.","answer":"White doesn't cross back, one or more legs are dark, spots irregular or splashy, often have bald, bonnet or apron face"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1959 bonus HIH140-1/TH48","question":"Name 3 characteristics of the tobiano color pattern","answer":"White crosses back, head is solid color or has white face marking, all 4 legs are white below knees & hocks, spots are regular, oval shaped & distinct, one or both flanks are usually solid"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1960 bonus TH81","question":"What are the 3 color variations that describe a roan?","answer":"Red, strawberry & blue"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1961 bonus ES45/TH485/HH4-5","question":"Name 3 color variations of a gray horse.","answer":"Dapple gray, fleabitten, steel gray, rosettes, rose gray"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1962 bonus HIH173-1","question":"Name 3 dun factors.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, leg barring/zebra stripes, shoulder stripe or shadow/cape, black ear tips, cobwebbing/face masking, neck stripes, mane & tail frosting"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1963 bonus TH81","question":"The basic coat colors of the horse can be modified 4 different ways.  Name them","answer":"Dilution, roaning, graying, spotting"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1964 bonus ES38","question":"Name 4 primitive markings of the horse or ass.","answer":"Dorsal stripe, wither stripe/cross, zebra stripes, cobwebbing/spider webbing on forehead"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1965 bonus TH82","question":"Name 3 face markings that have more white than a blaze.","answer":"Bald face, bonnet face, apron face, medicine hat"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1966 bonus HIH140-2/TH83","question":"Other than the 5 main white markings, name 3 different leg markings","answer":"Distal spots/ermine spots, inside heel, outside heel, zebra stripes"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1967 bonus TH80/HIH140-2","question":"What are 3 characteristics of true white horses?","answer":"White hair, pink skin, brown/blue/hazel eyes, born & dies same color"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1968 bonus TH80/HH5","question":"Roan horses have a combination of white & colored hairs.  What are the 3 most common base colors of a roan?","answer":"Black, bay & chestnut"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1969 bonus TH81/HH4-5","question":"What are the 5 major variations of horse coat color?","answer":"Dun, gray, palomino, roan, pinto"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1971 bonus HIH140-2","question":"Name the 5 white leg markings.","answer":"Coronet, pastern, ankle or sock, half stocking, full stocking"},
{"category":"COLORS & MARKINGS","level":"bonus","number":"1972 bonus HIH140-2","question":"Name the 5 white face markings.","answer":"Star, stripe, blaze, snip, bald face."},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1973 easy HIH220-6","question":"Why is it important to have a 45 degree angle to the shoulder?","answer":"Allows foreleg to extend the stride          (longer stride)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1974 easy H1-13","question":"Why are the withers used as the measuring spot for a horse's height?","answer":"Highest, non-movable part of the horse"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1975 easy HIH1060-3","question":"Describe parrot mouth.","answer":"Lower jaw is shorter than upper jaw  	   (overshot jaw)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1976 easy HIH220-4","question":"Name the defect where the upper jaw is shorter than the lower jaw","answer":"Monkey mouth --- also accept Overshot jaw"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1977 easy HIH230-7/DET71/TH154","question":"When looking at the horse from the rear, how would you describe a horse whose hocks are too close together?","answer":"Cow hocked"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1978 easy HIH1060-5","question":"What is the term for the conformation defect where the upper teeth extend beyond the lower teeth?","answer":"Parrot mouth            (also accept parrot mouth)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1979 easy HIH220-6","question":"Describe a coon-footed horse.","answer":"Too much slope at pasterns OR long, sloping pasterns     (fetlock may hit the ground as the horse moves)
(accept either)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1980 easy HIH220-4/HH9","question":"Describe monkey mouth (undershot jaw)","answer":"Upper jaw (maxilla) is shorter than lower jaw (mandible)        accept any reasonable wording  "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1981 easy HS6","question":"Name one time when the front feet & legs serve primarily to support the horse.","answer":"When horse is at rest, when landing over a jump, when on leading foreleg at lope/gallop
(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1982 easy HIH230-6","question":"What is another term for back at the knees?","answer":"Calf-kneed"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1983 easy HIH230-5,6","question":"Which condition is more serious, over at the knee or back at the knee?","answer":"Back at the knee"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1984 easy HIH220-3","question":"What is a base wide horse?","answer":"One that has a greater distance between their front feet at the ground than at the chest"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1985 easy TH124/HIH220-4","question":"What is the term for a horse with small eyes?","answer":"Pig eyed"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1986 easy HH10","question":"At what angle should the head join the neck?","answer":"45 degrees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1987 easy HIH230-2","question":"What do you call a horse that toes out in front?","answer":"Splay footed or toed out"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1988 easy HH8/TH144","question":"What is the term for protruding eyes?","answer":"Bug eyed or bovine eyes"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1989 easy TH144/H2-6","question":"Parrot mouth or overshot jaw is a conformation defect involving what bone?","answer":"Mandible &/or maxilla	 (accept either) "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1990 easy HIH220-3/TH144","question":"Describe a horse with lop ears.","answer":"Ears positioned on sides of head OR ears pointing outwards/carried horizontally"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1991 easy HIH220-4","question":"Typically, which horse will be more responsive to the bit - a shallow mouthed or a deep mouthed one?","answer":"Shallow mouthed"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1992 easy HIH220-3","question":"Give 2 descriptive terms for ideal stock horse ears.","answer":"Small, short, pointed, straight, set wide apart"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1993 easy HIH220-6","question":"Give 2 descriptive terms for ideal stock horse pasterns.","answer":"Medium length, strong, clean, sloping at 45 degree angle, angle same as shoulder angle"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1994 easy HIH230-7","question":"What is cow-hocked?","answer":"Hocks close together, feet wide apart"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1995 easy TH135","question":"In reference to conformation, describe a horse that is "built downhill"?","answer":"Height at hips is higher than height at withers OR height at the withers is lower than height at the hips"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1996 easy HIH230-6","question":"What is calf-kneed?","answer":"Knees bent backward"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1997 easy TH154/HH9","question":"Describe goose rumped.","answer":"Short, steep croup"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1998 easy HIH230-1,2","question":"What is the difference between splay foot & pigeon toe?","answer":"Splayfoot - front toes turned out/heels turned in; 
Pigeon toe - front toes turned in/heels turned out"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"1999 easy HH10/HIH220-4","question":"What is Roman nosed?","answer":"Face bows out instead of being flat    (convex face)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2000 easy HIH220-6","question":"What angle of slope should the shoulder have?","answer":"45 - 50 degrees		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2001 easy TH154/HH9","question":"Name an undesirable trait of the croup.","answer":"Goose rumped"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2002 easy HIH230-7","question":"What is the most common defect in the rear legs?","answer":"Cow hocks"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2003 easy HIH220-6","question":"Why should the bottom line of a horse be longer than the top line?","answer":"For a longer stride	(also accept so the legs donï¿½t interfere)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2004 easy HIH230-6","question":"What is buck-kneed?","answer":"Knees bent forward"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2005 easy HIH220-6","question":"Why shouldn't a horse have low, flat withers?","answer":"They don't hold a saddle very well"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2006 easy HIH230-7","question":"What is the term for a horse possessing too little angle in the hock?","answer":"Post legged"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2007 easy HIH220-6","question":"Give one reason why the pastern should have adequate slope.","answer":"If it's too straight, it doesn't cushion the shock of the foot striking the ground (shock absorption)
Predisposes horse to navicular disease, more concussion, can lead to injury and/or rough ride"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2008 easy HIH230-1","question":"What do all breeds have in common?","answer":"Skeletal structure"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2009 easy HIH230-1","question":"What is the term for toes pointing inward?","answer":"Pigeon toe or toe-in"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2010 easy HIH230-7","question":"What is the term for a horse with too much angle in the hock?","answer":"Sickle hocked"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2011 easy HIH220-4","question":"What is a pig-eyed horse?","answer":"Horse with small eyes"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2012 easy HH9","question":"Name a conformation fault of the neck","answer":"Ewe necked"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2013 easy HH11","question":"What is the ideal angle of hoof to ground?","answer":"45 degrees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2014 easy HH9","question":"Describe the term "paunchy".","answer":"Too much belly"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2284 easy HIH450-6/TH152/DET260","question":"Describe swayback.","answer":"Concave appearance of back             (back sags down)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2285 easy HH9/TH152","question":"Describe roached back.","answer":"Convex appearance of back OR back arched up	(accept either)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2286 easy HH9/TH133","question":"What term means that a horse is proportionally as long as it is tall?","answer":"Balance"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2287 easy HIH220-6","question":"Besides supporting the weight of the saddle & rider, what is another reason that the loin should be short & strong?","answer":"Carries power from the hind legs forward OR lifts forequarters when horse is in motion
(accept either)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2288 easy HIH230-5","question":"Define the term "camped out behind".","answer":"Hind legs appear to reach out behind a line drawn from the buttock to the ground"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2289 easy HIH230-7","question":"Describe the term "out at the hock".","answer":"Hocks too far apart "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2290 easy HIH230-7","question":"A horse whose hocks are far apart with his feet set close together is said to be what?","answer":"Bow legged, out at the hock, or open behind"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2291 easy HIH220-7","question":"When viewed from the side or rear, name one desirable characteristic of the rear quarters.","answer":"Thick, deep, well-muscled"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2292 easy HIH220-3","question":"To evaluate conformation, it's necessary to know what?","answer":"The parts of the horse	(anatomy)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2293 easy HIH230-5","question":"What is sickle-hocked?","answer":"Too much angle at the hock OR curved, crooked hock when viewed from the side"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2294 easy TH151/HIH230-5 picture","question":"Which movement is a more serious fault ï¿½ inward or outward?	","answer":"Inward"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2295 easy TH153-54/HIH153-54","question":"Name one area of the hindquarter where the muscle should have thickness.","answer":"Thigh, gaskin, stifle"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2296 easy HIH220-4","question":"Name one characteristic you want in a horse's eye.","answer":"Large, clear, set wide apart, bright, bold, alert, soft, kind	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2297 easy HIH220-6","question":"Shoulder, pastern & hoof should all have approximately what angle?","answer":"45 degrees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2298 easy HIH220-8","question":"Body type, color patterns, gaits & way of going are all examples of what type characteristics?","answer":"Breed characteristics"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2299 easy HIH230-2","question":"Define base narrow.","answer":"Horse's legs are closer at the ground than they are at the chest"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2300 easy HIH230-6","question":"Base-wide, narrow-chested horses have feet that are usually what?","answer":"Toed out or splay footed"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2301 easy HIH220-6","question":"Should the topline of a horse be shorter or longer than the underline?","answer":"Shorter"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2302 easy HIH220-4","question":"What is monkey-mouthed?","answer":"Undershot jaw  OR  lower jaw sticks out more than the upper jaw"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2303 easy HIH230-6/TH151","question":"Which is a more serious condition - toed in or toed out?","answer":"Toed out"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2304 easy HIH220-1","question":"What is the term for the physical appearance of an animal?","answer":"Conformation OR phenotype		(accept either)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2305 easy HH9","question":"What part of the horse's body has a conformation problem when it's referred to as being goose rumped?","answer":"Croup or rump"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2306 easy HIH220-6","question":"Why should horses have proper shoulder & pastern angles?","answer":"Shock absorption 		(also accept length of stride, comfortable ride)  "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2307 easy TH139/H1-34","question":"Referring to horses, what is a hand?","answer":"Measurement of height		 (Additional info -- one hand = 4 inches)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2308 easy HH9","question":"What is the average weight of a desirable saddle horse?","answer":"900 - 1300 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2309 easy HIH220-4","question":"What term describes a face that is concave in appearance?","answer":"Dished"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2310 easy HH4","question":"What is tucked up?","answer":"Thin & cut up in the flank like a greyhound"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2311 easy HH9","question":"What is the term for flat-ribbed?","answer":"Slab sided"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2312 easy TH143/HIH220-3","question":"What is the term for the convex profile of a horse's face?","answer":"Roman nose"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2313 easy HH47","question":"If the judge describes your halter horse as being ï¿½open behindï¿½, what is he saying about the horse?","answer":"Hocks are too far apart & feet are too close together"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2314 easy HS10","question":"The cannon bones should give what appearance when viewed from the side?","answer":"Flat           (straight)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2315 easy HIH220-6/ADV323-2L/HH8","question":"A coon-footed horse has too much slope at what joint?","answer":"Pastern"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2316 easy HS9","question":"The length of neck plays an important part in what?","answer":"Length of stride"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2317 easy HIH220-8","question":"In general, what type of muscling is preferred in all breedsï¿½ 1.) thick, bulging muscle with definition, or 2.) long, clean, well-defined muscle?				","answer":"Long, clean and well-defined"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"easy","number":"2318 easy HH9/TH152","question":"What is the term for a thin, sharp, arched back?","answer":"Roached back"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2413 medium DET60","question":"What is the general term thatï¿½s used to describe a horse thatï¿½s closely coupled and stoutly built?","answer":"Cobby"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2414 medium TH162","question":"A horse with a short, steep pastern will endure more concussion and may be predisposed to what disease?","answer":"Navicular disease"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2415 medium HIH230-1","question":"Why is it extremely important that the skeletal structure of the front limbs be correct?","answer":"Because the horse carries over 60% of his weight on his front legs"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2416 medium HS11","question":"What are limber or rotating hocks?","answer":"When points of hocks turn outward"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2417 medium TH145","question":"At rest, what percent more weight do the front legs support than the hind legs?","answer":"9 - 10 percent"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2418 medium HS7/DET53","question":"Where is the center of motion?","answer":"Approximately over the 15th vertebrae OR 10" behind the center of gravity"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2419 medium HS7","question":"Which can be altered the center of motion or center of gravity?","answer":"Center of gravity"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2420 hard HS7","question":"How far behind the center of gravity is the center of motion?","answer":"10 inches"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2421 medium DET222","question":"What is the slang term that describes a short & thickset horse?","answer":"Pudgy"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2422 medium TH146","question":"Steep shoulders are usually associated with what type pasterns?","answer":"Short & steep"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2423 medium CAHA40","question":"If a horse is sickle hocked, excessive strain will be placed on what ligament?","answer":"Plantar   (ligament at back of hock)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2424 medium DET52/HS6","question":"At a standstill, where is the center of gravity located on a horse?","answer":"6 inches behind the elbow OR about the rider's knee in the mid-section of the horse OR near outer edge of the 8th rib		(accept either)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2426 medium TH146","question":"Short, straight pasterns are associated with what other conformation problem?","answer":"Straight, steep, or upright shoulder"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2427 medium TH154","question":"When viewed from the rear, which part of the horse's hindquarters should be the widest?","answer":"Stifle area"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2428 medium HIH220-6","question":"How does the slope of the shoulder influence the length of the stride?","answer":"The steeper/straighter the shoulder the shorter the stride; the more sloping/angular the shoulder, the longer the stride"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2429 medium TH147","question":"A buck-kneed horse is sprung forward or over at the knee.  This is considered a less serious fault than what type of knee conformation?","answer":"Calf kneed or back at the knee"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2431 medium DET129","question":"You do the math:    In inches, how tall is a 16 hand horse?","answer":"64 inches"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2432 medium TH181","question":"What type of deviation in movement usually occurs when a horse is toed in?","answer":"Paddling or winging out"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2433 medium TH151","question":"Winging-in is associated with what conformation defect?","answer":"Splay foot or toed out         "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2434 medium DET600","question":"What term refers to an overhanging of the top lip?","answer":"Elk lip              "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2435 medium TH150/DET84","question":"What are mutton withers?","answer":"Low, flat withers    "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2436 medium DET109","question":"Explain a flat-footed horse.","answer":"When the angle of the foot is less than 45 degrees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2437 medium HS8","question":"Define symmetrical.","answer":"Proper balance or relationship of all parts"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2438 medium HIH220-6","question":"Describe the conformation defect of the leg (not hoof) that predisposes a horse to navicular disease","answer":"Short, steep pasterns"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2439 medium HIH230-7","question":"2 part question:  What are the terms used when there is a) too little angle in the hock and b) too much angle at the hock with the feet set too far under the body?","answer":"Too little angle - post legged; 	too much angle - sickle hocked"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2440 medium TH181/HH11","question":"If a horse has his front legs set too wide on the corners of his body, what is the resulting action?","answer":"Rolling, labored action"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2441 medium HH9","question":"What term describes the condition when all of the parts of a horse blend together well, with long, tapering muscling?","answer":"Smoothness"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2442 medium TH143","question":"The proportions of the head tend to be an indicator of what?","answer":"Body proportions"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2443 medium HIH220-5","question":"The shape of the neck is due largely to the amount & shape of what?","answer":"Muscles"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2444 medium FCH384","question":"A horse that stands camped under in the hind legs usually has what other conformational defect when viewed from the side?","answer":"Sickle hock                            "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2445 medium HIH230-6","question":"2 part question:  What is the best angle for the front & rear pasterns?","answer":"Front - 45 degrees; 		Back - 50 degrees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2446 medium TH139","question":"What term means refinement in the horse?","answer":"Quality"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2447 medium TH144/HIH220-3","question":"Explain the difference between the conformation faults mule ears & lop ears.","answer":"Mule ears - long, thick & heavy; 	lop ears - carried horizontally to the side"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2448 medium TH153-54","question":"What 2 things can influence whether the slope of a horseï¿½s croup is considered desirable?","answer":"Breed preferences & intended use"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2449 medium HIH220-7/TH153-54","question":"What happens when the angle of the croup is too steep?","answer":"Stride is shorter"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2450 medium HIH230-1,250-1","question":"Conformation is directly related to what?","answer":"Skeletal structure	 (also accept action or way of going)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2451 medium HH12","question":"Describe the ideal motion of a horse.","answer":"Straight, true, long, well-coordinated stride       (accept any appropriate answer)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2452 medium ADV323-2L/DET68","question":"What term describes too much angle in the pastern joint?","answer":"Coon footed      "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2453 medium TH146","question":"Name 2 ideal conformation traits that are associated with a long, elastic, springy stride.","answer":"Sloping shoulders & sloping pasterns"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2454 medium HIH230-3","question":"What are bench knees?","answer":"Cannon not centered on knee OR off-set knees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2455 medium TH146 HIH220-6","question":"What generally determines the length of a horse's stride?","answer":"Length /angle of shoulder"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2456 medium TH145/HIH230-5 picture","question":"Which is the more dangerous deviation in the flight of the foot, paddling or dishing?","answer":"Dishing"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2457 medium HIH230-6","question":"Which conformation defect interferes with movements that require work off the haunches such as stopping, turning or sliding?","answer":"Cow hocks"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2458 medium HIH220-7","question":"A flatter & more level croup results in what type of hind leg action - vertical or horizontal?","answer":"More vertical"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2459 medium TH145","question":"What percent of a horse's weight is carried on its forequarters?","answer":"60 - 65%		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2460 medium TH151","question":"Describe the motion of a horse that has low, flat withers.","answer":"Rolling gait & heavy on front end   (overall - moving poorly)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2461 medium HIH230-2","question":"A base-narrow horse is predisposed to landing on what part of the foot?","answer":"Outside hoof wall"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2462 medium TH145","question":"What is the term for an excessively thick crest that lops to the side?","answer":"Broken crest or lop neck"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2463 medium FCH389","question":"What is the term for a neck that has a thickened, rounded underline & a concave top line?","answer":"Ewe neck"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2464 medium TH151","question":"A horse that travels with a rolling gait & a heavy front end often has what type of conformation?","answer":"Low, flat withers                 (also accept round, thick withers or mutton withers)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2465 medium CAHA40","question":"What is a common conformation fault in the rear limbs that puts a strain on the plantar ligament leading to a curb?","answer":"Sickle hocks"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2466 medium DET34","question":"In reference to measurements in horses, how is ï¿½boneï¿½ measured?","answer":"Circumference of the cannon bone about half way between knee & fetlock"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2467 medium HIH220-1","question":"Where can you find a description of the ideal horse's head for a certain breed?","answer":"In the breed association's standards/publications"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2468 medium TH157","question":"Give a reason why you wouldn't consider purchasing a horse with poor conformation","answer":"Predisposes horse to unsoundness OR genetic defects could be passed to offspring"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2469 medium HS9","question":"Why does a thick neck cause increased shock to the front legs?","answer":"Adds excess weight to the front legs      (front legs ordinarily carry more weight than hind ones)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2470 medium TH145","question":"What is a broken crest?","answer":"When horse has excessively thick crest that lops to side   "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2471 medium HIH220-6","question":"What is the most critical conformational factor in the balance of the horse?","answer":"Slope of shoulder"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2472 medium DET58","question":"What is meant when it's said that a horse has "clean legs"?","answer":"No blemishes/unsoundnesses on the legs OR legs from knees/hocks down are all smooth"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2473 medium HIH220-5","question":"Why is a trim throatlatch desirable on a horse?","answer":"Doesn't restrict air/blood flow OR helps in balance "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2474 medium HIH220-6 ","question":"What 2 things are most affected by the angle of the shoulder?","answer":"Length of stride & shock absorption"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"medium","number":"2475 medium HIH220-6","question":"What 2 conformational factors determine how collected, balanced & horizontal movement the horse is?","answer":"Croup angle & hock position               "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2476 hard FCH385","question":"This conformational problem causes the horse to walk on the toe, resulting in the heel growing long and the toe wearing off. The foot will have an upright appearance.  Name this defect.","answer":"Club foot"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2477 hard HS10","question":"What is the most undesirable shoulder & leg conformation?","answer":"Steep shoulder, long arm, short forearm, long cannon"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2478 hard HS9/HIH220-6","question":"Why does a steep shouldered horse generally have a short stride?","answer":"The arm doesn't extend very far forward "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2479 hard HS9","question":"How far rearward should the withers extend?","answer":"Approximately 1/4 the distance from the point of shoulder to rear flank"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2480 hard TH146","question":"What are the two most important aspects of ideal conformation of the forelimbs?","answer":"Slope and angle of the bones; straightness of the limbs"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2481 hard HIH510-1","question":"On the front leg, where is the center of gravity?","answer":"The middle of the leg from point of shoulder down leg to hoof"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2482 hard HS7","question":"How can a horse's center of gravity be altered?","answer":"By rider shifting his weight OR by horse raising, lowering or extending his head"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2483 hard INT223-2","question":"2 part question:  Describe the ideal shape of a horse's withers & identify why this shape is important.","answer":"Shape - sharp, prominent & well-defined;       Why -- helps hold the saddle in place"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2484 hard HIH230-7","question":"What happens as a result of the hocks being too wide apart?","answer":"As horse drives forward, hocks are forced outward & energy is lost OR added strain on bones, ligaments & joints can cause many kinds of movement interference OR horse is predisposed to ringbone and/or sidebone, toeing out, winging		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2485 hard HIH230-1","question":"How would you determine the straightness of a horse's front legs?","answer":"Viewing from the front, you can follow a straight line from the point of shoulder down the leg through the center of the knee, pastern & hoof"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2486 hard HIH220/TH153-54","question":"Which of the following horses will most likely have a longer stride ï¿½ a horse with a long, gently sloping croup or a horse with a short steep croup?","answer":"A horse with a long, gently sloping croup"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2487 hard HIH220-6","question":"In addition to the ratios of the neck line, a change in the slope of a horse's shoulder also affects what other major body ratio?","answer":"Length of back to length of underline		 (Also accept -- top line to bottom line ratio)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2488 hard CAHA11","question":"What conformation defect predisposes a horse to carpal chip fractures, especially in young racehorses?","answer":"Calf knees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2489 hard HIH220-5","question":"What is the determining factor in the ratio of the top to bottom line of the horse's neck?","answer":"Slope of shoulder"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2490 hard HIH220-7","question":"What thoracic characteristics are desirable in the broodmare?","answer":"Good spring of rib & deep depth of heart"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2491 hard TH147","question":"2 part question:  What are the results of the elbow being either too close or too far from the horse's body?","answer":"Too close -- horse will toe out; 	too far - horse will toe in"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2492 hard HH12/TH181","question":"What does excess lateral movement of the feet cause?","answer":"Reduces efficiency & detracts from coordination"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"Hard","number":"2493 Hard HIH220-5 picture","question":"The bottom line of a horse's neck is measured from where to where?","answer":"Throatlatch to the neck/shoulder junction at chest"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2494 hard TH152-3","question":"Why are the length & width of croup important?","answer":"Long muscles are associated with speed & endurance and width of muscling is related to strength & power."},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2495 hard HIH220-6","question":"In a balanced horse, the legs are approximately the same length as what measurement?","answer":"Depth of heart "},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2496 hard TH145-46","question":"What allows the horse to stand tremendous concussion when running?","answer":"Shock absorption properties of the foot"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2497 hard HIH1090-1","question":"What are the most critical parts of conformation that make a horse athletic?","answer":"Long sloping shoulder & long hip"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2498 hard HIH230-5","question":"If a horse is termed base narrow, how would he travel?","answer":"Move his knees outward slightly & swing his feet inward"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2499 hard DET26","question":"Give the slang term for thick, meaty hocks that lack in quality.","answer":"Beefy hocks"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2500 hard HIH230-1","question":"What is greatly increased when a horse has correct skeletal structure?","answer":"Durability OR athletic ability"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2501 hard TH145","question":"What is the relationship of body parts to performance called?","answer":"Form to function	(also accept functional anatomy)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2502 hard HIH220-6","question":"What relationship should there be between a line from the point of shoulder through the shoulder blade and a line through the pastern to the ground?","answer":"They should be parallel"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2503 hard TH145/HIH220-5","question":"If a horse is thick & coarse in the throatlatch, what can happen when he is asked to flex at the poll?","answer":"Air & blood flow may be restricted   (a trim, refined throatlatch will allow the horse to flex at the poll & perform while breathing correctly"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2504 hard HS11","question":"What does a calf-kneed position of the front legs do to the stride?","answer":"Results in pounding gait & hard concussion on the feet"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2505 hard TH155-56","question":"Why do you want a straight leg as viewed from behind?","answer":"To deliver power to the stride"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2506 hard HIH220-5","question":"What is the approximate top to bottom line neck ratio?","answer":"2:1"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2507 hard HIH220-5","question":"Why is the neck an important conformation point?","answer":"Horse uses it as a balance arm"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2508 hard HIH220-5","question":"Camped out horses are predisposed to what 2 things?","answer":"Navicular & laminitis or founder"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2509 hard HIH220-5","question":"Why is balance the single most important characteristic in equine selection?","answer":"Forms basis for movement, length of stride & ultimately performance"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2510 hard HIH230-3/CAHA39","question":"Name a conformation problem that increases the possibility of a horse developing splints.","answer":"Bench knees or offset knees"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"hard","number":"2511 hard DET126","question":"What slang term refers to legs in which the tendons lack definition and do not stand out clearly?","answer":"Gummy legged				"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2512 bonus TH152","question":"When viewed from the side, what is the best combination of length for the various parts of the front quarters?","answer":"Long shoulder, short arm, long forearm, short cannon"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2513 bonus TH147","question":"Name 3 characteristics of a good knee.","answer":"Large, broad, flat, wide, clean, capable of great flexion, straight when viewed from side or front"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2514 bonus TH145","question":"Name 3 purposes of the forequarters.","answer":"Provide propulsion in front, serve as base of support, shock absorption"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2515 bonus TH145","question":"Name 3 things that depend on the conformation of the forequarters.","answer":"Length of stride, smoothness of gait, soundness of legs, power/propulsion"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2516 bonus HIH250-1","question":"In a balanced horse, what 3 areas of the horse should be approximately the same measurement?","answer":"Height at hips, height at withers, length of body"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2517 bonus HIH220-1","question":"Name 3 things - not including parts - that you consider when evaluating a horse's conformation.","answer":"Type, muscling, balance, structural smoothness, form, proportion of various body parts"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2518 bonus HIH220-3","question":"Attractive, well-conformed heads for most breeds have common characteristics.  Name 3.","answer":"Short/well-set ears, large/bold eyes, refined muzzles, "breediness", large nostrils, short from eye to muzzle, sex characteristics (mares look feminine, stallions & gelding look masculine)"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2519 bonus HIH230","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the hindleg.","answer":"Stands wide, stands close, bow-legged/out at the hock, cow-hocked, sickle hock, post legged, camped out, camped under"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2520 bonus TH147","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the horse's body excluding its legs.","answer":"Plain/coarse head, mutton withers, sway back, roach back, ewe neck, straight shoulders, paunchy/pot belly, wasp waisted/tucked up, narrow chest, shoulders too wide, short/thick neck, slab sided"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2521 bonus TH150","question":"When viewed from the side, what 3 parts of the forequarters should be in a straight line with the shoulders?","answer":"Forearm, knee, cannon"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2522 bonus TH141","question":"Give 3 characteristics of a coarse head.","answer":"Large ears, thick muzzle, Roman nose, small eye (pig eye), thick throatlatch/neck, long head"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2523 bonus INT223-2L","question":"Name 3 things whose length is determined by shoulder angle.","answer":"Length of neck, length of stride, length of back, depth of heart"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2524 bonus HIH220-3","question":"Where should the head be a) broad, b) short, c) deep?","answer":"Broad in forehead/between eyes, short from eyes to nostrils, deep in jaws"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2525 bonus HS8","question":"Give 3 reasons why gaskin muscles should be powerful","answer":"They give strength to the legs in turning & pivoting, to pull leg forward & enable propulsion, to give a long, powerful stride"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2526 bonus HIH220","question":"The length of a horse's stride is related to what 3 things?","answer":"Length of shoulder & pastern, length of forearm & gaskin, length of neck"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2527 bonus TH145-57/HH230","question":"What are 3 structural faults of the front legs?","answer":"Base narrow, base wide, bench/offset knees, bow legs, buck knee, calf knee, coon footed, straight pasterns, tied in at knee, knock knee. Toe in/pigeon toe, toe out/splay foot"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2528 bonus HS11","question":"When viewing the rear quarters from the side, what is the best combination of parts to give the best stride?","answer":"Long croup, short thigh, long gaskin, short cannon"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2529 bonus TH152","question":"Give 2 common terms used to describe a horse that is weak in the coupling & shallow in the flank.","answer":"Hound-gutted, herring-gutted, wasp waisted, lady waisted, tucked up"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2530 bonus HIH various","question":"Name 5 conformation faults whose common name refers to another animal species.","answer":"Parrot mouth, monkey mouth, ewe neck, calf knee, pigeon toe, cow hocked, coon footed, pig eye, roach back, wasp waist, cow eyes, goose rump, herring/hound gut"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2531 bonus TH147","question":"Give 3 anatomical defects associated with a horseï¿½s knee & explain each.","answer":"Bowlegged - entire leg appears to bend outward when viewed from front; 
Knock knee/close knee - entire knee set to inside of straight line from chest to toe;
Bench knee/offset knee - cannon bones set too far to outside of knee;
Calf knee/back at knee - knees bend backward (hyperextend);
Buck knee/over at knee - knees sprung forward"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2532 bonus TH150","question":"Long, sloping pasterns will put strain on what 3 things?","answer":"Tendons, sesamoid bones, suspensory ligaments"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2533 bonus HH11","question":"Name 3 ideal features in the bones of the legs.","answer":"Flat, clean, free from fleshiness & puffiness, adequate strength/substance to support the horse during activity"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2534 bonus CAHA39/HIH/HHvarious","question":"Name 3 conformation faults of the horse's knee.","answer":"Calf knee, buck knee, bench/offset knee, knock knee, cut under at knee"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2535 bonus HIH250-1,2","question":"Besides dividing a horse's body into thirds, name 3 measurements that should be the same in a balanced horse.","answer":"Length of neck & length of head; depth of heart & length of leg; height at withers & height at hips; width of shoulders & width of hindquarters"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2536 bonus HIH220-4","question":"List 3 undesirable characteristics of the head.","answer":"Roman nose, pig eyes, parrot mouth, monkey mouth, mule ears, lop ears"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2537 bonus HH10,11","question":"Name 3 areas on the front section of the horse that have an approximate 45 degree angle.","answer":"Head joined to neck, shoulder, pastern, hoof to the ground"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2538 bonus HIH220-6","question":"Name 3 features of ideal withers.","answer":"Sharp, prominent, well defined, as high as hips"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2539 bonus TH154/HH11","question":"Name 3 desirable characteristics of the hock.","answer":"Wide, deep, clean, large"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2540 bonus TH152","question":"Describe 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's ribs.","answer":"Well-sprung, long, close"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2541 bonus INT223,225","question":"What are 3 things that correct structure provides?","answer":"Symmetry, smoothness, quickness/balance to action"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2542 bonus TH146-56","question":"Name 3 parts of the horse that should be long.","answer":"Shoulder, forearm, croup, gaskin, neck, withers"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2543 bonus HIH220-4/TH144","question":"What are 3 characteristics you want in the eye?","answer":"Deep, wide-spaced, large, clear, bold, alert, soft/kind expression"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2544 bonus TH152-54","question":"In what 3 areas of the hindquarters should muscles have thickness?","answer":"Thigh, gaskin, stifle"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2545 bonus TH149-50","question":"Name 3 characteristics of good cannons.","answer":"Short, broad, straight, flat, tendons clearly defined, set well back"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2546 bonus HS8","question":"The forehand refers to the forepart of a horse & consists of 3 areas.  Name them.","answer":"Head & neck, shoulders, forelegs"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2547 bonus HIH220-5","question":"Name 2 characteristics of a good neck.","answer":"Long, lean, attached high on shoulders with prominent withers"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2548 bonus HIH510-2","question":"Name 3 things that may affect a horse's foot balance.","answer":"Conformation, gait, speed, level of training, hoof length, shoe weight, head position, head weight, rider's skill, rider's weight, load being pulled/carried"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2549 bonus HIH220-6/TH151","question":"What are 3 reasons why the back & loin must be strong?","answer":"Protect the internal organs, bear weight of rider, transmit propulsion generated by the hind legs"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2550 bonus HIH505-1/HH11","question":"What are 3 desirable characteristics of a horse's hoof?","answer":"Well-shaped, roomy, balanced in size with horse"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2551 bonus HHvarious/HIHvarious","question":"What are 3 normal measurements pertinent to a horse's size?","answer":"Height, weight, girth, bone"},
{"category":"CONFORMATION","level":"bonus","number":"2552 bonus TH153","question":"In what 2 ways is the angle of the croup important to the stride of a horse?","answer":"Length, efficiency"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2553 easy TH93/HIH405-1,2","question":"What type of jaw movement is necessary for a horse to grind its food?","answer":"Lateral or side to side movement"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2554 easy HIH705-1","question":"What is the technical name for chewing?","answer":"Mastication"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2555 easy ES111","question":"Which takes more time to pass from the horseï¿½s stomach into the small intestineï¿½hay or water?","answer":"Hay"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2556 easy HIH705-2","question":"What part of the digestive system is referred to as a blind pouch?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2557 easy HIH705-1/TH190/HS27","question":"What does mastication mean?","answer":"Chewing"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2558 easy HIH705-2","question":"What is the final part of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Rectum	 (also accept anus)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2559 easy HIH360-2","question":"The average 1000 pound horse can produce how much manure in one day?","answer":"28 - 50 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2560 easy HIH710-1,705-1","question":"In which part of the digestive system does the majority of digestion/absorption occur?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2561 easy INT203-1/HIH705","question":"Of the following 3 organs, where does food stay the least amount of time in the digestive system:  stomach, small intestine, or large intestine?","answer":"Stomach"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2562 easy ES700","question":"What term describes the breakdown of feed into its smaller components?","answer":"Digestion			"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2563 easy HS23","question":"How many compartments are in a horse's stomach?","answer":"One"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2564 easy TH190/HIH705-1","question":"In reference to digestion, describe 2 main functions of the horse's mouth.","answer":"Intake food, chew food, wet food with saliva"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2565 easy HIH635-2","question":"How does the great length of the small intestine lead to many problems?","answer":"Gets twisted or telescoped"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2566 easy HS29","question":"How long does it take to completely empty a horse's stomach?","answer":"24 hours after eating"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2567 easy HS27","question":"What do we call the grasping of food in order to get it into the mouth?","answer":"Prehension"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2568 easy HIH705/DET81","question":"The mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, small intestine, large intestine, rectum, and anus are all parts of what system of the horse? ","answer":"Digestive system "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2569 easy HIH705-1","question":"Saliva is produced by what gland?","answer":"Salivary gland"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2570 easy HIH705-1","question":"Why do you need to have knowledge of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"So you know how to feed them correctly OR you know how to look for signs of colic	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2571 easy HIH705-1","question":"What is the purpose of the esophagus?","answer":"Moves feed from the mouth/pharynx to the stomach"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2572 easy HS31","question":"What is the name given to the waste matter of digestion?","answer":"Manure or feces"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2573 easy HIH710-1,705-1","question":"Where does digestion begin?","answer":"In the mouth"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2574 easy HIH705-1","question":"What is produced by the salivary glands?","answer":"Saliva"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2575 easy HIH705-1","question":"Which system of the horse is responsible for converting feed into a form that can be utilized by the body?","answer":"Digestive"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2576 easy HIH705-1/TH190","question":"What is the first part of the digestive system?","answer":"Mouth"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2577 easy HS31","question":"What does defecation mean?","answer":"Pooping "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2578 easy HIH705-1","question":"What is the horse's main structure for grasping food?","answer":"Lips	 (also accept upper lip)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2579 easy HS27","question":"What stimulates the secretion of saliva in the horse?","answer":"Chewing"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"easy","number":"2580 easy HS27","question":"What does prehension mean?","answer":"Grasping of food"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2581 medium TH127","question":"What is the function of the horse's pancreas?","answer":"Secretes insulin & enzymes"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2582 medium HIH710-1","question":"Excess gas produced in the stomach can cause what?","answer":"Rupture of the stomach & death"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2583 medium TH606 DET6, 81, 118","question":"What is the name of the tract that consists of a musculo-membraneous tube that extends from the mouth to the anus?","answer":"Digestive tract,  Gastrointestinal tract or alimentary canal"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2584 medium HIH742-3,4","question":"What are probiotics used for?","answer":"To increase the population of beneficial micro-organisms in the digestive tract"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2585 medium HS27","question":"Where do most of the fats get digested?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2586 medium DET56","question":"What is the material leaving the stomach & entering the small intestine called?","answer":"Chyme"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2587 medium HIH710-2","question":"Where in the digestive tract are amino acids synthesized?","answer":"Large intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2588 medium HIH705-1","question":"What organ of the horse secretes gastric juices?","answer":"Stomach"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2589 medium HIH710-2/ES112","question":"Hay is digested primarily in what part of the digestive system?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2590 medium HIH710,705-1","question":"How long is the horse's small intestine?","answer":"65-70 feet 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2591 medium HIH710-1","question":"The salivary glands, pancreas & liver are accessory organs of what system?","answer":"Digestive"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2592 medium FCH395","question":"What is the name for chemical reactions occurring in the body?","answer":"Metabolism"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2593 medium HIH705-1","question":"Continued exposure of the lower part of the stomach to excessive gastric secretions can cause what?","answer":"Gastric ulcers"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2594 medium HIH705-1","question":"What does the enzyme pepsin do?","answer":"Helps digest proteins"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2595 medium HIH705-1","question":"Which enzyme helps digest proteins?","answer":"Pepsin	(also accept trypsin)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2596 medium HIH705-1","question":"What are 2 things that happen in the small colon?","answer":"Any remaining water is removed;      fecal balls are formed"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2597 medium HIH705-1","question":"Why is the cecum sometimes called a blind pouch?","answer":"Because feedstuffs both enter & exit at the top "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2598 medium CAHA52/HIH710-2","question":"The horse's small colon lies between what 2 other parts of the horse's digestive system?","answer":"Large colon & rectum				"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2599 medium CAHA54","question":"What 2 organs deliver enzymes & products into the duodenum to assist in the digestive process?","answer":"Pancreas & liver"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2600 medium HIH710-2","question":"Your horse is experiencing recurrent mild colic.  Your veterinarian is listening to the right side of your horse's abdomen for rumbling, gurgling noises.  What specific part of the digestive tract is he listening to?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2601 medium HIH705-1","question":"What is the esophagus?","answer":"A muscular tube that extends from the pharynx to the stomach"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2602 medium TH192","question":"Why doesn't a horse need a gall bladder?","answer":"Horses graze/eat many small meals, so there's no need for a gall bladder;  bile is constantly secreted & therefore doesnï¿½t need to be stored;  (a gall bladder allows bile to be stored so that large amounts can be released in response to eating a large meal)		(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2603 medium HIH710-1","question":"What is the process by which fiber is digested?","answer":"Fermentation"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2604 medium HIH710-1/TH199","question":"The soluble carbohydrates are digested & absorbed in what part of the digestive system?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2605 medium HIH710-2","question":"How long is the large colon?","answer":"10 - 12 feet		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2606 medium TH201","question":"Where is the primary site of water absorption?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2607 medium HIH705-2,710-2","question":"Which part of the horse's large intestine has the largest capacity?","answer":"Large colon"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2608 medium TH127","question":"Insulin controls glucose levels in the horse's body.  Where is it produced?","answer":"Pancreas"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2609 medium DET153","question":"What is the function of insulin?","answer":"Controls blood sugar levels & the utilization of sugar in the body"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2610 medium HIH 435a-1","question":"Why is the small intestine susceptible to displacement, telescoping, or twisting?","answer":"Its long length & its loose attachment to the abdominal wall (mesentery) 	 "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2611 medium HIH705-2","question":"Where are the characteristic balls of feces formed?","answer":"Small colon"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2612 medium HS25","question":"The cecum lies between what 2 parts of the horse's digestive system?	","answer":"Small intestine (ileum) & large colon"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2613 medium HIH710-2","question":"How long is the cecum?","answer":"4 feet"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2614 medium HIH710-2","question":"What is the muscular tube 50 - 60 inches in length which extends from the pharynx to the stomach?","answer":"Esophagus"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2615 medium HIH705-1/TH192","question":"What is the name of the dark green-yellow substance secreted by the liver?","answer":"Bile"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2616 medium HS28","question":"What does deglutition mean?","answer":"Swallowing"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2617 medium HS23","question":"Because the upper jaw is wider than the lower jaw, how does mastication occur?","answer":"On one side of the jaw at a time	(also accept in a circular motion)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2618 medium TH190","question":"Where is the small intestine located in the horse?","answer":"Between stomach and cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2619 medium HS26","question":"Most farm animals have an organ that stores bile, but horses do not.  What is this organ?","answer":"Gall bladder"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2620 medium HS28","question":"What is the technical name for swallowing?","answer":"Deglutition"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2621 medium HIH705-1","question":"What is the short, funnel-shaped tube between the mouth & esophagus?","answer":"Pharynx"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2622 medium HIH705-2","question":"What is the cecum?","answer":"Large, sock-shaped pouch between small intestine & large colon"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2623 medium HS28","question":"Why must food move through the pharynx quickly?","answer":"So it won't enter the windpipe or be forced into nasal passage"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2624 medium HIH705-1,710-1","question":"Food remains in the stomach for about how long before it starts passing into the small intestine?","answer":"15 - 45 minutes		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2625 medium CAHA50/HIH705-1","question":"What is the pharynx?","answer":"A short, funnel-shaped tube between the mouth & esophagus"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2626 medium HIH710/HS31/TH194","question":"The rate of food passage from mouth to anus is how long?","answer":"1 ï¿½ - 3 days OR 36 - 72 hours 		(accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2627 medium HIH705-1/TH219","question":"Name the primary site of protein digestion in the horse.","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2628 medium HIH705-1","question":"The stomach is what percent of the total capacity of the horse's digestive tract?","answer":"9 - 10%"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2629 medium H3-35","question":"Commercial preparations of dried beneficial intestinal micro-organisms are called what?","answer":"Probiotics"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2630 medium TH401","question":"What body part should be examined closely in a horse that is quidding?","answer":"Teeth or mouth"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2631 medium CAHA55","question":"What causes the intestinal (gut) sounds that can be heard with a stethoscope pressed to the horse's abdomen?","answer":"Movement of gas or fluids through the large intestine OR cecal activity	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2632 medium TH93","question":"What is referred to as a strong, sensitive, mobile organ of prehension?","answer":"Upper lip	(lips)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2633 medium HIH710-2","question":"What is the capacity of the small colon?","answer":"4 gallons"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2634 medium HIH705-1,710-2","question":"What is the capacity of the stomach?","answer":"2 - 4 gallons/8-16 quarts 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2635 medium HIH705-1,710-2","question":"What is the capacity of the small intestine?","answer":"Approx. 12 gallons/68 quarts  "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"medium","number":"2636 medium TH93","question":"Which two anatomic structures aid the horse in collecting loose feed such as kernels of grain from a feed bucket or manger?		","answer":"Upper lips (also accept lips) and tongue"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2637 hard FCH294/DET93","question":"What is an enterolith?","answer":"Intestinal stone or stone-like mass that forms around a foreign object in horse's intestines"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2639 hard HIH705-2","question":"Fibrous feedstuffs are broken down into volatile fatty acids.  What percent of the horse's energy needs do these acids provide?","answer":"80%"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2640 hard HIH705-2","question":"Referring to the digestive system, what does VFA mean?","answer":"Volatile fatty acid"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2641 hard HIH705-1","question":"What are 2 functions of the pharynx?","answer":"Food passage between mouth & esophagus; air passage between nostrils & trachea"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2642 hard TH192","question":"What part of the large intestine serves as a microbacterial vat?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2643 hard HS25","question":"Sugar is absorbed in what form?","answer":"Glucose OR in the forms of other simple sugars"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2644 hard HIH705-2","question":"The large colon has the largest capacity of the horse's digestive system.  What percent of total capacity is it?","answer":"40%"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2645 hard HS31","question":"What is the diameter of the large colon?","answer":"19-22 inches down to 3-4 inches		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2646 hard TH192","question":"2 part question:  How long is the large intestine & what is its' capacity?","answer":"25 feet long;    32 gallons capacity"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2647 hard HS30","question":"What are the small projections in the small intestine called?","answer":"Villi"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2648 hard CAHA51","question":"What powerful, ring-like muscle closes the opening of the esophagus into the stomach?","answer":"Sphincter      (cardiac sphincter)   "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2649 hard DET154","question":"What is the general term for the bacteria and other microorganisms that normally reside in the large intestine?","answer":"Intestinal Flora"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2650 hard CAHA51/DET48","question":"What part of the stomach connects to the esophagus?","answer":"Cardia  "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2651 hard HS23/DET209","question":"What is peristalsis?","answer":"Wavelike movements of the esophagus that move food through the digestive tract"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2652 hard HIH705-2,710-2","question":"2 part question:  What is the length & capacity of the cecum?","answer":"4 feet long;               capacity 28 - 32 quarts/4 gallons"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2653 hard HS29","question":"What is the purpose of gastric lipase?","answer":"Helps digest fats"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2654 hard TH191/HS28","question":"Approximately how many gallons of saliva are produced & swallowed by the horse each day?","answer":"8 - 10 gallons	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2655 hard HIH710-2,705-2","question":"2 part question:  What is the length & capacity of the large colon?","answer":"10 - 12 feet;		 capacity 86 quarts/20 gallons "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2656 hard CAHA51/DET224","question":"What is the opening of the stomach into the small intestine called?","answer":"Pylorus "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2657 hard CAHA51","question":"What do the bile duct & the pancreatic duct empty into?","answer":"The duodenum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2658 hard TH191","question":"Besides water, what composes the saliva of a horse?","answer":"Inorganic salts & proteins/enzymes"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2659 hard HIH435-1","question":"What part of the horse functions similar to the rumen in cattle & sheep?","answer":"Cecum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2660 hard HIH705-1/HS29","question":"What does hydrochloric acid do in the stomach?","answer":"Helps with digestion OR mixes with the food & acidifies it so pepsin & gastric lipase can work"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2661 hard CAHA51","question":"Where in the digestive system is hydrochloric acid secreted?","answer":"Stomach lining"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2662 hard HS29","question":"What does pancreatic amylase do?","answer":"Digests starch"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2663 hard TH191/HS28","question":"2 part question:  What makes up 99% of the saliva & what is the other 1%?","answer":"99% water & 1% inorganic salts & proteins/enzymes"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2664 hard HS29","question":"Food does not leave the stomach until what happens?","answer":"Stomach is 75% full"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2665 hard TH194/HIH710-1","question":"When a horse is fed a balanced hay to grain ratio, it generally takes about how many hours for the ingested material to pass through the digestive tract & be passed out as fecal material?","answer":"36 - 72 hours (1-1/2 - 3 days)		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2666 hard HIH710-1","question":"What percent of proteins in grain-based diets is digested to amino acids & absorbed from the small intestine?","answer":"50 ï¿½ 70%"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2667 hard HIH705-1,710-2","question":"Passage of feeds through the small intestine takes approximately how long?","answer":"30 - 90 minutes		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2668 hard HIH705-1","question":"The angle at which the esophagus meets the stomach & the powerful spinchter at that junction makes it nearly impossible for feed to do what?","answer":"Re-enter the esophagus once it's deposited in the stomach"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2669 hard DET210","question":"Explain how the pharynx functions with the respiratory tract","answer":"When horse isnï¿½t swallowing, it connects the nasal passages with the windpipe"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2670 hard TH192/HS29","question":"Explain how bile is released in the horse's digestive system.","answer":"Continuously secreted by the liver    (into the bile duct which empties into the duodenum)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2671 hard TH196/HS29","question":"What does the enzyme trypsin do?","answer":"Breaks down proteins     (assists in the digestion of proteins)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2672 hard HS29","question":"Which enzyme assists in the digestion of fats?","answer":"Lipase  "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"Hard","number":"2674 Hard HS24","question":"2 part question:  A normal horse requires how many minutes to eat a pound of hay & how many minutes to eat a pound of grain?","answer":"15 - 20 minutes to eat a pound of hay & 5 - 10 minutes to eat a pound of grain"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2675 hard HIH710-1","question":"Describe a non-ruminant digestive system.","answer":"Carbohydrates, proteins & fats are digested in foregut by enzymes & fiber is digested in hindgut by bacteria"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2676 hard HIH710-1","question":"Describe a ruminant digestive system.","answer":"Fiber is digested in the rumen, enzymatic digestion in foregut & relatively minimal digestion occurs in hindgut"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2677 hard HIH710-1","question":"Digestively speaking, what is the horse categorized as?","answer":"Non-ruminant herbivore"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2678 hard FCH399","question":"Why can't a horse vomit?","answer":"Blocking action of the soft palate OR angle at which esophagus meets stomach OR cardiac sphincter prevents food from re-entering esophagus		(accept either)"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2679 hard DET250","question":"What structure in the horse's mouth is forced up by the tongue during swallowing to keep food out of the nose?","answer":"Soft palate"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2680 hard CAHA51","question":"What muscle regulates the flow of stomach contents into the duodenum?","answer":"Pyloric sphincter    "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2681 hard DET209","question":"What is the name for the wavelike muscular contractions that move food down the esophagus?","answer":"Peristalsis"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2682 hard TH204","question":"What is intestinal flora?","answer":"Bacteria normally present in the intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2683 hard HIH710-2","question":"2 part question:  Where does the sound-generating action of digestion occur & where do you listen for it?","answer":"Occurs in cecum.  You should listen for it on right side of the horse's abdomen at junction of the hind leg & trunk"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"hard","number":"2684 hard DET224","question":"What two areas of the digestive tract are connected by the pylorus?","answer":"Stomach and small intestine (duodenum)			"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2685 bonus HS25","question":"What 3 things do intestinal movements do?","answer":"Mix digested food with digestive secretions, enhance absorption, move material through intestines, expel the residue, assist in blood flow & lymph through vessels in intestinal wall"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2686 bonus TH201-02","question":"What are 3 factors that may affect the rate of passage of ingesta through the gastrointestinal tract of the horse?","answer":"Processing of food, level of intake/how much is eaten, frequency of feeding, exercise, individuality, time of watering, associative effects, ratio of hay to grain"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2687 bonus TH118-119/FCH4,5","question":"The gastrointestinal tract of the horse has many functions.  Name 3.","answer":"Ingestion, grinding/chewing, mixing, digestion, absorption, elimination of waste"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2688 bonus HIH710-2","question":"Name 4 parts of the horseï¿½s hindgut.","answer":"Cecum, large colon, small colon, rectum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2689 bonus HIH710-1","question":"Name 4 parts of the foregut.","answer":"Mouth, esophagus, stomach & small intestine"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2690 bonus HS31","question":"Name 3 things that make up feces.","answer":"Waste matter of digestion, water, indigestible and/or undigested food, cells sloughed off intestinal walls, remains of digestive secretions"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2692 bonus HS25","question":"What are 3 sections of the digestive tract where impactions are most likely to occur?","answer":"Cecum, small colon, & large colon  "},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2693 bonus HIH705-1","question":"Name 3 things secreted by the stomach.","answer":"Hydrochloric acid, pepsin, gastric lipase   		"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2694 bonus HIH710-2,705","question":"Name the parts of the horse's foregut in correct order - starting from the mouth & including the 3 parts of the small intestine.","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, duodenum, jejunum, ileum"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2695 bonus TH189/HS31/HIH705","question":"The important digestive action of the cecum & colon is due to the presence of bacteria & protozoa which do 3 things.  Name these 3 things.","answer":"Digest cellulose, synthesize B vitamins, synthesize amino acids"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2696 bonus HS24","question":"What are 3 substances that are secreted into the duodenum?	","answer":"Bile, trypsin, pancreatic lipase"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2697 bonus TH190","question":"What are the 7 parts of the alimentary canal?","answer":"Mouth, pharynx, esophagus, stomach, small intestine, large intestine, rectum/anus"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2698 bonus HIH701,705","question":"Name 3 mechanical factors in digestion.","answer":"Chewing, swallowing, movements of stomach & intestines, defecation/pooping"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2699 bonus HIH710-1","question":"Name 3 accessory organs of the digestive system.","answer":"Teeth, tongue, salivary glands, pancreas, liver"},
{"category":"DIGESTIVE","level":"bonus","number":"2700 bonus CAHA51","question":"What are the 3 parts of the small intestine?","answer":"Duodenum, jejunum, ileum"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2701 easy HS47/TH332","question":"What is an acute infection?","answer":"Symptoms appear quickly"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2702 easy HIH630-1/TH600","question":"What is another name for Equine Infectious Anemia?","answer":"EIA OR swamp fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2703 easy HIH625-1","question":"What is Encephalitis?","answer":"Inflammation of the brain"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2704 easy HIH630-2","question":"A Coggins positive horse is a threat to whom?","answer":"Other horses"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2705 easy HIH445-1,2","question":"What is the term that describes the animal's ability to resist a particular organism?","answer":"Immunity"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2706 easy HS46","question":"What is the first step in a disease prevention plan?","answer":"Consult a veterinarian"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2707 easy HS34/HIH810-3","question":"What is the name of the respiratory disease whose symptoms include forced breathing, heaving of flanks & coughing?","answer":"Heaves OR COPD"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2708 easy HIH445-7,3","question":"How is rabies transmitted?	","answer":"Bite from infected animal"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2709 easy H1-34/TH600-01","question":"The Coggins test is used to detect what disease?","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia OR EIA OR swamp fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2710 easy HIH665-2","question":"What is the treatment for West Nile?","answer":"Treat the symptoms (fluids, rest, etc.)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2711 easy HIH630-1","question":"What insect transmits Equine Infectious Anemia to horses?","answer":"Horse flies, deerflies, mosquitoes		 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2712 easy HIH440-1,445-2","question":"What disease could most likely follow the infection of a deep puncture wound?","answer":"Tetanus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2713 easy HIH680","question":"Name 2 wildlife species that serve as reservoir hosts for rabies.","answer":"Raccoon, skunk, fox, coyote, bat "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2714 easy TH600/HIH445-8","question":"In reference to diseases, what is a carrier?","answer":"An animal who transmits a disease, but who may or may not show any symptoms for the disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2715 easy HIH445-1new","question":"Ideally, to help prevent disease transmission, how long should a new horse be isolated before introducing it into an established group?","answer":"14-21 days  	(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2716 easy HIH445-7","question":"What disease of the nervous system is caused by a bite from an infected animal?","answer":"Rabies"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2717 easy HIH445-4","question":"What system of the horse does sleeping sickness affect?","answer":"Nervous system"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2718 easy HIH610-1","question":"What system of the horse does rhinopneumonitis affect?","answer":"Respiratory"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2719 easy HIH645-1","question":"What system of the horse does tetanus affect?","answer":"Central nervous system"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2720 easy HIH605-1/445-10 new","question":"Name two of the symptoms of influenza.","answer":"Fever, depression, frequent dry cough, watery nasal discharge, loss of appetite, anorexia/weight loss  "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2721 easy HIH605-2/FCH171","question":"What is the main treatment for influenza?","answer":"Rest"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2722 easy HIH605-1","question":"How does influenza spread rapidly through a group of horses?","answer":"Through the air, coughing, contaminated surfaces, droplets of moisture	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2724 easy HIH445","question":"Define "contagious disease".","answer":"One that may be transmitted from one animal to another by direct or indirect contact"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2725 easy HS48/TH96,98","question":"Name a disease spread through the air when droplets of moisture are coughed or sneezed.","answer":"Strangles, influenza, rhinopneumonitis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2726 easy HIH445-4","question":"What is a slang term for tetanus?","answer":"Lockjaw"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2727 easy HIH445-5/FCH405,173","question":"What is another name for strangles?","answer":"Distemper OR Shipping Fever OR Streptococcus equi"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2728 easy HIH445-4","question":"Encephalomyelitis can be spread by which parasite?","answer":"Biting flies or mosquitoes"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2729 easy HIH450-5,810-3","question":"What is a common respiratory disease of older horses?","answer":"COPD OR chronic obstructive pulmonary disease OR heaves"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2730 easy HIH445-3 new","question":"Which animal is considered the most sensitive to the tetanus toxin?","answer":"Horse"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2731 easy HIH445-4","question":"What is a slang term for Western and/or Eastern encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Sleeping sickness"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2732 easy HIH445-10/BEG104-2","question":"What is the most common infectious respiratory disease of the horse?","answer":"Influenza"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2733 easy HIH630-1","question":"What is a chronic infection?","answer":"One that lasts a long time		 (additional info -- infection makes little or no headway)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2734 easy TH164/HIH655-1","question":"What is the vector for Lyme disease?","answer":"Ticks	 (specifically Ixodes ticksï¿½deer, bear & Western black-legged)
(accept either general ï¿½ticksï¿½ or specific type of tick)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"easy","number":"2735 easy HIH850-3","question":"Heaves can be compared to what human medical condition?","answer":"Asthma"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2736 medium FCH173","question":"What is another name for shipping fever?","answer":"Strangles 	(also accept Equine Distemper or Streptococcus equi)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2737 medium DET151","question":"Define incubation period.","answer":"The period between time of exposure & time of first signs/symptoms of disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2738 medium DET40,187","question":"What is the difference between a broad spectrum & a narrow spectrum antibiotic?","answer":"Broad spectrum - effective against wide range of bacteria; 
Narrow spectrum - effective against only a few types or single type of bacteria"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2739 medium DET12","question":"What is the name for the disease fighting substance produced by the immune system in response to the presence of an antigen?","answer":"Antibody"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2740 medium DET213","question":"2 part question:  What is Equine Piroplasmosis & how is it transmitted?","answer":"Equine infectious disease that is usually transmitted by ticks"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2741 medium TH611/HIH665","question":"Wild birds are the principal reservoir host of which virus?","answer":"West Nile OR encephalomyelitis virus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2742 medium FCH169/HIH665-1","question":"Which one of the equine encephalomyelitis viruses is communicable to people?","answer":"West Nile OR Venezuelan Equine Encephalomyelitis/VEE        "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2743 medium TH514","question":"A tumor of pigment-forming cells that's commonly seen in older gray horses is known as what?","answer":"Melanoma	"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2744 medium HIH445-6 930-5","question":"Equine Herpes Virus causes respiratory disease in horses.  One strain of the virus - EHV-1 - can also cause what other problems?","answer":"Abortion in pregnant mares, birth of weak foals or a paralytic neurological disease 	(only need to name one)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2745 medium HIH445-12","question":"What is the most common viral cause of foal diarrhea?","answer":"Rotavirus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2746 medium HIH445-4new","question":"How is a diagnosis of rabies confirmed?","answer":"Post mortem examination of an animal's brain (necropsy)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2747 medium HIH445-5new","question":"From where did the slang name "sleeping sickness" for EEE, WEE & VEE infections come?","answer":"Profound/deep depression (sleepiness) associated with the infections"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2748 medium HIH445-5new","question":"Many horses infected with West Nile will begin to improve how many days after displaying clinical signs?","answer":"3 ï¿½ 7		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2749 medium ES194","question":"A home-made boot dip can be made using a gallon of water & what else?","answer":"1/4 cup bleach"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2750 medium FCH385","question":"Cirrhosis is a chronic disease that affects which organ?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2751 medium HIH445-8","question":"Why is botulism in foals sometimes called shaker foal syndrome?","answer":"Foal has muscle tremors, weakness, & difficulty standing"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2752 medium TH169","question":"Which type of Encephalomyelitis can be transmitted ï¿½horse to horseï¿½? ","answer":"Venezuelan "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2753 medium HIH445-9new","question":"It's estimated that what percent of horses have been infected with Equine Herpes virus at some time within their lives?","answer":"90 ï¿½ 100 %		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2754 medium HIH445-9new","question":"How long can horses shed the EHV-1 virus?","answer":"Up to 21 days"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2755 medium HIH445-9new","question":"Of the 9 types of Equine Herpes viruses, how many infect the domestic horse?","answer":"5 types"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2756 medium HIH445-10new","question":"Rest is a primary treatment for horses with influenza.  How long a time period should the horse be rested?","answer":"One week for each day of fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2758 medium TH521","question":"In what breed is equine night blindness most common?","answer":"Appaloosa"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2759 medium DET149","question":"2 part question:   What is immunity & how do horses develop immunity?","answer":"Immunity ï¿½ ability to resist a particular disease; 
get it from vaccinations, previous exposure to disease, placenta, motherï¿½s milk, or through artificially made antibodies"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2760 medium DET206","question":"What does the term "pathological" mean?","answer":"A diseased condition"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2761 medium HIH445-4/HS56/DET281","question":"What is an insect vector?","answer":"Insect that carries & transmits disease-causing organisms"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2762 medium HIH665-1","question":"Which disease was first detected in the US in 1999?","answer":"West Nile"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2763 medium HIH795-2","question":"Cushing's disease & equine metabolic syndrome are often confused.  What is one thing that would visually indicate Cushingï¿½s?","answer":"Long hair coat"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2764 medium HS49","question":"Diagnosis of EPM (Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis) is difficult & will require the vet to do what?","answer":"Perform a spinal tap"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2765 medium HIH445-12","question":"How is Strangles spread?","answer":"Direct or indirect contact with horses, tack, equipment or handlers who might be carrying the bacteria"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2766 medium FCH191","question":"Characteristic signs of this disease of older horses are excessive hair growth & failure to shed.  What is this disease?","answer":"Cushingï¿½s disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2767 medium TH595/HIH950-6old","question":"Describe one early symptom of neonatal septicemia.","answer":"Decreased appetite, general weakness/depression, weak sucking reflex, fever, diarrhea, excessive sleeping/resting"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2768 medium BEG112-2/HIH975-4","question":"What is passive transfer of immunity?","answer":"When a newborn foal receives antibodies from the mare through the colostrum"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2769 medium FCH385","question":"What is the general term for a disease that is communicable or transmissible from one individual to another?","answer":"Contagious"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2770 medium HIH625-1","question":"A reservoir host is an animal in which a virus lives before it causes disease in other animals.  Name one of the most common types of animals which serve as reservoirs.","answer":"Birds, rodents, reptiles"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2771 medium FCH405","question":"What disease is characterized by swollen or abscessed lymph glands - particularly those under or behind the jaws?","answer":"Strangles OR Equine Distemper OR Shipping Fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2772 medium HIH950-5 old","question":"An untreated umbilical cord can cause a bacterial infection known as what?","answer":"Septicemia or sepsis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2773 medium HIH650-1","question":"What does PHF stand for?","answer":"Potomac Horse Fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2774 medium FCH174/DET227","question":"What disease is being described?  This disease is caused by a rhabdovirus that infects the nervous system of the horse.  It can be transmitted to any mammal.  There is no treatment & it's fatal if the horse has not been previously vaccinated.","answer":"Rabies"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2775 medium DET265","question":"What is the name for the disease caused by Clostridium tetani?","answer":"Tetanus OR Lockjaw"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2776 medium HIH450-5","question":"What are 2 characteristics of Cushing's disease?","answer":"Excessive hair growth, failure to shed, excessive thirst, excessive urination, weight loss"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2777 medium HIH630-1","question":"What do the initials EIA stand for?","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2778 medium HIH630-1","question":"A troublesome feature of Equine Infectious Anemia is what?","answer":"That once a horse is infected, it remains infected for the rest of its life"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2779 medium HIH445-6/HS48","question":"Name a disease that can be contracted from contaminated food or water.","answer":"Strangles or Leptospirosis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2780 medium FCH168/HIH445-3new","question":"Approximately how long does tetanus antitoxin give protection?","answer":"2-4 weeks "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2781 medium TH598 HIH930-4","question":"The most common viral cause of abortion in mares is what?","answer":"Equine herpes (EHV-1)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2782 medium TH596","question":"What antibiotic is used to treat strangles?","answer":"Penicillin"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2783 medium TH427 HIH975-2","question":"An annual injection of tetanus toxoid produces active immunity.  Give an example of passive immunity","answer":"Mare passing antibodies to the newborn foal through colostrum  "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2784 medium HIH665-1","question":"What is the recovery rate for horses infected with West Nile?","answer":"Approximately 50% or higher"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2785 medium FCH393","question":"What is the term for the time period between exposure to an infection & the onset of clinical signs?","answer":"Incubation"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2786 medium FCH401","question":"What virus causes Rhinopneumonitis?","answer":"Equine herpes  (EHV-4, EHV-1)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2787 medium TH599/HIH445-","question":"Which strain of equine encephalomyelitis has the lowest mortality rate?","answer":"WEE or Western"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2788 medium TH602","question":"What disease, first recognized in Maryland in 1979, is characterized by diarrhea, founder, colic, fever & a high mortality rate?","answer":"Potomac Horse Fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2789 medium HS47","question":"What do you call the type of disease that is caused by pathogenic microorganisms such as bacteria, viruses, & fungi?","answer":"Infectious  "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2790 medium HIH445-7","question":"A horse with a potentially contagious disease should be isolated from other horses for how many days after recovery?","answer":"At least 10 days"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2791 medium TH595","question":"With septicemia, infection spreads throughout the horseï¿½s body causing multi-organ problems.  How does this infection spread?","answer":"Through the bloodstream"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2792 medium HIH615-1","question":"What will happen to the lymph nodes of a horse when it has strangles?","answer":"They become hot, swollen, & painful & may abscess"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2793 medium HIH625-2","question":"Where do mosquitoes contact the viruses known as Eastern, Western & Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"A wild host"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2794 medium HIH630-1","question":"Equine Infectious Anemia viruses can only live in which animals?","answer":"Horses & their close relatives  (donkeys & mules)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2795 medium TH595","question":"What is another name for blood poisoning?","answer":"Septicemia		 (also accept sepsis)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2796 hard HIH630-1/TH600","question":"What does the Coggins test specifically check for in the blood?","answer":"Antibodies against the EIA virus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2797 medium HIH610-1,445-6","question":"Abortions attributable to EHV-1 usually occur at what stage of gestation?","answer":"8 - 11 months      (last 3 months/last trimester)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2798 medium FCH385","question":"Cirrhosis is a chronic disease that affects which organ?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2800 medium HIH465-2","question":"Name 2 breeds that are predisposed to developing squamous cell carcinoma?","answer":"Appaloosa, Paint, Belgian 	(additional info -- horses with large areas of white hair & pink skin on the face)    "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2801 medium HIH445-4","question":"How far can the influenza virus travel when an infected horse coughs?","answer":"35 yards"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2802 medium TH600","question":"What is a slang name for EIA?","answer":"Swamp fever"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2803 medium HIH660-1","question":"What is a common clinical symptom of horses infected with Salmonellosis?","answer":"Diarrhea"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2804 medium HIH620-1,2","question":"Name the sex of the horse that can become a long-term carrier of Equine Viral Arteritis.","answer":"Male"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2805 medium HIH440-4","question":"Cushingï¿½s disease is more common in horses over what age?","answer":"18"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2806 medium FCH173/ES171/HIH615","question":"What characteristic makes strangles easy to identify?","answer":"Swollen and/or Abscessed lymph nodes in the throatlatch area"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2807 medium HIH445-3","question":"For what disease is a vaccine given to broodmares at the 5th, 7th & 9th month of pregnancy?","answer":"Rhinopneumonitis    (EHV-1)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2808 medium HIH445-5","question":"Which respiratory disease is an allergic disorder that may develop after respiratory infections?","answer":"COPD (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease) or heaves"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2809 medium TH615","question":"What bacterial disorder involves production of toxins that result in paralysis, rigidity of muscles & often death?","answer":"Tetanus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2810 medium HIH615","question":"What severely contagious bacterial disorder results in swollen lymph nodes under the jaw which often need to be lanced & drained?","answer":"Strangles	 (also accept Streptococcus equi, shipping fever, or distemper)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2811 medium BEG114-1","question":"How long after a wound is sustained are symptoms of tetanus likely to appear?","answer":"Two days to one month (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2812 medium FCH101/TH514","question":"By age 15 most gray horses will have developed what condition?","answer":"Melanoma	"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2813 medium FCH362","question":"What general age category of horses is most prone to botulism?","answer":"Foals"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2814 medium DET91","question":"Name the term that means "an inflammation of the brain".","answer":"Encephalitis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2815 medium DET18","question":"What is the COMMON name for the eye disease that causes cloudiness of the uveal tract of the eye and may lead to blindness? ","answer":"Moon blindness"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2816 medium HIH445-10new","question":"Which disease has a convalescence period that's typically much longer than the owner would expect?","answer":"Influenza    (additional info -- horses might not return to athletic activities for up to 6 months)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2817 medium DET253","question":"Stable cough is the slang term for which viral equine disease?","answer":"Rhinopneumonitis					"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2818 medium HIH680-1		","question":"What mammal is considered to be the primary source of rabies in horses?","answer":"Skunk					"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2819 medium HIH670-1","question":"What is the definitive host for Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis?","answer":"Opossum					"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2820 medium ES172","question":"Describe the typical stance of a horse with tetanus","answer":"ï¿½Saw horseï¿½ stance          "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2821 medium TH603","question":"Which bacterial disease is called shaker foal syndrome when it affects foals?","answer":"Botulism         "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2822 medium HIH685-1/DET282","question":"Vesicular stomatitis is a viral disease that results in the formation of vesicles in the mouth & on the lips, hooves & teats.  What is a vesicle?","answer":"Fluid-filled sac  (blister)         "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2823 medium HIH975-17, 18","question":"What is another name for septic arthritis?","answer":"Joint Ill              "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2824 medium DET76","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½cystoï¿½ refer to?		","answer":"Bladder"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2825 medium DET168","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½leukoï¿½ refer to?			","answer":"White blood cells"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2826 medium DET79","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½desmoï¿½ indicate?		","answer":"Ligament"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"medium","number":"2827 medium DET15","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½arthroï¿½ describe?		","answer":"Joint"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2828 hard HIH445-12 975-12","question":"Name 2 ways to help prevent rotavirus infection. ","answer":"Vaccinate pregnant mares (at 8, 9 & 10 months gestation), good hygiene/ management practices"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2829 hard TH104","question":"What term is used to describe a disease of a muscle?","answer":"Myopathy        (my-AHH-path-ee)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2830 hard HIH 660-1 975-13,14		","question":"What type of bacteria is considered the most common cause of infectious enterocolitis in adult horses?","answer":"Salmonella"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2831 hard HIH650-2","question":"You do the mathï¿½  Your horse has Potomac Horse Fever and is being treated with the antibiotic Tetracycline.  You horse weighs approximately 500 Kg (kilograms).  The recommended dosage is 10 mg (milligrams) per Kg (kilogram) of body weight. How many total milligrams of Tetracycline will your horse receive?","answer":"5000 milligrams "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2832 hard FCH361-62/DET36","question":"What is the name for a type of food poisoning that can be caused by hay or silage contaminated by a Clostridium bacteria?   ","answer":"Botulism"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2834 hard HIH445-10,11","question":"Stallions from which 2 breeds are extremely likely to test positive for EVA?","answer":"Standardbreds & Warmbloods  (especially Austrian Warmbloods)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2835 hard HIH445-11new","question":"What are 2 ways to prevent outbreaks of EVA?","answer":"Identify the carrier stallions & use management practices to prevent the introduction of EVA positive horses into a non-infected herd"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2836 hard HIH445-7new","question":"Which type of baled hay is associated with a higher risk for botulism?","answer":"Round bales"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2837 hard HIH445-5new","question":"Which virus is the leading cause of arbovirus encephalitis in horses & humans in the US?","answer":"West Nile"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2838 hard HIH445-4new","question":"Viruses that cause Eastern, Western & Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis are arboviruses.  What does arbovirus mean?","answer":"They are transmitted by bloodsucking insects	 (also accept -- arthropod borne)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2839 hard HIH445-4new","question":"What is a zoonotic disease?","answer":"One that is transmissible from animals to humans"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2840 hard HIH610-1,445-6","question":"Are signs of EHV-4 usually observed primarily among foals or mares?","answer":"Foals"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2841 hard HIH445-7/650-1","question":"What specific type of microorganism causes Potomac Horse Fever?","answer":"Parasite (Neorickettsia ristici formerly called Ehrlichia risticii)          
(additional info ï¿½ not necessary to give:  rickettsia are gram negative bacteria that are in their own category because they canï¿½t live outside of cells)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2842 hard TH111","question":"What is pleurisy?","answer":"Inflammation of the membranes surrounding the lungs
(additional info ï¿½ not necessary to give-- often a complication of influenza, pneumonia, etc.)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2843 hard TH305","question":"What is another name for Enterotoxemia?","answer":"Over-eating disease 		
(additional info not necessary to give:  bacterial disease caused by Clostridium perfringens)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2844 hard FCH301","question":"What is the viral disease that causes blister-like lesions of the mouth, dental pad, tongue, lips, nostrils, hooves & teats of infected animals?","answer":"Vesicular stomatis	 (also accept hoof & mouth disease)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2845 hard HS37","question":"What are the 2 most important factors that determine whether a disease-causing organism will produce the disease in an exposed animal?","answer":"Virulence/strength of the organism & animal's resistance"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2846 hard HIH665-1/455-5 new","question":"What is a "dead end" or terminal host?","answer":"A host from which infectious agents are not transmittable"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2847 hard HIH665-1","question":"What is the incubation period for West Nile?","answer":"5 - 15 days		 (accept any answer within range)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2848 hard HIH660-1","question":"What is Equine Salmonellosis?","answer":"Infection with salmonella bacteria"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2850 hard HIH660-3","question":"What is the treatment for equine salmonellosis?","answer":"Supportive care - including fluid administration"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2851 hard HIH660-2 HIH975-13,14","question":"Why is it difficult to eradicate salmonella bacteria?","answer":"They are very resistant & adaptable to environmental conditions OR they can survive long periods in soil/water/feed"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2852 hard FCH31,32","question":"In areas where the soil has low available selenium content, what disease can be prevalent in foals if the mares are fed homegrown feeds?","answer":"White muscle disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2853 hard TH96","question":"What specific parts of the horse does strangles affect?","answer":"Submaxillary & parotid lymph nodes"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2854 hard HIH810","question":"What is another name for laryngeal hemiplegia?","answer":"Roaring"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2855 hard TH521","question":"What is another name for equine periodic ophthalmia?","answer":"Moon blindness or ERU (Equine Recurrent Uveitis)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2856 hard HIH445-13","question":"What is one way a horse is infected with anthrax?","answer":"Ingestion of bacteria spores, inhalation of bacteria, skin penetration by biting flies or injury especially when horse has been exposed to infected soil or carcasses	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2857 hard HIH670-1","question":"What animal is the reservoir host for Sarcocystis neurona?","answer":"Opossum"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2858 hard HIH605-1","question":"What is the study of the transmission & control of diseases called?","answer":"Epidemiology"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2859 hard HIH650-1","question":"What is the common name for Borrelliosis?","answer":"Lyme disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2860 hard TH601/HIH445-3new","question":"Identify the disease based on the following symptoms:  prolapse of the third eyelid, trismus(spasms of the masseter muscle), difficulty walking, high mortality rate & a sawhorse posture","answer":"Tetanus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2861 hard HIH670-1","question":"The parasite Sarocystis neurona causes what disease?","answer":"EPM or Equine Protozoal Myoloencephalitis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2862 hard HIH685-1","question":"What is the incubation period for vesicular stomatitis?","answer":"2 - 8 days			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2863 hard HIH445-7new","question":"Why does Botulism in foals sometimes happen when they start to nibble at hay & grass?","answer":"Ingest the bacteria from the soil (which produces toxins in the foal's intestinal tract)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2864 hard HIH810","question":"What disease is characterized by an excessive breathing noise caused by an upper airway obstruction?  The noise is usually heard during exercise","answer":"Laryngeal hemiplegia or roaring"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2865 hard HIH615-2/DET25","question":"What is "Bastard Strangles"?","answer":"A form of strangles that affects tissue in the horse's whole body instead of only the lymph nodes of the head OR infection is spread to other lymph node sites in the horse's body (such as abdomen, brain, liver, kidneys, lungs)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2866 hard FCH357","question":"What disease is caused by a toxin-producing fungus located in contaminated corn grain that's consumed by horses?","answer":"Moldy corn poisoning, leukoencephalomalacia, or blind staggers 		(only need to name one)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2867 hard TH111","question":"An inflammation affecting the fine membrane that lines the chest & covers the lungs is known as what?","answer":"Pleurisy"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2868 hard HIH625-1","question":"How many types of Venezuelan Equine Encephalomyelitis are there?","answer":"4 subtypes"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2869 hard HIH610-1,445-5","question":"Equine Herpes Virus-4 is also known as what?","answer":"Equine Rhinopneumonitis virus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2870 hard HIH655-1","question":"Name the disease carried by deer ticks that's caused by the bacterium Borrelia burgdorferi .","answer":"Lyme disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2871 hard FCH301","question":"Which disease has outward signs which are very similar to vesicular stomatitis?","answer":"Hoof & mouth disease"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2872 hard HIH795-2","question":"What syndrome is characterized by obesity, regional adiposity, insulin resistance, high blood triglycerides, & hyperleptinemia?","answer":"Equine Metabolic Syndrome"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2874 hard HIH795-2","question":"Compared to other causes of obesity, name 2 areas where fat is deposited in Equine Metabolic Syndrome. ","answer":"Crest & tailhead"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2875 hard DET12","question":"What disease is caused by the bacterium Bacillus anthracis?","answer":"Anthrax"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2876 hard HIH630-1,2","question":"What disease is being described?  There is no effective treatment or vaccination for this disease, but a horse may survive the acute phase & remain a carrier for the remainder of its life.  The virus attacks cells in the horse's body - including the red blood cells - & causes anemia & jaundice.  All horses should be periodically tested for this disease using the Coggins test.","answer":"Equine Infectious Anemia or EIA"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2877 hard FCH168,251,361/DET118/TH305","question":"Name 2 diseases caused by the bacteria Clostridia.","answer":"Tetanus, botulism, foal septicemia/umbilical cord infection, enterotoxemia/overeating disease, gangrene"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2878 hard HIH465-3","question":"What is the most common infectious agent that causes Equine Recurrent Uveitis (ERU)?","answer":"Leptospira"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2879 hard HIH465-3","question":"Give 2 other names for the condition Equine Recurrent Uveitis (ERU).","answer":"Moon blindness, periodic opthalmia"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2880 hard HIH465-3","question":"What is the treatment for Equine Recurrent Uveitis (ERU)?","answer":"Anti-inflammatory medications"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2881 hard HIH445-11","question":"Why should you test stallions for the presence of EVA antibodies BEFORE you vaccinate them?","answer":"Because it's not possible to differentiate between vaccine induced antibodies and those caused by natural infection"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2882 hard HIH615-1","question":"What is another name for a Streptoccus equii infection?","answer":"Strangles	 (also accept equine distemper or shipping fever)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2883 hard HIH620-1","question":"What is EVA?","answer":"Equine Viral Arteritis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2884 hard `	HIH620-1","question":"What virus affecting horses has recently been discovered to also affect swine?","answer":"EAV or Equine Arteritis Virus"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2885 hard HIH445-13","question":"Anthrax bacteria can live in the soil for decades.   Give a reason why.","answer":"Low nutrient requirements, ability to survive temperature extremes"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2886 hard HIH620-1","question":"Two distinct equine influenza A viruses have been identified.  Name them.","answer":"Equine 1 or H7N7 & Equine 2 or H3N8"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2887 hard HIH605-1","question":"Where does the influenza virus multiply?","answer":"In the upper respiratory tract (specifically, in the epithelial cells)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2888 hard HIH610-1","question":"What does EHV-1 stand for?","answer":"Equine Herpes Virus- 1"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2889 hard HIH610-1","question":"Equine Herpes Virus-1 is also sometimes known as what?","answer":"Abortion virus "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2890 hard HIH445-2","question":"What causes tetanus?","answer":"Clostridium tetani"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2891 hard HS47","question":"Disease-causing organisms vary greatly in their ability to produce disease.  What is the term used when the ability to produce disease is great?","answer":"Virulent"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2892 hard HIH445-11-12","question":"Horses who recover from Potomac Horse Fever develop an immunity which lasts how long?","answer":"Up to 2 years "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2893 hard HS49","question":"What is EPM?","answer":"A disease of the spinal cord & nervous system
(additional info -- EPM is Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2894 hard HIH445-13","question":"What is purpura hemmorrhagica?","answer":"A serious complication of strangles OR it's the result of an exaggerated immune response & causes inflammation & hemorrhaging    "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2895 hard HIH795-2","question":"Explain how insulin resistance in Equine Metabolic Syndrome (EMS) predisposes horses to laminitis.","answer":"Like with diabetes, insulin resistance may decrease blood flow; decreased blood flow to the feet causes laminitis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2896 hard HIH445-13","question":"This disease is listed as a bioterrorism alert in the US.  All cases of this disease -- suspect and confirmed -- must be reported to the state veterinarian.  What disease is it?","answer":"Anthrax"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2897 hard DET146-47","question":"What is the difference between hyperplasia & hypertrophy?","answer":"Hyperplasia is an increase in the number of cells
Hypertrophy is an increase in the size of the cells"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2898 hard HIH795-3","question":"What is the correct medical terminology for the long, wavy, non-shedding hair coat associated with Equine Cushingï¿½s Disease?","answer":"Hirsutism             "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2899 hard HIH930-5","question":"What is the definition of endemic?","answer":"Prevalent or very commonly found          "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"hard","number":"2900 hard HIH930-5","question":"The 2 most common abortion-causing viral diseases in the US are what?","answer":"Equine herpes virus (EHV-1) & equine viral arteritis virus (EVA)           "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2901 bonus HIH445-12","question":"What are 3 clinical signs of rotaviral infection in foals?","answer":"Depression, anorexia, decreased sucking, watery diarrhea, dehydration"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2902 bonus HIH465-3","question":"Give 3 initial signs of ERU.","answer":"Tears, redness, squinting"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2903 bonus HIH445-13","question":"Name 3 clinical signs of an animal infected with anthrax.","answer":"Fever, muscle tremors, dyspnea/difficulty breathing, congestion, sudden death, blood-stained milk, & following death discharge of blood can be seen from body openings"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2904 bonus HIH445-10new","question":"Two part question:  How many general types of influenza viruses are there & who is primarily affected by each?","answer":"3;    Type A -infects wide variety of animals, including horse, 
Type B ï¿½ primarily infects humans, Type C - Has been found in humans, pigs & dogs"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2905 bonus HIH445-8new","question":"Give 3 clinical signs of botulism.","answer":"Weakness, decreased muscle tone of tail/eyelid/tongue, trembling, dilated pupils, lying down, difficulty swallowing, drooling, green or milky nasal discharge"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2906 bonus HIH445-6new","question":"Name 3 ways horses can contract botulism.","answer":"Eating forage/feed containing the bacteria, eating forage/feed containing the toxins, wounds contaminated by bacteria"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2908 bonus HIH445-2","question":"Name 2 common wounds that serve as port of entry for tetanus.","answer":"Lower limb wounds, punctures in sole of foot, castration wounds, contaminated surgical sites, injection abscesses, infected umbilical structures"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2909 bonus HIH445-2","question":"Name 3 diseases whose vaccinations are considered in the at-risk group.","answer":"Anthrax, botulism, equine herpes/rhino, equine viral arteritis, influenza, Potomac Horse Fever, rotaviral diarrhea, strangles"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2910 bonus HIH445-8","question":"Name 3 diseases caused by soil-borne, spore-forming bacteria. ","answer":"Tetanus, Botulism, Anthrax"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2911 bonus HIH445-1","question":"Name 3 factors that may decrease resistance or increase susceptibility to disease.","answer":"Stress, over-crowding, parasites, poor nutrition, inadequate sanitation, contaminated water source/supply, concurrent disease, stringent exercise program, no turnout time, transportation, inclement/bad  weather, weaning, disruption of established social groups, movement of people/vehicles/equipment on or off property during infectious disease outbreak"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2912 bonus HIH445, 975-2","question":"3 part question:  What is immunity?  Name 2 types & define them","answer":"Immunityï¿½animal's  ability to resist a particular organism; permanentï¿½lasts for the life of the animal; temporaryï¿½only lasts a short time; 
ALSO ACCEPT activeï¿½develops antibodies after exposure or vaccine
passive given antibodies through placenta (not in horses), motherï¿½s milk, or artificial transfer of antibodies"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2913 bonus HIH630-1/ES176","question":"What are 3 symptoms of Equine Infectious Anemia?","answer":"Fever, anemia, horse tires easily, weight loss, swelling/edema, depression, weak pulse, irregular heartbeat, jaundice, enlarged spleen"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2914 bonus HIH445-5new/DET177","question":"Name 3 symptoms of sleeping sickness.","answer":"Fever, depression,  ataxia/irregular gait, loss of coordination, head hanging low, head pressing, unable to swallow, acts blind, convulsions, grinding teeth, circling, staggering, paralysis, stupor"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2915 bonus TH596-604","question":"Name 3 ways disease organisms escape from the host.","answer":"Eliminated with blood, eliminated with urine or feces, droplets of moisture, saliva, mucus membranes"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2916 bonus HIH615-1,445-4","question":"What are 3 symptoms of strangles?","answer":"Fever, depression, increased respiration, swelling of lymph glands in throat area, nasal discharge, sore throat, pain on eating, stands with neck stretched out"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2917 bonus HIH445-3","question":"Name 3 immunizations given a horse annually as standard procedure.","answer":"Eastern Encephalomyelitis/EEE, Western Encephalomyelitis/WEE, Tetanus, Flu, West Nile
Rhino /Rhinopneumonitis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2918 bonus HIH650-1","question":"What are 3 symptoms of Potomac Horse Fever?","answer":"Fever, depression, reduced or absent gut sounds, colic, dehydration, profuse diarrhea, shock, laminitis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2919 bonus HIH950-5 ","question":"Name 3 symptoms of septicemia.","answer":"Fever, depression, excessive sleeping, joints hot/swollen/ painful, navel hot & swollen, navel may have discharge"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2920 bonus HIH605-1","question":"Name 3 common features of influenza.","answer":"Fever, depression, watery nasal discharge, loss of appetite, frequent dry cough, rapid spread of infection"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2921 bonus HIH445-6","question":"What are the 2 primary reasons for Equine Herpes Virus vaccination?","answer":"Prevention of abortion in pregnant mares, prevention of respiratory disease/rhino"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2922 bonus HIH645-1","question":"Give 3 symptoms of tetanus.","answer":"Fever, depression, constant excitement, muscle stiffness/rigidity, stiff/stilted gait, elevated tail carriage, protrusion of third eyelid/haw/nictitating membrane, excessive reaction to noise/touch/light/sound, sawhorse stance, jaw muscle locked/trismus, unable to eat, neck stiffness, high pulse, high respiration rate, flared nostrils, muscle spasms, sweating, convulsions, respiratory or cardiac arrest"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2923 bonus HIH445-7 445-3-4 new,","question":"What are 3 symptoms of rabies?","answer":"Fever, depression, loss of appetite, altered behavior, hyper-responsiveness to touch, weakness, uncoordinated gait, lameness, colic, inability to swallow, blindness, hyperactivity, convulsions, fear, aggressiveness, etc"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2924 bonus BEG104","question":"Give 3 symptoms of rhinopneumonitis.","answer":"Fever, depression, nasal discharge, loss of appetite, coughing"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2925 bonus FCH191","question":"Give 3 clinical signs of Cushing's disease in the horse.","answer":"Long wavy/curly hair, fragile bones, weakness, excessive drinking, excessive urination, poor shedding, thin skin, stupor, sweating, loss of muscle mass, chronic lameness"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2926 bonus HIH665-2","question":"What are 3 clinical signs of West Nile?","answer":"Fever, depression, loss of appetite, weakness of hind legs, paralysis of hind legs, impaired vision, head pressing, ataxia, head tilt, aimless wandering, convulsions, inability to swallow, circling, hyperexcitability,  coma, personality changes"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2927 bonus HIH665-2","question":"Definite diagnosis of West Nile must first rule out other diseases with similar symptoms.  Name 3 of these diseases.  ","answer":"EPM (Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis), EEE (Eastern Equine Encephalitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalitis), VEE (Venezuelan Equine Encephalitis), rabies, botulism"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2928 bonus HIH665-1","question":"Since birds are the reservoir host for West Nile, finding a large number of dead ones can be a signal that the virus is present in the area.  Name 3 of the birds most often associated with West Nile.","answer":"Blue jays, crows, ravens, raptors (eagle, owl, etc)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2929 bonus HIH660-1","question":"Name 3 risk factors for equine salmonellosis.","answer":"Transportation, crowded conditions, abrupt change in diet, intense physical exercise, antimicrobial treatment, gastrointestinal tract disorders, surgery"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2930 bonus HIH660-2","question":"What are 3 symptoms of salmonellosis?","answer":"Diarrhea (profuse, watery, smelly), colic, depression, anorexia, dehydration, fever, tachycardia (fast heart rate)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2931 bonus TH599","question":"What are 3 types of equine encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Eastern, Western, Venezuelan, West Nile"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2932 bonus TH607","question":"Describe 3 things you can do to alleviate some of the horse's distress caused by heaves.","answer":"Provide lots of fresh air, eliminate dust, leave horse on pasture, wet hay/grain, feed pelleted ration, give antihistamine medication, use dust-free bedding, adjust high temperature with fans/coolers, adjust humidity level"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2933 bonus HIH655-1,2","question":"Name 3 of the most common signs of Lyme disease.","answer":"Fever, arthritis, dermatitis, difficulty swallowing, glazed eyes, head tilt, joint swelling, lameness, neurological disease, tail paralysis, profuse sweating, wandering aimlessly, uveitis/eye disorder"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2934 bonus ES p. 167","question":"Infection is the result of the presence of organisms in the body that cause health problems or disease.  Name three types of ï¿½infectious agentsï¿½ or organisms.	","answer":"Bacteria, virus, protozoa, fungus, rickettsia     (arthropod borne obligate intracellular parasites)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2935 bonus HIH445-5new","question":"The West Nile virus belongs to the family Flavivirdae.  This virus family has the distinction of containing some of the most severe human pathogens in the world.  Name 3 human diseases - other than West Nile -caused by these pathogens.","answer":"Yellow fever, dengue fever, Japanese encephalitis, tick-borne encephalitis, St. Louis encephalitis, Hepatitis C, louping ill (ovine encephalitis)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2936 bonus ES173","question":"Identify 2 systemic fungal diseases that affect horses				","answer":"Aspergillosis				Blastomycosis
Coccidiomycosis			Hisoplasmosis"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2937 bonus ES174","question":"Identify 2 equine diseases that are caused by protozoa","answer":"Equine Piroplasmosis (babesiosis)
Equine Protozoal Myeloencephalitis  (EPM)
Giardia infection  (Giadiasis)"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2938 bonus ES170-71, FCH362","question":"Identify three bacterial diseases that affect both humans and horses.","answer":"Tetanus, Botulism, Anthrax, Brucellosis, Lyme Disease           "},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2939 bonus FCH259","question":"Give 4 observations that would indicate that a foal with diarrhea would require medical attention","answer":"Large amount of diarrhea			Diarrhea contains blood
Decreased appetite				Fever
Depression/lethargy				Dehydration
Large volume of water in diarrhea"},
{"category":"DISEASES","level":"bonus","number":"2940 bonus TH305,601,603","question":"2 part:  Identify 3 diseases that are caused by a type of clostridium bacteria & identify the specific type of clostridum bacteria for each disease","answer":"Tetanus ï¿½ clostridium tetani
Botulism  clostridium botulinum
Enterotoxemia ï¿½ clostridium perfingens"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2942 easy DET273/CCS/HIH","question":"Name one type of trail ride","answer":"Social (pleasure), competitive, & endurance"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2943 easy H5-34","question":"How many barrels are there in a cloverleaf pattern?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2944 easy HIH162-2,183D-2","question":"What do you call reining maneuvers set to music?","answer":"Freestyle reining"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2945 easy HHch8","question":"Scurry, potato race, speed barrels, flags & pole bending are all activities seen at what type of equestrian event?","answer":"Gymkhana (games)    "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2946 easy HH40","question":"What do the following horse show classes have in commonï¿½pole bending, dressage & harness ponies?","answer":"They are all performance classes"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2947 easy HH24","question":"When showing with romal reins in stock seat equitation, what extra piece of equipment must be attached to the saddle?","answer":"Hobbles"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2948 easy HH24","question":"Generally, in horse shows, when is a snaffle bit or bosal allowed?","answer":"When showing a junior horse 5 years old or younger"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2949 easy HH24","question":"What is a "junior" horse?","answer":"One that's 5 years of age or younger"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2950 easy HH46","question":"Explain how to back your horse in showmanship.","answer":"Turn to face towards the rear of the horse with your right hand extended.  Walk forward beside the horse as it backs up"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2951 easy HH44","question":"In showmanship, if you are dressed in hunt seat attire, what equipment should your horse wear?","answer":"English bridle    (also accept plain leather halter)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2952 easy HH44","question":"What personal equipment is prohibited in showmanship classes?","answer":"Spurs"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2953 easy HIH182D-1","question":"What is possibly the oldest team equine sport?	","answer":"Polo"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2954 easy HIH180D-1","question":"Which breed dominates cutting competitions?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2955 easy HIH185D-1","question":"How many vaulters may be on the horse at one time?","answer":"One, two or three		 (accept any)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2956 easy HIH615-2	","question":"What is freestyle reining?","answer":"Reining maneuvers set to music "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2957 easy H5-34","question":"Where are the dividing lines that define the quarter system of showmanship?","answer":"Down the backbone of the horse & across its shoulders"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2960 easy HIH181D-1","question":"Dressage is one of how many official Olympic equestrian sports?","answer":"Three
(Info only -- dressage, show jumping, & eventing; reining is currently a demonstration sport at the Olympics)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2961 easy H5-34","question":"What is the name of the game played by teams on horseback using mallets to hit a wooden ball?","answer":"Polo"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2962 easy HIH185D-1","question":"What discipline is defined as gymnastics on horseback?","answer":"Vaulting"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2963 easy H5-21","question":"What is the only current women's event in PRCA rodeo?","answer":"Barrel racing"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2964 easy H4-34/TH21","question":"What is the term for the person who rides a horse in a race?","answer":"Jockey"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2965 easy HIH250","question":"In general, what type of horse is the best candidate for a therapeutic riding horse?","answer":"An extremely tolerant /gentle one"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2966 easy HIH172-1,183D-1","question":"The term "dressage" comes from a French word meaning what?","answer":"Training"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2967 easy HIH162-2,183D-2","question":"What is the automatic beginning score for a reining pattern?","answer":"70"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2968 easy HIH180D-1","question":"What is the beginning score for a cutting horse entry?","answer":"70"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2969 easy H1-35","question":"What is the common term for riding a horse across country, in fields, on roads, in parks, on logging trails, etc.?","answer":"Trail riding"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2970 easy H4-33","question":"Which type of class is judged on the rider?","answer":"Equitation or horsemanship"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2971 easy H4-34","question":"What do you call the official who ranks the horses at horse shows?","answer":"Judge"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2972 easy HH40","question":"What do you call advanced exercises & training in horsemanship?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2973 easy HH22","question":"Referring to reining, in order to achieve a sliding stop, when should you signal your horse for the stop?","answer":"When the horse's rear legs are moving forward under its body"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2974 easy HH52","question":"On long trail rides, how often should you dismount & lead your horse?","answer":"5 minutes each hour"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2975 easy H1-31","question":"Name a horse show class in which patterns are generally used.","answer":"Showing in hand/showmanship, Western, English, Dressage, Trail 	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2976 easy HIH1100-1","question":"Name an English riding activity that a saddle seat rider does not participate in?","answer":"Jumping"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2977 easy IH180D-1","question":"In which equine sport does the rider "drop" the reins & allow the horse to work independent of any guidance?","answer":"Cutting"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2978 easy HH40","question":"Polo matches are divided into 7 ï¿½ minute periods called what?","answer":"Chukkars    "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2979 easy HH44","question":"What is the purpose of a showmanship pattern?","answer":"To test the exhibitor's ability to present a horse to the judge"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2980 easy HH44","question":"When is a show stick acceptable for showmanship classes?","answer":"When you're showing a draft horse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2981 easy HH44","question":"When do you NOT switch sides in showmanship?","answer":"When showing a draft horse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2982 easy HH40","question":"What is the term for games on horseback?","answer":"Gymkhana"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2983 easy HH10","question":"What is the term for the rider's personal attire & any equipment he might require for showing?","answer":"Appointments"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2984 easy HH40","question":"What is a flat race?","answer":"Race without jumps"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2985 easy HH46","question":"In showing your horse at halter, how much space should be left between your horse & the next nearest one?","answer":"One horse length OR 8 feet"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2986 easy HH42-43","question":"What builds character faster than purple ribbons?","answer":"Good sportsmanship"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2987 easy HH45","question":"In a show, what side are you supposed to be on when leading your horse?","answer":"Left"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2988 easy HH40","question":"Where is the emphasis placed in a pleasure or performance class?","answer":"On the horse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2989 easy HH24","question":"On which side of the horse should the ends of split reins fall when using one finger between the reins?","answer":"Same side as reining hand"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2990 easy HH24","question":"How should you change directions on the rail in a horse show?","answer":"Turn towards the inside (away from the rail)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2991 easy HH40","question":"What is gymkhana?","answer":"Games on horseback"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2992 easy HH40","question":"What do you call a race without jumps?","answer":"Flat race"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2993 easy HH42","question":"In the show ring, how many lengths should you stay from other riders?","answer":"One horse length OR 8 feet"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2994 easy HH46","question":"When turning the horse in front of a halter show judge, which direction do you generally turn?","answer":"To the right OR away from you"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2995 easy HH24","question":"After you have mounted, on which side of the horse should the romal be found?","answer":"Opposite side from the reining hand"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2996 easy HH42","question":"When riding in group classes like equitation, name one thing you can do to avoid bunching up?","answer":"Pass, cut corner, circle to get to clear area"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2297 easy HH45","question":"Do not show a horse at halter until you are sure of what?","answer":"That you can control the horse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2998 easy HH44","question":"How far ahead of the class starting time should the judge post any required pattern?","answer":"At least one hour "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"2999 easy HH24","question":"If you are using split reins, how many fingers can be between the reins in a Western Equitation class?","answer":"One"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3000 easy HIH180D-1","question":"What is the purpose of a cutting competition?","answer":"To show the ability of the horse to cut a cow from a herd & prevent it from returning"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3001 easy HH9","question":"What is the term for having a pleasing, graceful, alert general appearance?","answer":"Stylish"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3002 easy HH46","question":"What type of turn is generally preferred in showmanship?","answer":"Pivot turn"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3003 easy HH20","question":"What are appointments?","answer":"Equipment & clothing used in showing"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3004 easy HH9/DET245","question":"What does the term "shown in hand" mean?","answer":"Shown at halter or showmanship"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3005 easy HH46","question":"Besides keeping your horse posed so the judge gets the best view, name one other thing you should do at all times during a showmanship class.","answer":"Be aware of where the judge is, know what's expected of you/know the pattern"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3006 easy HH43","question":"Please fill in the blanks.  Be a good sport.  Win without _______ and lose without _____.","answer":"With without bragging & lose without complaining"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3007 easy DET23,40","question":"Name the 2 kinds of rodeo bronc riding.","answer":"Saddle & bareback"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3008 easy TH22","question":"At what age do Thoroughbred horses compete for the Triple Crown?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3009 easy DET71","question":"What do you call a man who herds & tends cattle?","answer":"Cowboy"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3010 easy TH22","question":"In 1973, Secretariat became the first horse in 25 years to do what?","answer":"Win the Triple Crown"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3011 easy DET274","question":"Collectively, the Kentucky Derby, Preakness Stakes, & Belmont Stakes are known as what?","answer":"Triple Crown"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3012 easy DET104","question":"What term refers to a horse that breaks through the starting gate prematurely? ","answer":"False start "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3013 easy DET166","question":"In which horse show class are young riders mounted and led by an adult handler? ","answer":"Lead line "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3015 easy DET215","question":"How many poles are used in pole bending?","answer":"Six"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3016 easy DET82","question":"In a pattern riding class, what is the penalty for NOT following the pattern?","answer":"Disqualification"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"easy","number":"3017 easy DET219","question":"What is the 2nd race in the Triple Crown for 3 year old Thoroughbreds?","answer":"Preakness              "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3018 medium DET33","question":"What does the term "blow a stirrup" refer to?","answer":"To lose a stirrup iron"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3019 medium DET36","question":"In a ranch operation, what is the purpose of a boundary rider?","answer":"To ride the fences of the property and repair any problems."},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3020 medium DET263","question":"What is another name for the activity described as ï¿½heading and heelingï¿½?","answer":"Team roping"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3021 medium DET211","question":"What is the name for the person at a rodeo who helps the rider off the the bronc when the ride is completed, pulls the flank strap off the bronc and removes the bronc from the arena?","answer":"The pickup man "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"Medium","number":"3022 Medium TH20","question":"You do the math --  How many furlongs are in a 1ï¿½ mile race? ","answer":"12 furlongs 		(Info only -- 8 furlongs per mile) "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3023 medium DET57","question":"What historic event took place at Circus Maximus?","answer":"Roman chariot races"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3024 medium DET18","question":"What equipment is being described? This is used in speed-based events. The horse determines the ï¿½timeï¿½ for this device. It has a clock that is ï¿½automaticallyï¿½ triggered when the horse starts the event and stops when the horse goes through the finish. ","answer":"Automatic timer or electronic timer"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3025 medium DET168","question":"In which type of competition do horses perform without personal contact from a rider or handler, as in circus acts? ","answer":"Liberty classes "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3026 medium DET107","question":"What is the term for the mounted followers of a fox hunt?","answer":"Field"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3027 medium HIH185D-1","question":"2 part question:   Vaulting is judged on teamwork and how well the human and equestrian athletes work together. Similar to Olympic ice skating competitions, the individual or teams will be scored on two different types of performance. Name them ","answer":"Compulsory moves and Freestyle routines. "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3028 medium HIH185D-2","question":"2 part question:  For an ideal team in vaulting there are bigger, stronger vaulters and some smaller vaulters. What are the common terms for both of these types of vaulters? ","answer":"Bases & flyers "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3030 medium DET266","question":"The Tevis Cup is an endurance ride that takes place in California each year.  What famous route does this ride follow?","answer":"Pony Express route"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3032 medium TH97","question":"Why are the tails of driving & work horses docked?","answer":"To prevent the tail from interfering with the driving lines & harness"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3033 medium DET14","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is an apprentice?","answer":"Jockey in training"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3034 medium DET213","question":"When performed correctly, which hind foot should remain more or less in place when completing a spin to the right in a reining pattern?","answer":"Right hind"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3035 medium DET9","question":"What does AHSA stand for?","answer":"American Horse Show Association"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3036 medium DET74","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is the term for the "bay" of a hound?","answer":"Cry"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3037 medium DET103","question":"What is the general term for a separation between rider & horse that necessitates remounting?","answer":"Fall"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3038 medium HIH160-1","question":"What do the initials USTA stand for?","answer":"United States Trotting Association"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3039 medium DET85 picture","question":"At what marker does the horse & rider enter the dressage arena?","answer":"A"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3040 medium HH40","question":"What is the central theme of all performance classes?","answer":"To display the horse at its best - doing what it does best"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3041 medium HH24","question":"If a lariat or rope is carried in stock seat equitation, where is it fastened?","answer":"To fork of saddle"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3042 medium DET218","question":"In a horse race, what is the official name for one's starting position?","answer":"Post position"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3043 medium DET223","question":"What is the official name for the prize money in a horse race?","answer":"Purse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3044 medium DET293","question":"You are completing a cross country race & are approaching a brush fence with a white flag on the right side of the obstacle.  What does this indicate?","answer":"You are approaching the fence from wrong direction    (white flag should be on left side of the obstacle)			
3045	(medium)						DET79
Q:  In reference to fox hunting, what is a den?
A:  Home of a fox"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3045 medium DET79","question":"In reference to fox hunting, what is a den?","answer":"Home of a fox"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3046 medium THvarious","question":"Which horse typically races the slowest - a trotter or a pacer?","answer":"Trotter"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3047 medium THvarious","question":"Who was the first undefeated Triple Crown winner?","answer":"Seattle Slew"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3038 medium TH164","question":"What do the initials PRCA stand for?","answer":"Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3049 medium DET130","question":"What is the name of the cowboy who rides on the side of the steer opposite the steer wrestler  ","answer":"Hazer"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3050 medium HIH181D-1","question":"The popularity of dressage greatly increased with the addition of which competition?","answer":"Freestyle	"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3051 medium HIH250-1","question":"Special Olympics riding is a therapeutic riding program designed to develop what?","answer":"Rider's social skills"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3052 medium HIH181D-1,183D-2","question":"Freestyle patterns ridden to music are found in which 2 equestrian sports?","answer":"Dressage & reining"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3053 medium DET7","question":"In reference to horse racing, what does the term "also ran" refer to?","answer":"Any horse who ran, but didn't place in the race"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3054 medium HIH180D-1","question":"Modern cutting competitions give a horse & rider how long to demonstrate their skills?","answer":"2 1/2 minutes"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3055 medium HIH185D-1","question":"Modern vaulting was developed in Germany in the 1940's as a way to do what?","answer":"Offer children an inexpensive way to participate in equestrian sports"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3056 medium HIH185D-1","question":"What is a longeur?    (pronounced lawn-zour)","answer":"The person who controls the vaulting horse   (Info only -- with longe line & whip)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3057 medium HIH1940-1","question":"What is the umbrella organization for leaders or groups who work with youth & horses?]","answer":"American Youth Horse Council"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3058 medium TH145","question":"For an entry in a get of sire class, how many horses are shown together?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3059 medium DET227","question":"What is a claiming race?","answer":"A flat race in which every horse - including the winner - may be claimed/purchased for a previously stated price"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3060 medium TH664","question":"What is a free-legged pacer?","answer":"A pacer who races without hobbles"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3061 medium DET245","question":"What are the cap & jacket of a jockey called?","answer":"Silks"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3062 medium TH22","question":"What is the 3rd & final race in the Triple Crown?","answer":"Belmont"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3063 medium DET13,237","question":"What is the term for the cloth that's draped across the lap of passengers to keep them warm & dry when riding in a carriage?","answer":"Apron, rug, or lap robe"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3064 medium DET266","question":"What is the name of the endurance competition which is ridden over the old Pony Express route from Lake Tahoe to Auburn, California?","answer":"Tevis Cup"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3065 medium DET145","question":"What term describes the person who hunts the hounds & is in charge of the kennels?","answer":"Huntsman"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3066 medium DET212","question":"What is the name of the 6 foot length of rope used to tie the legs of the calf in calf roping?","answer":"Pigging string"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3067 medium TH138","question":"What organization compiles the rulebook for the horse show world?","answer":"American Horse Show Association  or AHSA"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3068 medium DET274","question":"Name the 3 thoroughbred races included in the Triple Crown?","answer":"Kentucky Derby, Preakness, Belmont "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3069 medium DET105","question":"What organization is responsible for making the rules & regulations for the conduct of the equestrian sports in the Olympic Games?","answer":"FEI or Federation Equestre Internationale"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3070 medium TH154","question":"What horsemanship competition was originally a trial for cavalry patrol mounts & was designated as an Olympic sport in 1912?","answer":"Combined training  or 3 day eventing"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3071 medium DET79","question":"In which equestrian sport would winning competitors receive "day money"?","answer":"Rodeo"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3072 medium DET56","question":"What is the term for the box from which livestock are released into the arena in rodeo events?","answer":"Chute"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3073 medium DET77","question":"What is the term for the wrap taken with a lariat around the horn of a Western saddle when roping?","answer":"Dally"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3074 medium DET21","question":"In reference to horse racing, what is the term for the side of the track furthest from the winning post?","answer":"Backstretch"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3075 medium DET6","question":"The All-American Futurity is a race for which breed of horse?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3076 medium DET78","question":"In rodeo, what is the name for the prize money paid to the winners of each go-round of a competition?","answer":"Day money  "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3077 medium DET24","question":"In reference to rodeo, name an event that has a rope barrier","answer":"Tie down/calf roping, team roping, steer wrestling/bulldogging"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3078 medium DET183","question":"A racehorse that runs well on wet, sloppy or heavy tracks is known by what term?","answer":"Mudder"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3079 medium DET108","question":"In three day eventing, to which side of the jump would a rider correctly see a red flag?","answer":"Right"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3080 medium DET281","question":"What is a vaquero?","answer":"Spanish term for cowboy"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3081 medium DET213","question":"In horse racing, what is the term for finishing second in a race?","answer":"Place"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3082 medium DET14,42","question":"In horse racing, what is the term used for a jockey in training?","answer":"Apprentice or bug boy"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3083 medium DET45","question":"What is a "calf horse"?","answer":"Horse specifically trained for use in roping"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3084 medium DET76","question":"A rider who stays far away from the arena corners & does not make good use of the full arena is sald to be doing what?","answer":"Cutting corners"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3085 medium DET76","question":"What is a cutting horse?","answer":"Horse who's trained to separate one animal from the herd   OR horse used in a cutting class"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3086 medium DET259","question":"What is the name of a light, 2-wheeled racing rig?","answer":"Sulky"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3087 medium TH387","question":"In driving, on which side does the driver mount the vehicle?","answer":"Right or off side"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3088 medium DET255","question":"What is the name given to a race over natural or artificial obstacles such as fences, hedges & water jumps?","answer":"Steeplechase"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3089 medium DET119,130","question":"2 part question:  When driving a team, what are the verbal commands for turning & which direction are they for?","answer":"Gee = right                 Haw = left"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3090 medium HIH172-1,181D-1","question":"What do the initials USDF stand for?","answer":"United States Dressage Federation"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3091 medium DET235","question":"Referring to race horses, what is a "ringer"?","answer":"A horse entered into a race under false identity   (usually below his class - where he is almost certain to win)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3092 medium DET232","question":"What is a re-ride in rodeo?","answer":"Bronc or bull rider is given a second ride in the same go-round"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3093 medium DET116","question":"How long is a furlong?","answer":"1/8 of a mile    (220 yards or 102.17 meters)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3094 medium DET161","question":"What is the primary difference between the horses that are raced in the Kentucky Derby and the Kentucky Oaks?					","answer":"Kentucky Oaks is a race for only fillies    (Addtl info:  Both races are for 3 year old Thoroughbreds)	"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3095 medium DET272","question":"Give two terms commonly used to describe the condition of 	the racetrack footing.","answer":"Fast, sloppy, muddy, heavy				"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3096 medium DET222","question":"Touching the saddle with a free hand is referred to by the slang term	ï¿½pulling leatherï¿½ and is a disqualification in what rodeo event?","answer":"Saddle bronc riding				"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3097 medium DET298","question":"What is the name of the person who looks after the horses on a trail ride?","answer":"Wrangler                  "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3098 medium DET217","question":"What is the term for the Australian game on horseback that is based on polo & lacrosse?","answer":"Polocrosse            "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3099 medium DET4","question":"What 2 criteria determine the winner of an against the clock jumping competition?","answer":"Rider with fastest time & fewest faults              "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3100 medium DET139","question":"For what specific equine competition would you have herd holders?","answer":"Cutting				"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3101 medium DET114","question":"What kind of hitch is described by 2 pairs with one in front of the other?","answer":"Four-in-hand       (four up)           "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3102 medium DET17","question":"What type of activity would you use an Association saddle for?","answer":"Rodeo                       "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3103 medium DET116","question":"What are you doing if you are fuzztail running?","answer":"Herding & catching wild horses                "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3104 medium HIH186D-2","question":"What do the initials NHSRA stand for?","answer":"National High School Rodeo Association                  "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3105 medium DET103","question":"In general, in regards to the horse, what designates a fall?","answer":"When both the shoulder & hip on the same side touch the ground            "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3106 medium DET74","question":"What is the slang term for the main office of a rodeo where excuses & grievances are aired?","answer":"Crying room               "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"medium","number":"3107 medium DET60","question":"English stagecoaches often were accompanied by a cockhorse that was ridden behind the coach.  What was the purpose of the cockhorse?","answer":"Hitched in front of the team when going up steep hills or heavy going            "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3108 hard DET180		","question":"In regards to foxhunting, what do the initials MFH indicate when used after a personï¿½s name?","answer":"Master of Fox Hounds"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3109 hard DET229		","question":"In regards to foxhunting, what is the proper term for the type of dress worn during cubbing season?","answer":"Rat catcher
(additional info:  ï¿½cubbingï¿½ is hunting young fox cubs before the formal season.  This is the training period for young hounds about to enter the pack)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3110 hard DET145","question":"Why is the scarlet livery worn by foxhunting staff commonly called ï¿½pinksï¿½?","answer":"A famous British tailor named Pinque supposedly made the first coats"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3111 hard DET54","question":"What is the hunting term used when the hounds lose the scent of the fox & stop?","answer":"Check or throw up"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3112 hard DET p. 61 ","question":"Although this is probably more commonly known as a slang term for a favorite type of soda, this is also the Spanish term for roping classes.  What is this term? ","answer":"Colas "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3113 hard TH223","question":"Secretariat won the Belmont Stakes in record time ï¿½ what was the time?","answer":"2 minutes and 24 seconds"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3114 hard DET255","question":"Where did the name "steeplechase" come from?","answer":"In the late 1700's, the races often went from one church to another"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3115 hard DET128","question":"When riding dressage, what do you call a two-track exercise in which the horse moves forward & sideways at the same time?","answer":"Half Pass"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3116 hard DET245","question":"Who chooses the colors of the jacket & cap worn by a jockey in the Kentucky Derby?","answer":"Horse's owners"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3117 hard DET129","question":"When horses are handicapped in racing, what is done to try to equalize the performance of the horses?","answer":"Weight is added   - more to the better horses"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3118 hard DET62","question":"What is the general name for a halter class in which coat color & pattern - not conformation - is a deciding factor?","answer":"Color class"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3119 hard DET100","question":"What is the horse racing term for a type of wagering where the person placing the bet must pick the first & second finishers in exact order?","answer":"Exacta"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3120 hard FCH382","question":"To exercise a horse at moderate speed is called what?","answer":"Breeze"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3122 hard HH26","question":"Where should the bight of the rein be when riding in saddle seat equitation?","answer":"Off or right side"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3123 hard HH26","question":"In saddle seat riding, on which side of the horse would the rider hold his crop or whip?","answer":"Side of horse facing ring  OR inside hand   (rider changes whip hand when changing direction)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3125 hard HIH181D-1","question":"What phases make up a 3-day or combined training event?","answer":"Dressage, cross country jumping, stadium jumping"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3126 hard FCH395","question":"As a racing term, maiden refers to what?","answer":"Horse that has not won a race at a recognized track"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3127 hard TH9","question":"In Colonial New England, why was horse racing socially unacceptable?","answer":"Too closely associated with the landed gentry in England"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3128 hard FCH382","question":"In reference to race horses, what is the difference between a breeze & a blowout?","answer":"Breeze - easy workout                 Blowout - short, fast run"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3129 hard FCH382","question":"In reference to horse racing, a short fast training run (usually 3-4 furlongs in length) is referred to as what?","answer":"Blowout"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3130 hard HIH 183D-1","question":"You do the mathï¿½You are judging a reining class and have just finished scoring the last horse.  You have given this horse a total maneuver score of + 3 ï¿½ (plus 3 ï¿½) and total penalties of -5 (minus 5).  What would be the final score for this horse?","answer":"Final score 68 ï¿½"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3131 hard HIH170-1,186D-1","question":"What were the founding principles or reasons for High School Rodeo?","answer":"To encourage youth to stay in school & to promote sportsmanship"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3132 hard HIH172-1,181D-1","question":"What term refers both to a system of training horses & a competitive equestrian sport?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3133 hard HIH172-1,181D-1","question":"Why can dressage for the horse be compared to ballet training for humans?","answer":"Progressively develops the horse's musculature & coordination   (develops balance & correct movement)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3134 hard HIH172-1,181D-1","question":"Dressage has its roots in classical Greek horsemanship, but it was not recognized as an important equestrian pursuit until what era?","answer":"Renaissance"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3135 hard HIH716-1,198O-1","question":"What does NARHA stand for?","answer":"North American Riding for the Handicapped Association"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3136 hard HIH180-1,193O-1","question":"Which association was established to promote safe, knowledgeable riding instruction?","answer":"American Riding Instructors Association"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3137 hard HIH162-1,183D-1","question":"Reining is a judged event designed to show what?","answer":"The athletic ability of a ranch-type horse in the confines of the show arena"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3138 hard HIH162-1,183O-1","question":"How is a reining pattern scored?","answer":"Individually from zero to infinity.  Starting score is 70 with plus/minus points given for each maneuver"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3139 hard HIH250-1","question":"Describe how hippotherapy provides benefits for a paralyzed rider","answer":"Movement of the horse imparts movement of the rider's pelvis that closely resembles walking"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3140 hard HIH250-1","question":"The form of therapeutic riding that uses functional horsemanship skills to achieve goals such as improved speech or motor skills is called what?","answer":"Rehabilitative"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3141 hard HIH172-2,181D-1","question":"Dressage has its roots in the classical horsemanship of what country?","answer":"Greece"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3142 hard HIH165-3","question":"In what year did the National Reining Horse Association hold its first team tournament championship?","answer":"1995"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3143 hard HIH180D-1","question":"2 part question:  Where did the sport of cutting begin & where did the name come from?","answer":"On ranches in the early 1800s.  Cows had to be separated or "cut" from the herd for branding, medical treatments, etc."},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3144 hard HIH185D-1","question":"How is vaulting judged?","answer":"On how well the horse & vaulter work together"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3145 hard DET15","question":"What horse was the first winner (in 1875) of the Kentucky Derby?","answer":"Aristides"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3146 hard DET78","question":"What is the racing term which refers to 2 or more contestants that arrive simultaneously at the finish line?","answer":"Dead heat"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3147 hard DET130","question":"Where does the coachman sit on a hansom cab?","answer":"On a seat outside the body of the carriage behind the enclosed passenger seat"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3148 hard DET55","question":"What is the name for the manager of an equestrian team who's responsible for making all the arrangements - both on & off the field - for a national team who's competing abroad?","answer":"Chef d'Equipe       (pronounced chef de keep)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3149 hard DET34","question":"What is the term for a cowboy whose job is to rescue cattle that have gotten trapped in mud or marshland?","answer":"Bog Rider"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3150 hard DET36","question":"In reference to carriages, what is the "box"?","answer":"The driver's seat"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3151 hard DET261","question":"What term is used to describe the middle team in a 6 horse hitch?","answer":"Swing team"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3152 hard DET251","question":"In QH racing, what is a speed index?","answer":"Method of rating racehorses that's determined by both horse's speed & distance covered"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3153 hard DET232,274","question":"Describe the difference between the dressage movements travers & renvers? (TRA-vair & RON-vair)","answer":"Traversï¿½haunches in; 	Renversï¿½haunches out"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3154 hard DET162","question":"In equine competition, what is a kur?","answer":"A musical freestyle ride in dressage"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3155 hard DET2","question":"To keep their balance on sharp turns some jockeys will ride with one stirrup leather adjusted longer than the other. What is the term used to describe this practice? ","answer":"Acey-deucey "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3157 hard DET122","question":"In foxhunting, what does the term "gone to ground" mean?","answer":"Fox has taken refuge in the ground, drain, den or other shelter"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3159 hard DET48","question":"Airs above the ground refers to any of the dressage movements in which the horse's forelegs or both forelegs & hind legs are off the ground.  Which legs are off the ground when performing a capriole?","answer":"Both fore & hind legs"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3160 hard DET279","question":"What term describes a hitch with 2 wheel horses & a single lead horse?","answer":"Unicorn"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3161 hard DET p. 47 ","question":"In foxhunting, what is a capping fee?","answer":"Fee paid by a visitor for a day of foxhunting"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3162 hard DET p. 164 ","question":"Larking refers to unnecessarily jumping fences when participating in what equine activity?","answer":"Foxhunting"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3163 hard DET p. 262 ","question":"What is the cry of the hunt once the fox has been sighted?","answer":"Tally ho"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3164 hard DET162","question":"Kur is the term for what type of musical freestyle performance?","answer":"Dressage					"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3165 hard DET279","question":"Describe a unicorn hitch.","answer":"Two horses hitched as a pair with a third in front of them  (also accept pair of wheel horses with a single lead horse)			"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3166 hard DET215","question":"Give the location for the point team in an 8-horse hitch.","answer":"Team behind the leaders			"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3167 hard DET22, 48, 73","question":"Identify two of the classical ï¿½airs above the groundï¿½ when all four feet are off the ground.","answer":"Ballatade, capriole and croupade			"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3168 hard DET284","question":"What is the correct term for a full turn on the haunches in dressage?","answer":"Volte                                   "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3169 hard DET157","question":"What is a jerk line?","answer":"Single rein fastened to the brake handle of a carriage and run through the driverï¿½s hand to the bit of the lead horse              "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3170 hard DET160","question":"The Russian equestrian sport of kabakhi is ridden at a full gallop & includes what other type of sport?","answer":"Archery           "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"hard","number":"3171 hard DET215","question":"What term refers to the team of horses behind the lead tem in an 8 horse hitch?","answer":"Point team         "},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3172 bonus HIH435a-1","question":"Identify 4 physiological and/or anatomical factors that would indicate a horseï¿½s racing performance or athletic ability","answer":"Conformation, Genetics, Oxygen intake ability (respiratory capacity),    Gait,  Heart Size & heart rate capacity (cardiac capacity)    Proportion/type of muscle fibers	"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3173 bonus HIH170-2","question":"When showing the Hackney Pony in harness classes, name 3 types of hitches used?","answer":"Single, pairs, tandem"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3174 bonus DET84,227","question":"Administering drugs to a horse to improve or hinder his performance in a race or competition is known as doping.  Name 3 body fluids that may be tested to detect doping","answer":"Urine, saliva, blood"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3175 bonus H5-15 ","question":"Showmanship patterns contain common elements.  Name 3","answer":"Walk, jog/trot, pivot turn, set up/stand for inspection, 90, 180 or 360 degree turn,  change of direction/turn"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3176 bonus DET166,215,261,292","question":"Correctly identify the 4 pairs of horses in an 8 horse hitch in order from front to back","answer":"Leaders, point or body team, swing team, wheelers"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3177 bonus HH24","question":"What are the appropriate gaits performed in stock seat equitation?","answer":"Walk, jog/trot & lope"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3178 bonus TH40","question":"What gaits does a 3-gaited horse perform?","answer":"Walk, trot, canter"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3180 bonus HH43","question":"What are 2 things you should remember when winners are announced?","answer":"Win graciously, lose graciously; don't run over the judge when picking up ribbons; listen to judge's reasons for placing - it may help in the future"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3181 bonus LTJ","question":"What are 3 possible solutions for a small rider to mount a tall horse in hunt seat?","answer":"Use a mounting block, have a friend give you a leg up, drop left stirrup for mounting & readjust it after you're mounted"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3182 bonus HH44","question":"Explain how a draft horse is decorated for show.","answer":"Mares & geldings both have tails tied.  Mares may have manes rolled.  Geldings have manes rolled & decorated."},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3183 bonus HH24","question":"Name 3 pieces of optional personal appointments in stock seat equitation.","answer":"Spurs, chaps, sweaters, vests, coats"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3184 bonus HH25","question":"Name 3 pieces of optional personal appointments in hunt seat equitation.","answer":"Unroweled spurs, crops/bats, gloves"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3185 bonus HH25","question":"Name 3 pieces of prohibited equipment for hunt seat equitation.","answer":"Martingales, tie-downs, flash nosebands"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3186 bonus HIH162-1,183D-1","question":"Name 3 things that are included in a reining pattern.","answer":"Circles, flying lead changes, roll backs, 360 degree spins, slide stops, speed changes"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3187 bonus HIH250-1","question":"Therapeutic riding includes 4 methods or activities.  What are they?","answer":"Hippotherapy, rehabilitative, sports/Special Olympics, vaulting"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3188 bonus HIH250-1","question":"Name 3 things a therapy horse must learn to tolerate.","answer":"Wheelchairs, loading ramps, crutches, sudden noises, rider's lack of balance, inadvertent pressure (leg/hand) by rider, etc.			(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3189 bonus TH20-22,28-31","question":"Name 3 different types of horse racing.","answer":"Flat, harness, steeplechase, chuckwagon, chariot"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3190 bonus HIH199O-1","question":"Name 3 programs offered by the United States Pony Club.","answer":"Dressage, cross country, show jumping, mounted games, tetrathalon, know-down, vaulting, fox hunting, polocross"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3191 bonus HIH181D-1","question":"Name 3 ï¿½officialï¿½ Olympic equestrian sports.","answer":"Dressage, 3 day eventing/combined training, show jumping
(Info only -- reining is currently a demonstration sport with no medals)
,
3192	(bonus)							HIH180D-1
Q:  Name 3 things that cutting performances are judged on
A:  Challenges made by the cattle cut, horse's instinctive reactions, errors made by horse and/or rider"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3192 bonus HIH180D-1","question":"Name 3 things that cutting performances are judged on","answer":"Challenges made by the cattle cut, horse's instinctive reactions, errors made by horse and/or rider"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3193 bonus HIH185D-1","question":"Explain the different ways vaulting was practiced during the early Roman times, Middle Ages & Renaissance","answer":"Early Romansï¿½acrobatic displays on cantering horses; 
Middle Agesï¿½knights practiced jumping onto horses;
Renaissanceï¿½agility training for young nobles"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3194 bonus DET273","question":"What are the three types of trail rides?","answer":"Social (pleasure), competitive, & endurance"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3195 bonus DET85","question":"Starting with the entry point & going clockwise, what are the 8 letters of the small (20 meter x 40 meter) dressage ring?","answer":"A  K  E  H  C  M  B  F"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3196 bonus DET225,229,263","question":"When hitching horses one in front of the other - what are the correct terms for a 2, 3 & 4 horse hitch?","answer":"2 = tandem;    3=random;    4=quadrem"},
{"category":"EQUINE ACTIVITIES","level":"bonus","number":"3197 bonus TH422","question":"Name three functions of the American Horse Show Association.","answer":"Sanctioning horse shows; keeps records; licenses judges & stewards; handles disciplinary measures; awards annual prizes; compiles annual rule book"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3199 easy HIH415-2","question":"Give the common name for the fly that feeds on the mucous membranes of the horse's eyes & nostrils","answer":"Face fly"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3200 easy TH644/HS53","question":"What are nits?","answer":"Lice eggs"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3201 easy HIH415-1","question":"On what part of the horse do stable flies bite?","answer":"Legs    (especially the lower front legs)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3202 easy HIH415-3","question":"Continual use of insecticides to control flies can have the opposite effect.  Why?","answer":"Flies develop resistance"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3203 easy HIH415-6","question":"Which external parasite attaches to its host & feeds on its blood?","answer":"Tick"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3204 easy HS43","question":"Why is it important to know the life cycle of various parasites?","answer":"So you can have an effective parasite control program    (so you can control them)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3205 easy HIH415-1	","question":"What are some of the most persistent pests of horses?","answer":"Flies"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3206 easy TH ch17/HS52","question":"Which type of parasite is easier to eradicate - external or internal?","answer":"External"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3207 easy HIH415-3","question":"The best way to control flies is to keep the barn what?","answer":"Clean  "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3208 easy HIH415-1","question":"Name a major breeding site for flies","answer":"Manure, decomposing organic matter, garbage, etc.		(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3209 easy HIH415-6","question":"What do ticks feed on?","answer":"Blood"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3210 easy HIH415-5","question":"Which fly lays its eggs on the horse's hair?","answer":"Bot fly"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3211 easy HIH415","question":"Which fly is a concern to both humans & horses?","answer":"House fly or mosquito"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3212 easy HIH415-6","question":"Where do adult lice attach their eggs?","answer":"To the hair"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3213 easy HIH665-2","question":"What is the peak time for mosquito activity?","answer":"Dusk or dawn"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3214 easy HS55","question":"What causes ringworm?","answer":"A fungus"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3215 easy HIH415-3","question":"Removal of waste & decaying vegetable matter is a major factor in controlling what external parasite?","answer":"Flies"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3216 easy HS52","question":"What do you call a plant or animal that depends on another living animal for its food & shelter?","answer":"Parasite"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3217 easy HIH415-9","question":"Who should you contact for information on recommended insecticides for your area?","answer":"Your vet or county extension agent"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3218 easy HIH415-6","question":"Which parasite of the horse comes in 2 main types - biting & sucking?","answer":"Lice"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3219 easy HIH415-3","question":"What is an excellent non-chemical way to keep flies out of areas such as feed rooms, tack rooms & box stalls?","answer":"Screens or fans"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3220 easy HIH415-2","question":"Which type of fly is known for the female's vicious bite?","answer":"Horse fly, yellow fly, or deer fly 	(only need to give one) "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3221 easy HIH415-1","question":"How many pairs of wings do flies have?","answer":"One"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3222 easy HIH415-3","question":"What is the easiest, non-chemical means of breaking the fly's life cycle?","answer":"Good sanitation OR remove breeding material"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3223 easy HIH415-2","question":"Where on a horse do black flies feed?","answer":"Inside ears"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3224 easy HIH415-2","question":"Which sex of the deer fly or horse fly bites?","answer":"Female"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3225 easy HIH415-2","question":"Where do horse flies deposit their eggs?","answer":"Plants/vegetation near water OR moist places	 (do not accept manure)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3226 easy HIH415-1","question":"Name a fly commonly found in pastures","answer":"Face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, eye gnat, sand fly, mosquito"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"3227 easy HS39","question":"What is the difference between external & internal parasites?","answer":"External parasites live on the outside of the horse; internal parasites live inside the horse"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3228 medium HS41","question":"A horse with mange has to be treated how often to avoid re-infestation?	","answer":"Every 7 days"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3229 medium HIH415-4","question":"What is the most common form of commercial fly bait?","answer":"Granular"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3230 medium HIH415-8","question":"What are microscopic creatures that cause horse mange?","answer":"Mites"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3231 medium HIH415-2","question":"Where do face flies lay their eggs?","answer":"Cattle manure"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3233 medium TH642-45","question":"What do external parasites use for comfort & shelter?","answer":"Horse's body temperature & hair"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3233 medium HIH415-2","question":"Which external parasite usually feeds on the inside ear folds 	and may cause a horse to be head shy?","answer":"Black flies or buffalo gnats                    "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3234 medium TH411","question":"What do you call organisms that are in the very early stages of development such as those before hatching from the egg?","answer":"Embryo"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3235 medium HIH415-8/TH645","question":"Irritation, itching, inflammation, loss of hair, crusty scab formation & skin folding are symptoms of what?","answer":"Mange"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3236 medium HIH415-4","question":"What are larvicides?","answer":"Insecticides designed to kill fly larva"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3237 medium TH645","question":"Which external parasite is a distant cousin of the spider?","answer":"Mange mite"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3238 medium HIH415-6","question":"Name the 2 general kinds of lice","answer":"Biting & sucking"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3239 medium ES186/HIH415-2","question":"How long is the life cycle of the mosquito?","answer":"10 - 21 days		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3336 medium )							HIH415-1","question":"Name the 4 stages of the fly's life cycle.","answer":"Egg, larva, pupa, adult"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3337 medium HIH415-1","question":"Adult house flies can act as intermediate hosts for what parasite?","answer":"Stomach worms (Habronema)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3338 medium DET144,253","question":"2 part question:  Which fly, house fly or stable fly, is a more severe pest & why?","answer":"Stable flies because they're bloodsuckers & have a painful bite"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3339 medium ADV300-2L","question":"What is meant by biological control of a pest such as flies?","answer":"Using other insects to break the life cycle (parasitic wasps)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3340 medium HIH415-8","question":"Where do sarcoptic mites reproduce & lay their eggs?","answer":"Under the skin"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3341 medium HS56","question":"What is molting?","answer":"Shedding hair, feathers, horns, or outer layer of skin		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3342 medium HS52","question":"Which 2 external parasites are communicable to man?","answer":"Ringworm, mange"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3343 medium HIH415-2","question":"What do face flies feed on?","answer":"Mucous secretions from the horse's eyes and/or nostrils"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3344 medium HIH415-2","question":"How many species of tabanids (horse flies) are there?","answer":"More than 100"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3345 medium HIH415-3","question":"House flies & stable flies have 3 prerequisites for successful completion of their life cycle.  Name 2 of these","answer":"Breeding materials, optimum moisture, & adequate warmth"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3346 medium TH649","question":"If a horse suddenly starts rubbing its tail or rump, it's commonly thought to be caused by pinworms.  However, there are other parasites that can cause this.  Name two other parasite that would cause this behavior in horses.","answer":"Lice, mange mites, biting midges/punkies/no-see-ums"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3347 medium HIH415-4","question":"Why is it more difficult to control face flies than stable & house flies?","answer":"Face flies feed on the face where it's difficult to apply insecticide OR they only land on horse for short period each day"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3348 medium HIH415-6/TH644","question":"2 part question:  During what season are lice more of a problem & why?","answer":"Winter because lice can reproduce & spread easier in long hair "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3349 medium HIH415-4","question":"Besides fly spray or wipes, what can you use to prevent black flies from feeding in horse's ears?","answer":"Petroleum jelly/Vaseline on the inside of the ear      (also accept fly mask that has ear covering)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3350 medium HIH415-2","question":"How big is a horse fly?","answer":"1/3 to one inch long"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3351 medium HIH415-2","question":"What is a tabanid?","answer":"Horse fly"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3352 medium HIH415-3","question":"To keep fly larvae from developing in the outer layers of stockpiled manure for compost heaps, you should cover the manure pile with what?","answer":"Black plastic"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3353 medium DET260","question":"What is a sweet itch?","answer":"Hypersensitivity to the saliva of flying insects"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"3354 medium HS40","question":"How long can lice live off the host animal?","answer":"About 3 days"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3355 hard FCH167","question":"Which 2 external parasites are intermediate hosts for habronemiasis?","answer":"House fly & stable fly     "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3356 hard HIH415-7","question":"The American dog tick is a 3 host tick - what does that mean?","answer":"Each life stage feeds on a different host"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3357 hard HS54","question":"How long after laying, do mite's eggs hatch?","answer":"3 - 10 days			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3358 hard HS54","question":"How many eggs do female mites lay?","answer":"10 ï¿½ 25			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3359 hard HS54","question":"At what age are female mites able to lay eggs?","answer":"10 - 12 days old		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3360 hard HS54","question":"How long does an egg-laying period last in mites?","answer":"12 - 15 days			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3361 hard TH617","question":"What is a parasite?","answer":"Plant or animal which lives in or on another living organism at whose expense it gets food & shelter
(accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3362 hard HS55","question":"What is the treatment for a horse with just a few ringworm lesions?","answer":"Soften crusts with warm soap & water & remove them.  Dry area & paint with iodine twice daily for 1 - 2 weeks"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3363 hard HIH415-4","question":"What causes most insecticide resistance problems?  ","answer":"Over use of insecticides OR improper sanitation with over use of insecticides"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3364 hard HS55","question":"What is another name for the 6-legged larva of the tick?","answer":"Seed tick"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3365 hard FCH167","question":"Why are blowflies problematic for horses?","answer":"They lay their eggs in tissues & their larvae feed on flesh"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3366 hard DET p. 79	","question":"What is the common name for dermatitis granulosa?","answer":"Summer sores (caused by Habronema larvae)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3367 hard FCH167","question":"Which flies lay eggs in wounds?","answer":"Blowflies"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3368 hard HIH415-6","question":"At what age do lice reach maturity?","answer":"2 - 4 weeks		 (answers accepted within this range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3369 hard HIH415-6","question":"How many days does it take for lice eggs to hatch?","answer":"Accept answers from 5 - 20 days 
(biting lice hatch between 5 - 10 days & sucking lice between 11 - 20 days)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3370 hard FCH167","question":"What is a maggot?","answer":"Larva of insect (soft-bodied, grub-like footless larva of an insect, especially those living in decaying matter)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3371 hard HS56","question":"What is a pupa?","answer":"Usually motionless stage of the life cycle of an insect between the larval & the adult stages (also accept chrysalis)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3372 hard HS65","question":"How does stage to stage transition occur in mites?","answer":"By molting"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3373 hard HS55","question":"If ringworm penetration is deep enough, a secondary infection may occur causing what?","answer":"Abscesses"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3374 hard HIH415-8","question":"2 part question:  What is the treatment for mange & how often should it be repeated?","answer":"Spraying thoroughly with insecticide - repeat weekly"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3375 hard HS55","question":"How do ticks breathe?","answer":"By means of spiracles/holes found on the abdomen"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3376 hard HIH415-2","question":"How long is the life cycle of the face fly?","answer":"15 - 25 days			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3377 hard HS55","question":"Treatment for what parasite problem includes painting lesions with tincture of iodine daily for 1-2 weeks?","answer":"Ringworm"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3378 hard HIH415-1","question":"What are obligate parasites?","answer":"Parasites that can't live away from their host"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3379 hard HIH415-1","question":"What is the approximate length of the life cycle of the house fly?","answer":"6 - 1/2 to 10 days		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3380 hard HIH415-1","question":"What is the scientific name for the stable fly?","answer":"Stomoxys calcitrans"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3381 hard HIH415-1","question":"Where do stable flies prefer to lay their eggs?","answer":"In rotting hay/straw mixed with horse or cattle urine/feces"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3382 hard HIH415-2","question":"How long is the life cycle of the stable fly?","answer":"3 - 4 weeks			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3383 hard HS54/FCH168","question":"Which type of mite may cause foot mange resembling scratches?","answer":"Choriopitic types"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3384 hard HIH415-8","question":"How do you verify a mange infestation?","answer":"By skin scrapings"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3385 hard HIH415-8","question":"Which mite does NOT cause mange, but does cause lumps or knots just under the skin?","answer":"Demodex"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3386 hard HIH415-8","question":"Wet mange is caused by which mite?","answer":"Psorptes equii"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3387 hard HIH415-2","question":"What is another name for black flies?","answer":"Buffalo gnats"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3388 hard HIH415-2","question":"Which fly has a bayonet-like mouthpart?","answer":"Deer fly or horse fly"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3389 hard HIH415-2,3","question":"What is another name for biting midges?","answer":"Punkies, no-see-ums, or sand flies	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3390 hard HIH415-2","question":"2 part question:  After hatching, where do the larvae of the horse fly go & when do they emerge as adults?","answer":"Larvae burrow into the mud & emerge the next spring as adults"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3391 hard TH617","question":"What is the difference between an ectoparasite & an endoparasite?","answer":"Ectoparasite - attaches to skin or body openings on horse;
Endoparasite - lives in internal organs, body cavities or tissues"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3392 hard HIH415-3","question":"When using parasitic wasps or fly predators for fly control, what must be done to be effective?","answer":"Re-apply at set intervals"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3393 hard HIH415-1","question":"What is the term for a parasite that cannot survive away from the host animal?","answer":"Obligate parasite"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3394 hard DET175","question":"What insect causes communicable dermatitis on a horse by burrowing into the skin to feed, live & reproduce?","answer":"Mange mite"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3395 hard HIH415-8","question":"Why is psorptic mange called "wet" mange?","answer":"The psorptic mite feeds by breaking the skin, causing a wet oozing that covers the feeding mite"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3396 hard HIH415-2","question":"Although black flies can infest horses, what animal do they primarily feed on?","answer":"Birds"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3397 hard HIH415-2","question":"Horse fly larvae spend a year burrowed in the mud.  What do they feed on during that time?","answer":"Earthworms, insects, or small crustaceans	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3398 hard HIH415-5","question":"What is another name for cattle grubs?","answer":"Heel flies or bomb flies"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3399 hard HIH415-2","question":"How many eggs can a stable fly produce?","answer":"Up to 20 batches of 50 eggs each"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3400 hard HIH415-7","question":"Which tick is NOT a known vector of diseases in horses?","answer":"American dog tick OR Rocky Mountain wood tick 	(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3401 hard HIH415-7","question":"Which tick carries Rocky Mountain spotted fever?","answer":"American dog tick or Rocky Mountain wood tick"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3402 hard HIH415-7","question":"Although the American dog tick & the Rocky Mountain wood tick are not known vectors of disease in horses, extreme infestations can result in what?","answer":"Tick bite paralysis, blood loss, or extreme emaciation		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3403 hard HIH415-7","question":"Which tick is a vector for Equine Piroplasmosis?","answer":"Tropical horse tick"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3404 hard HIH415-7","question":"Which tick is a vector for Lyme disease?","answer":"Ixodes ticks   (deer tick, bear tick, or Western black-legged tick)       (only need to give one)
Accept either general or specific type"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3405 hard FCH399","question":"A horse that has pediculosis is infested with what type of external parasite?","answer":"Lice				"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"3406 hard HIH430-5","question":"What is the scientific name for the common horse bot?","answer":"Gastrophilius intestinalis                "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3407 bonus HIH415-1","question":"Name 3 ways insects & other arthropods adversely affect their hosts.","answer":"Suck blood, feed on mucous discharges, spread diseases, cause pain & discomfort, cause sores on skin or inside ears, interfere with digestion resulting in poor growth "},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3408 bonus HIH415-3","question":"Other than good sanitation, name 3 types of fly control.","answer":"Baits, foggers, mists, fly spray, fly tapes/strips, fly wipes, biological control (parasitic wasps/fly predators)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3409 bonus ADV300/HIH415","question":"2 part question:  Name 3 types of flies AND the part of the horse they normally attack","answer":"House fly - all over		Face fly - eyes, nostrils		Horse fly - all over
Gnats - legs, eyes		Stable fly - legs			Black fly - ears
Horn fly - back, barrel, belly	Mites - ears, back, shoulders
Mosquito - all over		Deer flies - all over"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3410 bonus TH644","question":"Name 2 ways lice can be spread from one horse to another.","answer":"Direct horse to horse contact; indirect contactï¿½carried on items such as harness, saddles, blankets, brushes, etc"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3411 bonus TH645","question":"What are 3 symptoms of mange?","answer":"Irritation, itching, inflammation, loss of hair, crusty scabs, skin folding"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3412 bonus FCH168","question":"There are 3 types of mange:  sarcoptic, psoroptic & chorioptic.  Name the part of the horse that each affects.","answer":"Sarcoptic - head, neck & shoulders
Psoroptic - sheltered parts of body such as under forelock, mane, & tail
Chorioptic - lower parts of legs"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3413 bonus HIH415-6","question":"Name 4 areas of the horse where lice are usually first noticed.","answer":"Head, mane, neck, tail"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3414 bonus HS52-55","question":"Name the 5 most common external parasites.","answer":"Flies, lice, mites/mange mites, ticks, ringworm"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3415 bonus HIH665-2","question":"Name 3 ways to reduce your horse's exposure to mosquitoes.","answer":"Keep horse stabled between dusk & dawn/at night, keep stable lights off, lights at least 50 yards away from stables to attract mosquitoes away from horses, eliminate locations that serve as mosquito breeding sites,  clean water troughs weekly, use mosquito repellent      (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3416 bonus HIH415-3","question":"In cleaning up horse premises to help with fly control, what are 3 areas that are commonly missed?","answer":"Around fence posts, outside/under fences, feeders/hayracks, corners in barns/stalls, around silos/other feed storage areas, areas around water sources"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3417 bonus HIH415-7	","question":"What are 3 signs of a heavy tick infestation ï¿½ not including seeing the ticks?	","answer":"Loss of appetite, depression, eventual debilitation"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3418 bonus HIH415-7","question":"What are the 4 stages of the life cycle of the tick?","answer":"Egg, larva/seed tick, nymph, adult"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3419 bonus ES ch 8","question":"Name 2 tick borne diseases in horses.  ","answer":"Equine Piroplasmosis, African horse fever, Lyme disease, tick-bite paralysis, Equine Ehrlichiosis (Anaplasmosis)"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3420 bonus ADV300/HIH415","question":"Name 3 parts of the body that ticks normally infest.","answer":"Ears, neck, withers, mane, tail, flanks, chest, under chin"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3421 bonus HIH415","question":"Name 3 flies that suck blood.","answer":"Horn flies, stable flies, deer flies, horse flies, mosquitoes"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3422 bonus TH644/HIH415-7,8","question":"Name 3 effective treatments for lice.","answer":"Dipping, spraying, dusting, sponging"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3423 bonus TH644","question":"What are 4 symptoms of lice?","answer":"Unthriftiness, rubbing, biting, patches of skin without hair"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3424 bonus HIH415-8","question":"What are the 3 genera of mites?","answer":"Sarcoptes, Psoroptes, Chorioptes"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3425 bonus HIH415-1","question":"Name 3 flies that attack horses in pastures.","answer":"Face fly, horn fly, horse fly, deer fly, yellow fly, eye gnats, mosquitoes"},
{"category":"EXTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"3426 bonus HIH415-6","question":"Name 3 types of ticks that can infest horses.","answer":"Lone Star tick, Cayenne tick, Gulf Coast tick, winter tick, American dog tick, Tropical Horse tick, Western black legged tick, spinose ear tick, Rocky Mountain wood tick, deer tick, bear tick"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3427 easy HIH725-2","question":"What is the only mineral that horses have a definite appetite for?","answer":"Sodium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3428 easy HIH750-2","question":"Name a reason why your horse's digestible energy needs may increase.","answer":"Temperature changes, cold/wet weather, growing, reproduction, activity level/showing/racing, etc."},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3429 easy HIH755-2","question":"Which is safer to feed to meet a horse's energy needs, fat or grain?","answer":"Fat"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3430 easy HIH742-4","question":"What is a "calming supplement" designed to do?","answer":"Quiet down a nervous or excited horse"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3431 easy HIH730-2/TH221","question":"Vitamin D regulates the absorption of what important mineral?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3432 easy HIH740-12","question":"What is one of the most unstable nutritional components of hay?","answer":"Vitamins"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3433 easy HIH730-2/HS35/TH238","question":"Lack of what nutrient can cause a horse to go blind?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3434 easy HIH740-1","question":"What physical part of hay contains the highest level of carbohydrates & proteins?","answer":"Leaves"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3435 easy HIH710","question":"What is the most essential, easily available, & often overlooked nutrient?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3436 easy HS35/FCH48/HIH730-3","question":"Which vitamin is known as the "sunshine vitamin"?","answer":"Vitamin D"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3437 easy HIH725-4/TH233","question":"Which mineral is necessary in the blood to carry oxygen to the body's cells?","answer":"Iron"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3438 easy HIH730-3/HS35/TH240","question":"Which vitamin is responsible for the strength & proper development of the bones & mineral balance in the blood?","answer":"Vitamin D"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3439 easy HIH725-1,2/TH227-29/HS36","question":"What 2 minerals are necessary for proper bone & teeth formation?","answer":"Calcium & phosphorus"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3440 medium TH258-59/HIH730-3","question":"What 2 vitamins are found in good quality hay?","answer":"Vitamin A & D"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3441 easy HIHvarious","question":"Name 2 main types of nutrients.","answer":"Water, vitamins, minerals, protein, energy (carbohydrates & fats)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3442 easy HIH420-3,710-1","question":"Horses will usually drink enough water during the winter if water is maintained at what temperature?","answer":"45 - 68 degrees		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3443 easy HIH730-3","question":"Where do horses get Vitamin D?","answer":"Sunlight or sun-cured hay"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3444 easy HIH740-1/FCH68","question":"What part of grass is high in protein?","answer":"Leaves"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3445 easy HIH725-2","question":"Phosphorus should NEVER exceed the amount of what mineral in the horse's diet?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3446 easy HIH725-1/FCH395/HS35","question":"What is a macro-mineral?","answer":"Mineral that's needed in large quantities"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3447 easy HIH725-1","question":"What are trace or micro-minerals?","answer":"Minerals that are only required in small amounts "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3448 easy HIH735-3","question":"Which forage has a higher calcium content, legumes or grasses?","answer":"Legumes"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3449 easy TH208-9/HS37","question":"Why is it an advantage to know the amount of nutrients in a feed?","answer":"To determine quality of the feed OR  to determine if youï¿½re feeding your horse the right feed for its needs
(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3450 easy TH208/HS32/HIH","question":"What is TDN?","answer":"Total Digestible Nutrients"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3451 easy TH256/HS40","question":"Tell when a protein supplement is needed?","answer":"When horse is not getting enough protein in his current diet or if his protein requirements increase"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3452 easy TH239-40/HIH730-3","question":"Name 1 thing Vitamin D is responsible for.","answer":"Strength of bones, development of bones, store calcium in bones, mineral balance in blood, calcium absorption  "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3453 easy HIH760-10/TH256","question":"What are the 2 types of nutrients that animals need in relatively small amounts?","answer":"Vitamins & minerals"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3454 easy TH200/HIH730-2","question":"What vitamin comes from carotene in green grass?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3455 easy HIH720-1","question":"Which nutrient supplies the material from which body tissue is made?","answer":"Protein"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3456 easy FCH384/HIH715-1","question":"What is the major nutritional function of carbohydrates?","answer":"Energy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3457 easy HIH120-3","question":"Name one factor that influences a horse's nutritional requirements.","answer":"Size of animal, environment, age, type of use/activity, metabolic rate, growth, reproduction, lactation, recovery from injury/illness"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3458 easy HIH730","question":"Give 2 examples of minerals.","answer":"Iron, copper, phosphorus, calcium, magnesium, potassium, sulfur, chloride, zinc, manganese, iodine, selenium, sodium, etc."},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3459 easy HS41","question":"What is the main result of excess energy consumption?","answer":"Horse gains weight"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3460 easy HIH730-2/TH243","question":"What nutrient may be expected to maintain or improve the condition of the hooves?","answer":"Biotin	 (additional info -- biotin is one of the B vitamins)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3461 easy HIH765-1,2","question":"Of a weanling, yearling, or 2 year old, which one needs the most protein?","answer":"Weanling"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3462 easy HIH725-2","question":"Chloride in the horse's diet is usually accompanied by which other mineral?","answer":"Sodium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3463 easy HIH730","question":"Name the 2 general types of vitamins.","answer":"Fat soluble & water soluble"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3464 easy HIH750-2","question":"Green forage is an important source of which essential vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin A        "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3465 easy HIH715-1/TH272","question":"Which nutrient requirement is most increased for hard-working horses?","answer":"Energy	 (also accept water, calories, or carbohydrates)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3466 easy HIH710-1","question":"How do suckling foals meet the majority of their water needs?","answer":"Through mare's milk"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3467 easy HIH710-2","question":"How many times do most horses drink per day?","answer":"2 ï¿½ 8		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3468 easy HIH710-2","question":"By the age of 2 months, most foals are drinking how much water per day?","answer":"Up to one gallon"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3469 easy HIH710-2","question":"When allowed to choose between a bucket & an automatic watering system, which one did most horses prefer?","answer":"Bucket"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3470 easy HIH710-2","question":"What is an advantage to hand watering your horse?","answer":"You can monitor how much they drink"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3471 easy HIH741-3","question":"What is the most commonly used fat source in horse diets?","answer":"Vegetable oil	 (corn oil most common)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3472 easy HIH725-1","question":"What is a readily available storage location in the body for calcium?","answer":"Skeleton             "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3473 easy HIH730-1","question":"Why would horses stalled 24 hours a day need supplemental vitamin D?","answer":"Vitamin D comes from sunlight 	(if they're in the stall, they're not in the sunlight)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3474 easy HIH710-1","question":"How much water do horses require each day?	","answer":"8-12 gallons		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3475 easy HIH710-1","question":"What nutrient is vital to life & essential for all body systems?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3476 easy HIH725/TH221","question":"Iron, copper, & phosphorus are examples of which kind of nutrients?","answer":"Minerals"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3477 easy TH233/ES139","question":"Anemia can result from the deficiency of what mineral?","answer":"Iron  "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3478 easy TH251/FCH74","question":"Which grain is the highest source of energy?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"easy","number":"3479 easy HIH730-1","question":"Horses that are stalled 24 hours a day are more likely to be deficient in which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin D                     "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3480 medium HIH740-7","question":"What type of feed will provide the horse with the greatest amount of crude protein?","answer":"Alfalfa hay"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3481 medium ES146","question":"What happens to excess simple sugars when the glycogen storage capacity of the kidneys, liver, & muscles are full?","answer":"Stored as fat"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3482 medium TH241","question":"Give two reasons why you do not need to add Vitamin B to a horseï¿½s ration.","answer":"Good quality hay is an excellent source; significant amounts are produced in the horseï¿½s intestines"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3482 medium HIH799","question":"Legumes are higher in protein & calcium than what?","answer":"Grasses"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3484 medium FCH71/ADV302-1","question":"Which of the following common cereal grains fed to horses is lowest in crude protein - barley, oats, corn or wheat?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3486 medium TH199","question":"Which nutrients are more easily digested by the horse -  sugars & starches or fats?","answer":"Sugars & starches"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3487 medium HIH799","question":"Are mineral & vitamin contents higher, lower or equal in immature grasses & legumes than in mature plants?","answer":"Higher"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3488 medium TH219","question":"What are the "bricks & mortar" from which bodies are made?","answer":"Proteins"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3489 medium HIH730-1","question":"How do vitamins differ from minerals?","answer":"They're organic 	(also accept:  they contain carbon)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3490 medium HIH730-1","question":"What kind of compounds are vitamins?","answer":"Organic"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3491 medium TH199","question":"Why is it important to know the fiber content of feed?","answer":"Fiber is hard to digest OR feeds with higher fiber content will have less energy	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3492 medium DET16","question":"What is the name of the residue remaining in feeds after complete burning of the organic material?","answer":"Ash"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3494 medium TH218","question":"Energy deficiency in young animals results in what?","answer":"Slow growth OR poor condition	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3495 medium TH218","question":"Energy deficiency in mature animals results in what?","answer":"Weight loss, poor reproduction or poor athletic performance		(only need to name one)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3496 medium TH238","question":"Deficiency of what vitamin is rare if good quality hay or pasture is available?","answer":"Vitamin A"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3497 medium TH231","question":"What are trace nutrients?","answer":"Nutrients required in small amounts"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3498 medium TH219","question":"Define an essential amino acid.","answer":"It is one that must be supplied in the diet"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3499 medium TH238","question":"What is carotene?","answer":"Plant pigment that is converted to Vitamin A 
-
3500	(medium)				THch6/HIH730
Q:  Name the essential organic compounds that are needed in relatively small amounts by the horse.
A:  Vitamins"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3500 medium THch6/HIH730","question":"Name the essential organic compounds that are needed in relatively small amounts by the horse.","answer":"Vitamins"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3501 medium TH271","question":"When are the nutrient requirements of pregnant mares greatly increased?","answer":"Last 1/3 of pregnancy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3502 medium TH267-68","question":"Water, trace mineralized salt, & good pasture or good quality hay can supply all needed nutrients for what type of horse?","answer":"Idle mature one   (mature one thatï¿½s not in hard work)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3503 medium TH272","question":"Hardworking horses require more feed with a higher concentration of what?","answer":"Digestible energy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3504 medium FCH50","question":"Which vitamin is essential for blood clotting?","answer":"Vitamin K"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3505 medium FCH388","question":"Electrolytes are minerals that dissolve in water & are essential for many chemical processes in the body.  Name 3 important electrolytes that are lost in sweat.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3506 medium TH241","question":"What vitamins are synthesized in the large intestine?","answer":"B"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3507 medium TH245","question":"What is the first effect you would see if your horse isnï¿½t drinking enough water?   ","answer":"Horse not eating as much/decreased feed intake"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3508 medium FCH18","question":"What is the difference between fats & oils?","answer":"At room temperature, fats are solids & oils are liquids"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3509 medium TH220","question":"Which amino acid is often the limiting one in vegetable proteins?","answer":"Lysine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3510 medium HIH741-3","question":"Which has more digestible energy per pound, timothy hay or oats?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3511 medium FCH62/HIH730-3","question":"Name a forage that is a good source of Vitamin E.","answer":"Alfalfa, orchard grass, fescue or timothy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3513 medium HIH720-2","question":"What effect does excess phosphorus have on calcium?","answer":"Interferes with calcium absorption"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3515 medium FCH214","question":"Fatigue or exhaustion may result from a deficit of what 2 nutrients?","answer":"Energy, water, electrolytes"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3516 medium FCH60","question":"Which vitamin is not needed in the horse's diet, but a lack of it in human diets causes scurvy?","answer":"Vitamin C"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3517 medium HIH782old","question":"What represents 70-80% of the total cost of managing a mare to produce a foal?","answer":"Nutrition"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3518 medium HIH720-1/ES117","question":"How many amino acids are found in proteins?","answer":"22"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3520 medium TH219","question":"Which amino acid has been found to be the most essential to the horse?","answer":"Lysine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3521 medium BEG102","question":"What is the most economical protein supplement?","answer":"Soybean meal"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3522 medium FCH38","question":"In order to successfully transport oxygen, hemoglobin must combine with what mineral?","answer":"Iron"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3523 medium TH239","question":"Why does the carotene level in hay stored for a long time decrease?","answer":"It's easily oxidized"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3524 medium FCH9","question":"In feed analysis, what do the initials DE stand for?","answer":"Digestible Energy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3525 medium TH219","question":"During digestion, proteins are broken down into what?","answer":"Amino acids"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3526 medium FCH142","question":"Give 2 reasons why soybean meal is a popular supplement.","answer":"High in protein, economical"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3527 medium HIH715-1","question":"What are considered to be the building blocks of protein?","answer":"Amino acids"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3528 medium TH200,238-39/ES123","question":"What yellow pigment found in plant material is used to form Vitamin A in the horse?","answer":"Carotene or beta-carotene"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3529 medium FCH394","question":"Which amino acid is most often deficient in the growing horse's diet?","answer":"Lysine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3530 medium TH20","question":"99% of the calcium in a horse's body is concentrated in what 2 areas?","answer":"Bones/skeleton  & teeth"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3531 medium DET284/HIH730-3","question":"The lack of which vitamin can cause white muscle disease?","answer":"Vitamin E"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3532 medium HIH755-1","question":"What is the biggest nutritional difference between exercising & non-exercising horses?","answer":"Energy demands	 (also accept water)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3533 medium DET45","question":"Which mineral aids in muscular activity, blood clotting, blood balance, enzyme activation & bone formation?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3534 medium HIH715-3","question":"The measure of energy from feed that's available for absorption is called what?","answer":"Digestible energy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3535 medium HIH715-3","question":"What percentage of the available energy in feed do horses actually use?","answer":"20 - 25% 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3537 medium HIH750-4		","question":"What happens to the total nutrient content of hay when it is over-cured and baled with a moisture content that is too low?","answer":"The nutrient content decreases	 (because the leaves shatter and fall off)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3538 medium HIH725-1","question":"Over supplementing minerals may cause what?","answer":"Mineral imbalance"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3539 medium HIH725-1","question":"At what two stages of a horseï¿½s life are the calcium needs the greatest?","answer":"Young animals & lactating mares"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3540 medium HIH720-1/TH219","question":"Protein is composed of a chain of smaller units called what?","answer":"Amino acids"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3541 medium HIH725-2","question":"Sodium plays an important role in the function of which body system of the horse?","answer":"Central nervous system"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3542 medium HIH725-2","question":"What percent of the sodium consumed by the horse is absorbed?","answer":"75 - 100%		 (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3543 medium HIH725-2","question":"What percent of chloride consumed by the horse is absorbed?","answer":"100%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3544 medium HIH730-1","question":"Which vitamins are water soluble?","answer":"C & B complex/B vitamins"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3545 medium ES138/HIH725-4	","question":"What mineral is necessary for proper function of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Iodine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3546 medium HIH725-4","question":"It's important to know if your region's soil is deficient in this mineral before supplementing.  Which mineral is it?","answer":"Selenium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3547 medium HIH725-4","question":"What is the main cause of selenium toxicity?","answer":"Over supplementing it"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3548 medium HIH730-2","question":"What forage has the highest concentration of biotin?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3549 medium HIH742-1","question":"Glucosamine & chondroitin sulfate are supplements commonly used for what condition?","answer":"Joint problems or arthritis"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3550 medium HIH742-1","question":"Most horses supplemented with Glucosamine for joint problems will begin to show improvement within what time frame?","answer":"One month"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3551 medium HIH742-2","question":"By itself, selenium doesn't have much antioxidant capacity.  Its antioxidant properties become strong when selenium is paired with which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin E"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3552 medium HIH730","question":"2 part question:  What vitamins are essential in the horse's diet & why?","answer":"A & E;     because they can't be synthesized in the body"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3553 medium HIH750-2","question":"What should the calcium to phosphorus ratio be for horse feeds?","answer":"Between 1:1 and 6:1		 (accept any ratios in this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3554 medium HIH750-2","question":"Name a result of having inverted calcium to phosphorus ratio in your horse's ration.","answer":"Impaired calcium absorption impaired OR skeletal abnormalities"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3555 medium HIH710-1","question":"The body of an adult horse is approximately what percent water?","answer":"Over 60%		 (65-75%)		accept any number within range"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3556 medium TH236/FCH25-26","question":"Sweating & lactation are 2 physiological functions that will increase the free choice consumption of what mineral supplement?","answer":"Salt    (sodium chloride)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3557 medium FCH38 		","question":"The largest percentage of which mineral is found in the myoglobin or hemoglobin  in the horseï¿½s body?","answer":"Iron"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3558 medium TH233/DET139","question":"What is the primary cause of iron deficiency?","answer":"Loss of blood    "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3559 medium FCH20","question":"Approximately what percent of body calcium is contained in the bones & teeth?","answer":"99%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3560 medium TH233/DET111","question":"What condition can iron deficiency cause?","answer":"Anemia"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3561 medium ES116","question":"A deficit of what basic nutrient may increase the risk of impaction colic?","answer":"Water                           "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3562 medium HIH730-3","question":"Decreased immune function is associated with what vitamin deficiency?","answer":"Vitamin E			"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3563 medium HIH745-3","question":"Would a feed with a 2% or 5% crude fiber have a higher digestible energy?","answer":"Feed with 2% crude fiber			"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3564 medium HIH742-4","question":"What omega 3 fatty acid source when added to the diet has recently been identified as providing a significant improvement in sweet itch or other allergic skin conditions?","answer":"Flaxseed           "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"medium","number":"3565 medium FCH46/ES123","question":"What is the precursor of Vitamin A?","answer":"Beta-carotene	 (also accept carotene)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3566 hard HS33/ES117","question":"What element do proteins contain that carbohydrates & fats do not?","answer":"Nitrogen	"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3567 hard TH257/HS39/HIH741-3","question":"What is the percentage of digestible protein in protein supplements?","answer":"25 - 48% 	(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3568 hard FCH51","question":"Sweet clover poisoning results in altered blood clotting and a deficiency of which vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin K"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3569 hard FCH296","question":"A horse with chronic renal failure would require a diet that has less of certain nutrients.  Name 2 .","answer":"Protein, calcium, phosphorus"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3570 hard FCH39","question":"What mineral deficiency results in a deficiency of Vitamin B12?","answer":"Cobalt"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3571 hard FCH83","question":"What plant provides high quality protein, high levels of lysine, & is used as a common protein supplement?","answer":"Soybean"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3572 hard HS28","question":"When the percentage of water, minerals, fats, fiber are added together, the total will be somewhat less than 100 percent.  The difference is referred to as what?","answer":"Nitrogen free extract"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3573 hard HS24","question":"Trypsin converts proteins & partly hydrolyzed proteins into what?","answer":"Peptides & amino acids	"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3574 hard HIH760-5","question":"When comparing the nutrient value of timothy and orchard grass in a hay sample, which grass provides the highest percent of crude protein?","answer":"Orchard grass"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3575 hard HS31","question":"Which 2 vitamins do brans contain?	","answer":"Thiamine & Niacin"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3576 hard TH22","question":"What is required in the diet to aid in the absorption of vitamins A, D, E, & K?","answer":"Fat"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3577 hard HIH745-2","question":"The National Research Council (NRC) recommends horse rations be balanced on percentages of what 2 things?","answer":"Crude protein & lysine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3578 hard TH234-35/HIH730-3/DET284","question":"What can selenium deficiency cause?","answer":"Muscular problems OR loss of muscular coordination OR white muscle disease  	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3579 hard HIH715-3","question":"Compared to proteins & carbohydrates, fats contain what percent more digestible energy on a per pound basis?","answer":"2.25% 
(additional info:  fats have 9 calories/gram; proteins & carbohydrates have 4 calories/gram)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3580 hard ADV304-3L","question":"Why do some older horses have higher energy requirements?","answer":"Older horses may have problems chewing, digesting, and/or absorbing nutrients"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3581 hard BEG102","question":"Cottonseed meal is used as what in a horse's diet?","answer":"Protein supplement"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3582 hard TH208","question":"What does net energy refer to?","answer":"Energy actually used by the animal"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3583 hard TH220/HS34","question":"What happens when excess protein is fed?","answer":"Nitrogen is separated from the compound & is excreted in the urine& the rest of the molecule is used for energy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3584 hard HIH715,725-2/TH227","question":"What happens if thereï¿½s excess calcium in the horse's ration?","answer":"Prevents the absorption & utilization of phosphorus & other minerals; can cause bone disease in young horses		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3585 hard HIH715-1,120-3","question":"Horses require differing amounts of nutrients in their daily diet - why?","answer":"Depends on their nutritional class or status OR individual differences/uses"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3586 hard HIH505-2/ES123","question":"Name 2 things vitamin A does in the body.","answer":"Necessary for vision (especially night vision), needed for healthy skin/muscles/bones, involved in reproductive function, antioxidant"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3587 hard TH209","question":"After nitrogen is removed from proteins, what happens to the rest?","answer":"Converted into energy OR stored as fat		(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3588 hard TH219","question":"What determines the quality of the proteins?","answer":"The amount of essential amino acids 	(additional info -- more essential ones = higher quality)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3589 hard HS33/ES147","question":"Why do fats contain more energy than carbohydrates?","answer":"Energy is more concentrated in fats    
(Additional info -- fats have 9 calories/gram, carbohydrates & proteins have 4 calories/gram)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3590 hard HS33/ES117","question":"All proteins contain carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen & oxygen.  Name another element that some proteins contain.","answer":"Sulfur, phosphorus, or iron"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3591 hard HS33","question":"What is the composition of fiber?","answer":"Very complex carbohydrates			 (also accept cellulose)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3592 hard TH227","question":"What is rickets?","answer":"Weak, deformed bones due to deficiency of calcium, phosphorus, or vitamin D"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3593 hard TH234","question":"What is white muscle disease?","answer":"Disease of the muscles caused by deficiencies of selenium and/or Vitamin E    (muscles become pale)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3594 hard TH267/HIH765-2","question":"What percent protein is required by yearlings?","answer":"12 - 14%		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3595 hard TH256","question":"Protein supplements should contain a good mixture of what?","answer":"Essential amino acids"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3596 hard TH260","question":"What is the #1 principle of ration balancing?","answer":"Determine the nutrient requirements of the horse & formulate a diet to satisfy those requirements"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3597 hard TH231","question":"Define goiter.","answer":"Enlarged thyroid gland    (usually due to iodine deficiency)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3598 hard FCH42","question":"Why is an excess of fat soluble vitamins more detrimental than an excess of water soluble ones?","answer":"Water soluble ones are easily excreted from the body"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3599 hard FCH382","question":"What causes "big head" disease?","answer":"Excessive phosphorus & low calcium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3600 hard FCH265/HIH765-1,2/TH220","question":"At weaning time, most foals six months of age should be fed a diet containing what protein level?","answer":"16%		 (accept any number between 14%-18%) "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3601 hard FCH391","question":"What is the chief form in which carbohydrates are stored in the horse's body?","answer":"Glycogen"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3602 hard FCH25,26","question":"What are 2 physiological functions that will increase the natural intake of salt in a horse's diet?","answer":"Sweating & lactation"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3603 hard FCH34","question":"The Great Lakes basin, Rocky Mountains, Northern Great Plains, upper Mississippi Valley & Pacific Coast regions are all deficient in iodine.  Name a condition that may be caused by this deficiency.","answer":"Hypothyroidism, goiter, cretinism, myxedema"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3604 hard TH227","question":"Bran disease is caused by a deficiency of what mineral?","answer":"Calcium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3605 hard FCH24","question":"Give the more common name for ï¿½nutritional secondary hyperparathyroidismï¿½.","answer":"Big Head Disease OR Miller's Disease OR Bran disease    (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3606 hard FCH274","question":"The percentage of water & sugar in mare's milk is higher than that of cow's milk.  Name 2 components in which the mare's milk is lower.","answer":"Protein, fat, ash"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3607 hard HIH710-1","question":"Lactating mares may increase their water intake over their maintenance requirement by what  amount in order to meet lactation demands?","answer":"2 ï¿½ 3 times maintenance requirement   "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3608 hard FCH400","question":"The act of pica may be caused by a deficiency of what substance?","answer":"Sodium chloride (salt), potassium, phosphorus, or protein		 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3609 hard HIH420-1","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, a hay ration for mature horses should contain what percentage of crude protein?","answer":"10 - 12%     (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3610 hard HIH730-1","question":"Where in the digestive tract are amino acids synthesized?","answer":"Large intestine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3611 hard FCH16","question":"When caused by feed, hives are often referred to as what?","answer":"Protein bumps"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3612 hard TH231			","question":"What is the term for enlargement of the thyroid gland?","answer":"Goiter"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3613 hard FCH52","question":"In what 2 areas of the body is thiamin converted to its active form?","answer":"Kidneys & liver"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3614 hard TH303","question":"What is the term used to describe a horse that eats dirt because of a mineral deficiency?","answer":"Geophagia"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3615 hard HIH710-1","question":"What percent of proteins in grain-based diets is digested to amino acids & absorbed from the small intestine?","answer":"50 - 70%		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3616 hard TH209","question":"What is the term for the digestible organic nutrients (protein, fiber, nitrogen-free extract & fat)?","answer":"TDN or Total Digestible Nutrients"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3617 hard TH227","question":"Which mineral is essential for blood coagulation?","answer":"Potassium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3618 hard HIH525-3","question":"Foals can develop a metabolic bone disease called Developmental Orthopedic Disease (DOD) if fed excessive amounts of what?","answer":"Protein or phosphorus"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3619 hard HS40","question":"Barley has about what percent more TDN per pound than crushed oats?","answer":"10%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3620 hard TH257/HS39","question":"Energy-rich grains have what percent digestible protein?","answer":"7 - 10%		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3621 hard TH51","question":"Sweet clover poisoning results in a deficiency of what vitamin?","answer":"Vitamin K"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3622 hard TH252/HS39","question":"Corn, oats, barley & milo contain what percent TDN?","answer":"70 - 80% 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3623 hard HIH742-2","question":"Omega 3 fatty acids have been reported to do what?","answer":"Enhance the coat"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3624 hard HS43","question":"What is the percentage of TDN in brans?","answer":"65%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3625 hard ES119","question":"What is "crude protein"?","answer":"The total nitrogen content of the feed"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3626 hard HS43","question":"How many grams of phosphorus per pound is there in rolled oats?","answer":"1.95 grams"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3627 hard ADV302","question":"Steamed bone meal & dicalcium phosphate are the most common sources of what minerals?","answer":"Calcium & phosphorus"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3628 hard FCH411","question":"2 part question:  Name a time period when the energy requirement for a broodmare increases & what is the percentage of increase?","answer":"Last 1/3 of gestation period/pregnancy or last 3 months; increases 10-20% above maintenance OR during early lactation; increases 45% above late pregnancy"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3629 hard HIH420","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, a hay ration for mature horses should contain what percentage of crude protein?","answer":"8 - 12%		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3630 hard ES119","question":"What is digestible crude protein?","answer":"The amount of nitrogen content that's available to the horse during digestion"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3631 hard TH9","question":"How is a nutritional calorie defined?","answer":"The heat required to raise 1 gram of water 1 degree C
(additional info -- 1 kilocalorie  increases 1 kilogram of water 1 degree C)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3632 hard TH99-100","question":"What is the advantage of feeding Zeolite to young horses?","answer":"Increases bone density, decreases exertion induced bone injuries"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3633 hard TH241","question":"Name 2 things vitamin E does in the body.","answer":"Maintains & protects cell membranes from oxidation/acts as antioxidant, enhances immunity, involved in DNA production, enhances absorption & storage of Vitamin A"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3634 hard HS25","question":"What 2 minerals are necessary in a horse's diet for the regulation of all body fluids, maintenance of acid-base fluids, & nerve impulses?","answer":"Sodium & chloride"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3635 hard DET173","question":"Name the amino acid necessary for growth & milk production.","answer":"Lysine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3636 hard FCH16","question":"What are the structural components of carbohydrates?","answer":"Simple sugars"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3637 hard TH321","question":"Name the trace nutrient that is a compound of thyroxine, a thyroid hormone.  ","answer":"Iodine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3638 hard DET160","question":"What protein is the main ingredient of hair & the hoof horn?","answer":"Keratin"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3639 hard ES140","question":"Which micro-mineral acts as a partner with vitamin E in helping to prevent cell damage due to oxidation?","answer":"Selenium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3640 hard TH256","question":"Which protein supplement contains more lysine than most other vegetable proteins?","answer":"Soybean meal"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3641 hard HIH710-1","question":"The water intake of individual horses with the same diet & under the same environmental & exercise conditions may vary by how much?","answer":"Up to 50%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3642 hard HIH799-4","question":"Which hay would have a higher calcium content, timothy or clover?","answer":"Clover"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3643 hard HIH740,741","question":"Which is higher in protein, alfalfa hay or corn?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3644 hard HIH710-2","question":"What is TSS?","answer":"Total Soluble Salts"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3645 hard HIH720-1,750-1","question":"Name 2 ways protein is used in the horse's body.","answer":"Formation of tissue, muscle function, makes hormones/enzymes/antibodies"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3646 hard HIH725-1","question":"Name one thing that minerals influence about other nutrients.","answer":"Absorption, metabolism, excretion of other nutrients"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3647 hard HIH725-2","question":"60% of the magnesium in a horse's body is found where?","answer":"Skeleton/bones"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3648 hard HIH725-2","question":"What is the major electrolyte involved in the maintenance of the acid-base balance?","answer":"Sodium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3649 hard HIH725-2","question":"Give 2 signs of sodium deficiency.","answer":"Decreased skin turgor, desire to lick sweat contaminated objects, decreased eating rate, lowered water intake"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3650 hard HIH725-2","question":"What percent of common salt is chloride?","answer":"61%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3651 hard HIH725-3","question":"What is one thing that sulfur is necessary for in the horse?","answer":"Production of proteins/enzymes, involved in carbohydrate metabolism"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3652 hard HIH725-3","question":"Excess consumption of sulfur may cause a secondary deficiency in what other mineral?","answer":"Copper"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3653 hard HIH725-4","question":"What micro mineral is essential for the synthesis of vitamin B12?","answer":"Cobalt"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3654 hard HIH430-3","question":"Slow drying for hay preparation can cause up to what percent loss of carotene?","answer":"80%"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3655 hard HIH730-3","question":"A deficiency of Vitamin E can cause white muscle disease.  What general age horse does this predominantly affect?","answer":"Young horses  or  horses less than 11 months old"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3656 hard HIH742-1","question":"Glucosamine has various anti-inflammatory properties which can help prevent what?","answer":"Cartilage breakdown           (also accept - arthritis)  "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3657 hard HIH&742-1","question":"What does an anti-oxidant do?","answer":"Helps decrease the negative effects of free radicals"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3658 hard HIH742-1","question":"When does oxidative stress occur?","answer":"When the antioxidant defense system in the body is overwhelmed"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3659 hard HIH742-2","question":"Selenium & Vitamin E work together in the body.  Name 2 things they help with.","answer":"Stop nerve cell damage from free radicals, help prevent muscle problems"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3660 hard HIH742-2","question":"Name a disease condition that has been linked to excessive free radicals or a deficiency of key antioxidants.","answer":"Equine motor neuron disease (EMND), chronic rheumatic disease, degenerative joint/bone disease"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3661 hard HIH742-2","question":"Most studies to date have shown that herbal supplements don't enhance normal immune response, but may help with what?","answer":"A compromised immune system"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3662 hard HIH745-3","question":"2 part question:  When reading a feed tag, what is the best indicator of energy content & why?","answer":"Fiber content;    as fiber content increases, energy content decreases"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3663 hard HIH755-1","question":"Determining whether requirements are being met for most nutrients, other than energy, is difficult without doing what?","answer":"Analyzing the diet & comparing it to animal's nutritional requirements"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3664 hard HIH760-2","question":"In the past, horse diets were formulated at 6-7% fat, but now some have up to what percent?","answer":"15%.  "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3665 hard HIH850-1","question":"What is the term that refers to the breakdown of carbohydrates, fats, & proteins into energy with the involvement of oxygen?","answer":"Glycosis	 (also accept aerobic glycolysis or aerobic metabolism)  "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3666 hard DET122/FCH391","question":"What nutrient is primarily stored in the horse's body as glycogen?","answer":"Carbohydrates	 (also accept glucose)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3667 hard ES142","question":"Halitosis with an odor of garlic would be an indication of what specific mineral toxicity?","answer":"Selenium					"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3668 hard DET146","question":"A mare that has hyperkalemia has an abnormally high level of what electrolyte in her blood?","answer":"Potassium                                      "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3669 hard FCH297		","question":"Horses with recurrence of urinary calculi would benefit from feeding a diet that has less of what specific mineral?","answer":"Calcium					"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3670 hard HIH765-1","question":"During rapid growth, foals need more of which two amino acids?","answer":"Lysine and threonine				"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3671 hard HIH745-5","question":"A feed containing 10% crude protein & 15% crude fiber would be appropriate for what type of horse?","answer":"Mature idle horse or horse with minimal work           "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3672 hard FCH329","question":"What mineral imbalance results in the condition commonly referred to as ï¿½bob-tail diseaseï¿½?","answer":"Excess selenium      (must designate excess)   "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3673 hard HIH742-3","question":"Equine supplements that contain valerian root provide what effect?","answer":"Calming effect, sedative effect or anti-spasmodic effect       (only need to give one)    "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"hard","number":"3674 hard HIH752-2","question":"Under which circumstance is the requirement for magnesium the highest?","answer":"Lactating mares or exercising horses       (only need to give one)           "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3675 bonus HIH741-3/TH255","question":"Name 3 protein supplements fed to horses.","answer":"Soybean meal, cottonseed meal, Brewer's grains, peanut meal, linseed meal, fish meal, urea, milk protein, meat/bone meal"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3676 bonus HIH710-3","question":"Many factors can influence digestibility of nutrients in the digestive tract.  Name 3.","answer":"Source of feed, level of maturity, method of processing, quantity fed, frequency of feeding, rate of passage, compounds that interfere with digestion, individual differences"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3677 bonus HIH765-1","question":"Name 4 minerals that should be included in a concentrate feed for foals.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, copper, zinc"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3678 bonus TH252-260","question":"Name 3 ways in which grains differ nutritionally.","answer":"Energy, Crude proteins, Vitamins, Minerals, Fiber"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3679 bonus ES111/HS25","question":"What are 3 types of nutrients that are absorbed in the small intestine?","answer":"Protein, vitamin A, vitamin D, vitamin E, vitamin K, carbohydrates (non-fibrous), fat, minerals (calcium, phosphorus)   amino acids, glycerol, sugars    Accept any 3  (accept either general or specific vitamins/minerals)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3680 bonus HIH725","question":"Name 3 macro minerals.","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, magnesium, sulfur, sodium, chloride, potassium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3681 bonus HIH730-1","question":"Which vitamins are fat soluble?","answer":"A D E K"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3682 bonus HIH820-2","question":"Name the 3 electrolytes that are essential for maintaining fluid balance & nerve & muscle function.","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3684 bonus HS33","question":"Energy nutrients are chemically similar to what 3 fuels we use?","answer":"Gas, coal, oil"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3685 bonus ES33","question":"Name 4 things that proteins contain.","answer":"Carbon, hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen, sulfur, iron, phosphates"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3686 bonus HS38-39","question":"Dehydrated roughages are usually rich in what 3 things?","answer":"Vitamin A, B vitamins, proteins"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3687 bonus TH260","question":"What are 2 ways you can use the Nutrition Requirement Tables?","answer":"Check to see if ration being fed is balanced; formulate an adequate ration for your horse"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3688 bonus FCH186-87","question":"Name 3 factors influencing the nutritional needs of a horse.","answer":"Age, size, growth, health, activity/exercise, environment, temperature, reproduction, pregnancy, lactation, breed, individual characteristics, metabolic rate"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3689 bonus TH244-46","question":"Name 3 of the 10 essential amino acids.","answer":"Phenylalaine, tryptophane, leucine, isoleucine, lysine, methionine, valine, histidine, tereonine, arginine"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3690 bonus TH244","question":"There are many tasks that water performs in the body.  Name 3.","answer":"Necessary for life, transports nutrients to cells, transports waste from cells, makes up most of the blood, regulates body temperature, acts as a lubricant, necessary in most of the body's chemical reactions"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3691 bonus HIH725","question":"Name 3 micro minerals.","answer":"Copper, zinc, iron, manganese, iodine, selenium, cobalt, fluorine, molybendenum, chromium, silicon"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3692 bonus TH ch6","question":"Name 3 problems that can be caused by feeding either too much or too little vitamin or mineral supplements.","answer":"Muscle disorders, bone problems, hormone imbalances, poor hair coat, eye problems, decreased immune function"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3694 bonus HIH710,715,720,725,730/ES114-15","question":"What are the 5 main nutrients needed by the horse?","answer":"Water, energy (carbohydrates & fats), protein, vitamins, minerals "},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3695 bonus HIH735-1","question":"Horses can be divided into classes relative to their nutritional requirements.  Name 3 of these classes.","answer":"Maintenance, growing, pregnancy, lactating, working"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3696 bonus TH220","question":"Give 3 results of protein deficiency in horses.","answer":"Poor growth, unthrifty, weight loss, poor hair coat, decreased reproduction, poor hoof growth"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3697 bonus HIH710-1","question":"What are 3 factors that affect water requirements for horses?","answer":"Work type, work load, diet, weather, temperature, food intake, type of food, exercise, environmental factors, physiological state, individual variations"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3698 bonus FCH43-44","question":"Name 3 times vitamin supplements are needed.","answer":"Horse getting prolonged oral drug therapy, horse getting high grain/low forage diet, horse getting poor quality hay, horse under stress (traveling, showing, racing, etc), nervous/hyperactive horse, horse in training/prolonged exercise, anemia, horse not eating well (sick/post surgery), etc"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3699 bonus FCH47","question":"What are 3 symptoms of Vitamin A deficiency?","answer":"Excessive tearing, night blindness, reduced feed intake, slow growth, rough/dry/brittle/long hair coat, reduced fertility"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3700 bonus FCH52-57/ES126","question":"Name 3 of the B vitamins.","answer":"Thiamin (B1), Riboflavin (B2), Niacin (B3), Pantothenic Acid (B5), Pyridoxine (B6), Biotin (B7), Folic Acid (B9), Cobalamin (B12)		(accept either the name or the vitamin number ï¿½ not necessary to give both)"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3701 bonus FCH20","question":"What are 3 minerals that are of most concern when feeding horses?","answer":"Calcium, phosphorus, selenium, sodium, chloride"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3702 bonus FCH113","question":"To formulate or change a horse's diet, you must know what 3 things?","answer":"Animal's nutrient requirements, nutrient content of feed, amount being fed, amount needed to provide the nutrients"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3703 bonus FCH85/HIH742-4","question":"What are 2 benefits of feeding flaxseed to horses?","answer":"Gives glossy hair coat/bloom, softens stools to prevent impaction, has high level of Omega 3 fatty acids, treat allergic skin disease/sweet itch"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3704 bonus FCH26","question":"Give 4 signs of "salt poisoning".","answer":"Colic, frequent urination, staggering, excessive thirst, diarrhea, weakness, paralysis of hind limbs"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3705 bonus FCH16","question":"2 part question:  What are maltase, sucrase & lactase & specifically what does each of them do?","answer":"Sugar-digesting enzyme; 
Maltase - breaks down maltose;
Sucrase - breaks down sucrose; lactase - breaks down lactose"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3706 bonus FCH various","question":"What 4 electrolytes are lost in sweat & urine?","answer":"Sodium, chloride, potassium, calcium"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3707 bonus FCH13-14","question":"The protein requirements are greatest & most critical during what 3 phases of a horse's life?","answer":"Growth, reproduction, lactation"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3708 bonus ES148/TH272","question":"Adding fat to the equine diet has several benefits.  Name 3.","answer":"Growth, performance/work, helps reproductive function, helps milk production, increase stamina/performance, reduce gut fill, help maintain body weight"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3709 bonus HIH725-1","question":"Name 3 functions of calcium in the horse's body.","answer":"Bone/teeth formation, normal muscular action, blood clotting, enzyme action, cell membrane function, temperature regulation, neuromuscular function, blood balance"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3710 bonus HIH720-1","question":"Give 3 reasons why feeding too much protein isn't a good idea.","answer":"Protein can't be stored in body for later use, may affect acid-base balance, may affect calcium retention, protein is one of the more expensive parts of horse rations"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3711 bonus HIH725-2","question":"Give 3 results of too little magnesium in a horse's diet.","answer":"Nervousness, muscle tremors, ataxia/potential for collapse, hyperpnoea/increased breathing rate, death"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3712 bonus HIH725-4","question":"Give 3 signs of acute selenium toxicity.","answer":"Blind staggers, hair loss, change in hooves"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3713 bonus HIH730","question":"Name 3 vitamins & one thing they do in the horse's body.","answer":"Vitamin   A - helps with vision, immune response; 
Vitamin B - most help with enzyme processes;
Vitamin C ï¿½ antioxidant;
Vitamin D - calcium absorption/balance;
Vitamin E ï¿½ antioxidant;
Vitamin K - blood clotting, bone metabolism, vascular health"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3714 bonus HIH742-1","question":"Name 3 things that many commercial supplements may include.","answer":"Vitamins, minerals, amino acids/protein, carbohydrates/fats, herbs, microbials"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3715 bonus HIH742-3","question":"Just because herbs are natural, doesn't necessarily mean they're safe.  Name 3 negative things about using them in the horse's diet.","answer":"Can cause toxicity, negative side effects, drug-like interaction with other components of diet, some contain prohibited substances, potential for some to be banned from various competitions"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3716 bonus HIH742-3","question":"Name 3 commonly fed herbs & their potential actions.","answer":"Devil's claw - anti-inflammatory; 	
Echinacea - anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, immune stimulating;
Garlic - anti-bacterial, anti-viral, anti-fungal, anti-parasite;
Ginger - anti-thrombotic, antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-bacterial;
Ginseng - immune stimulating, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant;
Valerian root - sedative, anti-spasmodic;
Yucca - anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-spasmodic, used to reduce arthritis pain"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3717 bonus ES126-27","question":"What is the correct name for the following four vitaminsï¿½Vitamin B1, B2, B6 and B12?","answer":"Vitamin B1	= Thiamin	Vitamin B2  = 	Riboflavin            Vitamin B6 = 	Pyridoxine		        
Vitamin B12	 =  Cobalamin"},
{"category":"FEED NUTRIENTS","level":"bonus","number":"3718 bonus FCH196","question":"Identify 2 reasons why additional protein is not a desirable source of energy in the athletic horse","answer":"Produces excessive body heat				Increased electrolyte deficit
Increased water loss (due to increased sweating)		More expensive"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3719 easy HIH735-2/FCH154","question":"When changing horses from grass hay to lush pasture, how should you manage the change?","answer":"Turn them out for just a few hours a day at first, then slowly increase the time OR give them a full meal of hay before turning them out OR use a grazing muzzle"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3720 easy ADV302-2","question":"Beet pulp is used extensively in the diet of horses with what type of problem?","answer":"Respiratory problems, heaves, poor body condition (thin, underweight), chronic colic, dental problems, exercise-related muscle problems	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3721 easy HIH740-1","question":"What general  type of feed should be the start of any horse feeding program?","answer":"Forage    (also accept hay/pasture)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3722 easy HS40/FCH98","question":"Molasses is added to feed to reduce dust and improve palatability.  Name the two plants that are the primary source of molasses fed to horses in the United States. ","answer":"Sugar cane & beets  (sugar beets)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3723 easy HS36/TH189","question":"Feed stuffs that are high in fiber are referred to as what?","answer":"Forages"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3724 easy HS38","question":"Which type of hay tends to be the dustiest?","answer":"Legume hay (alfalfa)	`	accept either general or specific"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3725 easy HS38","question":"Which general type of hay tends to be the most dust free?","answer":"Grass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3726 easy HS38","question":"As hay grows older, does it become more or less digestible?","answer":"Less"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3727 easy HS38","question":"Describe the color of overly mature hay.","answer":"Pale yellow or brown"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3728 easy HIH740-7","question":"The amount of seed heads or flowers present at the time of harvest tells you what about the hay?","answer":"Stage of maturity"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3729 easy HS38	TH254	","question":"Name the 2 basic types of hay.","answer":"Grass & legume"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3731 easy HIH735-1","question":"Horses like to have a regular routine & are less likely to go off feed or develop vices if fed how?","answer":"On a regular schedule"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3732 easy HIH741-2","question":"What is the byproduct of the sugar beet industry that's used extensively in diets for horses with respiratory problems?  ","answer":"Beet pulp"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3733 easy HIH730","question":"What is the chemical name for salt?","answer":"Sodium chloride (NaCl)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3734 easy HIH740-6","question":"Why should you store hay off the ground?","answer":"So moisture from ground won't spoil bottom bales OR so air can circulate"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3735 easy HIH740-9","question":"What is the most common legume fed to horses?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3736 easy HIH740-1","question":"At least 2-3 acres of pasture per horse are needed in order to maintain what?","answer":"Forage productivity"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3737 easy HIH740-1","question":"Why is leafiness in hay an important guide to feeding value?","answer":"Most of the nutrients are found in the leaves"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3738 easy HIH740-12","question":"Hay should be fed in what?","answer":"Some type of feeder 		(manger, hayrack, hay net, feed trough, feed tub, etc.) "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3739 easy HIH735-1","question":"Horsemen should provide feed by weight, not by what?","answer":"Volume"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3740 easy HIH725-2","question":"Besides water, horses on pasture not having access to commercial feeds should always have access to what?","answer":"Salt OR trace mineralized salt"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3741 easy HIH420-3/740-10","question":"During winter, the average 1000 pound idle mature horse requires how much hay per day?","answer":"15 -20 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3742 easy HIH735-1","question":"When feeding groups of horses, what may develop because of dominance issues & cause aggressive behavior?","answer":"Pecking order"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3743 easy HIH790-1/FCH118","question":"What is the most common way to estimate your horse's weight?","answer":"Weight tape"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3744 easy HIH715-4,775-2","question":"What is the easiest way to determine if your horse's energy needs are being met?","answer":"Monitor body weight"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3745 easy HIH415-8","question":"What insect should you check your hay for?  They can harm the horse if eaten.","answer":"Blister beetles"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3746 easy HIH415-8","question":"Which grain should be rolled or crimped before using?","answer":"Barley, milo/sorghum, or wheat		 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3747 easy INT202-2L/HIH760-9old","question":"What is crimping?","answer":"Flattening & rippling grain"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3748 easy HIH735-2,740-11","question":"If forage is good, approximately how long do free-ranging horses graze per day?","answer":"10 - 17 hours		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3749 easy HIH745-3","question":"Fiber is necessary in horse diets to ensure the normal functioning of what body system?","answer":"Digestive"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3750 easy HIH740-1/TH254/ADV302/FCH168","question":"What is the most important factor affecting the nutrient content of grasses & legumes?","answer":"Stage of maturity"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3751 easy HIH741-1/TH303","question":"Name a possible cause of eating problems such as wood chewing, eating dirt, tail chewing or eating tree bark.","answer":"Boredom, lack of exercise, lack of long stem forage/"chew time", nutrition problems, copying other horses"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3752 easy HIH770-1,2","question":"Geriatric horses with dental problems may not be able to eat forage in the traditional form of hay & may need alternatives.  Name 2 of these alternatives.","answer":"Chopped hay, hay cubes (soak first), hay pellets, complete feeds"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3754 easy FCH151/HIH735-1","question":"Why is it recommended to feed a horse 2-3 times a day instead of once?","answer":"Horse has a small stomach - overeating can cause colic"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3755 easy H2-13/FCH74/HIH741-3","question":"Why is corn considered a hot feed?","answer":"Has high energy content"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3756 easy HIH705-1/FCH392","question":"Explain the difference between a herbivore & a carnivore","answer":"Herbivore - eats plants;    carnivore - eats meat"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3757 easy HIH745-1","question":"What feed additive is commonly used to reduce dust & increase palatability of a feed?","answer":"Molasses"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3758 easy HIH725-2","question":"How should sodium chloride be fed in a horse's diet?","answer":"Free choice"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3759 easy HIH741-3","question":"2 part question:  When feeding barley to horses, in what form should it be fed & why?","answer":"Crimped or rolled because it has a hard hull"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3760 easy HIH710-5 old","question":"To maintain freshness, what is the maximum that commercially prepared feed should be stored in a stable?","answer":"One month"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3761 easy HIH735-2","question":"When changing types of hay, how should you manage the change?","answer":"Mix the types together for a period of approximately 2 weeks"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3763 medium HIH760-9old/INT202-2L","question":"The process of cracking grain by passing it through corrugated rollers is called what?","answer":"Crimping"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3764 easy HIH705-1/FCH392","question":"What is the term for animals that prefer to eat plants?","answer":"Herbivore  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3765 easy BEG102-2","question":"What grain can be fed cracked, rolled, shelled, whole or on the cob?","answer":"Corn  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3766 easy HIH740-5","question":"If you have less than 1 ï¿½ acres of pasture per horse, the grass won't be able to do what?","answer":"Won't be able to be productive under constant grazing"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3767 easy HS41/HIH745-1","question":"What is sweet feed?","answer":"Grain mix that contains molasses"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3768 easy HIH975-5","question":"What is creep feeding?","answer":"Providing an area where the foal can eat without interference from the mare"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3769 easy HIH735-1","question":"When feeding a group of horses together in open areas, how far apart should the feeders be placed?","answer":"40 - 50 feet		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3770 easy HIH420-1","question":"What is the most important winter feed for horses?","answer":"Hay"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3771 easy ADV337-2L","question":"Give one reason why hay should not be baled if the moisture level is over 30%.","answer":"Hay will become moldy, hay will heat up, will lose vitamins, decreased protein digestibility, spontaneous combustion"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3772 easy HIH740-12","question":"Hay can be stored for how long without losing more than 20% of its nutrients?","answer":"1 - 2 years		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3773 easy HIH740-12","question":"Why should hay be fed in a feeder?","answer":"To minimize the intake of sand, dirt or feces  also accept:  so horses donï¿½t waste hay"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3774 easy HIH750","question":"Give a reason why a horse may not have cleaned up his feed","answer":"Overfed, something wrong with the feed, limited access to water, horse is sick, horse has teeth problems
Sore tongue/mouth, not familiar with the feed, when horse is stressed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3775 easy HIH740-7","question":"Name 2 things to look for when selecting good hay.","answer":"Green, no dust, no mold, fine stems/lots of leaves, no weeds, no poisonous plants, no blister beetles, etc."},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3776 easy HIH783-1 old","question":"Ideally, how much time should foals spend on pasture?","answer":"24 - 7 (all the time)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3777 easy HIH735-1","question":"Not referring to specific types of hay, what are the 2 main forms of roughages? ","answer":"Hay & pasture"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3778 easy HIH750-5","question":"What is the oldest & most common method of selecting hay?","answer":"Visual appraisal     (looking at it)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3779 easy HIH741-1","question":"Give one reason why you'd use a complete feed.","answer":"When you only have poor quality hay, when you have no hay available, horse with poor teeth/horse can't chew hay, etc."},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3780 easy HIH various","question":"Give 2 characteristics of moldy hay.","answer":"Musty smell, whitish color, dusty, unpalatable, moist/damp, hot"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3781 easy HIH705-1","question":"What is an omnivore?","answer":"Eats both plants & meat"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3782 easy HIH735-1","question":"The horse's digestive system was not designed to be fed large quantities of what type of feed?","answer":"Concentrates or grain"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3783 easy HIH735-2/710-6","question":"A dramatic increase in the amount of concentrates in the diet should occur gradually over what period of time?","answer":"10 to 14 days	 	 (accept anything within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3784 easy HIH735-2","question":"Horses are less likely to consume toxic plants if provided with what?","answer":"Enough hay or pasture"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3785 easy HIH735-2","question":"What height should pasture grasses be for grazing horses?","answer":"4 - 8 inches  			 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3786 easy HIH735-2,360-4","question":"Rest pastures when the grass is eaten down to what height?","answer":"1-1/2 - 4 inches		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3787 easy HIH735-2","question":"Horses spend what percent of their time grazing at night?","answer":"20 - 50%			 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3788 easy HIH735-3","question":"Do horses prefer pastures of mixed grass types or a single type?","answer":"Mixed types"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3789 easy HIH740-2","question":"Which type of clover is grown on more acres than any other clover type?","answer":"Red clover"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3790 easy HIH740-2","question":"Red clover grows best on acidic, wet soils & is usually used in areas where which other legume will not grow?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3791 easy HIH740-6","question":"Give a reason why hay prices fluctuate from year to year.","answer":"Weather (when growing/cutting/baling .... might not be enough fresh forage available), type of hay grown, how it's stored, fuel costs, number of horses in region, demand from other livestock species, perceived value of forage type"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3792 easy HIH740-7","question":"Hay bought during the winter will often be high priced for what reason?","answer":"Demand is high OR hay's hard to find, so prices are raised"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3793 easy HIH740-7","question":"Hay with a bleached color indicates exposure to what?","answer":"Sunlight or rain"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3794 easy HIH740-8","question":"Which cutting of hay will usually have the highest fiber content?","answer":"First cutting"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3795 easy HIH740-10","question":"You do the math -- A horse will eat approximately 2% of its body weight daily.  If a 1000 pound horse is only fed hay, how many pounds will he eat per day?","answer":"20 pounds		"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3796 easy HIH740-11","question":"Forage should never be less than what percent of a horse's daily diet?","answer":"50%"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3797 easy HIH740-11","question":"Horses kept on pasture will spend 10 - 17 hours per day doing what?","answer":"Grazing"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3798 easy HIH740-12","question":"To decrease the chance of hay in the eyes or inhaling dust, hay feeders for horses should be no higher than what?","answer":"Shoulder level of the horse    (also accept withers)	"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3799 easy HIH740-1","question":"In reference to hay, what part of the plant is the least digestible?","answer":"Stems"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3800 easy HIH741-1","question":"If fed without any other source of roughage, complete feeds may increase the risk of what?","answer":"Colic, laminitis, wood chewing 		(only need to give one answer)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3801 easy HIH741-1","question":"How many pounds of a complete feed are needed to meet the average 1000 pound horse's daily needs?","answer":"10 - 15 pounds		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3802 easy HIH741-11","question":"When using a complete feed, how many pounds is it advised to feed at one feeding?","answer":"2 - 4	pounds		 	(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3803 easy HIH741-1","question":"What are hay cubes?","answer":"Hay that's been chopped & compressed or formed into cubes"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3804 easy HIH741-1","question":"What is an advantage of hay cubes?","answer":"Easy to transport, easy to store		 (only need to give one answer)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3805 easy HIH741-2","question":"Traditionally, what is done to beet pulp pellets before feeding?","answer":"Soak in water "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3806 easy HIH741-3","question":"What is the most popular grain fed to horses?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3807 easy HIH745-1","question":"Basically, what does a feed tag do?","answer":"Tells you what's inside the bag"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3808 easy HIH750-1","question":"A horse is considered at maintenance if he is what?","answer":"Not doing any work OR not producing (breeding/pregnant/lactating) OR not growing   (accept any)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3809 easy HIH735-2","question":"What does resting your pasture do?","answer":"Gives grass time to regrow (lets grass develop strong roots to prevent soil erosion)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3810 easy HIH770-3","question":"Older horses may need some adjustments to their diet in order to maintain what?","answer":"Their body condition or weight"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3811 easy HS41","question":"Why should you offer salt free choice?","answer":"Horse will usually eat enough to meet its needs without overeating"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3812 easy HIH740-6	","question":"What is a main factor to consider when storing hay?","answer":"Protect it from moisture"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3813 easy HS38/TH607","question":"If you have to feed your horse dusty hay, how can you reduce the dustiness before feeding?","answer":"Sprinkle with water"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3814 easy HIH740-1","question":"What type of feed may serve as the only feed for idle horses?","answer":"Forages  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3815 easy HIH740-1","question":"How many acres of pasture per horse do you need in order to maintain productivity of the forages (grasses/legumes)?","answer":"2 ï¿½ 3 acres		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3816 easy TH251/FCH173","question":"What grain is the most difficult to overfeed?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3817 easy FCH398","question":"A horse which is not eating with a normal appetite is said to be what?","answer":"ï¿½Off its feedï¿½"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3818 easy TH183","question":"Name a way to decrease the chance of a horse bolting its grain.","answer":"Place large/round rocks in the feed tub, spread grain thinly over large surface, put several bars/compartments in feed box, feed small amounts more often, feed nervous horses first (so they don't get excited & eat faster), mix chaff or chopped hay with the grain"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3820 easy HIH740-6","question":"How long does hay usually take to dry after being cut?","answer":"3 - 5 days       (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3821 easy FCH331","question":"Name a part of the red maple tree that is toxic to horses.","answer":"Dry/wilted leaves;  bark"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"3822 easy FCH109","question":"Identify the two most palatable grasses for horse pastures.","answer":"Kentucky bluegrass and timothy              "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"easy","number":"4825 easy HIH790-3","question":"Why should you feed overweight or underweight horses separately?","answer":"So you can control the amount of feed each horse gets OR to accurately monitor their feed intake"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3823 medium HS37","question":"In which of the 3 main types of feed do grains & molasses fall?","answer":"Concentrates"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3824 medium HS32/DET229","question":"What is the definition of a ration?","answer":"The entire feed allowed an animal for a day"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3825 medium HIH745-4","question":"How much free-choice salt will horses typically consume each day?","answer":"1 - 3 ounces		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3826 medium HS32","question":"Explain the difference between a balanced ration & a maintenance ration.","answer":"Balanced ration - contains all digestible nutrients required
Maintenance ration - furnishes just enough of each required nutrient to maintain horse in current condition"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3827 medium HIH741-2","question":"How much beet pulp can be fed per day to horses?","answer":"Up to 10 pounds"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3828 medium FCH201","question":"What is lite salt?","answer":"1/2 sodium chloride & 1/2 potassium chloride"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3829 medium FCH360/TH253","question":"Corn infected with aflatoxins can cause damage to what organ of the horse's body?","answer":"Liver"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3830 medium FCH346","question":"What is a mycotoxin?","answer":"Poison produced by a mold"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3831 medium HIH740-11,735-1 ","question":"A single feeding of concentrates should never exceed what amount?","answer":"Five pounds OR not more than 3/4% of horses body weight	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3832 medium HIH741-1","question":"Hay cubes have the same nutritional value as hay, but are a more consistent product in terms of what? ","answer":"Quality  or nutrients"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3833 medium TH256","question":"Which type of hay has a higher nitrogen content - alfalfa or grass?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3834 medium HIH740-7","question":"If hay is rained on before baling, it will lose some nutrients - especially carbohydrates.  However, good quality rained on hay can benefit horses that are sensitive to what?","answer":"Forage sugar content"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3835 medium HIH740-6","question":"Referring to forages, what is early boot stage?","answer":"When the seed head is just beginning to form"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3836 medium ES146","question":"What type of equine is more efficient in digesting fiber & therefore can be fed a diet that is higher in fiber?","answer":"Donkey"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3837 medium HIH740-9","question":"Which cool season grass is adaptable to a wide range of soils, tolerant of continuous grazing, has excellent fall productivity & is winter hardy?","answer":"Tall fescue"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3838 medium HIH741-2","question":"Straw should not be considered as a source of nutrition for horses other than for supplemental use as what?","answer":"Source of fiber or "chew factor""},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3839 medium HIH741-3","question":"What is the advantage that cereal grains have over forage?","answer":"They are a concentrated source of energy & nutrients"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3840 medium HIH745-3","question":"When reading a feed tag, the percent of crude fiber is the best indicator of what?","answer":"Energy content"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3841 medium HIH740-8","question":"What is the major cool season grass that's grown from Florida to Canada?","answer":"Tall fescue"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3842 medium HIH735-1","question":"What is the first step in designing a workable feeding program?","answer":"Figuring out the nutrient requirements of the horse"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3843 medium TH280","question":"Extruded feeds are half the weight of pelleted feeds because of what substance found in each pellet?","answer":"Air"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3844 medium HIH770-2","question":"Just before winter, some may feed their older horses to achieve a body condition score greater than 5.  Why would this be helpful?","answer":"Horse has to use more energy in the cold weather"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3845 medium HIH740","question":"Overall, which grasses tend to be lower in nutritional value - warm season or cool season ones?","answer":"Warm season grasses"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3846 medium HIH799","question":"Which grain is more economical per unit of energy - oats or corn?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3847 medium HIH740-9","question":"Which cool season grass is grown mainly for hay instead of pasture?","answer":"Timothy"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3848 medium HIH740-4","question":"Which common pasture grass is present in all states, winter hardy, rapid growing, palatable & tolerates close grazing?","answer":"Kentucky bluegrass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3849 medium HIH740-8","question":"What is a disadvantage to using orchard grass in a pasture?","answer":"Doesn't tolerate poor drainage, marginal winter hardiness, competes with legumes, can be bunchy in growth"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3850 medium HIH415-8","question":"What is the biggest danger associated with blister beetles?","answer":"Secrete a toxic chemical (cantharidin) which can cause death if eaten, even if they're dried"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3851 medium FCH, p. 69","question":"Which type of forage should be ideally harvested no later than the ï¿½bootï¿½ state?","answer":"Grass - specifically timothy
."},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3852 medium FCH391","question":"What is an oat groat?","answer":"Oat with the hull removed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3853 medium TH258","question":"What is trace mineralized salt?","answer":"Salt that contains trace minerals"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3854 medium TH275","question":"What general type of pasture plants provides the greatest total amount of nutrients & a longer grazing season?","answer":"Mixture of grasses & legumes"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3855 medium FCH392","question":"An animal that's nutritionally unthrifty & who requires more feed than others in a similar situation is called what?","answer":"Hard keeper"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3856 medium DET54","question":"What is cellulose?","answer":"Plant fiber (complex carbohydrate in the cell walls of plants)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3857 medium HIH710-1","question":"What is dry matter?","answer":"What's left in a feed after the water has been removed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3858 medium HIH741-2","question":"Give a reason why grass clippings and/or garden refuse are not recommended for feeding horses.","answer":"Garden refuse - many plants are potentially lethal to horses
Lawn clippings - ferment easily in warm weather, may contain endophytes which might be toxic
(not necessary to give all)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3859 medium FCH186","question":"The amount fed should be adjusted as necessary to maintain what?","answer":"Optimal body weight or condition"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3860 medium FCH196/HIH740-1","question":"In order to decrease the risk of laminitis, colic, diarrhea & stable vices, forage should be what percent of the horse's diet?","answer":"50 - 70% 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3861 medium FCH393","question":"What is the common name for the outer covering of grains?","answer":"Hulls"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3862 medium FCH388","question":"What is an easy keeper?","answer":"Animal that doesn't need as much feed as others under similar conditions"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3863 medium ES107","question":"You do the mathï¿½If a lactating broodmare should be fed 3% of her body weight in total feed each day, how much total feed should a mare that weighs 900 pounds receive in a day?","answer":"27 pounds of total feed intake"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3864 medium FCH152/TH218","question":"What is considered to be the most common form of malnutrition in horses in the US?","answer":"Obesity"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3865 medium HIH741-1","question":"What is a disadvantage of feeding hay cubes?","answer":"Potential for horse to chew wood if no long stem forage also fed OR potential for choke if cubes are fed dry"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3866 medium HIH745-1","question":"What is required for all commercial feed products & is used as a method of communication between feed manufacturer & customer?","answer":"Labeling"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3867 medium HIH740-4","question":"What species of pasture grass contains a fungal endophyte that can cause problems in horses - especially pregnant mares?","answer":"Tall fescue"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3868 medium TH253","question":"What are 2 main reasons molasses is used in feeds?","answer":"Settles dust, increases palatability"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3869 medium FCH391","question":"Groats are grain kernels that have had what removed?","answer":"Hulls"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3870 medium HIH975-5","question":"When do foals usually show an interest in eating grain?","answer":"As early as 2 weeks old"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3871 medium HIH745-4","question":"Name something that must be in a prominent location on the tag of a medicated feed.","answer":"Caution statement, active drug ingredient(s), feed ingredients, detailed use description
(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3872 medium HIH740-7","question":"The visual appraisal of hay is more than just sight or looking at it - what are the other 2 components?","answer":"Feel & smell"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3873 medium HIH740-7","question":"How is plant maturity of grass hay visually determined?","answer":"By the amount of seed heads of grasses present at time of harvest"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3874 medium HIH735-1","question":"2 part question:  How should concentrate feeds be measured & give an example why.","answer":"Measure by weight (not volume);	 concentrates weigh different amounts - (ex -a coffee can of oats will weigh less than a coffee can of corn)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3875 medium FCH331","question":"At what stage are red maple leaves toxic to horses?","answer":"Wilted or dried"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3876 medium HIH740-9","question":"Timothy is useful when planted in pastures for rotational grazing.  How long should timothy pastures rest before re-grazing?","answer":"3 weeks"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3919 medium HIH740-4","question":"2 part question:  Give one advantage & one disadvantage for timothy in pastures.","answer":"Advantage - very palatable, winter hardy, late maturing (good quality forage for a longer time)
Disadvantage - uneven yield, slow re-growth, poor heat/drought tolerant, can develop cereal rust mites in some areas"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3920 medium FCH92","question":"Which weighs less - a quart of pellets or a quart of extruded feed?","answer":"Extruded feed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3921 medium TH209/FCH318","question":"At what time of the year is Yellow Star Thistle a concern when ingested by horses?","answer":"Late summer to early fall	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3922 medium ES107","question":"Grain, or concentrate, should not account for more than what percent of a horseï¿½s total diet?","answer":"Not more than 40 percent"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3923 medium HIH740-4","question":"2 part question:  Give one advantage & one disadvantage for using orchard grass in pastures.","answer":"Advantage - leafy, rapid re-growth, good early/late season growth
Disadvantage - marginal winter hardiness, very bunchy in growth habits"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3924 medium TH272","question":"What causes hay belly?","answer":"Horse eating more hay - extra bulk distends the intestinal tract"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3925 medium HIH741-1","question":"How many pounds of hay cubes can be fed to horses per day?","answer":"Up to 15 pounds"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3926 medium FCH149","question":"If the hayrack is too high for the horse eating from it, what are 2 problems that may occur?","answer":"Hay gets into horse's eyes, increased dust inhalation, respiratory problems"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3927 medium DET22/FCH385","question":"What is the term for a ration that supplies the proper amounts of all nutrients needed by the animal?","answer":"Balanced ration     (also accept complete feed)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3928 medium FCH301","question":"Foxtail barley is not toxic, yet is harmful to horses.  Why?","answer":"The awns can become imbedded in the mucous membranes of the mouth & cause ulcers"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3929 medium HIH740-4","question":"What height should pearl millet or browntop millet be for letting horses begin to graze it?","answer":"20 - 24 inches	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3930 medium TH115","question":"What is a hay probe?","answer":"Instrument used for taking samples of hay for nutrient analysis"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3931 medium BEG113-1","question":"How can storing "heavy" bales of hay be a cause of fires?","answer":"Dampness or mold in heavy bales can cause hot spots that can lead to spontaneous combustion"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3932 medium FCH385","question":"A complete feed contains all of the nutrients needed by the horse except for what 2?","answer":"Water & salt"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3933 medium FCH323","question":"What is the most common symptom of black walnut poisoning?","answer":"Laminitis or founder"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3934 medium FCH114","question":"What is the instrument called that's used to take hay samples for nutrient content analysis?","answer":"Hay probe	"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3935 medium FCH192","question":"You are feeding your barrel horse 10 pounds of grain a day.  How many pounds of hay would you need to feed per day?","answer":"At least 10 pounds"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3936 medium HIH710-5 old","question":"In feeding management, what is the wicking effect?","answer":"Uptake of moisture from ground into a bale of hay"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3937 medium HIH450-3","question":"Which type of hay should not be fed to horses with kidney problems?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3938 medium DET174","question":"A ration designed to keep the horse in the same physical condition - not allowing weight gain or loss - is called what?","answer":"Maintenance Ration"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3939 medium TH201/FCH75","question":"What should be done to help digestion of grains by foals & horses with bad teeth?","answer":"Feed cracked, crimped, rolled, soaked, steamed or extruded grains  	  (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3940 medium FCH226","question":"Name 2 types of salt blocks available for horses.","answer":"Plain, trace mineralized, iodized, added selenium, rock salt"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3941 medium FCH365/DET46","question":"The poison cantharidin is a highly irritating substance that produces inflammation & blistering within hours of contact.  What common pest of alfalfa is this toxin found in?","answer":"Blister beetle"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3942 medium FCH354","question":"Fescue poisoning affects pregnant mares in the late stages of gestation.  What is the best & easiest way to rapidly relieve the effects of fescue toxicosis?","answer":"Remove mare from infected fescue pasture or access to infected hay"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3943 medium HIH450-3","question":"Why is eating grain less effective than eating hay for keeping a horse warm in winter?","answer":""},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3944 medium HIH741-2","question":"Name 2 by-product feeds that can be added to a horse's ration as a source of additional fiber.","answer":"Beet pulp, wheat bran, brewer's dried grains, rice bran"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3945 medium FCH371","question":"Which of the following cereal grains fed to horses is the highest in crude fiber - barley, corn, oats or wheat?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3946 medium HIH710-2","question":"What does hyper-hydration mean?","answer":"Excess water consumption"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3947 medium HIH710-1","question":"How can you reduce the likelihood of blister beetle infestation in hay you purchase?","answer":"Only buy hay from known sources OR first/early season cuttings are seldom infested       (accept either)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3948 medium HIH741-2","question":"What is the only advantage of hay pellets over hay?","answer":"You get a consistent product"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3949 medium HIH741-2","question":"What is a disadvantage of feeding hay pellets?","answer":"Potential for choke OR horse might chew wood because he didn't get enough "chew time"	"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3950 medium HIH741-2","question":"What is typically used as a fat supplement, but is also a fair source of fiber?","answer":"Rice bran"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3951 medium HIH740-6","question":"Why can the weather be an important factor in hay prices?","answer":"If there's harsh winter or summer drought, fresh forage will be in short supply or unavailable so hay will be in high demand (also accept rain after cutting/before baling will ruin cutting & lead to short supply/higher prices)		Accept any reasonable answer"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3952 medium HIH740-6","question":"The horse is an animal that developed grazing on grasslands.  Its digestive tract was therefore designed to do what?","answer":"Handle frequent, small feedings of forage"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3953 medium HIH735-2/FCH105-6","question":"How long should you rest a pasture?","answer":"10 - 60 days    (accept any number within this range)    OR   until grass grows to at least 3 inches high"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3954 medium HIH740-4","question":"How soon after planting pearl millet in warm soil should it be ready for grazing?","answer":"30 - 40 days		 (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3955 medium HIH740-2,3","question":"If this type of forage is mold-infested, it can cause problems such as photosensitivity or slobbering - what is it?","answer":"Clover"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3956 medium HIH740-2","question":"Why is pure alfalfa hay & pasture not recommended for most horses?","answer":"Usually contains more protein than most horses require"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3957 medium HIH740-2","question":"Which type of clover has low productivity, but it's commonly found in pre-packaged pasture mixes?","answer":"White clover"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3958 medium HIH740-3","question":"What is a biennial plant?","answer":"One that lasts for 2 years"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3959 medium HIH740-4","question":"Name a warm season grass that frequently invades Bermuda grass & tall fescue pastures.  It also invades lawns.","answer":"Crabgrass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3960 medium HIH740-4","question":"What is the warm-season perennial sod-forming grass that's grown for both pasture & hay?","answer":"Bermuda grass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3961 medium HIH740-4","question":"Although crabgrass is generally thought of as a nuisance, it produces extremely palatable, high quality forage & is generally preferred by horses over what?","answer":"Other perennial grasses"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3962 medium HIH740-4","question":"Why should you not use crabgrass as the primary species in planting your pasture?","answer":"It's highly dependent on rainfall"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3963 medium HIH740-4","question":"Give an advantage to growing crabgrass in pastures with tall fescue.","answer":"Summer production is highest at time when fescue growth has slowed OR dilutes toxins present in endophyte infected tall fescue"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3964 medium FCH331","question":"2 part question:  There is a red maple tree on your neighborï¿½s property next to your fence line.  You discovered your horse eating green leaves off the branches that are within the horses reach.  What effect would you expect from the horse eating the red maple leaves & why?                    ","answer":"None ï¿½ Red maple leaves are not toxic when fresh 	(leaves are toxic when wilted or dried)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3965 medium FCH303","question":"What is the main symptom observed after ingestion of pokeweed?","answer":"Diarrhea          "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3966 medium HIH785-3","question":"Based on research studies for initial re-feeding of the starved horse, the best approach is feeding what type of feed?","answer":"High quality alfalfa hay    (frequent small amounts)               "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3967 medium HIH745-1","question":"What is the primary benefit of extruded feed?","answer":"Improved digestibility              "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"medium","number":"3968 medium HIH765-2","question":"You do the mathï¿½..You are feeding a weanling that weighs approximately 400 pounds.  If you are feeding twice a day & need to feed a total of 1% of the body weight, how many pounds would you feed for the morning feeding?","answer":"2 pounds                  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3969 hard CAHA69/FCH275 HIH975-6","question":"Orphan foals have a very high dietary energy requirement and should be fed how often during the first 1 ï¿½ 2 weeks of life?","answer":"Every 2 to 4 hours		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3971 hard FCH318","question":"What is the main symptom of the poisoning that occurs when horses eat Yellow Star Thistle or Russian Knapweed?","answer":"Inability to take in & chew food"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3974 hard FCH320","question":"Why do lactating mares have the best chance of survival after ingesting the poisonous plant White Snakeroot?","answer":"The toxin is excreted from the body by lactation"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3975 hard HS31","question":"Commercially mixed feeds may contain what percent molasses?","answer":"15%"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3976 hard HIH740-9","question":"Why is Teff safe to feed to horses with metabolic or digestive disorders?","answer":"It's low in carbohydrates or sugars"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3977 hard HIH740-10","question":"Perennial peanut hay is a good substitute for what other legume in tropical regions?","answer":"Alfalfa"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3978 hard HIH740-6","question":"Give 2 reasons for spraying preservatives such as mold inhibitors or propionic acid on forage as its cut","answer":"Reduces bacterial & fungal growth, allows farmer to bale at higher moisture content"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3979 hard HIH740-5","question":"When making hay, what is the main objective?","answer":"Preserve the nutrient & energy content of the growing forages"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3980 hard HIH741-1","question":"Hay cubes have the same nutritional value as hay, but are more consistent in what?","answer":"Quality"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3981 hard HIH740-3","question":"Name a warm season grass whose production is similar to that of sorghum & sorghum hybrids but without the cystitis or prussic acid problems.","answer":"Pearl millet or browntop millet"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3982 hard HIH740-3","question":"2 part question:  Name a warm-season grass that's generally safe to feed as hay, but that's NOT recommended for use in pastures & why.","answer":"Sorghum, Sudan grass or Johnson grass; they've been implicated in cases of cystitis/urinary tract infections & abortions, also may develop toxic levels of prussic acid (cyanide) 		(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3983 hard HIH740-2","question":"Birdsfoot trefoil is a low-growing legume perennial that's commonly used by highway departments for what purpose?","answer":"Roadside seeding OR erosion control"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3984 hard HIH740-2","question":"Which legume is more expensive than others & is also difficult to establish?","answer":"Birdsfoot trefoil"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3985 hard HIH740-1","question":"Referring to feeds, what does the term "tillering" mean?","answer":"Plants in early stages of growth"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3986 hard HIH755-2","question":"Athletic horses who are already producing heat through exercise can find it challenging to get rid of the extra heat produced by digesting a high carbohydrate diet.  What type of diet can make it easier for the horse to cool itself?","answer":"Feeding fat instead of grain OR high fat diet"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3987 hard FCH347","question":"The molds Penicillum, Aspergillus & Fusarium are responsible for most mycotoxin production.  They are found sporadically in both harvested & unharvested feeds.  What is the most significant environmental factor in determining whether the molds will grow & produce mycotoxins?","answer":"Moisture"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3988 hard FCH303","question":"Tannic acid is produced by what plant?","answer":"Oak"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3989 hard FCH68","question":"As forages mature & the percentage of lignin & structural carbohydrates increases, what happens to the digestibility of the forage?","answer":"Decreases"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3990 hard ADV337-2L","question":"2 part question:  Hay should be baled at a maximum moisture content of 15%   Give one reason why moisture content above this level & one reason why moisture content below this level could reduce the quality of the baled hay.","answer":"Above - potential for mold, increased heat production (decreases protein levels); 
Below - leaves will be lost during baling and/or storage (decreases nutritional value & palatability)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3991 hard HIH741-3","question":"What grain is being described?  It's the second most palatable grain for horses.  It's low in fiber & provides twice as much digestible energy through its starch content.","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3992 hard INT202-1","question":"What does a legume contain that allows it to produce higher levels of energy & protein than grasses?","answer":"Bacteria               (addtl info - found in root nodules)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3993 hard ADV301-1L","question":"What is the term for forage that's been fermented & stored in anaerobic conditions?","answer":"Silage or haylage  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3994 hard HS39","question":"What percent of dry roughage is dry matter?","answer":"90%"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3995 hard HIH741-2","question":"Which concentrate is the most expensive in terms of cost per unit of nutrients?","answer":"Oats"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3996 hard HIH741-3","question":"What concentrate has the alternate name of sorghum?","answer":"Milo"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3997 hard HIH740-6","question":"Hay must be less than what percent moisture before baling?","answer":"15%"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3998 hard FCH343","question":"What common ornamental evergreen shrub is very poisonous to horses if eaten?","answer":"Yew	       (also accept common yew OR Japanese yew)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"3999 hard ADV337-2L","question":"What is the most accurate method of assessing the nutrient makeup of hay?","answer":"Chemical analysis"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4000 hard TH284","question":"Fresh green pasture is what percent water?","answer":"Approximately 75%"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4001 hard HS41","question":"A horse would have to eat how many quarts of snow in the winter to equal drinking one quart of water?","answer":"12 quarts"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4002 hard TH256/FCH109","question":"What is the main symptom of a horse that has grazed red clover that's affected with the mold commonly known as "black patch"?","answer":"Excessive salivation or slobbering"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4003 hard ADV337-2L","question":"What is meant by the term forage quality?","answer":"Characteristics affecting the consumption & nutrition quality"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4004 hard ADV337-2L","question":"For each 1% increase in the amount of lignin present in hay, how much does the digestibility decrease?","answer":"3-4%	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4005 hard HIH740-1","question":"In general, how much feed should a horse consume per day?","answer":"1-1/2 to 3% of his body weight	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4006 hard HIH415-8","question":"What is the toxin produced by blister beetles?","answer":"Cantharidin"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4007 hard TH310","question":"Horses that eat the leaves of wild cherry trees can get what kind of poisoning?","answer":"Cyanide poisoning"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4009 hard FCH346","question":"What is the most common group of toxins that result in feed related poisoning?","answer":"Mycotoxins                           "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4010 hard FCH196","question":"2 part question:  Name a type of diet beneficial for highly competitive horse activities & name a diet that's detrimental to them","answer":"Beneficial - high fat; 	Detrimental - high protein"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4011 hard HIH741-3","question":"Name a reason why wheat isn't generally fed to horses.","answer":"High cost, small/hard kernels must be processed to be digested, low palatability 	(accept any)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4012 hard HIH740-4","question":"Rye grain is high in protein but is typically not fed to 	horses for what reason?","answer":"Poor palatability        "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4013 hard TH256","question":"Good quality silage is a suitable replacement for how much hay or pasture?","answer":"1/3 to ï¿½ 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4014 hard HIH760-5","question":"When comparing the nutrient value of timothy & orchard grass in a hay sample, which grass provides the highest percent of crude protein?","answer":"Orchard grass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4015 hard TH254","question":"What feed has more digestible energy than hay & more bulk than grain?","answer":"Beet pulp"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4016 hard TH254","question":"Why can't hay supply all the energy needs of a hard-working horse?","answer":"Energy concentration of hay is lower than that of grain OR horse can't eat enough hay to meet the increased energy needs"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4017 hard TH254","question":"What happens to the lignin content as hay matures?","answer":"It increases"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4018 hard TH276","question":"What is the biggest potential problem with tall fescue as pasture?","answer":"Some contain endophytes that can cause prolonged gestation, abortion, decreased milk production, weak foals    	 (do not need to give all)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4019 hard FCH68,69","question":"How is the plant maturity of legume hay visually determined?","answer":"By the amount of flowers present at time of harvest"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4020 hard FCH67","question":"Hay that's been mowed, then rained on, can lose what percent of its nutritional value?","answer":"40 - 50% 	(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4021 hard FCH352","question":"Aimless wandering, circling, & apparent blindness caused by locoweed or moldy corn disease is called what?","answer":"Blind staggers"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4022 hard FCH361","question":"Why should you NOT feed cattle or poultry feed to horses?","answer":"Some of the antibiotics commonly added to these can poison the horse"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4023 hard FCH365","question":"Horses affected by blister beetle poisoning commonly die or recover within what time period?","answer":"1 - 5 days		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4024 hard FCH317,329","question":"What causes blind staggers?","answer":"Moldy corn, locoweed, or selenium poisoning 	(only need to give one answer)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4025 hard FCH69, HIH780-3","question":"What is the ideal percentage for the moisture content of hay when it is baled?","answer":"15-20%"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4026 hard HIH745-3","question":"What do the letters CF stand for?","answer":"Crude fiber"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4027 hard INT202-2L","question":"Grains are processed in many ways.  What benefit does steam rolling have over dry rolling?","answer":"Lessens amount of dust in the grain"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4028 hard HIH741-2","question":"Although wheat bran is a good source of fiber, why should it NOT be fed in large quantities or for prolonged time periods?","answer":"It's extremely high in phosphorus & could cause calcium/phosphorus imbalances"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4029 hard HIH741-2","question":"When feeding wheat bran as a supplement, how much can be fed per day?","answer":"1 pound "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4030 hard HIH745-4","question":"What cattle feed additive is extremely toxic to horses?","answer":"Those that contain ionophores/monesin or growth hormones	 (also accept Rumensin)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4031 hard DET80","question":"What is dicoumarin?","answer":"Toxin found in moldy clover (can cause clotting problems)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4032 hard HS39/HIH799","question":"What is the dry matter content of silage?","answer":"20 - 50%	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4033 hard ADV337-3L","question":"You have just purchased a truckload of grass hay & would like to have it tested for nutrient analysis.  Explain how you would go about obtaining a sample for analysis","answer":"Use a hay probe & take a sample from at least 20 bales.  Mix them thoroughly together & send 1 quart of the mixed hay to the lab"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4034 hard FCH68-69","question":"At what stage of growth is hay most easily digested by the horse?","answer":"Boot stage OR pre-bloom stage (immature hay) OR when seed heads begin to appear  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4035 hard HS39/TH286-92","question":"What is the dry matter content of pasture?","answer":"20 - 30%		 (accept any number with in this range)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4036 hard FCH94","question":"Why would you mix chaff or chopped hay with grain?","answer":"To discourage horse from bolting feed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4037 hard HIH741-2","question":"What is a common type of bran that's fed in North America?","answer":"Rice bran or wheat bran"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4038 hard FCH95","question":"2 part question:  Explain the difference between straw & cereal grain forage & what each is used for.","answer":"Straw - what's left of the plant after the seed heads have been removed - used as bedding; cereal grain - plants such as oats that've been harvested with the seeds still attached -- used as hay"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4039 hard FCH343","question":"Water hemlock contains one of the most poisonous compounds known.  What is this compound?","answer":"Cicutoxin"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4040 hard FCH361","question":"2 part question:  What is Rumensin & how is it associated with horses?","answer":"Feed additive used to increase feed efficiency/weight gain in cattle; should NOT be fed to horses as it's highly toxic"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4041 hard FCH361-62/DET36","question":"What is the name for a type of food poisoning that can be caused by hay or silage contaminated by a   Clostridium bacteria?   ","answer":"Botulism"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4042 hard FCH303","question":"Acorns produce what plant toxin?","answer":"Tannic acid"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4043 hard FCH321/HIH740-3","question":"Name one of the two poisons that are found in Johnson & Sudan grasses.","answer":"Cyanide (prussic acid) & nitrates"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4044 hard FCH306","question":"What perennial weed has five bright yellow petals & 5 green sepals & may cause diarrhea or colic if ingested by the horse?","answer":"St. John's Wort"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4045 hard FCH365","question":"2 part question:  Blister beetle poisoning is more common when horses consume what type of hay & why?","answer":"Alfalfa or clover hay; the beetles are crushed during the hay making process & remain in the baled hay"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4046 hard FCH352","question":"Fescue poisoning affects which 2 types of horses?","answer":"Mares during last months of pregnancy & growing foals"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4047 hard HIH740-9","question":"What is a summer annual grass that originated in Ethopia where it's used primarily as a cereal crop?","answer":"Teff "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4048 hard HIH735-2","question":"How does the relative humidity affect length of grazing time?","answer":"Higher humidity results in longer grazing time                  "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4049 hard FCH391","question":"When looking at the feed tag for the concentrate you are currently feeding you notice the abbreviation GRAS.  What does GRAS indicate?                ","answer":"Generally Recognized as Safe (safe for animal consumption)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4050 hard FCH334","question":"What type of sudden death poisoning would be the result of ingestion of water hemlock?","answer":"Alkaloid sudden death       "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4051 hard TH334     ","question":"Plant poisoning from consumption of milkweed would be treated as what type of sudden death poisoning?","answer":"Cardiac sudden death                "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"hard","number":"4052 hard FCH309","question":"Poisonous plants that are classified as hepatotoxic primarily affect which organ?","answer":"Liver                 "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4053 bonus HIH740-8","question":"Virtually all feed has some mold spores, but presence of excessive mold can cause several problems if inhaled.  Name 3 of these problems.","answer":"Coughing, heaves, allergic reactions"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4054 bonus FCH 64, 192, 214, 286, 365","question":"(Bonus) Identify 3 considerations and/or potential hazards associated with feeding alfalfa pasture or hay.","answer":"Blister beetles			Mycotoxins	 
Use with caution in older horses,
Use with caution in horses with decreased kidney  or liver function  (alfalfa contains higher amounts of protein and calcium),
Use with caution in horses with equine metabolic disease or insulin resistance
Potential for DOD (Developmental Orthopedic Diseases) due to the imbalance of calcium & phosphorus &
increased amount of protein resulting in rapid growth,
More likely to be dusty or moldy (respiratory problems),
Colic (if excessive consumption of lush green alfalfa),
Increased incidence of tying-up (due to increased calcium)
Increased incidence of synchronous diaphragmatic flutter (thumps)  (due to increased calcium),
Need to balance calcium: phosphorus ratio"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4055 bonus HIH740-6","question":"Name 3 things to consider when storing hay.","answer":"Store off the ground so ground moisture won't spoil bottom bale, allow for air circulation, protect from sunlight, protect from moisture/rain, protect from vermin"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4056 bonus HIH740-5 - 7","question":"What are the 3 basic steps in making hay?","answer":"Harvesting/cutting, preserving/baling, storage"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4057 bonus HIH740-5","question":"Name 3 factors that influence when to cut hay.","answer":"Weather conditions, labor availability, equipment availability, if cut too early or too late, plants may not re-grow well for next cutting"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4058 bonus HIH740-3","question":"Name 3 warm season grasses that are NOT recommended for pastures.","answer":"Sorghum, Sudan grass, Johnson grass, Sorghum/Sudan hybrids"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4059 bonus HIH740-2","question":"Name 3 things that mold infested red clover can cause.","answer":"Slobbers, sunburn, photosensitivity"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4060 bonus HIH745-5","question":"For each of the following pairs, tell which grazes longer per day on average according to the Horse Industry Handbook:  a - stallions or mares, b - Thoroughbreds or Arabians, c - Individuals or herds","answer":"a - Mares       b - Arabians       c- Herds"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4061 bonus FCH301","question":"Name 3 plants that induce excessive salivation in the horse.","answer":"Red clover, azalea, bristle grass, buttercup, death camas, foxtail/bearded barley, awns from wheat/rye, laurel, poison hemlock, Russian thistle, water hemlock, white snakeroot, yellow star thistle"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4062 bonus FCH334","question":"Name 3 poisonous plants that can cause sudden death in the horse.","answer":"Larkspur, yew, hemlock, arrow grass, dog bane/Indian hemp, goose grass, oleander, Sudan grass, chokecherry, elderberry, lily of the valley, pod grass, water hemlock, death camas, foxglove, Johnson grass, milkweed, serviceberry, wild blue flax	(accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4063 bonus FCH66","question":"Give 3 ways hay can be fed to horses other than loose or from bales.","answer":"Cubes, pellets, chopped, silage, compressed, wafers"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4064 bonus HIH741, 710 old","question":"Name 3 things that cause horses to chew bark off trees.","answer":"Boredom, lack of chew time, changes in weather, taste of bark of certain trees"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4065 bonus FCH301","question":"Name 2 measures which can be taken to help prevent plant poisoning in your horse.","answer":"Proper pasture management, feed clean hay, don't feed garden prunings/waste, don't enclose horses close to toxic plants, be able to recognize toxic plants"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4066 bonus BEG102","question":"Name 3 ways corn can be fed to horses.","answer":"Cracked, shelled, ground, rolled, crimped, whole, ear/on cob"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4067 bonus HIH750 old","question":"Name 3 ways that hay can be processed.","answer":"Small rectangular bales, big round bales, big rectangular bales, hay cubes, pellets, chopped, silage, compressed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4068 bonus HIH760 old, 741/FCH76","question":"Give 3 ways grain is processed.","answer":"Grinding, roasting, crimping, dry rolling, cracking, steaming, extruded, popping, pelleting"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4069 bonus HIH740-8,735-3","question":"Give 3 advantages of a grass-legume pasture.","answer":"Increased productivity (mature at different times), increased nutritional value of forage, pure alfalfa pasture often too rich/has too much protein, horses prefer mixed types of grass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4070 bonus ADV337-2L","question":"Name 3 things that can happen when hay is baled with a moisture level of 30%.","answer":"Hay will become moldy, hay will heat up, will lose vitamins, decreased protein digestibility, spontaneous combustion"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4071 bonus HIH740","question":"2 part question:  Grass hays can be divided into 2 types.  What are the types & name 2 examples of each?","answer":"Warm season - Bahia grass, Bermuda grass, Teff, Prairie grass
Cool season - Orchard grass, Timothy, Tall Fescue, Smooth brome, Reed canary grass, Perennial ryegrass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4072 bonus HIH770-2 old","question":"Give 3 questions you might ask when trying to determine if nutrition is a cause of disease or poor performance.","answer":"How long has horse been on this feeding program?  Pasture or stall?  How many horses were affected?  Were toxic plants actually eaten?  Type of feed?  How much fed & when/frequency?  Other signs of disease?"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4073 bonus TH281/HIH745","question":"In addition to the general information, name 3 additional things included on medicated feed tags.","answer":"Caution statement, active drug ingredients, detailed use description"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4074 bonus HIH741","question":"Give 4 examples of by-product feeds.","answer":"Rice bran, wheat bran, brewer's grains, corn gluten, beet pulp, corn distiller's dried grains"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4075 bonus FCH91/HIH745","question":"What are 3 things listed on a feed tag?","answer":"Ingredients, manufacturer name/address, minimum crude protein, crude fat, maximum crude fiber, weight, brand, product name, use directions, caution statements, guaranteed analysis, "},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4076 bonus HIH741/FCH108","question":"Name 3 different varieties of clover that can be used in pastures or for HAY.","answer":"Red, alsike, sweet, white, ladino"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4078 bonus FCH ch 18","question":"What are 3 effects of ingesting poisonous plants?","answer":"Excessive salivation/slobbering, colic, diarrhea, photosensitivity, liver disease, neurologic disease, lameness, muscle weakness, anemia, sudden death, birth defects"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4079 bonus HIH740","question":"Name 3 conditions that can cause mold in feed.","answer":"Moisture, overheated/fermented feed, damaged/broken grain kernels, insect infestation, improper harvesting, improper packaging, improper storage"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4080 bonus FCH346-47","question":"What are 2 major feeds affected by mycotoxins?","answer":"Tall fescue, corn, peanuts, cottonseed, red clover"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4081 bonus TH295-96","question":"Name 3 factors - other than feeding too little - that result in thin horses.","answer":"Parasites, lactating mares, hard work, poor teeth, pecking order/too much competition for food, malabsorption, hot/humid weather, disease, starvation"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4082 bonus TH295","question":"Name 3 contributing factors that result in obese horses.","answer":"Fed extra because people enjoy feeding them, overfeeding to mask undesirable traits, increasing feed as soon as they know mare's pregnant, inadequate exercise, etc."},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4083 bonus HIH745-5","question":"Name 3 feeding guidelines.","answer":"Feed at regular times, feed balanced ration, don't feed moldy hay, keep mangers/hayracks clean, small/frequent feedings best, feed by weight - not volume, change feeds gradually, water available at all times, don't  overfeed, don't dilute balanced concentrate mix, salt available free choice, etc."},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4084 bonus TH280/HIH741","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of pelleted feed.","answer":"Increased cost, rapid rate of eating can lead to choke, if roughage not also fed can lead to bad habits like wood chewing"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4085 bonus TH280/HIH741","question":"What are 3 advantages of pelleted feeds?","answer":"Consistent product, decreased feed waste, less storage space, easier to transport, reduced dust, better feed efficiency, beneficial for horses with poor teeth"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4086 bonus TH309","question":"Name 3 poisonous plants.","answer":"Bracken fern, tansy ragwort, whitetop/whitehead, wild cherry, red maple, castor bean, fiddleneck fern, goldenweed, horsetail, yew/Japanese yew, jimsonweed, locoweed, oleander, prince's plume, rattleweed, Russian knapweed, wild onion, wild tobacco, woody aster, yellow star thistle, St. John's wort, hemlock/water hemlock, white snakeroot, black walnut,  larkspur, arrow grass, dog bane/Indian hemp, goose grass, sudan grass, chokecherry, elderberry, lily of the valley, pod grass, , death camas, foxglove, Johnson grass, milkweed, serviceberry, wild blue flax	(accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4088 bonus HIH745-5","question":"Name 3 things on which selection of feeds should be based.","answer":"Nutrient content, cost, availability, acceptability to horse, (purchase the most balanced diet that uses the most digestible ingredients & costs the least per unit) OR quality, suitability, availability, cost, convenience"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4089 bonus HIH741-3","question":"Name 3 of the 4 commercial feed classes.","answer":"Textured concentrates/sweet feed, processed concentrates/pellets or extruded feeds, complete feeds, supplements"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4090 bonus HIH740-6","question":"Many factors influence the supply & demand for hay & thus hay prices.  Name 2 supply factors & 2 demand factors","answer":"Supply - weather, species, preservation techniques, storage availability, fuel cost
Demand - number of horses in region, perceived value of certain forage species, demand from other livestock species, weather"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4091 bonus HIH740-7","question":"Name 4 qualities to look for when purchasing hay.","answer":"Leafiness, green color, no bad odor, no dust, no weeds, no blister beetles, not rained on, no mold, etc"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4092 bonus HIH741","question":"Name 4 of the most energy-rich grains.","answer":"Oats, corn, barley, milo/sorghum"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4093 bonus HS9","question":"What are the 3 general types of feed?","answer":"Roughage/forage, concentrates, mixed feeds"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4094 bonus FCH348","question":"Name 3 health problems caused by mycotoxins.","answer":"Feed refusal, reproductive problems, immune system suppression"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4095 bonus HIH740","question":"Name 3 types of grass HAY.","answer":"Orchard grass, timothy, smooth brome, Bermuda, prairie, teff, reed canary, bahia, tall fescue, perennial ryegrass"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4096 bonus HIH740","question":"Name 3 types of legume HAY","answer":"Alfalfa, birdsfoot trefoil, red clover, white clover, perennial peanut"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4097 bonus HIH740","question":"Name 3 types of cereal grain HAY.","answer":"Oat, beardless wheat, barley"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4098 bonus HIH740","question":"Name 3 legumes commonly used in PASTURES.","answer":"Alfalfa, birdsfoot trefoil, red clover, white clover,alsike clover, sweet clover"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4099 bonus HIH740","question":"Name 3 grasses commonly used in PASTURES.","answer":"Orchard grass, timothy, perennial ryegrass, annual ryegrass, tall fescue, reed canary, Kentucky bluegrass, smooth brome, bahia, Bermuda, crabgrass, pearl millet, browntop millet"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4100 bonus HS36","question":"Give 3 examples of roughages.","answer":"Pasture, hay, silage, by-product feeds, straw"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4101 bonus HIH740-7/ADV337","question":"Name 3 factors affecting the quality of hay.","answer":"Type (grass or legume), species, stage of maturity when cut, leafiness, weather conditions, harvest conditions, curing procedures, storage conditions, presence of weeds, presence of pests, presence of dust, presence of mold, etc"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4102 bonus TH255-56","question":"Grasses & legumes have differing nutrient contents.  Name 2 things that each type is generally higher in","answer":"Grass - higher in fiber & dry matter
Legumes - higher in protein, energy, vitamins, minerals"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4103 bonus HS38","question":"What are 3 possible causes for the lack of a sweet or pleasant smell in hay?","answer":"Over maturity, bleaching, old hay, mold, leaching"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4104 bonus HIHvarious","question":"Give 3 examples of concentrates.","answer":"Grain, molasses, by-product feeds (rice bran/wheat bran), vitamin supplements, mineral supplements, protein supplements, energy supplements, fats"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4105 bonus FCH39","question":"Name 3 advantages of feeding oats to your horse.","answer":"Difficult to overfeed, less likely to cause founder, most palatable of grains, soft kernel so processing not necessary, stores better, less likely to have mold/mycotoxins, not considered a hot feed"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4106 bonus HIH735-2","question":"Name 3 things that influence grazing time for horses on pastures.","answer":"Age, gender, breed, grouping, time of day, season, environmental conditions (rain, wind, snow, temperature, humidity, etc.)"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4107 bonus FCH68","question":"Give 3 reasons why immature hay at the pre-bloom or boot stage is more desirable as horse feed than mature hay.","answer":"Most easily digested, highest leaf to stem ratio, highest nutrient value"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4108 bonus HIH740-10","question":"Give an advantage & a disadvantage of using red clover in pastures.","answer":"Advantage - highly nutritious, deep rooted, grows where alfalfa won't, easy to establish
Disadvantage - biennial/only grows 2 years, can cause photosensitivity, can cause slobbering"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"4109 bonus FCH336-37","question":"Other than death, give 3 symptoms of cyanide poisoning.","answer":"Cherry-red venous blood, rapid labored breathing, frothing at the mouth, dilated pupils, incoordination, muscle tremors, convulsions, dark red or cyanotic mucous membranes"},
{"category":"FEEDS & FEEDING","level":"bonus","number":"7151 bonus ADV337","question":"Name 2 methods of appraising forage quality.","answer":"Visual appraisal, chemical analysis"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4110 easy HIH505-7","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the LEAST amount of moisture?","answer":"The wall "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4111 easy HIH525-1","question":"What part of a horse's foot provides traction & absorbs shock?","answer":"Frog  "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4112 easy HIH540-2","question":"What is a quarter or sand crack?	","answer":"Crack in the side of the hoof wall "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4113 easy HIH455-3","question":"A darkened or moist area on the sole is usually an indication of what?","answer":"Puncture wound	 (also accept sole bruise OR abscess)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4114 easy HIH540-2","question":"Where is a foot abscess most common?","answer":"Sole OR white line	 (accept either) "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4116 easy ADV334-1L","question":"In reference to a horse's foot, where would you find a corn?","answer":"Heel area of sole"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4117 medium HIH540a","question":"A specific type of sole bruise occurring in the heel area is called what?","answer":"Corn"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4118 easy HIH540-1	","question":"A disease of the foot characterized by a pungent odor is called what?	","answer":"Thrush"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4119 medium HIH535-2","question":"Why should the clinches be cut or straightened before pulling off the shoe?","answer":"To prevent tearing or chipping the hoof wall"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4120 medium HIH525-1","question":"About how many times a year should your horse be trimmed or shod?","answer":"6 ï¿½ 12 	 (accept any number within range) "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4121 easy HIH420-3","question":"What is the best way to prevent snow & ice from accumulating in a horse's hooves during the winter?","answer":"Pull shoes & keep feet trimmed	 (also accept keep feet clean)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4122 easy TH728/HIH530-2","question":"What type of farrier's hammer is used for making & shaping shoes?","answer":"Rounding"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4123 medium INT231-2","question":"Aluminum horseshoes have the advantage over steel horseshoes of being lighter in weight, but have what disadvantage compared to a steel shoe?","answer":"Aluminum shoes wear faster"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4124 easy HIH530-1","question":"You reach into your toolbox looking for your hoof nippers & grab what looks like nippers, but they have knobs on the ends of the handles.  What tool to you have?","answer":"Pull offs/ shoe pullers "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4126 easy HIH515-4/HH49/TH732","question":"Name the type of keg shoe that is made of aluminum & is used on racehorses.  ","answer":"Plates or racing plates"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4127 easy HIH515-4/TH732","question":"Aluminum shoes are most commonly used in what equine sport?","answer":"Racing"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4128 easy HIH515-4/TH732","question":"Racing plates are generally made from what type of metal?","answer":"Aluminum"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4129 easy HIH505-6","question":"Hoof growth rate decreases as the animal's what increases?","answer":"Age"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4130 easy HIH515-2/TH737-38","question":"What type of shoe modification is used primarily to take the stress of the nail & stabilize the shoe?","answer":"Clips                       "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4131 easy HIH540-1","question":"What is thrush?	","answer":"Disease/infection  of the frog	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4132 easy HIH530-4","question":"What farrier tool is used to shape & make shoes on the anvil?","answer":"Rounding hammer or turning hammer"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4133 easy HIH525-1","question":"Exercising a horse will help keep his feet what?","answer":"Healthy"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4134 easy HIH515-2/TH737-38","question":"What are toe clips?","answer":"Metal projections on outside, front of shoe
(additional info ï¿½ they help hold the shoe on & take stress off the nails)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4135 easy HIH530-1/TH728","question":"Name the farrier's tool used to remove excess hoof wall.","answer":"Nippers"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4136 easy HIH515-3","question":"What kind of special shoes would be found on the hind feet of a horse in a reining competition?","answer":"Sliding plates or sliders"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4137 easy HIH515-3","question":"Sliding plate horseshoes will be found on the rear hooves of a horse performing in what kind of competition?","answer":"Reining"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4138 easy HIH525-3","question":"List one reason why you should work with your foal's feet.","answer":"Get him used to being handled while young, heï¿½s easier to control while young, he will grow up knowing he won't be hurt"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4139 easy HIH505-2","question":"What is the primary function of the sole?","answer":"Protection     (protects the coffin bone)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4140 easy TH742/HH49","question":"In reference to shoeing, what is meant by the term "re-set"?","answer":"When farrier uses the same set of shoes for a second time"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4141 easy HIH230-1","question":"A pincher-like instrument used to squeeze the hooves to find a sore spot is called what?","answer":"Hoof tester"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4142 easy HIH540-3","question":"What is the purpose of hoof testers?","answer":"To identify problems in the hoof"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4143 easy HIH515-5","question":"In horseshoeing, what are pads used for?","answer":"Protect the bottom of the foot"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4144 easy HH49/TH721","question":"When trimming the hooves of a pigeon toed horse, which half of the hoof do you trim more?","answer":"Inner half"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4145 easy HIH540-2","question":"Name one cause of a sand or quarter crack.","answer":"Uneven weight bearing, irregular hoof growth, wire cuts, excessive hoof length, dry conditions"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4146 easy HH49/TH721","question":"How would you trim a splayfooted horse?	","answer":"Trim more off the outer half of the hoof "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4147 easy INT231-2","question":"Caulks & studs are devices added to horseshoes for what purpose?","answer":"Traction"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4148 easy HIH505-1/HH49","question":"What is the basic purpose of horseshoes?	","answer":"Protect the feet from wear or damage"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4149 easy HH47/TH720","question":"When should hoof dressing be used?","answer":"When wall is dry, brittle, or cracked"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4150 easy HIH540-8/TH720","question":"Approximately how often should a horse's foot be trimmed?","answer":"Every 4-8 weeks	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4151 easy HIH505-8","question":"What in the horse's feet helps to maintain their flexibility?","answer":"Moisture"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4152 easy HIH530-1/HH36","question":"Give one reason for picking out a horse's foot.","answer":"Check for injuries or bruises, check for loose shoes, check for rocks, check for thrush"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4153 easy HIH525-2","question":"Referring to horseï¿½s feet, what does ï¿½picking outï¿½ mean?  ","answer":"Cleaning out a horseï¿½s hoof"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4154 easy HH36-37","question":"How do you pick up a front foot?","answer":"Stand beside shoulder, facing rear.  Run your hand down back of leg to just above fetlock. Grasp fetlock area & pick up foot	 (can pinch tendon or push shoulder away to help)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4155 easy HIH535-5","question":"Give one reason for shoeing your horse.","answer":"Protect hoof from excessive wear, provide traction, help correct stance or gait, correct faulty hoof structure or growth, protect hoof from corn/contraction/cracks/other abnormal conditions, ease pain of injured hoof"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4156 easy HH49","question":"Keeping the hoof moist & toe shortened will help correct which defect?","answer":"Quarter crack"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4157 easy HH49/TH20-22","question":"Name a common fault corrected by trimming.","answer":"Splay foot/toe out, pigeon toe/toe in, contracted heels, quarter crack, cocked ankle"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4158 easy HIH535-2","question":"2 part question:  When trimming a horse thatï¿½s going to be ridden on rocky ground and/or roads, what part of the foot should NOT be trimmed & why?","answer":"Sole;   because it protects the foot"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4159 easy HH47","question":"If the hoof is not trimmed & it grows too long, what will happen?","answer":"Hoof wall cracks, breaks off, or won't wear evenly (accept any)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4160 easy HIH505-4","question":"Where is the greatest point of wear on a horse's hoof?","answer":"Toe (breakover point)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4161 easy HIH525-3","question":"2 part question:  When holding a horse for the farrier, on which side should you stand & why?","answer":"Same side as farrier; if horse acts up, you can pull head toward you & horse's body will move away from farrier"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4162 easy HIH530-1","question":"What is one purpose of a horseshoer's leather apron?","answer":"Protects the shoer's legs from cuts, nails or tools, protects against heat when working at forge, provides barrier between horse & farrier for dirt, wet, etc., holds small tools"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4163 easy HIH530/TH728","question":"Which farrier tool is used to cut and/or raise clinches?","answer":"Clinch cutter"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4164 easy HIH530","question":"What are nippers used for?","answer":"Trim hoof            "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4166 easy HH49","question":"What 2 things will usually help correct a quarter crack?","answer":"Keep hoof moist & toe shortened  OR   File a groove or notch across the top of the crack (crack & filed groove will look like a ï¿½Tï¿½) 		(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4167 easy HIH505-6/CAHA25","question":"What is the average hoof growth rate per month?","answer":"3/8 inch OR 1/4 ï¿½ 1/2 inch		 (accept any number within this range -- also accept 0.5-1 cm)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4168 easy HH49/TH721","question":"By lowering the inside hoof wall, the farrier is correcting what problem?","answer":"Toe in or Pigeon toe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4169 easy HIH505-7","question":"What is nature's hoof conditioner?","answer":"Water"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4170 easy HIH525-3/HH48","question":"Careless trimming of a foal's feet can cause what?","answer":"Strained tendons or lameness"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4171 easy HIH505","question":"Why should you never rasp the walls of the hoof?","answer":"Removes the periople (outer varnish layer); can cause hoof to dry out	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4172 easy HIH540-1","question":"2 part question:  What part of the foot is most important to clean properly & why?","answer":"Deep depressions between bar & frog(commissures, sulci, or collateral grooves; most likely place for thrush to start OR area where rocks & debris get stuck"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4173 easy HIH1140-14","question":"When shoeing a horse during fly season, what can you use to make things more comfortable for your farrier & your horse?","answer":"Fly spray"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4174 easy HIH505-6","question":"Horse's hooves grow faster in what general temperature?","answer":"Warm"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4175 easy HIH505-6","question":"Which grows faster - the front hooves or the back hooves?","answer":"Front"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4176 easy HIH515","question":"When should the angle of the hoof be changed?","answer":"Only as a corrective measure"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4177 easy HIH530-4/TH727","question":"What is the farrier's workbench?","answer":"Anvil"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4178 easy HIH530-2/TH728","question":"What is one purpose of the farrier's driving hammer?	","answer":"Driving nails or finishing clinches 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4179 easy HIH515-1/TH722","question":"What portion of the hoof should never bear weight?","answer":"Sole"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4180 easy HH47","question":"How do you pick up a hind foot?","answer":"Stand to side facing tail.  Put hand on hindquarters & run down leg to fetlock.  Ask horse to pick up foot. Pinch tendon/fetlock to help. 		(accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4181 easy HH49/TH742","question":"What is the term for the type of shoeing job when the farrier uses the same set of shoes for a second time?","answer":"Re-set or re-shod"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4182 easy HH37","question":"The part of the horseshoe nail that's bent over after being nailed through the hoof is called what?","answer":"Clinch"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4183 easy HIH515-1,535-1","question":"Give 2 terms for the person who trims & applies shoes to horse's hooves?","answer":"Farrier, blacksmith, horseshoer/shoer"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4184 easy HIH505-6","question":"Horses hooves grow at different rates of speed.  Which hooves grow slower?","answer":"Hind"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4185 easy HIH530-3/TH745","question":"What is the name of the tool that farriers use to bend over the end of a horseshoe nail?","answer":"Clincher	"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4186 easy HIH540-2/ADV334-2","question":"2 part question:  Will the edges of a crack in the hoof wall grow back together (heal) if the hoof wall is supported & immobilized.  Explain why.","answer":"No; hoof wall must grow out to eliminate the crack"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4187 easy HIH505-1 HIH930-4","question":"Regarding horsesï¿½ feet, what is one of the best known quotations in the horse world?","answer":""No foot, no horse""},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4188 easy HIH505-1","question":"What is the foundation of a horse?","answer":"His feet"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4189 easy HIH515-1","question":"What is the first rule to remember in fitting a shoe to a horse's foot?","answer":"Shape the shoe to fit the foot"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4190 easy HIH515-1","question":"How many nail holes are there in most ready-made horseshoes?","answer":"8"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4191 easy HIH535","question":"A satisfactory trimming job can be accomplished with a hoof knife, nippers & what else?","answer":"Rasp"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4192 easy HIH505-4","question":"What part of the normal, ideal hoof supports the primary weight of the horse?","answer":"Hoof wall"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4193 easy HIH530-1","question":"What is the difference in use between nippers & pull-offs?","answer":"Nippers are used to trim the hoof & pull-offs are used to remove shoes"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4194 easy HIH530-1","question":"Nippers & pull-offs look similar.  Describe how you can quickly tell one from another?","answer":"Pull-offs have knobs on the end of the handles"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4195 easy HIH505-7","question":"What part of the horse's foot contains the GREATEST amount of moisture?","answer":"Frog  "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4196 easy TH727","question":"What can be added to a horseshoe to help hold the shoe in place?","answer":"Clips (toe clips, heel clips, or both)     (accept either general or specific)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4197 easy HS13","question":"When is the only time a horse will shift his weight to the other front foot?","answer":"When one foot is injured"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4198 easy DET142","question":"Why would you use a hoof boot for your horse? ","answer":"Replace a lost shoe, treat a foot by placing medication in boot, protect hoof from further injury, keep a hoof clean, traction"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4199 easy TH732","question":"What is the name for a variation of keg shoe that's shaped to fit a mule's foot?","answer":"Mule shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4200 easy TH719","question":"Why is hoof care one of the most important aspects of horsemanship?","answer":"If your horse is lame, you can't use him		"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4201 easy TH731","question":"What size shoe fits most average horses?","answer":"#1"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4202 easy TH740","question":"If the farrier holds the horse's feet too high, what is likely to happen?","answer":"Horse will be uncomfortable or try to jerk foot away"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4203 easy DET23","question":"Referring to horses, define the term "barefoot".","answer":"Unshod"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4204 easy TH150","question":"You are spending the day with a farrier.  The farrier has 4 shoes that look identical set aside for the horse he is shoeing.  He would like you to hand him a front shoe.  How will you know which is a front shoe?","answer":"Front shoe is more round     (also accept wider at the heel)          "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4205 easy HIH930-4","question":"Hoof growth is slower during which season?","answer":"Winter                   "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4206 easy HIH505-6","question":"What part of the horse's foot grows the fastest?","answer":"Toe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"easy","number":"4207 easy HIH540-2/DET68","question":"Name a common cause of corns in the horse.","answer":"Shoe too small, leaving shoe on too long, trimming heel too low"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4208 medium HIH540-1","question":"What is white line disease?","answer":"Infection in the white line that causes separation of the sole & wall (seedy toe)   "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4209 medium HS12","question":"What unsoundness may result from a dried out shrunken frog?","answer":"Contracted heels or navicular disease					"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4210 medium TH167","question":"A narrow, shrunken frog & heels that are pulled together are signs of what?","answer":"Contracted heels"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4212 medium TH722/DET142","question":"What does the farrier remove from the hoof when trimming the hoof with a hoof knife? ","answer":"Excess dead tissue from the horseï¿½s frog and sole "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4213 medium HIH515-3,525-4","question":"Half round shoes are most commonly used on what type of horse?","answer":"Harness racing horses, reining horses or occasionally foals	 (only need to give one answer)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4214 medium HIH505-5","question":"2 part question:  What is the shape of the sole & its purpose?","answer":"It's concave;   purpose is protection"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4215 medium DET45","question":"Where on a horseshoe would you find caulks?","answer":"On the ground surface of the shoe - usually at the heels and/or toes"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4216 medium HIH535-3","question":"Why do you trim the bars level with the sole?","answer":"So they won't be broken or torn on rocks, etc."},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4217 medium TH727","question":"What farrier tool is used for cutting hot metal? ","answer":"Hardy"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4218 medium TH696","question":"How many times a year is a frog naturally shed?","answer":"Two;    every 6 months"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4219 medium TH745","question":"What is the term used to describe when a nail is being driven too close to the white line.","answer":"Quicking"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4220 medium TH742","question":"What poor trimming practice may cause forging or over-reaching?","answer":"Leaving the toe too long"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4221 medium TH739","question":"What type of horseshoe nail is used to increase traction on icy surfaces?","answer":"Frosthead nail"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4222 medium ADV334-1 ","question":"Thrush is a black, strong smelling infection of the hoof that causes destruction of the frog. Is it caused by aerobic or anaerobic bacteria?","answer":"Anaerobic bacteria	 (Fusobacterium necrophorum)   Accept either general or specific answer"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4223 medium HIH535-2","question":"When removing a shoe, why should you pull down on the pullers instead of pulling them from side to side?","answer":"So you won't twist the foot or pull a tendon		"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4224 medium TH167","question":"Name a cause of contracted heels?","answer":"Improper trimming or shoeing, leaving shoes on too long, lack of frog pressure, lack of moisture in hoof, heredity, faulty conformation, uneven weight distribution"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4225 medium INT231-2","question":"2 part question -- Give one advantage & one disadvantage of aluminum shoes","answer":"Advantage ï¿½ lightweight		 disadvantage - wears out quicker than steel"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4226 medium HIH535-5","question":"What is the purpose of beveling on a horseshoe nail?","answer":"Directs the point of the nail to come out the side of the hoof wall instead of going straight into the hoof"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4227 medium HIH530-3","question":"What is the purpose of a hoof gauge?","answer":"Used to measure the hoof angle or toe length"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4228 medium HIH515-1","question":"What is corrective shoeing?","answer":"Shoeing to correct the stance or gait of a horse "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4229 medium HIH515-2","question":"What is therapeutic shoeing?","answer":"Shoeing to treat a medical condition of the foot or leg"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4230 medium HIH515-4","question":"What is the name for a removable traction device for horseshoes?","answer":"Studs 	(additional info -- they can be screwed or driven into shoe as needed & then removed)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4231 medium HIH540-1/ES183","question":"How can you treat thrush?","answer":"Clean out hoof, remove affected tissue, & treat with anti-thrush medication"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4232 medium TH727","question":"What is the purpose of a hardy?","answer":"Used by farrier to cut hot metal"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4233 medium TH727","question":"What farrier tool is used to make or enlarge nail holes in horseshoes?","answer":"Pritchel"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4234 medium TH731","question":"The kind & weight of shoes worn by horses depends on what?","answer":"Type of work the horse does"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4235 medium TH751","question":"What is a keg shoe?","answer":"Pre-sized, ready-made shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4236 medium TH745","question":"Horse shoe nails have a shank that is flat on one side and the other side is concave.  When driving a nail, the nail should be started with which side facing the outside of the hoof?","answer":"Flat side should be outside"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4237 medium TH738","question":"What alloy can be added to horseshoes to increase traction & life of the shoe?","answer":"Borium"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4238 medium TH734","question":"How does a mule shoe differ from a horse shoe?","answer":"Mule shoe is narrower"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4239 medium TH732","question":"You are the ring steward at a horse show.  An animal in the previous driving class lost a shoe.  You found it & notice that its size is triple zero.  What type of equine lost this shoe?","answer":"Pony OR horse with very small feet"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4240 medium CAHA39","question":"A base narrow horse will wear its feet unevenly.  What part of the foot needs to be rasped more in order to bring the foot level?","answer":"Inside wall"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4241 medium TH742","question":"What does an uneven wear pattern on a horseshoe indicate?","answer":"Foot is landing out of balance OR foot is breaking over at a point other than the toe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4242 medium HIH420-3","question":"Give 2 reasons for letting a horse go barefoot for a few months.","answer":"Increases circulation in foot, makes for healthier foot, in winter -helps keep snow/ice from accumulating in hooves"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4243 medium TH167","question":"What are contracted heels?","answer":"Heels of hoof are too close/upright for normal foot conformation    (frog may be shrunken)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4244 medium HIH505-6","question":"Where does the moisture come from that helps maintain flexibility & prevent cracking of the horse's feet?","answer":"Within the foot OR environment"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4245 medium HIH535-3/CAHA24","question":"What is the difference in shape between front & back feet?","answer":"Front feet are naturally flat.  Hind feet are naturally concave, narrower & more pointed"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4246 medium TH167","question":"What is the condition known as grease heel or scratches?","answer":"Inflammation/infection of the skin on the back of the heel or pastern"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4247 medium TH731","question":"Fullering, web & branch are parts of what?","answer":"Horseshoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4248 medium TH731","question":"The width & thickness of the metal in the horseshoe is called what?","answer":"Web"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4249 medium HIH535-4","question":"What are outward distortions of the hoof called?","answer":"Flares"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4250 medium HIH530-2","question":"What piece of equipment is used by a farrier to determine the angle of the hoof?","answer":"Hoof gauge"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4251 medium HIH515-2","question":"Why are clips used on horse shoes?","answer":"To take stress off the nails OR to stabilize the shoe on the foot"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4252 medium HIH455-4","question":"Why are quarter cracks more common than toe cracks?","answer":"Wall is thinner at the quarter"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4253 medium HIH515-4","question":"What type of horseshoe is commonly used on horses with laminitis to transfer weight from the wall of the hoof to the frog?","answer":"Heart Bar"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4254 medium FCH391","question":"What is the term used to describe a bacterial or fungal infection of the skin on the heel or back of the pastern?","answer":"Grease heel, scratches, or mud fever	 (only need to name one)       "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4255 medium DET160","question":"The most commonly used manufactured or preformed horseshoes are called what?","answer":"Keg shoes"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4256 medium ADV 334-2		","question":"An abscess of the hoof may open and drain on its own.  What simple treatment can you do to encourage the abscess to dry up and heal? ","answer":"Soak the foot (Epsom salts & warm water or iodine solution) OR pack the hoof (Animalintex, Ichthammol, etc.) "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4257 medium TH720","question":"How long does it take the hoof to grow out from the coronet to ground at the toe?","answer":"9 - 12 months	  (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4258 medium TH99","question":"What is a pritchel used for?","answer":"Make or enlarge nail holes in a horseshoe		(accept either)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4259 medium HIH530-2/TH728","question":"Which farrier's hammer is heavier, rounding or driving?","answer":"Rounding 
(addtl info - rounding hammer weighs 2-2 ï¿½ pounds; driving hammer weighs less than a pound)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4260 medium HIH515-4","question":"A heart bar shoe would be used temporarily to treat a hoof problem where you want to transfer weight from the hoof wall to what structure of the foot?","answer":"Frog"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4261 medium HIH530-3/TH745","question":"A clinch block can be used to turn the head of the nail to start the clinch.  If your horse objects to this procedure, what other tool could be used to turn the clinch?","answer":"Clinchers or clinching tongs"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4262 medium FCH402","question":"What is the name of the condition of the hoof when there is a separation of the sensitive & insensitive laminae at the white line in the toe area?","answer":"Seedy toe	(also accept white line disease)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4263 medium HIH535-1,525-3/TH720","question":"A normal, healthy mature horse without foot problems has its feet trimmed every 6 - 8 weeks.  How often should foals feet be trimmed?","answer":"Once a month, every 30 days, or every 4 weeks            (accept any)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4264 medium HIH525-3","question":"Why should one trim a young foal's feet often?","answer":"Regular foot balancing will allow growth to be as straight as possible"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4265 medium TH168/FCH402","question":"What is seedy toe?","answer":"Separation of the sole from the hoof wall near the toe       (additional info ï¿½ also called white line disease)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4266 medium HIH530-2","question":"Which farrier tool would be used to correct a flare?","answer":"Rasp                "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"medium","number":"4267 medium TH735","question":"What is the purpose of adding stickers or mud caulks to the heel of a racing plate?","answer":"To increase traction on muddy race track        (accept to increase traction)      "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4268 hard HIH515-5","question":"What type of horseshoes can be used on a horse that temporarily need shoe protection without damaging the foot with horseshoe nails? ","answer":"Glue-on shoes"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4269 hard INT231-2","question":"In race horses, why are traction devices such as toe grabs not being used by trainers as commonly as they used to be?","answer":"They produce too many injuries"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4270 hard HIH515-5","question":"When would you use a hospital plate on a shoe?","answer":"When foot is abscessed OR sole has injury
(additional info ï¿½ itï¿½s easy to remove & apply medication to foot bottom; also keeps out debris)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4272 hard TH746","question":"What is the position of a properly driven horseshoe nail?","answer":"Parallel to the tubules in the hoof wall"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4273 hard DET272","question":"Referring to horseshoes, what is a trailer?","answer":"Horseshoe heels that are extended 1/2 inch or more beyond the horse's heel      (addtl info ï¿½ hind feet)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4274 hard HIH515-4","question":"What metal alloy can be used for horseshoes that maintains the light weight of aluminum, but has the durability of steel","answer":"Titanium"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4275 hard TH731","question":"What happens if the branch of a shoe is too long?","answer":"If on front foot - hind foot may overreach& pull it off;    if on back foot - usually nothing happens"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4276 hard TH700","question":"What is the name for a type of shoe where the inside rim on the web is raised above the outside rim?","answer":"Polo shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4277 hard TH742","question":"When removing a shoe from a horse, describe how the pull-offs are used.","answer":"Put jaws of pull-offs under one heel of the shoe.  Close handles & pull down towards the toe & in towards the center of hoof.  Work pull-offs gradually towards the toe - first on one branch of the shoe, then on the other.  Continue till shoe works loose from foot."},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4278 hard TH737","question":"What distinguishes a polo shoe from a cowboy shoe?","answer":"Inside rim of the polo shoe is raised above the outside rim"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4279 hard HIH515-5","question":"What is the term for a specialized type of horseshoe pad that can be removed to treat or apply medicine to the hoof & then re-attached?","answer":"Hospital pad"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4280 hard INT231-3L","question":"What is the name of the type of shoe that's used to elevate the heels of a horse that's confined to stall rest?","answer":"Patten shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4281 hard HIH510-1","question":"Referring to horseshoeing, what is balance?","answer":"Equal weight distribution (additional info -- around the center of gravity on the horse's leg)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4282 hard HIH505-1","question":"How many years have horseshoes been protecting horse's feet?","answer":"More than 2000"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4284 hard HIH505-1","question":"Hoof size can depend on what 2 things?","answer":"Genetics & nutrition"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4285 hard TH237","question":"What characteristic of a polo shoe increases traction?","answer":"Inside edge is raised higher than the outside edge"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4286 hard HIH535-3","question":"How much should you trim the frog of a horse that's stabled?","answer":"Only enough to remove dead tissue "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4287 hard HIH505","question":"How do extremely wet conditions promote rapid drying of the horse's feet?","answer":"Constant contact with moisture can erode or remove natural oils/protective films from the horse's feet"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4288 hard HIH515","question":"Why should the horseshoe be slightly wider at the heels than at the quarters?","answer":"To accommodate the expansion of the heels when the foot bears weight"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4289 hard HIH505-4","question":"In referring to the hoof, what can happen if there isn't any frog pressure or contact with the ground?","answer":"Contracted heels may develop"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4290 hard HIH515-1","question":"How does the farrier choose the proper weight of shoe for the horse?","answer":"Generally, the lightest weight the horse can wear is best; heavier shoes are used on gaited horses to achieve higher action"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4291 hard FCH392","question":"What is the term for the condition where a horse's foot may become smaller at ground level than at the top of the foot?","answer":"Contracted heels"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4292 hard HIH535-4","question":"What causes the hoof wall to flare?","answer":"Unequal weight distribution"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4293 hard HIH530-2","question":"After a farrier's rasp has become too dull for rasping hooves, what can the farrier use it for?","answer":"As a clinching or finishing rasp"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4294 hard HIH515-4","question":"What is a fullered shoe?","answer":"One with a crease all the way around the shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4295 hard HIH515-4","question":"What is the purpose of an eggbar shoe?","answer":"Supports rear portion of hoof (used for navicular, under-run heels, etc.)               (accept any of these)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4296 hard HIH515-4","question":"In order to alleviate tension of the flexor tendons and/or reduce the risk of forging, what horseshoe feature is frequently used in conjunction with an eggbar shoe for horses with navicular disease?","answer":"Rocker toe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4297 hard HIH540-2","question":"What type shoe can you use to protect the foot while a corn is healing?","answer":"Bar shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4298 hard TH721","question":"Correction of a foal's hooves must begin when the foal is a few days old & must be completed before what happens?","answer":"Before growth plates close"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4299 hard TH227-29","question":"Which farrier tool is used to make a crease in hand-fullered shoes?","answer":"Fullering iron"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4300 hard TH732-36","question":"What is the approximate weight of a #1 shoe?","answer":"8 - 12 ounces	 (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4301 hard TH748","question":"What style of horseshoe can help correct the horse landing on either the outside or inside wall?","answer":"Square toe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4302 hard TH734","question":"How much does an aluminum racing plate weigh?","answer":"2 - 3 ounces 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4303 hard TH738","question":"A horseshoe nail has 2 sizes of head - regular & city head.  Which is smaller?","answer":"City head"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4304 hard TH750-51","question":"Name a reason your horse might wear a bar shoe.  ","answer":"Contracted heels, navicular disease, founder/laminitis, corn		(accept any)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4305 hard TH735","question":"In reference to horseshoes, explain the difference between a sticker & a block.","answer":"Both are heel caulks ï¿½ block is set lengthwise on heel; sticker is set so it goes across the foot"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4306 hard HIH530-1","question":"What are the 2 main parts of a clinch cutter?","answer":"Blade & point"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4307 hard TH739,745","question":"What is the name for the part of the horseshoe nail that prevents the nail from pulling through the shoe?","answer":"Head or nail head"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4308 hard DET53","question":"The Chadwick Spring provides constant outward pressure on the bars of the foot & would be used for what conformation defect of the hoof?","answer":"Contracted heels              "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4309 hard HIH510-1","question":"What are the 2 types of balance to consider when trimming the hoof?","answer":"Heel to toe (front to back) & medial/lateral (side to side)           "},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4310 hard DET270","question":"A thin protrusion of metal on the ground surface of the toe of a racing plate is known as what shoe alteration?","answer":"Toe grab  (toe grip)          accept either"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4311 hard HIH525-4","question":"Why would you choose to use a rocker-toe horse shoe for a healthy young horse?","answer":"A rocker-toe shoe eases the breakover of the hoof and to help prevent forging    	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"hard","number":"4312 hard TH737","question":"Identify one advantage of the raised inside rim on polo shoes.","answer":"Increases traction, prevents sliding, enables foot to roll over faster, allows horse to pivot on shoe, allows horse to maintain a toe grip regardless of where foot breaks over"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4313 bonus HIH515,540-2","question":"List 3 causes of a sand crack.","answer":"Uneven weight bearing, irregular hoof growth, wire cuts, excessive hoof length, dry conditions"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4314 bonus HIH540a","question":"Name 3 steps in treating an abscessed foot.","answer":"Locate & drain abscess, remove dead tissue (but avoid excessive tissue removal), use poultice, soak foot in water & Epsom salts, protect hoof with shoe, pad, or bandages, tetanus booster"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4315 bonus HIH455-3","question":"Name 3 shoeing practices that may contribute to the development of corns.","answer":"Shoe too small, leaving shoe on too long, trimming heel too low"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4316 bonus HIH535","question":"Timelineï¿½You are a farrier and are demonstrating how to remove a shoe & trim the hoof.  What is the correct order to use the following five farrier tools when accomplishing this task:  nippers, hoof knife, clinch cutter, rasp, pull offs","answer":"Clinch cutterï¿½pull offsï¿½hoof knifeï¿½nippersï¿½rasp"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4317 bonus INT206-2L","question":"Name 3 things that affect hoof growth","answer":"Warm temperature, improved nutrition, young age, stimulation or massage of the coronary band, irritation or injury to sensitive structures, exercise, heart rate  age, genetics, season/temperature, moisture, nutrition, individual differences/sensitivity"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4318 bonus TH728","question":"2 part question:  What are the 2 basic types of hammers used by farriers & how are they used?","answer":"Rounding - used for making & shaping shoes
A:  Driving - used for driving nails, finishing clinches  (claws also used for wringing off the old nails)"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4319 bonus BEG104","question":"Give 3 characteristics of a healthy hoof.","answer":"Outer wall hard/slick, hoof wall shiny or slightly waxy appearance, free of growth or fever/founder rings, free from heat, coronet band has enough moisture to feel slightly resilient, frog firm/slightly pliable, no foul odor,  no discharge, sole firm/thick (doesn't "give" to thumb pressure), white line free of discoloration, white line uniform thickness, no bruising, no corns"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4320 bonus TH167","question":"Give 3 causes of contracted heels.","answer":"Lack of frog pressure, lack of moisture in hoof, heredity, faulty conformation, improper trimming, improper shoeing, leaving shoes on too long, uneven weight distribution"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4321 bonus TH720HIH530-1/HH49","question":"Name 3 things you should look for when inspecting the horse's feet.","answer":"Rocks/other debris, bruises, loose shoes if shod, disease/thrush, loose or missing horseshoe nails, puncture wounds, abnormal growth, uneven wear, cracks, splitting, too dry, etc."},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4322 bonus HIH515","question":"2 part question:  Name 2 types of shoe used specifically for the front feet & their uses.","answer":"Half round - harness racing or reining; 	weighted - enhance action of gaited horses"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4323 bonus HIH530","question":"2 part question:  Name 2 types of shoes used specifically for the hind feet & their purpose","answer":"Sliding plates - help horse slide stop;		 square toe - stabilizes breakover point"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4324 bonus HIH515-1","question":"There are 10 things that distinguish an ideally fitted horseshoe.  Name 3.","answer":"Balanced under leg's center of gravity, stable on hoof,  retains most traction from frog/natural cupping shape of foot,  seated away from/protects sole, fit to compensate for low heels or heel movement,  beveled to prevent pulling or injury to another leg,  nail holes in front half of shoe & at proper pitch/angle, provide confidence for performance without slipping, minimum weight necessary"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4325 bonus TH749","question":"Name 3 corrective or therapeutic horseshoes.","answer":"Bar, egg bar, half rim, half sole, heart bar, shoe w/heel caulks, rolled toe, slippered heels, square toe, trailer, bar across breakover point, caulk at first outside nail hole, Chadwick spring, lateral toe extension with trailer, rocker toe, wedge toe, Patten shoe"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4326 bonus TH738 fig 19-42","question":"Name 3 parts of a horseshoe nail.","answer":"Head, neck, shank, bevel, point, inner face, outer face"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4327 bonus TH38","question":"Name 3 types of horseshoe nails.","answer":"Regular, cityhead, frosthead"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4328 bonus TH750","question":"Name 2 types of horseshoes that can be used to re-establish frog pressure.","answer":"Bar shoe, slippered/beveled heel, Chadwick spring"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4329 bonus TH747-750","question":"Name 3 common faults corrected by trimming.","answer":"Splay foot/toe out, pigeon toe/toe in, quarter crack, cocked ankle, contracted heels"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4330 bonus HIH535","question":"Name 4 steps in shoeing a horse.  ","answer":"Observe horse , cut clinches, pull off old shoe, trim hoof wall, trim frog & sole, shape shoe, nail shoe on, clinch nails, rasp"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4331 bonus HIH505-7","question":"What is the moisture content of the following parts of the hoof - wall, sole & frog?","answer":"Wall - 25%            Sole - 33%                   Frog - 50%"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4332 bonus HIH510","question":"When the shod hoof grows out & the angle changes, name two things that can happen.","answer":"Puts strain on the ligaments & tendons, can affect the horseï¿½s action, can cause lameness"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4333 bonus HH48/HIH","question":"Name 3 important points in the care of a horse's foot.","answer":"Keep them clean to prevent thrush, remove rocks to prevent bruises, keep them trimmed properly, prevent the hoof full from drying out"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4334 bonus HIH505-1","question":"Name 3 things a horse's foot was designed to do.","answer":"Support weight, resist wear, absorb shock, provide traction, conduct moisture, assist in pumping blood"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4335 bonus HIH525","question":"Name 3 problems that can occur to the feet of horses that are stalled year round","answer":"Dry hooves, contracted heels, navicular disease"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4336 bonus HIH515-1,535-5","question":"What are 3 reasons a horse may require horseshoes?","answer":"Protect hoof from excessive wear, when used on hard surfaces/roads, to correct stance or gait, traction, to correct faulty hoof structure or growth, to protect hoof from corn, contraction, cracks or other abnormal conditions, ease pain of injured hoof"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4337 bonus HIH515-2","question":"Name 3 reasons for hot shoeing.","answer":"Shoes can be made specifically for foot, more secure nailing, less interference with natural hoof function"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4339 bonus TH742","question":"Name 3 things that can happen if you leave a shoe on too long.","answer":"Shoes can become loose or fall off, shoes can become thin, foot can get bruised or punctured, tendons & ligaments can become strained, hooves can grow out of proportion"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4340 bonus ADV334-2","question":"Name 3 different variations of a hoof crack.","answer":"Extends partway down from coronary band, extends partway up from ground level, extends full length of wall, horizontal crack"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4341 bonus HIH505/BEG116/TH727-29","question":"Name 3 uses of a hoof knife.","answer":"Pare away dead sole, trim ragged frog, relieve pressure on corns or cracks, remove foreign bodies from hoof"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4342 bonus HIH535-5/INT221","question":"Name 3 things that influence horseshoe style.","answer":"Type of work/activity horse does, type of terrain horse is worked on, integrity of hoof/how good hoof is, size of horse, weight of horse"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4343 bonus HIH535-3/INT221","question":"Name 3 things - other than hoof size - that influence what size horseshoe to use.","answer":"Length of shoe heels, position of heel nail holes, web/width, weight of shoe, nail hole size"},
{"category":"FOOT CARE","level":"bonus","number":"4344 bonus BEG116-2L","question":"Identify the 3 general types of clinchers or clinching tongs","answer":"Saddle horse, gooseneck & draft horse          "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4345 easy TH715/HH18-19","question":"Which gait is faster, trot or pace?","answer":"Pace"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4346 easy TH178/HH17","question":"Name 2 acquired gaits.  ","answer":"Single foot or rack, slow gait or stepping pace, amble, paso, racking walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4347 easy TH173/HH17","question":"The walk is a 4-beat gait.  Is the sequence of footfalls lateral or diagonal?","answer":"Diagonal"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4348 easy H5-34/DET70","question":"What is the term for a balanced canter on one lead while the horse is traveling in the opposite direction?","answer":"Counter canter    "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4349 easy DET3/HH17","question":"In reference to motion, what is an acquired gait?","answer":"Gaits that are the result of specific training & practice; one that must be taught   Accept either"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4350 easy ES76/HH24","question":"When a horse is cantering in a counterclockwise direction in a riding arena, which lead is considered the correct one?","answer":"Left"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4351 easy TH174/HIH/CCS/HH various","question":"There are 5 different walks in a dressage test.  Which of these would be completed with the horse on a "long rein"?","answer":"Free walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4352 easy HH18-19/TH173-75","question":"What is the difference between a trot & a pace?","answer":"Trot - 2 beat diagonal gait (opposite front & hind feet start & stop at same time)
Pace - 2 beat lateral gait (front & hind feet on same side start & stop at same time)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4353 easy HH17/TH169","question":"What is meant by the term "way of going"?","answer":"How a horse moves; the natural movement of the horse  "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4354 easy HIH152-1/TH51","question":"What is the term used to describe the canter of the Tennessee Walker?","answer":"Rocking chair canter"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4355 easy HH17","question":"What gait of the horse is comfortable to ride, easy to sit, & easy for beginners?","answer":"Walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4356 easy HH19","question":"In the gallop, where does the drive or power come from?","answer":"Hind legs or hindquarters"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4357 easy HH18","question":"What makes it possible for a horse to do a flying lead change?","answer":"The brief period of suspension following the beat of the leading leg OR All 4 legs are off the ground for a brief period"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4358 easy HIH230-1","question":"When a horse is limited in his movement, what else is limited?","answer":"His usefulness"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4359 easy TH181/HS13","question":"What is the term used when describing a winding or twisting of the striding leg around in front of the supporting leg -- which results in contact like that of a rope-walking artist?","answer":"Rope walking or winding"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4360 easy HIH230-5/HH13","question":"Describe paddling.","answer":"Throwing the front feet outward as they're picked up"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4361 easy TH179/HS13/DET73","question":"Define cross firing.","answer":"One lead in front with the opposite lead in back OR hind foot on one side strikes the diagonal forefoot OR
forging in a pacing horse	(accept any)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4362 easy TH171/HH17","question":"What is the term used to describe the rhythmic, characteristic movements of a horse's feet & legs?","answer":"Gaits"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4363 easy TH176/HH18","question":"A medium-fast collected canter exhibited in Western classes is called what?","answer":"Lope"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4364 easy TH175/HH19","question":"2 part question:  Define lateral gait & give an example.","answer":"Legs move in lateral pairs (front & hind feet on the same side start & stop at the same time); example ï¿½ pace"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4365 easy TH171/HH17","question":"What is a natural gait?","answer":"One that's performed by natural impulses/without training OR one that the horse is born knowing how to do  	"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4366 easy HIH152-1","question":"Which gait is a distinguishing characteristic of the Tennessee Walker?","answer":"Running walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4367 easy HIH230-5/TH181/HH12","question":"What is the term used when a pigeon toed horse throws the front feet outward while traveling?","answer":"Paddling"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4368 easy TH178/HIH152-1","question":"What is the name for a fast, 4-beat ground-covering walk?","answer":"Running walk		"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4369 easy HH23/DET274","question":"What movement is important for opening gates?","answer":"Side pass      (also accept traverse)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4370 easy TH175/HH18","question":"What is the last foot to hit the ground in the canter when on the right lead?","answer":"Right front"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4371 easy TH172/HH17","question":"Which gait is the slowest gait & is common to all breeds of horses?","answer":"Walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4372 easy HH47","question":"What gait is posting associated with?","answer":"Trot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4373 easy TH175/HH18","question":"At the canter or lope, what do you call the independently moving front leg?","answer":"Lead"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4374 easy TH173/HH18","question":"2 part question:  What is a diagonal gait & give an example?","answer":"Legs move in diagonal pairs (front foot & opposite hind foot start & stop at same time); example ï¿½ trot, (also accept jog)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4375 easy TH178/HH18","question":"What is the 5th gait of the American Saddle Horse?","answer":"Rack    (single-foot)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4376 easy TH173picture/HH17","question":"What kind of base of support does the horse have at the walk?","answer":"Triangular     (3 legs are on the ground at once)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4377 easy TH175/HH18","question":"What is another name for the slow trot?","answer":"Jog"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4378 easy TH175/HH18","question":"What gait is an easy, rhythmical 3-beat gait?","answer":"Canter      (also accept lope)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4379 easy TH175/HH19","question":"Describe the movement of the pace.","answer":"Legs move in lateral pairs OR front & hind feet on the same side start & stop at the same time  "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4380 easy HH18","question":"What is another name for sidestep?","answer":"Sidepass or traverse"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4381 easy HH12","question":"How will the splay-footed horse travel?			","answer":"Dish or wing in "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4382 easy H5-34/DET236","question":"What is a rollback?","answer":"When a galloping horse stops, lifts his forelegs, swings around 180 degrees & starts galloping again in the direction from which he came		accept any reasonable wording"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4383 easy TH181/HH18","question":"Striking the ground hard in the stride is called what?","answer":"Pounding"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4384 easy HH19/TH175","question":"Which gait is a lateral, 2-beat gait?","answer":"Pace"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4385 easy TH176/HH19","question":"What is another name for the gallop?","answer":"Run"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4386 easy TH173/HH18","question":"Which gait is a rapid, 2-beat diagonal gait?","answer":"Trot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4387 easy H5-34","question":"What is a counter-canter?","answer":"Intentionally cantering a horse on the opposite lead from the direction it is travelling 
(accept any reasonable wording; do not accept cantering on the wrong lead)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4388 easy TH175/DET166/HH18/ES74","question":"What is a lead?","answer":"Independently moving front leg in a canter or gallop OR the front foot that the horse appears to be ï¿½leadingï¿½ with at the canter or gallop"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4390 easy HH18/TH169/FCH405","question":"The distance from imprint to imprint by a horse's foot is called what?","answer":"Stride"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4391 easy HH18","question":"Define traverse or sidestep.","answer":"When the horse steps sideways without moving forward or backward"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4392 easy HH17/TH172","question":"Which natural gait is the slowest 4-beat gait with each foot striking the ground independently from the other 3 feet?","answer":"Walk "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4393 easy HH18/DET219","question":"What is pounding?","answer":"Heavy contact with the ground in the stride   (striking the ground hard in the stride)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4394 easy HH18/TH175","question":"How many beats are in the canter?","answer":"3"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4395 easy HH13/HIH525-4","question":"Referring to gaits, if a horse is forging, what is he doing?","answer":"Striking the forefoot with the toe of the hind foot (on same side)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4396 easy TH180-81/HH13/DET153","question":"In reference to gaits & as a general term, what is interfering?","answer":"When a horseï¿½s leg hits another leg while the horse is moving"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4397 easy TH180/HH13","question":"What is it called when the hairline at the top of the hindfoot hits the toe of the forefoot as it breaks over?","answer":"Scalping"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4398 easy TH171/HH17-18/ES69-78","question":"Name 3 natural gaits common to most breeds.","answer":"Walk, trot/jog, canter/lope, gallop/run, & back  "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4399 easy HIH230-5","question":"What type of defect does a horse have if he dishes or wings in when he travels?","answer":"Splayfoot or toe out    (also accept base wide)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4400 easy TH181/HH13","question":"What is the term for excessive lateral shoulder motion?","answer":"Rolling"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4401 easy TH181/HH13","question":"What is the term used for a short, quick, choppy stride?","answer":"Trappy"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4402 easy TH169/HH12","question":"Define action.","answer":"How a horse moves its feet & legs at walk/trot, etc"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4403 easy HH13/TH181","question":"Define rolling.","answer":"Excessive lateral shoulder motion   (like the motion of a bulldog walking)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4404 easy TH173/HH13","question":"What is the term used to describe a noticeable pause in the flight of the foot as though the stride were completed before the foot reaches the ground?","answer":"Floating or dwelling"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4405 easy DET82/HIH/HH/ES78","question":"What term refers to the canter when the front and hind legs are different leads?","answer":"Disunited canter, cross firing, or cross canter     (accept any)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4406 easy TH171/HH17-18/ES69-78","question":"Name 2 gaitsï¿½other than the walk, trot, canter, gallop, or backï¿½that may be ï¿½natural gaitsï¿½ to some breeds.","answer":"Running walk, fox trot, pace, paso"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4407 easy TH175/HH19","question":"What is the base of support for the pace?","answer":"2 lateral legs      (2 legs on same side on the ground at once)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4408 easy HIH152-1/HH18","question":"At what approximate speed does the running walk travel?","answer":"7 - 10 mph      (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4409 easy TH175/HH18","question":"When on the left lead, which leg or legs are on the ground for the second beat of the canter?","answer":"Left hind & right front
( addtl info -- 1st beat right hind, 2nd beat left hind & right front, 3rd beat left front)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4410 easy HH17","question":"Explain free-going.  ","answer":"Free forward movement OR   when the horse moves forward freely in a smooth, collected manner without pain or difficulty 	(accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4411 easy HH17","question":"What is the term used when the stride lacks spring or action, therefore causing unnecessary rider fatigue?","answer":"Rough or hard gaited"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4412 easy ES p.70    HIH/CCS/HH various	","question":"The walk is the horseï¿½s slowest gait.  What is the average speed of the horseï¿½s walk?","answer":"4 miles per hour"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4413 easy HH17/DET163","question":"What is labored action?","answer":"When a horse has to work hard to move OR when a horse's action/motion is difficult to perform & is painfully excessive 	(accept any reasonable wording) "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4414 easy HH17","question":"What is the term used for a horse's gaits when the rider's reaction is pleasant & enjoyable?","answer":"Easy gaited"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4415 easy TH179/HH13 DET59","question":"What is the term used when the inside of the diagonal fore & the hind pasterns make contact, sometimes seen in fast-trotting horses?","answer":"Speedy cutting       Also accept:  clipping"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4416 easy HH18","question":"What do you call a pacer that rolls his body sideways as he paces?","answer":"Sidewheeler"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4418 easy TH176/HH19","question":"How many beats are there in a gallop?","answer":"4"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4419 easy HS11","question":"A short underline can cause a horse to do what?","answer":"Forge (also accept interfere)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4420 easy HH18/TH40","question":"What is another name for the rack?","answer":"Singlefoot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4421 easy TH181/HH13","question":"Describe the term "trappy".","answer":"Short, quick, choppy stride"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4422 easy HH17","question":"What is the term used when a horse's gaits are executed in a smooth, collected manner & action is not excessive or labored?","answer":"Free going"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4423 easy HH17","question":"What is the general term for gaits that must be taught?","answer":"Acquired gaits"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4424 easy HH17","question":"What is the term used when a horse's action is difficult to perform & painfully excessive?","answer":"Labored action"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4426 easy HIH152-1","question":"Name the 3 gaits of the Tennessee Walker.","answer":"Walk (flat walk), running walk, canter (rocking chair canter)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4427 easy HH13/TH179","question":"What is scalping?","answer":"Hitting coronet of hind foot with toe of front foot OR hairline at top of hind foot hits toe of forefoot as it breaks over "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4428 easy TH181/HH13/DET24","question":"What do you call an exaggerated paddling that is particularly noticeable in high-going animals?","answer":"Winging or winging out"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4429 easy HH18/TH40","question":"What is the name for the fast, flashy 4-beat gait that's sometimes referred to as the single-foot?","answer":"Rack"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4430 easy TH172/ES81/HH18-19","question":"Referring to gaited horses, what is another name for the slow gait?","answer":"Stepping pace"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4431 easy HH18-19","question":"Which of the following is an artificial gait:   trot, slow gait or canter?","answer":"Slow gait"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4432 easy TH175/HH18","question":"With which foot does a horse start a right lead canter?","answer":"Left hind"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4433 easy HH18/TH169","question":"How do you determine the stride length of a horse?","answer":"Distance from imprint to imprint of the same foot when completing a step"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4434 easy TH179/HH13","question":"Give the name of the traveling defect where the toe of the hind foot hits the sole or shoe of the forefoot?","answer":"Forging"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4435 easy H5-35/DET273","question":"What is the term for changing from one gait to another?","answer":"Transition"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4436 easy ES70,72, HIH/CCS/HH various","question":"What is the average speed for the trot?","answer":"6 - 8 mph      (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"easy","number":"4437 easy TH179","question":"In reference to interfering, forging is most  likely to occur at what gait?","answer":"Trot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4438 medium HH13","question":"A trappy stride is most commonly seen in horses with what conformation defects?","answer":"Straight shoulders & pasterns"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4439 medium TH169","question":"A horse's speed is determined by what 2 things?","answer":"Stride length & stride frequency"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4440 medium TH181","question":"Pounding is a defect in way of going often associated with what conformation defect?","answer":"Straight shoulders & pasterns"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4441 medium TH179/DET73","question":"When a pacer hits the sole or shoe of a front foot with the diagonal rear foot, this interference is called what?","answer":"Cross firing"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4442 medium DET101","question":"What is the term for the lengthening of the trot stride without an increase in tempo?","answer":"Extended trot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4443 medium TH179-80","question":"2 part question:  Name 2 of the striding leg interferences in which the toe of the forefoot hits the hind leg & describe where on the rear leg the striking is occurring.  ","answer":"Hock hittingï¿½toe of front foot hits hock on hind leg; scalping ï¿½toe of front foot hits coronet of hind foot; shin hittingï¿½toe of front foot hits cannon of hind leg on same side; speedy cuttingï¿½toe of front foot hits pastern or fetlock on hind foot on the same side"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4444 medium DET205","question":"What is the dressage movement in which the horse trots in a very cadenced, floating manner with a marked period of suspension?","answer":"Passage     (pronounced like massage)										"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4445 medium HH13","question":"What is a perceptible extension of the stride with little flexion called?","answer":"Pointing"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4446 medium TH178","question":"How many beats are in the gait referred to as the stepping pace?","answer":"4"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4447 medium TH173","question":"In which of the following breeds would you see the longest suspension during the trot, Hackney or Standardbred?","answer":"Standardbred"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4448 medium TH175","question":"While cantering on the right lead, which feet bear more weight & are subject to more strain?","answer":"Left hind & right front"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4449 medium HH17","question":"When a horse in action lifts his front & hind feet very high, flexing at the knees & hocks, he is said to be what?","answer":"Flashy or high-gaited"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4450 medium TH179","question":"What is brushing?","answer":"Slight contact between one leg & the other"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4451 medium TH40","question":"What 2 gaits does a 5-gaited horse perform that a 3-gaited horse does not?","answer":"Slow gait (stepping pace) & rack (single foot)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4452 medium DET84","question":"2 part question:  What is meant when it's said that a horse is "double-gaited" & in which breed would you see it?","answer":"Horse can both trot & pace; Standardbred"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4453 medium TH177","question":"At a gallop on a right lead, what is the next foot to hit the ground after the right front?","answer":"Left rear"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4455 medium TH150","question":"Roughened hair, nicks & scars on the inside of the fetlock are evidence of what?","answer":"Interfering"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4456 medium TH177","question":"Beginning with the contact of the left hind foot with the ground explain the footfall sequence of a horse on the right lead at the gallop. ","answer":"Left hind, right hind, left front, right front"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4457 medium TH151","question":"Describe the motion of a horse that has low, thick withers.","answer":"Heavy on front end OR rolling gait"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4458 medium DET114","question":"What is four-beating?","answer":"When a horse canters/lopes with his front legs & trots with hind OR when footfalls at canter/lope are all separate making it a 4-beat gait instead of a 3-beat one"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4459 medium TH172","question":"Most gaits are symmetrical.  However, there are 2 asymmetrical gaits.  Name them.","answer":"Canter/lope & gallop"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4460 medium TH169","question":"Explain the difference between stance phase & swing phase of a leg.","answer":"Stance phase - when leg is on ground;     swing phase - when leg is off the ground"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4461 medium ES83","question":"When running a quarter mile, racing Quarter Horses have been clocked at up to what speed?","answer":"50 mph"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4462 medium ES78","question":"What is the Thoroughbred's average length of stride at the gallop?","answer":"21 - 23 feet 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4463 medium HIH161B-1","question":"What is the name of the gait described as walking in front & trotting behind?","answer":"Fox trot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4464 medium TH178","question":"Name the fastest artificial gait.","answer":"Rack   (single foot)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4465 medium DET245","question":"Name this movement:   There is no forward or backward movement.  The horse steps laterally with both forequarters & hindquarters moving together with a crossover step.  ","answer":"Sidepass or traverse or sidestep"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4466 medium DET214","question":"In dressage, what is the name of a high, collected trot in place with a prolonged period of suspension?","answer":"Piaffe 	(pronounced Pee-ahf)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4467 medium TH390","question":"How many beats are there in the horse's gait when backing?","answer":"2"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4468 medium TH178","question":"Which gait of the horse is easy on the rider, but is extremely tiring for the horse?  It's the fastest 4-beat artificial gait.","answer":"Rack    (singlefoot)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4469 medium CAHA39","question":"2 part question:  In reference to way of going, what is plaiting & what type of conformation results in this way of travel?","answer":"Forefeet travel inward to land in front of one another; occurs in base narrow, toed-out horses"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4470 medium DET260","question":"Referring to gaits, what is a "period of suspension"?","answer":"All 4 feet are off the ground"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4471 medium HH18/TH169","question":"What term is used to refer to the nature of movement in the horse?","answer":"Way of going (or action)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4472 medium DET101","question":"In a dressage test, what is an extended trot?","answer":"Lengthening of the stride without an increase in tempo/speed"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4473 medium TH174","question":"How does a collected walk differ from a medium walk as used in dressage?","answer":"Collected walk is shorter & has more action than the medium walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4474 medium TH175","question":"Why should the leads at a canter be changed periodically?","answer":"So the muscles develop evenly on both sides of the horse OR to prevent too much strain on one side of the horse"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4475 medium HS7","question":"How much weight may a horse dissipate on his lead foot when running?","answer":"One ton per second"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4476 medium HIH505-4/DET38","question":"What is the term for the moment in a horse's stride between landing & takeoff?","answer":"Breakover"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4477 medium HIH152-1","question":"What is the footfall sequence for the running walk - starting with the left front?","answer":"Left front, right rear, right front, left rear"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4478 medium TH181","question":"In what type of horse is winging out most commonly seen?","answer":"High stepping harness or saddle horses 	(examples - Saddlebred, Hackney, Morgan)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4479 medium DET117,129","question":"What is the difference between a full gallop as run by a racehorse & a hand gallop?","answer":"Full gallop is a 4-beat gait; hand gallop is a 3-beat gait & is more of an extended canter"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4480 medium ES83","question":"Why do working ranch horses need to have gaits that are comfortable for the rider & are easy on the horse?","answer":"Both work long days"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4481 medium TH178","question":"2 part question:  The Plantation Gait was a smooth, ground-covering gait that made the Tennessee Walking Horse popular in the South.  What is the proper name for this gait & how many beats does it have?","answer":"Running walk;  4 beats"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"medium","number":"4482 medium TH179","question":"What term refers to supporting leg interference that results in an open wound?","answer":"Striking                "},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4483 hard HH45","question":"What was the original name for the canter?","answer":"Canterbury gallop"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4484 hard HH13/TH179","question":"In reference to gaits, what is the term for striking the inside one leg with the inside of the hoof or skin of the opposite leg?","answer":"Interfering"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4485 hard TH179","question":"In reference to supporting leg interference, explain the difference between brushing & striking","answer":"Brushingï¿½slight contact between legs; striking ï¿½ harder contact between legs that may result in an open wound"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4486 hard TH179","question":"Name the 2 major general types of leg interference that can occur in horses.","answer":"Supporting leg & striding leg"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4487 hard TH42/HIH161B-1","question":"2 part question:  Identify the following gait & in what breed of horse it's found.  The gait starts out as a simple trot.  However, the hind diagonal foot comes down before the front foot, making it a 4 beat gait.   The horse's body is rising in front & lowering behind in unison.","answer":"Gait -   Foxtrot;      breed - Missouri Foxtrotter"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4488 hard TH43","question":"2 part question:    What is ï¿½terminoï¿½ & in which breed is it seen?","answer":"Forelegs roll towards the outside as horse strides forward (like the arm motion of a swimmer); seen in the Peruvian Paso"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4489 hard TH43","question":"What is the sequence of beats in the paso gait?","answer":"Right rear, right front, left rear, left front"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4490 hard DET77","question":"In reference to horses, what is a "daisy cutter"?","answer":"Horse that skims the surface of the ground at the trot  (doesn't bend legs much)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4491 hard DET93","question":"Generally speaking, when it's said that a horse is "engaged", what does this mean?","answer":"Horse is using its hindquarters for impulsion"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4492 hard TH179","question":"What type of striding leg interference is generally confined to pacers?","answer":"Cross firing"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4493 hard TH177","question":"What is the proper footfall sequence of a galloping horse?","answer":"One hind foot, the other hind foot, diagonal front foot, the other front foot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4494 hard ES76","question":"At the gallop, Secretariat had a stride of what length?","answer":"29 feet"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4495 hard HH18	","question":"When referring to foot action, what is meant by height?","answer":"The amount of elevation in the stride"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4496 hard TH179","question":"In striding leg interference, a moving leg makes contact with another moving leg.  What is this called when it occurs at a slow trot, disappears at a faster trot & causes a characteristic clicking sound?","answer":"Forging"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4497 hard HH45","question":"Which gait is a slow, easy pace where the front & rear feet on a side move in unison?","answer":"Amble"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4498 hard HH17/HIH161B-1","question":"Describe the fox trot gait.","answer":"4 beat diagonal gait with a slow, short, broken type of trot in which the head usually nods; 4 beat diagonal gait where the hind foot hits the ground an instant before the diagonal forefoot; 4 beat diagonal gait where the horse is walking in front & trotting behind	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"hard","number":"4499 hard TH43","question":"Describe the paso gait.","answer":"A broken pace (4 beat lateral gait)"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4500 bonus TH179-81","question":"In reference to gaits, name 4 abnormal ways of going.","answer":"Paddling/winging out, dishing/winging in, rolling, winding/rope walking, trappy, pounding, cross-firing, forging, interfering, lameness, pointing, scalping, speedy cutting"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4501 bonus TH179","question":"Give 4 examples of striding leg interference.","answer":"Forging, scalping, cross-firing, speedy cutting, shin hitting, hock hitting, overreaching"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4502 bonus TH712","question":"Terms for gaits are somewhat synonymous.  Give the other name for each of the following gaits:   trot, lope, slow gait, & rack.","answer":"Trot ï¿½ jog, lope ï¿½ canter, slow gaitï¿½stepping pace, rack ï¿½ single foot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4503 bonus TH169","question":"List 4 gaits that do NOT have a stride suspension phase.","answer":"Walk, foxtrot, amble, running walk, paso"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4504 bonus TH178","question":"Name the gaits performed by a 5-gaited horse.","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, slow gait/stepping pace, rack/singlefoot"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4505 bonus HH17","question":"What are 2 reasons you should have a working understanding of gaits?","answer":"To detect lameness, to train a performance horse, to be able to use a horse for a specific purpose"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4506 bonus TH174","question":"Name 3 walks that might be called for in a dressage test.","answer":"Working walk, collected walk, extended walk, medium walk, free walk"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4507 bonus TH169","question":"Name 3 important features of the stride.  ","answer":"Balance, directness, height, length, rapidity, regularity"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4508 bonus HIH220","question":"What are 2 reasons you want a horse with a long stride?","answer":"Absorbs more shock, moves with less effort, covering longer distance with each stride"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4509 bonus TH173","question":"Name 3 of the trots that might be called for in a dressage test.","answer":"Collected, medium, working, extended"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4510 bonus TH178","question":"What are the 3 speeds of the paso gait?","answer":"Paso fino, paso corto, paso largo"},
{"category":"GAITS","level":"bonus","number":"4511 bonus TH172,178","question":"Name 3 gaits that have 4 beats.","answer":"Walk, stepping pace/slow gait, running walk, amble, paso, singlefoot/rack, gallop, fox trot"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4512 easy HH20","question":"A horseman will shift his seat to place his body in balance with what?","answer":"Action of the horse"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4513 easy HH29","question":"What are the natural aids used for while riding your horse?","answer":"To control your horse (tell your horse what you want him to do)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4514 easy HH29","question":"What is meant by the phrase "sit tall in the saddle"?","answer":"Sit up straight"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4515 easy HH29","question":"Constant, steady pulling on the reins can cause what problem?","answer":"Hard mouth 	(or damage to horseï¿½s mouth)		accept either"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4516 easy HH40","question":"When mounting your horse, which foot goes into the stirrup first?","answer":"Left"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4517 easy HH29","question":"Which of the natural aids is used lightly to guide the horse's forehand?","answer":"Hands"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4518 easy HH20","question":"When teaching a horse to neck rein, what is the rein called that pulls in the direction of the turn?","answer":"Leading rein or direct rein"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4519 easy HH20","question":"What is the rein called that's pushed against the neck in the direction of the turn?","answer":"Bearing rein	or neck rein"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4520 easy H5-35","question":"What do you call a turn on the front legs?","answer":"Turn on the forehand"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4521 easy H4-23","question":"When your horse is excited or full of steam, what should you do before riding him?","answer":"Longe line or work him in a round pen"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4522 easy HH29","question":"Why are light hands so important in riding?","answer":"Heavy hands can hurt horse's mouth "},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4523 easy HIH210-2","question":"What is meant by the appropriate size horse & rider?","answer":"Not a small rider on large horse or vice versa"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4524 easy HH23","question":"When mounting for Western Equitation, on what part of the saddle do you place the right hand?","answer":"Saddle horn"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4525 easy H4-29","question":"When riding, what should you do when the horse does well?","answer":"Give him a pat or praise him"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4526 easy HH20","question":"What is another name for the right side of your horse?","answer":"Off side or far side"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4527 easy HH20","question":"The left side of the horse is also called what?","answer":"Near side"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4528 easy HH20","question":"Define bearing rein.","answer":"The rein pushed against the neck in the direction of the turn when neck reining"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4529 easy HH20","question":"Name two natural aids.","answer":"Voice, hands, legs, weight"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4530 easy HH9","question":"What is a rubberneck?","answer":"Horse with a very flexible neck	 (additional info -- thatï¿½s hard to rein)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4531 easy HIH420-3	","question":"In cold weather, what should you do before placing the bit in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Warm the bit"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4532 easy HH20","question":"What is the off side?","answer":"Right side"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4533 easy HH9","question":"What do you call a horse that holds his head too high & his nose out?","answer":"Stargazer"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4534 easy HH53","question":"When bridling your horse, which ear is last to be pulled under the crownpiece?","answer":"Left"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4535 easy HH20","question":"When mounting a horse, on what side do you generally mount?","answer":"Left"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4536 easy HH20","question":"The legs, hands, weight & voice as used in controlling a horse are called what?","answer":"Aids   (natural aids)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4537 easy HH20","question":"When riding in groups, what kind of distance should you keep between horses?","answer":"One horse length	 (one horse length equals  8 feet)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4538 easy HH9","question":"What is a stargazer?","answer":"Horse that holds his head too high & his nose out"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4539 easy HH9","question":"What is the term for a horse with a very flexible neck that may be hard to rein?","answer":"Rubberneck"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4540 easy HH20","question":"What is posting?","answer":"Rising & descending of the rider in rhythm with the trot"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4541 easy HH22","question":"With which leg do you apply pressure to get your horse to take the left lead?","answer":"Right"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4542 easy HH23","question":"What is the proper way to ask your horse to back?","answer":"Grip with legs, hold reins low, pull lightly using give & take motion, use your voice"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4543 easy HH20","question":"What term means to step a horse backwards?","answer":"Back"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4544 easy HH20","question":"What is the rising & descending of the rider in rhythm with the trot called?","answer":"Posting"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4545 easy HH20","question":"Ride with your weight on what part of the foot?","answer":"Ball"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4546 easy HH40","question":"One who rides a horse without control, letting the horse go as he wishes, is called what?","answer":"Passenger"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4547 easy HH53","question":"When riding in groups, how should you ride in relation to others?","answer":"Abreast or a horse length    (8 feet) from horse in front of you"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4548 easy HH29","question":"Heavy hands can cause damage to what part of the horse?","answer":"Mouth (specifically bars or interdental space)		accept either general or specific"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4549 easy HH40","question":"When speaking of horseback riding, what is a passenger?","answer":"One who rides without control letting the horse go where it wants"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4550 easy HH20","question":"What term means "the art of riding horseback"?","answer":"Equitation   (also accept horsemanship)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4551 easy HH20","question":"A horse length equals how many feet?","answer":"8 "},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4552 easy HH20","question":"When you get ready to mount properly, what do you do to get your horse under control?","answer":"Adjust reins evenly with enough tension to feel bit & hold horse steady"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4553 easy HH21","question":"Explain how you would gather your horse.","answer":"Take up on reins & settle in saddle"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4554 easy HH21","question":"When riding a trot Western style, the body should be inclined slightly more in which direction than at the walk?","answer":"Forward"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4556 easy HH21","question":"What are you doing when you settle in the saddle & take in on the reins?","answer":"Gathering your horse"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4557 easy HH20","question":"What does it mean to "pull leather"?","answer":"Hold on to saddle with both hands when riding a bucking horse"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4558 easy HH23","question":"Explain how you would get your horse to side pass.","answer":"Hold horse to prevent forward movement, rein in the direction you wish to move the forequarters, & use outside leg to move hindquarters	(accept any reasonable explanation)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4559 easy HH20","question":"What term is used when you hold on the saddle with both hands while riding a bucking horse?","answer":"Pull leather"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4560 easy HH21","question":"When riding, your legs are used to signal what?","answer":"Speed & direction of movement"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4561 easy HH20","question":"True neck reining is the response of your horse to what?","answer":"Weight/feel  of rein against the neck"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4562 easy HIH1220-2","question":"What is the main means of communication between horse & rider?","answer":"Your legs"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4563 easy HH21","question":"What part of the horse's body do your hands control?","answer":"Forequarters"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4564 easy HIH815-1","question":"In which riding style is the rider seated sideways?","answer":"Sidesaddle"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"easy","number":"4566 easy ES74picture","question":"What direction should the horse's nose be pointing when loping in a circle?","answer":"To the inside"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4567 medium HH20","question":"What will happen if you get out of balance while riding?","answer":"You'll stiffen & lose the rhythm of motion with the horse OR throw horse off balance "},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"MEDIUM","number":"4568 MEDIUM HH44","question":"When showing a horse in-hand with a Pelham or double bridle, with which rein do you lead the horse?","answer":"Lead with the curb rein		
(additional info -- snaffle rein should be placed over the horseï¿½s neck/withers)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4569 medium DET26","question":"Define "behind the bit".","answer":"When horse evades the bit by bending his head towards the chest OR when horse is over-flexed at the poll & is insensitive to the aids"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4570 medium DET17","question":"When a rider is riding side saddle they have both legs on the near side of the horse. What term refers to riding with one leg on each side of the horse? ","answer":"Astride	"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4571 medium DET1","question":"When a horse is difficult to control because it's carrying its head too high, thus evading the bit, he is said to be what?","answer":"Above the bit"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4572 medium HH24","question":"When riding with romal reins in stock seat equitation, how much distance should there be between the hand holding the reins & the hand holding the romal?","answer":"At least 16ï¿½"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4573 medium DET195","question":"What is meant by the term "on the bit"?","answer":"When the horse has accepted contact with the bit (reacts to aids with quiet responsive manner)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4574 medium HIH1220-2","question":"Why is it important for a rider to stay deep in the saddle & sit up straight?","answer":"So you donï¿½t confuse the horse or throw it off balance OR so you donï¿½t fall off if the horse makes an unexpected move"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4575 medium DET26","question":"A horse that moves forward with his head tucked into his chest is said to be what?","answer":"Behind the bit"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4576 medium DET20ES79","question":"In performing a correct rein-back, how should the legs of the horse move?","answer":"In diagonal pairs	
(additional info 2 beat dressage maneuver where a horse backs with his legs in diagonal pairs)"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4577 medium HIH110-5","question":"What is the term for one who rides horseback?","answer":"Equestrian"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4578 medium HH25","question":"If the English rider is balanced correctly over her feet, where does the stirrup leather hang?","answer":"Straight down"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4579 medium HIH210-2","question":"What do you look for in an equitation horse?","answer":"Horse that can be ridden in the style desired OR horse can perform tasks required by the class"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4580 medium DET73","question":"What do you call a method of holding single reins where the reins overlap in the rider's hands across the horse's back?","answer":"Cross reins     "},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4582 medium DET231","question":"A ï¿½rein-backï¿½ is a movement signaled by the rider to the horse.  What does the horse do when this signal is given?","answer":"Back up"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4583 medium FCH383","question":"When a saddled horse stands with its back pushed up or bowed upward, what may this indicate?","answer":"That it's going to buck when rider mounts"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4584 medium DET214","question":"What is plow reining?","answer":"Direct reining"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4585 medium HH23","question":"Horsemanship requires what 2 things?","answer":"Practice & patience"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"medium","number":"4586 medium H4-17","question":"When riding & turning to the left, where would you place your legs?","answer":"Right leg behind the cinch & left leg at the cinch"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4587 hard HIH1100-1","question":"Which English rider sits in the saddle with a very sharp hip angle?","answer":"Jumping rider"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4588 hard DET26","question":"What causes a chair seat?","answer":"Sitting behind the motion of the horse"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4589 hard DET80","question":"Explain what is meant when a rider uses "diagonal aids".","answer":"Rider uses opposite hand & leg"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4590 hard HS7","question":"When a rider maintains a balanced seat, he is directly over what area of the horse?","answer":"Center of motion OR 15th vertebrae"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4591 hard HH26","question":"If the horse is traveling counter clockwise in the arena, what legs are moving forward when the rider rises for a correct diagonal?","answer":"Right front & left hind"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4592 hard HIH185-1","question":"What is a planchette?","answer":"Wooden step which supported the feet on the early sidesaddles"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4593 hard HHvarious","question":"While sitting properly on a horse, a perpendicular line may be drawn from the rider's shoulder, hip, & heel.  Another perpendicular line may be drawn between what other 2 parts of the body?","answer":"Knee & toe"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"hard","number":"4594 hard HIH1100-1","question":"2 part question:  The term "perched" refers to what type of English saddle & rider?","answer":"Close contact saddle - jumping rider"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4595 bonus HH21","question":"Name 4 natural aids.  ","answer":"Voice, legs, hands, weight"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4596 bonus HH23","question":"What are the 3 general steps to obtain a desired lead?","answer":"Leg pressure, weight shift, rein"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4597 bonus HIH185-1","question":"What are 3 reasons for riding sidesaddle?","answer":"Handicapped riders, those who for some reason can't ride astride, costume, parade, fox hunting, pleasure"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4598 bonus HIH1100-1","question":"Name 3 styles of English riding.","answer":"Hunt seat, saddle seat, & dressage"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4599 bonus HH21","question":"What are the 2 aids you would use to control the speed of your horse?","answer":"Leg pressure & rein tension (legs & hands)  You can also use body position to control speed"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4600 bonus H4-30","question":"Name 3 important general aspects of equitation.","answer":"Body position, hand position, leg position, seat, performing correctly at different gaits, performing pattern correctly"},
{"category":"GENERAL EQUITATION","level":"bonus","number":"4601 bonus HH20","question":"What are the 3 basic equitation or Horsemanship styles?","answer":"Stock seat/Western, Hunt seat, Saddle seat"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4602 easy HIH1040-1/ES94-95","question":"What color is recessive to black and bay?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4603 easy HIH1060-1/HS19/TH458-9/ES90","question":"If a gene has the ability to mask the genetic makeup of the other gene in the pair, it is said to be what?","answer":"Dominant"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4604 easy HIH1060-1","question":"How many pairs of chromosomes do horses have?","answer":"32 pairs"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4605 easy HIH1020-1","question":"How are characteristics passed from parents to offspring?","answer":"By genes	 (also accept chromosomes)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4606 easy HIH1040-1","question":"If a chestnut is mated to a chestnut, what color or colors can be produced?","answer":"Only chestnut	 (additional info -- chestnut is recessive to black)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4607 easy HIH1020-1","question":"What is the dense center of a cell that contains the genetic material?","answer":"Nucleus"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4608 easy TH447/HIH1060-1","question":"2 part question:  How many pairs of chromosomes are there in a horse & are these pairs always identical in nature?","answer":"32 pairs; not always identical"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4609 easy HIH1060-1/HS19/TH458-9/ES90","question":"If a gene cannot mask the genetic makeup of the other gene in a pair, it is said to be what?","answer":"Recessive"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4610 easy HIH1020-1","question":"How many chromosomes does the sperm of a stallion or an egg of a mare contain?","answer":"32 "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4611 easy TH458/HS20-21","question":"What does genotype mean?","answer":"Genetic make up"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4612 easy TH458/HS20","question":"What does phenotype mean?","answer":"Outward appearance "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4613 easy HIH1040-3","question":"Are roan horses heterozygous or homozygous?","answer":"Heterozygous	 (additional info -- like with white horses, homozygous roan horses die in utero)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4614 easy HIH1020-1","question":"What is the study of how characteristics are passed from parents to offspring?","answer":"Genetics"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4615 easy HIH1020-1","question":"What are the units of inheritance?","answer":"Genes"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4616 easy HIH1060-1","question":"What do we need to be able to see chromosomes?","answer":"Microscope  "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4617 easy HIH1020-2","question":"What is the term used to describe the condition when a pair of genes are identical?","answer":"Homozygous "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4618 easy HIH1060-1","question":"What is the sex genotype for a mare?","answer":"XX"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4619 easy HIH1020-2","question":"If paired genes are not identical, they are called what?","answer":"Heterozygous"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4620 easy HIH1060-1/TH61","question":"How many chromosomes are responsible for the sex of a foal?","answer":"Two    (one pair)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4621 easy HIH1060-1","question":"What is the sex genotype of a stallion?","answer":"XY"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4622 easy HIH1060-4","question":"What do you call an abnormal condition that an animal possesses at birth?","answer":"Congenital"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4623 easy HIH1060-4","question":"Explain congenital.","answer":"An abnormal condition that an animal possesses at birth"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4624 easy HIH1060-1","question":"In the inheritance of sex in the horse, what are the chances for the foal to be male?","answer":"50 - 50"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4625 easy TH459/HS19","question":"A gene that does not show up when it's paired with a dominant gene is said to be what?","answer":"Recessive"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4626 easy HS19/TH458","question":"Which of the following is the dominant coat color ï¿½ black or chestnut?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4627 easy TH482/HIH1040-1","question":"Which color can cover up or mask colored areas of a horse?","answer":"White"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4628 easy HIH1060-1","question":"What is the general term for the X & Y chromosomes?","answer":"Sex chromosomes"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"easy","number":"4629 easy HIH1040-3","question":"What color foal will a homozygous gray produce?","answer":"Gray - no matter what color the other parent is"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4630 medium TH511","question":"What sex-linked disease results in a deficiency of clotting factor VIII? ","answer":"Hemophilia A	 (also accept Hemophilia) "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4631 medium HIH1070-1","question":"Although a horse may have the genetic potential to be large, fast or intelligent, 30-50% of the trait is due to what?","answer":"Environmental factors (such as feed, care, training & injuries - all of which can have an effect on the horse's overall quality)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4632 medium ADV335","question":"Define heredity.","answer":"Passing of traits from parents to offspring"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4633 medium TH57","question":"Is the curly coat of the American Bashkir Curly caused by a dominant or a recessive gene?          ","answer":"Recessive            "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4634 medium HIH1040-1","question":"In reference to coat color, what genes must a chestnut horse have?","answer":"Two recessive extension genes OR ï¿½eeï¿½ 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4635 medium HIH1040-1/ES94,95","question":"Name two genotypes of a black horse.","answer":"EE, Ee, aaEE, aaEe               "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4636 medium HIH1060-5","question":"Why are all dominant white horses heterozygous & not homozygous?","answer":"Homozygous white fetuses die before birth "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4637 medium HIH675-2","question":"Which Quarter Horse sire has been linked to the disorder HC (HERDA)?","answer":"Poco Bueno"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4638 medium TH462","question":"One pair of chromosomes is responsible for the sex of a foal.  The chromosomes are designated as XX & XY.  Which pair designates the stallion?","answer":"XY"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4639 medium ES87","question":"What is the common term for deoxyribonucleic acid?","answer":"DNA"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4640 medium ES87","question":"What does "diploid" mean?","answer":"A pair of chromosomes"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4641 medium TH454-58","question":"What is the difference between genotype & phenotype?","answer":"Genotype is the genetic makeup, phenotype is the outward appearance"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4642 medium TH482","question":"The perlino color is a double dilution of what color?","answer":"Bay"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4643 medium HIH1060-4","question":"CID (Combined Immunodeficiency) is an inherited disease of which breed?","answer":"Arabian or part Arab		(accept either)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4644 medium TH81","question":"2 part question:  What color results from a single cream dilution of bay & what color results from a double cream dilution of bay?   ","answer":"Single cream dilutionï¿½buckskin; double cream dilutionï¿½perlino      (addtl info:  dun is not a dilution ï¿½ caused by another gene) "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4645 medium TH511-13","question":"Homozygous pairing of the dominant genes for what 2 coat colors cause early embryonic death of the fetus?","answer":"White & roan"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4646 medium DET6/HIH1020-1","question":"What is an allele  (ah-LEEL)?","answer":"Gene pair"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4647 medium HS19","question":"What is the term for normal (somatic) cell division?","answer":"Mitosis"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4648 medium HIH1040-2","question":"Are the genes for coat color separate or combined with the gene loci for occurrence & pattern of white hairs on the body?","answer":"Separate"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4649 medium HIH1020-1","question":"Where is the genetic material carried?","answer":"In the nucleus in form of chromosomes    (accept nucleus, chromosomes, or DNA)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4650 medium HIH1060-3","question":"Are male or female horses primarily affected by genetic diseases that have an X-linked mode of inheritance?","answer":"Male horses"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4651 medium TH81","question":"Grulla is a dilution of what basic coat color?","answer":"Black    (addtl info - dun dilution of black)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4652 medium HS20","question":"Name the two types of cell division.","answer":"Mitosis & meiosis"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4653 medium ES95","question":"What does the agouti gene do?      ","answer":"Restricts the black pigmentation pattern to the points of the horse (mane, tail, lower leg, ear rims)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4654 medium ES95","question":"In reference to coat colors, what color modifier do the letters A/a represent?       ","answer":"Agouti        "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4655 medium TH458/HS20","question":"If you breed a heterozygous black stallion to a heterozygous black mare, what percentage of the foals may be red?","answer":"25%"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4656 medium HIH1020-1/ES87","question":"Genes are made up of complex molecules of what?            ","answer":"DNA"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4657 medium HIH1040-2","question":"The cream gene is a partially dominant gene which does what when combined with other color genes?","answer":"Lightens/ dilutes the color   "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4658 medium HS19","question":"What is the term for sex cell division?","answer":"Meiosis"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4659 medium HIH1020-1","question":"In what type of cells do chromosomes exist as singles, not pairs?","answer":"Egg & sperm cells	 (also accept -- gametes, or haploid cells)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4660 medium HIH1020-1","question":"Define nucleus.","answer":"Dense center of a cell that contains the genetic material"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4661 medium HIH1060-6","question":"How do you diagnose HYPP?","answer":"Genetic blood test OR by clinical signs & elevated blood potassium levels"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4662 medium HIH1060-6","question":"Which breed of horse carries the genetic disease HYPP?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4663 medium HIH1060-4","question":"What is inbreeding?","answer":"Breeding closely related animals"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4664 medium HIH1060-1","question":"If a sperm carrying the X chromosome fertilizes the egg, what sex will the foal be?","answer":"Female"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4665 medium HS21","question":"How many chromosomes do mules & hinnies have?","answer":"63"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4666 medium TH447","question":"Who was the first to work out how genetic material is transmitted from one generation to the next?","answer":"Gregor Mendel"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4667 medium TH462","question":"Which chromosome carries the genes for most sex-linked traits?","answer":"X"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4668 medium TH462","question":"Give an example of a sex-linked trait.","answer":"Hemophilia"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4669 medium ES94","question":"What 2 base colors are determined by the extension gene?","answer":"Black & red (chestnut)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4670 medium TH50","question":"Palomino is a single  cream dilution of what color?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4671 medium TH50","question":"A double cream dilution of chestnut results in what color?","answer":"Cremello"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4672 medium TH81","question":"What does dilution of color mean?","answer":"Lessening the intensity "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4673 medium TH81","question":"Cremello results from a double dilution of which base color?","answer":"Chestnut"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4674 medium TH81","question":"What color is a cream dilution of bay?","answer":"Buckskin "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4675 medium FCH297","question":"HYPP is found in which Quarter Horse line?","answer":"Impressive"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4676 medium TH473","question":"Which one of the following modifications of black does NOT have black points:  bay, seal brown, buckskin, dun, grulla, or perlino?  ","answer":"Perlino"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4677 medium HIH1060-6","question":"On what chromosome do you find the gene for hemophilia?","answer":"X"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4678 medium TH81","question":"What color is a single cream dilution of chestnut?","answer":"Palomino	"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4679 medium HIH1060-6","question":"Which lethal genetic defect can result from mating 2 overo Paint horses?","answer":"Lethal white foal syndrome (OLWS)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4680 medium HIH1020-1","question":"What are loci?","answer":"Specific locations of genes on a chromosome (singular is locus)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4682 medium TH51","question":"Palomino horses do not ï¿½breed trueï¿½.  What does this mean?         ","answer":"When breeding a palomino to a palomino only 50 percent will produce a palomino (also accept breeding a palomino to a palomino will not always result in a palomino)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4683 medium ES50","question":"What sensory deficit is often present in horses with the splashed white color pattern?","answer":"Deafness                       "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4684 medium TH490","question":"Tobiano and overo color patterns are both controlled by genes.  Which color pattern is displayed only if the genotype is homozygous  for the recessive gene?","answer":"Overo                               "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4685 medium ES43","question":"Identify one of the two colors that must be present in the genetic  lineage of a cream colored horse.                          ","answer":"Palomino or Buckskin"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4686 medium ES20","question":"How many chromosomes does a donkey have?","answer":"62           "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"medium","number":"4687 medium HIH1040-2","question":"What is the base color of a red silver horse?","answer":"Bay       "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4688 hard TH481","question":"Referring to color, what is the pangere effect?","answer":"Causes light areas of color on muzzle, over eyes, on flanks & inside the legs"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4690 hard HIH675-1","question":"Identify the following disease that primarily affects Quarter Horses:  superficial & deep layers of the skin separate resulting in "stretchy" skin that's easily damaged or torn.","answer":"HERDA (Hereditary Equine Regional Dermal Asthenia) OR HC (Hyperelastosis Cutis)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4691 hard HIH675-1","question":"This disease results in ï¿½stretchyï¿½ skin due to separation of the superficial & deep layers of the skin. What breed is affected by HERDA or HC?","answer":"Quarter Horse"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4692 hard HS20/ES88","question":"Explain how mitosis differs from meiosis.","answer":"Mitosis is normal cell division where each daughter cell receives an identical copy of the original chromosome pairs; meiosis is sex cell division where each daughter cell only receives half of each chromosome pair (haploid number of chromosomes)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4693 hard ES94","question":"What is an extension gene as relates to color genetics?","answer":"The gene that regulates the color differences in black-pigmented horses & red-pigmented horses "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4694 hard HIH1020-3","question":"What does the term ï¿½quantitative gene actionï¿½ mean?","answer":"Trait is controlled by several gene pairs.  "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4695 hard ADV335-2","question":"Define Heritability Estimate.","answer":"The percentage of the horseï¿½s expressed trait that is due to genetics OR the probability of that trait being passed from one generation to the next"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4696 hard HIH1080-1","question":"What does the term "nicking" mean?","answer":"When offspring has more superior qualities than expected by their pedigree"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4697 hard HIH675-1","question":"HERDA or HC is an inherited disorder that causes what?","answer":"Causes skin to be very stretchable, fragile & vulnerable to trauma"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4698 hard ES85","question":"What is gene mapping?","answer":"Determining & recording the identities & positions of genes"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4699 hard H3-10","question":"What is a punnet square?","answer":"Way of determining what percentage of offspring of a mating will have which genes of the parents"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4700 hard TH51","question":"You are planning to breed your chestnut mare & would love her to produce a palomino foal.  In order to guarantee a foal of this color, what color stallion should she be bred to?","answer":"Cremello"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4701 hard HIH1040-3,1095-1","question":"What genetic disease is associated with the frame overo pattern?","answer":"Lethal white foal syndrome or OLWS  "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4702 hard HIH1060-6/ES99","question":"Identify two of the four breeds of horses that are affected by the sex-linked disease Hemophilia ","answer":"Thoroughbred, Standardbred, Quarter Horse and Arabian"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4703 hard TH486","question":"What is the expected ratio of roan to solid colored foals if a heterozygous roan stallion is bred to a heterozygous roan mare?","answer":"2 roan to one solid   (50% would be roan, 25% would be solid & 25% homozygous roan fetus would die in utero)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4704 hard HIH1060-1/ES94","question":"What is the name of the special procedure used to visualize or examine chromosomes under a microscope?","answer":"Karyotyping"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4705 hard DET118","question":"What is the proper name for a mature sex cell?","answer":"Gamete"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4706 hard ADV335/HIH1020-2","question":"In genetics, what does the term ï¿½partial dominanceï¿½ mean?","answer":"A gene action resulting in an intermediate state between the 2 alleles
(additional info ï¿½ a single dominant cream gene doesnï¿½t make a chestnut cremello)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4707 hard HIH1040-2","question":"Genetically, what is the difference between a buckskin & a dun?","answer":"Buckskin is a cream dilution of bay & dun is a dun dilution of bay."},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4708 hard HIH1060-3","question":"2 part question:   If a mare is a carrier for an X-linked genetic disease, what percent of her male foals will be affected with the disease and what percent of her female foals will be carriers?","answer":"50% males will be affected and 50% of females will be carriers"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4709 hard TH490","question":"Name the color pattern on a Pinto horse whose genetic color code for dominant white is at the T locus.","answer":"Tobiano"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4710 hard HIH1020-1","question":"Where is the location of the cytoplasm?","answer":"Between the nucleus & the cell wall"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4711 hard HIH1040-3","question":"2 part question:  What gene is responsible for the roan color & what letters represent it?","answer":"Roaning gene;   R/r"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4712 hard HIH1020","question":"What would be the difference in the offspring from a homozygous black stallion & a heterozygous black stallion when mated with a chestnut or brown mare?","answer":"All the foals from the homozygous black stallion would be black.  Half the foals from the heterozygous black stallion would be black & half would be chestnut."},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4713 hard HIH1040-1","question":"What gene must be present to produce the color bay?","answer":"Dominant agouti 	(additional info -- dominant agouti modification of black)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4714 hard HIH1060-5/335-3/ES99","question":"What term is used to describe the genetic disease characterized by the failure of the immune system to form?","answer":"Combined Immunodeficiency (CID) OR Severe Combined Immunodeficiency (SCID)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4715 hard HIH1060-6","question":"What causes foals with lethal white syndrome do die?  ","answer":"Failure of nerves in the gastrointestinal tract to develop   (ileocolonic aganglionosis)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4716 hard HIH1020-1","question":"What is a chromosome?","answer":"Long, thread-like structure in the nucleus of a cell that contains genetic material"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4717 hard HS25","question":"The genetic material of the sperm cell is contained in which part of the cell?","answer":"Head section"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4718 hard FCH298/HIH1060-6","question":"A horse with what genetic disease would benefit from a diet that is low in potassium?","answer":"HYPP or Hyperkalemic Periodic Paralysis	 (also accept PIPP or Potassium Induced Periodic Paralysis)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4719 hard HIH1040-2","question":"Give an example of partial or incomplete dominance where the dominant gene is not fully expressed.","answer":"Cream dilution in a palomino"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4720 hard ADV335/HIH1020-2","question":"In genetics, what does the term "co-dominance" mean?","answer":"When the 2 alleles are equally dominant  
( additional info ï¿½ example:  like  some color genes or genes for straight/curly hair)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4721 hard HIH1020-3","question":"When a number of genes are required to produce a trait, what type of gene action is this considered?","answer":"Quantitative"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4722 hard HIH1060-1","question":"What is a genetic disease?","answer":"One that's a result of a DNA mutation & can be passed on to offspring"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4723 hard TH539","question":"What do you call the form of inbreeding that's aimed at trying to maintain a close relationship with a particular animal?","answer":"Line breeding"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4724 hard TH555","question":"2 part question:  What is a quantitative trait & give an example?","answer":"Trait influenced by many genes; examples ï¿½ speed, cow sense, jumping ability, etc."},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4725 hard DET198","question":"What is outcrossing?","answer":"Mating animals that are members of the same breed, but which show no relationship close up in the pedigree"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4726 hard TH483","question":"The gene for what color is located at the G locus?","answer":"Dominant gray (gray)"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4727 hard TH481","question":"Light areas of color over the eyes, on the muzzle, flanks and inside the legs are seen with influence of what color gene?","answer":"Pangere                   "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4728 hard ES93","question":"Which type of melanin controls the expression of red & yellow pigment?","answer":"Pheomelanin               	"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4729 hard HIH1095-1","question":"What do the initials OLWS refer to?","answer":"Overo Lethal White syndrome           "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"hard","number":"4730 hard ES100","question":"Aniridia is a genetic disorder in which the iris of the eye is absent.  This occurs primarily in which horse breed?","answer":"Belgian                              "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4731 bonus HIH1020-1","question":"A horse's characteristics are due to 2 things.  Name them.","answer":"Heredity & environment"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4732 bonus HS19/ES88","question":"Explain 3 steps of mitosis.","answer":"1) Chromosomes duplicate,		 2) chromosomes line up in the middle of the cell, 	
3) chromosomes pull a part, 		4) cells start to divide,
5) cell division completes with each daughter cell receiving a complete copy of the chromosomes"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4733 bonus HIH1040-2","question":"Genetically, name 3 ways a black coat color be modified.","answer":"Dilutions such as cream or dun, spotting such as Overo or Tobiano, gray, roan, bay (agouti) "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4734 bonus HIH1090","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered when selecting breeding stock.","answer":"Conformation, breeding/pedigree, disposition, size, individual performance records, progeny records"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4735 bonus TH51","question":"If a palomino mare were mated to a palomino stallion, what percentage of foals would be what color?","answer":"50% palomino, 25% cremello, & 25% chestnut"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4736 bonus TH473","question":"Name 3 coat colors whose base color is black with a dilution, modification, white pattern, etc.","answer":"Bay (agouti modification),			 seal brown (agouti modification) 	
buckskin (single cream dilution of bay),		 perlino (double cream dilution of bay),
dun (dun dilution of bay), 			grulla (dun dilution of black),
gray (gray modification), 			smoky black (single cream dilution of black),
smoky cream (double cream dilution of black), blue roan"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4737 bonus HIH1020-1","question":"Name 3 things other than genetic-makeup that may affect a horse's potential.","answer":"Care, feeding, training, injuries"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4738 bonus HIH1020-2","question":"Define the 2 basic types of genetic action","answer":"Qualitative - trait influenced by 1-3 pairs of genes
Qualitative - trait influenced by 1-3 pairs of genes; Quantitative - trait influenced by a number of genes"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4739 bonus HIH153","question":"Define 3 of the following terms:  outcrossing, grading up, crossbreeding, inbreeding, & line-breeding.","answer":"Outcrossing ï¿½ mating of animals from different families within the same breed;
Grading up ï¿½ mating animal with unknown ancestry with registered animal;
Crossbreedingï¿½mating registered animals of different breeds;
Inbreedingï¿½mating of animals more closely related than average;
Line-breedingï¿½selective breeding along a certain genetic line to perpetuate certain desirable qualities."},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4740 bonus TH458-59/HIH1020-2","question":"In traits affected by qualitative gene action there are 3 primary types of gene action that affect the trait.  Name them","answer":"Dominance, co-dominance, partial dominance"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4741 bonus HIH1020-2","question":"Name 3 traits of horses that are influenced by many genes.","answer":"Conformation, temperament, physical performance, size, muscularity, longevity"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4742 bonus ADV335","question":"Name 3 genetic diseases in horses.","answer":"SCID (Severe Combined Immunodeficiencyï¿½Arabians), 
HYPP (Hyperkalemic Periodic Paralysisï¿½Quarter Horses)
HERDA (Hereditary Equine Regional Dermal Asthenia (formerly called Hyperelastosis Cutisï¿½Quarter Horses),
OLWS (Overo Lethal White Syndromeï¿½Paints),
GBED (Glycogen Branching Enzyme Deficiencyï¿½Quarter Horses & Paints),
JEB (Junctional Epidermolysis Bullosaï¿½Belgians),
CSNB (Congenital Stationary Night Blindnessï¿½Appaloosas),
ERU (Equine Recurrent Uveitisï¿½Appaloosas),
Hemophilia A (sex-linked trait seen in males),
RER (Recurrent Exertional Rhabdomyolysisï¿½Thoroughbreds),
Roaring (Laryngeal Hemiplegiaï¿½Thoroughbreds)
Do not need to give the breed ï¿½ accept either acronym or scientific name"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4743 bonus HS18","question":"Tell how many pairs of chromosomes each of the following farm animals has ï¿½ horses, cattle, goats","answer":"Horses ï¿½ 32, cattle ï¿½ 30, goats - 30"},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4744 bonus HIH1040-2","question":"What specific color would be the result of a single dilution of the following 3 colors with the dominant dilution gene ----- black, bay & chestnut?","answer":"Black ï¿½ grulla      Bay ï¿½ zebra dun       Chestnut ï¿½ red dun or claybank dun        "},
{"category":"GENETICS","level":"bonus","number":"4745 bonus HIH1040-2		","question":"What color would be the result of the silver dapple gene on the following three colorsï¿½black, bay and chestnut?				","answer":"Black ï¿½ Blue silver or silver dapple   Bay ï¿½ Red silver   Chestnut ï¿½ Chestnut (silver gene only affects black areas)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4746 easy DET34/HH38","question":"What is the name for the soft brush with fine bristles that's used to give a finishing touch?","answer":"Body brush (soft brush)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4747 easy HH39","question":"How long an area is clipped for the bridle path?","answer":"1-1/2 to 8 inches depending on the breed & style of riding           (accept anything within range)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4748 easy HH36","question":"Why should you follow the same procedure each time when cleaning your horseï¿½s feet?","answer":"So the horse will know what to expect"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4749 easy HIH1150-3","question":"When applying a wrap to a horse's tail, why is it important not to pull the wrap too tight?","answer":"You can cut off circulation to the tail"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4750 easy HH39","question":"Give a reason why you would clip your horseï¿½s legs a couple of weeks before a show.","answer":"To avoid clipper lines or contrasting colors  "},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4751 easy DET34/HH38","question":"What does it mean to body clip a horse?","answer":"Clipping the horse's entire body"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4752 easy HH28","question":"When picking out a hoof, what part of the hoof do you start on?	","answer":"Heel"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4753 easy HH23","question":"Why is it a good practice to walk your horse for the last half mile on a ride?","answer":"To cool him out"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4754 easy HH30","question":"To obtain a neat look, which way should you run clippersï¿½against the hair or with the natural lay?","answer":"With the natural lay"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4755 easy HH37","question":"What motion is most effective when currying?","answer":"Circular"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4756 easy HH37","question":"What type strokes will remove the most dirt when using a stiff brush (dandy brush)?","answer":"Short/strong strokes with outward motion away from the body     (flicking outward)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4757 easy HH35","question":"What is the method by which you thin a tail?","answer":"Pulling"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4758 easy DET77/HH37","question":"What grooming tool is a hard-bristled brush used to remove excess hair & loose dirt?","answer":"Dandy brush (stiff brush)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4759 easy HH40","question":"What is the term used when describing cutting the bones of the tail in order to shorten it?","answer":"Docked or docking"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4760 easy DET235, 141","question":"Referring to grooming, what is roached?","answer":"When the mane is clipped close to the skin     (short cut mane ï¿½ less than 3ï¿½ long)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4761 easy HH35","question":"When should you groom a horse that's going to be exercised or worked?","answer":"Both before & after the workout"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4762 easy DET39/HH39","question":"What is the name for the section of mane at the poll that's trimmed or clipped to allow space for a halter or bridle to rest?","answer":"Bridle path"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4763 easy HH38	","question":"How can you avoid a dull, sunburned appearance of your horse's coat?","answer":"Put him in the stable during the sunniest part of the day OR turn him out to pasture only in the early morning & late evening		(accept either)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4764 easy HH8","question":"What is the term for rough, harsh appearance?","answer":"Coarse"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4765 easy HIH535-2","question":"What is the name for the piece of equipment that's used to clean out a horse's foot?","answer":"Hoof pick		"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4766 easy HH35/FCH180","question":"What practice most helps the appearance of the horse's coat?","answer":"Frequent, thorough grooming"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4767 easy H5-11","question":"How can bathing your horse dull his coat?","answer":"Removes the skin's natural oils"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4768 easy HH37/DET75","question":"What grooming tool is used in a circular motion to loosen hair & dirt?","answer":"Curry comb"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4770 easy HH35","question":"What is a banged tail?","answer":"Hair cut straight off below the dock/bony part of the tail"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4771 easy HH7/TH83","question":"What is a rat-tailed horse?","answer":"Horse having little hair in its tail"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4772 easy HH35","question":"What is the only purpose for which you would use a metal currycomb?","answer":"To remove thick/dry mud or heavy/loose hair"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4773 easy HIH710-7","question":"Besides walking, what can you do to help cool out a horse?","answer":"Give him a couple swallows of water every few minutes (also accept sponge him down or spray him with a hose)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4774 easy HIH420-3","question":"Why is it recommended to groom a horse thoroughly before saddling?","answer":""},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4775 easy HH35","question":"What do you call a person who cleans & brushes horses?","answer":"Groom"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4776 easy HH35/DET141,235","question":"What does hogged mean?","answer":"Short cut mane	 
Addtl info --   Hogged mane is clipped to a length of no more than 3 inches;
Roached mane is clipped close to the skin"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4777 easy HIH710-7","question":"If you've ridden your horse hard, when should you let him have his fill of water?","answer":"After he's cooled out"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4778 easy HH39","question":"Referring to grooming, what is a bridlepath?","answer":"Clipped area behind the ears where the crownpiece of the bridle goes"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4779 easy HH35","question":"What function does the body brush (soft brush) serve?","answer":"Removes last particles of dust or adds oil to the coat  "},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4780 easy HH36","question":"What do you call a horse that's neither hot to the touch nor breathing hard after he's been exercised?","answer":"Cooled out"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4781 easy HIH1100-12","question":"What type of brush is best for sensitive areas of the face & legs?","answer":"Soft"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4782 easy HIH420-3","question":"Why should you brush the horse's belly in the area of the saddle cinch?","answer":"To remove dirt that might cause sores"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4783 easy HH37","question":"In grooming a horse, in what direction should the hair be brushed?","answer":"In the direction of its natural lay	(in the direction it grows)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4784 easy H2-34/DET75","question":"Define the term "curry".","answer":"To rub down or clean the horse's coat (also a type of rubber or metal brush used to remove deep dirt & loose hair)		(Accept either)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4785 easy H4-26 picture","question":"When braiding a horse's mane & tail, how many sections should be worked with at one time?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4786 easy H2-27/TH719","question":"What is the proper procedure for using a hoof pick?","answer":"Heel to toe"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4787 easy HH37","question":"What is a rubber currycomb used for?","answer":"Remove deep dirt, loose hair, saddle marks, or mud"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4788 easy HH38","question":"What grooming aid is used to remove excess water after washing your horse?","answer":"Sweat scraper"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4789 easy HH38","question":"In grooming a horse, where is the currycomb NEVER used?","answer":"Over the bony areas (head, below knees or hocks/lower legs)          (accept either general or specific)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4790 easy HH35","question":"Which grooming tool roughs up the hair to remove the deep dirt?","answer":"Currycomb"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4791 easy HH37","question":"How can you remove caked mud & manure from the hoof wall?","answer":"Wash with water & stiff brush OR use hoof brush"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4792 easy HIH1100-13,14","question":"Name 3 grooming tools.","answer":"Hoof pick, mane & tail comb, sweat scraper, grooming cloth, currycomb, dandy brush/hard brush, 
body brush/soft brush, clippers, etc."},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4793 easy HH37","question":"How do you clean the currycomb when grooming?","answer":"Strike it on something hard        (back of brush, boot heel, or post)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4794 easy HH35","question":"Ideally, how often should horses be groomed?","answer":"Daily"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4795 easy HH35","question":"What do you call a tail that's been shortened or thinned by pulling?","answer":"Pulled tail"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4796 easy DET77/HH37","question":"2 part question:  What is a dandy brush & what is it used for?","answer":"Stiff brush used to remove loose hair & dirt"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4797 easy HH38","question":"If you body-clip your horse, what should be done in cold weather?","answer":"Blanket horse or keep him in stable"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4798 easy H2-27","question":"Why should you NOT use a currycomb on your horse's face or legs?","answer":"You might hurt him   (there's less muscle to protect horse from injury)   	(accept either)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4799 easy HH38","question":"What is meant by "picking out" a mane or tail?","answer":"Separating the hairs with your fingers to keep them from tangling"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4800 easy HH39","question":"How far down the tail is a hunter's tail braided?","answer":"8 - 12 inches        (accept any number within this range)		"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4801 easy HH36","question":"In what order should you clean your horse's feet?","answer":"Counter clockwise (near fore, near hind, off hind, off fore)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"easy","number":"4802 easy TH675","question":"How do horses naturally groom themselves?","answer":"Mutual grooming OR rolling"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4803 medium DET30","question":"When a horse has a blanket clip, which body parts are left unclipped?","answer":"Head, neck & legs       (just the blanket area is clipped)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4804 medium HH39","question":"Describe how to pluck or pull a mane.  ","answer":"Begin on underside of mane with the longest hairs.  Grasp a few strands of hair close to the roots & jerk sharply removing hair & roots"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4805 medium TH129/FCH382","question":"What is the term that refers to hair that's clean & glossy, denoting a healthy appearance?","answer":"Bloom"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4806 medium HH39","question":"When clipping a horse during the winter, why is it advisable to leave an unclipped area for the saddle blanket?","answer":"Gives protection from abrasions / wearing the hair away on the back under the saddle     (accept either)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4807 medium HH39","question":"What determines the style of the mane & tail of a horse that's being exhibited?","answer":"Breed of horse and/or what type of classes itï¿½s being shown in"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4808 medium HH30","question":"Why is the hair clipped around the fetlock joints?","answer":"To give the legs a neater, cleaner appearance"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4809 medium TH63-64, DET141,235","question":"About how long is a hogged mane?","answer":"Three inches or less        
Addtl info --   roached mane is clipped close to the skin"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4810 medium FCH382","question":"In reference to horses, what is meant by the term "bloom"?","answer":"Glossy, healthy looking hair coat OR luster/shine to coat"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4811 medium HH29","question":"Name the final touch to the horse's appearance before entering the show ring.","answer":"Going over the coat with a grooming cloth"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"medium","number":"4812 medium DET950","question":"Clipping along the belly, under the neck & above the thigh is known as what type of body clip?","answer":"Trace clip                 "},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"hard","number":"4813 hard HH29","question":"How is the mane & tail of an Arabian prepared for a show?","answer":"Washed & left full"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"hard","number":"4814 hard HH30","question":"Why do some gaited saddle horses have their bridle paths trimmed down the neck 6-7 inches?","answer":"To make the horse's neck look longer & finer through the throatlatch"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"hard","number":"4815 hard TH63","question":"What is the difference in the traditional grooming presentation of a Hackney Pony shown in harness versus a Hackney class?","answer":"Ponies are shown with a cob-tail in Hackney class & a long tail in a harness class        "},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4816 bonus HH38","question":"What are 3 effects of hand rubbing your horse?","answer":"Brings out the bloom/shine, stimulates circulation, massages tired muscles, feels good to the horse, helps you bond with your horse"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4817 bonus DETvarious","question":"Name 3 types of clips used in grooming horses.","answer":"Blanket clip, trace clip, body clip, hunter clip"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4818 bonus HH36-38","question":"Name 5 important steps in grooming a horse.","answer":"Use curry comb on non-bony parts of body, use stiff brush, use body brush, use grooming cloth, groom horseï¿½s body before riding, clean feet, comb mane & tail, cool horse out after exercise, groom, sponge or hose horse after exercise"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4819 bonus HH39","question":"What are 3 areas of the Western stock horse that are usually clipped for a show?","answer":"Muzzle, under chin, under jaw, bridle path, ears, long hairs around eyes, below knees & hocks"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4820 bonus HH36","question":"Name 3 uses of a grooming cloth.","answer":"Polish coat, dry off wet horse, & wipe around eyes, nostrils, lips, dock, sheath"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4821 bonus HH35-56/HIH1100-13,14","question":"Name 3 grooming tools & their purpose.","answer":"Curry comb roughs up hair to remove deep dirt; dandy or stiff brush removes dirt; body or finishing brush removes last particles of dust & brings out natural oils; soft or face brush brushes face; mane & tail comb combs mane & tail; hoof pick cleans hooves; sweat scraper removes extra water; clippers trim hair (accept any reasonable answers)"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4822 bonus HH35","question":"Name 3 benefits of grooming your horse.","answer":"Improves appearance, cleans hair & skin, brings out natural oils in skin, prevents skin problems, looks for skin problems, massages muscles, increases circulation, removes dirt & external parasites, improves muscle condition"},
{"category":"GROOMING","level":"bonus","number":"4823 bonus HH35","question":"When brushing a horse, what are the last 3 parts to be brushed?","answer":"Head, mane & tail"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4824 easy HIH440-3","question":"What is the difference between a closed & an open wound?","answer":"Closed wound - skin is intact;    open wound ï¿½ skin is broken"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4826 easy HIH440-2/TH609","question":"Name 2 benefits of hosing a leg wound with cold water.","answer":"Cleans wound, decreases swelling, decreases pain, controls bleeding"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4827 easy HIH790-1","question":"Name a reason - other than being overfed - that horses or ponies might get fat.","answer":"High grain diet, unlimited pasture, lack of exercise, easy keepers, Cushing's disease"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4828 easy HIH440-5","question":"All eye injuries should be treated as what?","answer":"Emergencies ï¿½ call the vet!"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4829 easy HIH445-1","question":"Name a good reason for keeping your horse first aid kit in a small waterproof box.","answer":"Supplies stay clean/dry OR it can be taken with the horse when it travels from home"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4830 easy HIH440-5","question":"Name a cause of electric shock in horses.","answer":"Lightning, contact with overhead cables/wires, contact with wire fencing, contact with other sources of electric current (especially if the ground is wet)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4831 easy HIH440-4","question":"What does an anti-inflammatory drug do?","answer":"Reduce pain, swelling, and/or inflammation		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4832 easy HIH440-2","question":"What is the best way to initially clean a large wound that's contaminated with dirt?","answer":"Hosing with water"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4833 easy HIH440-3","question":"What is the biggest danger with puncture wounds?","answer":"Infection	 (also accept ï¿½ tetanus)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4834 easy HIH410-1","question":"What is the quickest way to cool an overheated horse?","answer":"Spray with cool/cold water"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4835 easy HIH410-1","question":"Which is more serious, heat exhaustion or heat stroke?","answer":"Heat stroke"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4836 easy HIH420-3","question":"After riding your horse in winter, you should cool him off & dry him thoroughly.  If you leave him with a wet coat, what can happen?","answer":"Catch cold or pneumonia"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4837 easy HIH420-3","question":"In winter, snow or ice accumulating in hooves can cause what?","answer":"Pain or unstable footing"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4838 easy HIH465-2","question":"What is the main result of a blocked tear duct on a horse?","answer":"Wet face (tears don't drain through tear duct & they spill out over face)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4839 easy HIH465-2","question":"With eye problems in the horse, redness of the eye indicates inflammation.  What does closing the eye indicat?","answer":"Pain"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4840 easy HIH420-1","question":"When determining body condition in the winter, it's easy to be misled by what?","answer":"Heavy coat (long hair)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4841 easy HIH350-2","question":"Name the health factor you must consider when purchasing paint or stain for horse stalls or fences.","answer":"Must be non-toxic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4842 easy HIH895-1/CAHA67","question":"What is the definition of respiratory frequency?","answer":"Number of breaths horse takes in a minute"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4843 easy HIH425-2/CAHA68","question":"What is the normal color of a horse's urine?","answer":"Clear yellow to orange"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4844 easy HIH540a/ADV334-2","question":"What is the first step in treating an abscess?","answer":"Open abscess so it can drain"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4845 easy HIH450-3/FCH381","question":"What is arthritis?","answer":"Inflammation of a joint"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4846 easy HIH440-2","question":"What is an abrasion?","answer":"Scrape  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4847 easy HIH790-1","question":"To help your horse lose weight, you need to do what?","answer":"Increase exercise OR reduce calories	   (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4848 easy HIH440-2","question":"After hosing a wound, what should you do next?","answer":"Clean with a mild antiseptic 	   (also accept bandage)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4849 easy HIH440-2","question":"Why should you clip the hair around a wound before cleaning it?","answer":"So the hair doesn't get into the wound"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4850 easy HIH635/435","question":"Name 2 symptoms of colic.","answer":"Pawing, rolling, turning head to side, stomping with back feet, kicking or biting at flanks, excessive sweating, wanting to lie down, depression, increased or decreased gut sounds, bloating, increased or decreased heart rate, change in manure appearance or lack of defecation, grinding teeth, laying on back"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4851 easy HIH710-2","question":"Absence of gut sounds may indicate what?","answer":"Colic or a lack of normal cecal activity	(accept either)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4852 easy HIH445-16","question":"In general, foals born to previously vaccinated mares would begin receiving routine vaccinations at what age?","answer":"6 months of age "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4853 easy HIH790-1","question":"Give one reason why you should know your horse's weight.","answer":"Know how much to feed your horse, know how much wormer to give your horse, OR know how much medicine to give your horse  	(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4854 easy HIH755-1","question":"What do the initials BCS stand for?","answer":"Body condition scoring"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4955 easy HIH735-1","question":"What is the ideal body condition score for most horses?","answer":"4-6 		(accept any within this range)  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4856 easy HIH635-2","question":"Name two of the most common causes of colic.","answer":"Lack of water, dietary changes, lack of exercise, parasites, bad teeth,  Moldy feed, overfeeding,  letting overheated horse gorge on cold water, riding hard after full feeding, twisted/telescoped intestine, blockage of intestine, enterolith, sand,  high grain diet, 
(accept any correct answer)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4857 easy HIH420-3","question":"While you might not feel much like riding in winter, limiting a horse's exercise can lead to what?","answer":"Lose cardiovascular fitness, lose muscle tone, become stiff or lame, colic, stocking up, become nervous, develop stable vices, gain weight  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4858 easy TH306/HS38/HIH","question":"What is another name for Azoturia?","answer":"Monday morning sickness OR tying up (also accept black water disease or extertional rhabdomyolysis)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4859 easy HIH420-3","question":"At a minimum, horses should be ridden or turned out to free exercise how often?","answer":"At least once daily"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4860 easy TH306/HS38","question":"What is another name for Monday Morning Sickness?","answer":"Azoturia OR tying up      (also accept black water disease or extertional rhabdomyolysis)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4861 easy HIH440-2","question":"What is the best way to control bleeding of a leg wound?","answer":"Apply pressure"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4862 easy HS45,46/DET282","question":"Who is trained & skilled in the treating of diseases & injuries of animals?","answer":"Veterinarian"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4863 easy HIH1150","question":"What is the best way to prevent dehydration?","answer":"Make sure your horse is drinking enough water"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4864 easy HIH425-1","question":"How do you check for dehydration in a horse?","answer":"Pull skin back - if it flaps back into place, horse isn't dehydrated"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4865 easy HIH720-1","question":"How is a tape used to estimate the weight of a horse?","answer":"Measure heart girth on a marked tape"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4866 easy HIH440-2","question":"If blood is spurting from a wound, is it an artery or vein?","answer":"Artery"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4867 easy HIH440-1","question":"What type wound has clean, straight edges & often bleeds quite profusely?","answer":"Incision   "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4868 easy HIH440-1","question":"What type of wound would a nail cause?","answer":"Puncture"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4869 easy HIH440-2","question":"Which is more serious, cutting an artery or a vein?","answer":"Artery"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4870 easy HIH440-2","question":"Your horse has been injured & is bleeding.  How would you know if an artery was involved?","answer":"Bright red blood spurting from the wound"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4871 easy HIH425-2","question":"What is the term for the condition in which water is lost from the body faster than it's taken in?","answer":"Dehydration"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4872 easy HIH1160-1","question":"What is the purpose of a pressure bandage?","answer":"Control bleeding"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4873 easy HIH435-1,795-1","question":"What is colic?","answer":"Acute abdominal pain"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4874 easy HIH435-1,795-1","question":"What is the common name for abdominal pain in horses?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4875 easy HIH435-3","question":"What is the most common medical emergency in horses?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4876 easy DET167/HIH1160-1","question":"Why would you use leg wraps or bandages while traveling?","answer":"To protect the legs, to prevent swelling, or to prevent fatigue      (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4877 easy HIH440-4","question":"Name a treatment for a contusion.  ","answer":"Ice packs or cold hosing; compression/wrap leg; rest; later may apply heat to encourage absorption of excess fluid"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4878 easy HH9","question":"What is the term for the condition of a horse that is healthy, active & vigorous?","answer":"Thrifty"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4879 easy HIH425-1","question":"What does TPR stand for?","answer":"Temperature, Pulse, Respiration"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4880 easy HIH425-1/H1-29/ES155/DET223","question":"What is the normal pulse rate of an average-sized horse?","answer":"28 - 40 beats per minute	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4881 easy HIH425-1,440-6,410-1/ES155","question":"What is the normal temperature of a horse?","answer":"99 - 101.5 degrees		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4882 easy HIH425-1/ES155","question":"What is the normal respiration rate of an average-sized horse?","answer":"8 - 16 breaths per minute		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4883 easy HIH450-1","question":"How many years of an equine's life are equal to one year of a human's life?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4884 easy HIH440-1/TH608/DET155","question":"What is a puncture wound?","answer":"Wound that is deep & that has a small skin opening "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4885 easy HIH440-5","question":"What is a contusion?","answer":"Bruise (closed wound resulting from blunt force - causing hemorrhage, bruising & edema without breaking the skin)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4886 easy HIH440-2/TH608","question":"What term describes the type of wound caused by a rope burn or poorly fitted tack?","answer":"Abrasion"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4887 easy HIH440-6","question":"What type scissors are best for cutting hair away from a wound?","answer":"Blunt end ones or bandage scissors"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4888 easy HIH440-4","question":"A common complication in the healing of leg wounds is the development of what?","answer":"Proud flesh"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4889 easy HIH440-1/TH608","question":"What is the term for a wound with clean, straight edges that's caused by a sharp object?","answer":"Incision         (may accept ï¿½cutï¿½ from juniors)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4890 easy HIH440-3/TH608","question":"What type of wound would be caused by barbed wire?","answer":"Laceration"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4891 easy HIH440-4/TH609","question":"Why should you not use cotton or material with loose fibers to wrap a wound?","answer":"Sticks to wound"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4892 easy HIH425-2/FCH200","question":"Skin pliability is a test for what?","answer":"Dehydration"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4893 easy HIH425-2/FCH6,7","question":"Define dehydration.	","answer":"Condition of the body where more water is lost than is taken in	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4894 easy HIH440-3/TH608","question":"Which type of wound can be identified by torn & irregular edges?","answer":"Laceration	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4895 easy HIH445-3","question":"How often should horses be immunized for tetanus, Eastern & Western Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Annually"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4896 easy HIH720-1","question":"What is the most accurate way to weigh your horse?","answer":"Scales"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4897 easy HIH440-6/FCH406","question":"With what instrument is the temperature of a horse taken?","answer":"Thermometer	 (additional info -- temperature is taken rectally)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4898 easy HIH410-1","question":"Name a complication of heat stroke.","answer":"Death, coma, seizures, heart arrhythmias, kidney damage, muscle damage    (accept any)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4899 easy HIH425-1","question":"In what season are upper respiratory infections more common?","answer":"Winter"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4900 easy HIH635-1","question":"What should you do if you think your horse has colic?","answer":"Call the vet"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4901 easy HIH435-3","question":"Name one way to prevent colic.","answer":"Good feeding practices  (accept any reasonable answer);  control parasites,  take care of horseï¿½s teeth"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4902 easy HIH440-1","question":"Puncture wounds always require the administration of what?","answer":"Tetanus vaccination or booster"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4903 easy INT228-1","question":"What is the most common & mildest type of colic in horses?","answer":"Spasmodic or gas colic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4904 easy HIH425-1","question":"Why is it necessary to know the normal parameters for your horse's vital signs & behavior?","answer":"So you'll know when something's wrong "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4905 easy HIH710-7","question":"Under NORMAL conditions, what is the best way to replenish your horse's electrolytes?","answer":"Provide him with a salt block or salt/mineral block"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4906 easy HIH210-5","question":"What is the general purpose of a pre-purchase exam?","answer":"To determine the overall soundness/health"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4907 easy HIH450-5","question":"What problem, characterized by inflammation of a joint, is more common in older horses?","answer":"Arthritis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4908 easy HIH450-5","question":"In what weather conditions is arthritis more severe?","answer":"Cold & wet"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4909 easy HIH1160-1","question":"Give one purpose of the outer bandage layer.","answer":"Holds other layers in place OR keeps other layers clean"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4910 easy HIH1160-3","question":"What is the key to applying a good bandage?","answer":"Practice"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4911 easy HIH710-4","question":"A horse with a body condition score of 9 would be considered to be what?","answer":"Obese or extremely fat"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4912 easy INT224-3","question":"What is the purpose of a flexion test?","answer":"To determine the flexibility of a joint  or to detect lameness"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4913 easy HIH625-2","question":"What is necessary for the prevention of Eastern, Western & Venezuelan Encephalomyelitis?","answer":"Vaccinate horses OR use insecticides & repellents   "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4915 easy H3-17","question":"What is the number one cause of premature death in horses?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4916 easy HIH445-1","question":"How many doses of a vaccine are initially needed to get an adequate immune response?","answer":"Two"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4917 easy HIH450-1","question":"How old is a 20 year old mare in human years?","answer":"60 years old"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4918 easy HIH440-3/TH609","question":"Describe a laceration.","answer":"Jagged tear in skin (edges are torn & irregular)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4919 easy HIH860-1","question":"What mammal other than a horse cools itself primarily by sweating?","answer":"Man"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4920 easy H2-34/FCH338","question":"What does the term "emaciated" mean?","answer":"Extremely thin  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4921 easy HIH605-1","question":"What may occur following severe pneumonia?","answer":"Death"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4922 easy TH210","question":"What can using the body condition scoring system tell you about your horse?","answer":"If itï¿½s too fat, too skinny, or just right     (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"easy","number":"4923 easy HIH1160-1","question":"Name one requirement for the primary or contact bandage layer.","answer":"Non-stick, non-irritating, stays in place, permits absorption  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4924 medium TH116","question":"What is an arrhythmia?","answer":"Irregular heartbeat"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4925 medium TH609","question":"What does hemorrhaging mean?","answer":"Uncontrolled bleeding"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4926 medium DET212","question":"What is the common name for conjunctivitis where the cornea of the eye becomes red & inflamed?","answer":"Pink eye"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4927 medium TH609","question":"2 part question:  Your horse has just sustained a laceration to the leg & it is bleeding profusely. Your veterinarian has been contacted & is coming. Name 2 things you should do prior to the arrival of your veterinarian.   ","answer":"Control bleeding & keep the wound clean"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4928 medium FCH382","question":"What is the slang term for a horse that bleeds from the lungs due to strenuous physical exertion?","answer":"Bleeder"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4929 medium HS38","question":"List 2 things that can be done to prevent azoturia.","answer":"Decrease grain when not working, provide exercise when not working, warm up slowly & carefully after time off work"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4930 medium DET117","question":"What is the term for an open sore that forms just behind a horseï¿½s elbow?","answer":"Girth gall	 (also accept abrasion or saddle sore)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4931 medium HIH440-4","question":"What is proud flesh?","answer":"Excess granulation tissue"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4932 medium DET35","question":"Medically speaking, what is a "booster"?","answer":"Second or subsequent dose of a vaccine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4933 medium DET59","question":"What is the term used for a diagnosis based on signs or symptoms?","answer":"Clinical diagnosis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4934 medium HIH460-1,795-4","question":"Horses that develop firm back & hindquarter muscles after exercise (to the point where they are unable to move) are said to be suffering from what?","answer":"Tying up	 (also accept Azoturia, Monday Morning Sickness, exertional rhabdomyolysis, chronic intermittent rhabdomyolysis)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4935 medium HIH435-2","question":"Which type of colic can be rapidly fatal & requires prompt diagnosis & treatment?","answer":"Displacement, incarceration, volvulus/torsion, intussusception	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4936 medium HIH435-1","question":"What is spasmodic colic?","answer":"Muscular spasms of the intestinal tract"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4937 medium HIH635-4","question":"Simple colic can often be treated how?","answer":"Administering a pain reliever & a laxative  (also - walking, fluids)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4938 medium FCH393","question":"What is the prefix which means below normal?","answer":"Hypo"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4939 medium DET137","question":"2 part question:  What is a hematoma & what causes it?","answer":"Abnormal collection of blood in body tissues; caused by trauma or by blood vessel injury"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4940 medium FCH401","question":"If a horse is experiencing renal failure, what part of his body isn't functioning properly?","answer":"Kidneys"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4941 medium FCH406","question":"What is the general term for inflammation of a tendon?","answer":"Tendonitis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4942 medium FCH400","question":"What is the term meaning the prospect of recovery from an injury or disease?","answer":"Prognosis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4943 medium DET2","question":"For what purpose is the drug Acepromazine used?","answer":"Tranquilizer or sedative"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4944 medium FCH387","question":"What type of drug increases the excretion of urine after administration?","answer":"Diuretic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4945 medium HIH425-1","question":"What is the appearance of the mucous membranes of a healthy horse?","answer":"Bright & moist, pink color"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4946 medium BEG115-1L","question":"In reference to TPR, what is inversion?","answer":"When respiration rate is higher than the pulse rate	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4947 medium YLM 334-2/HIH540a	","question":"An abscess of the hoof may open and drain on its own.  What simple treatment can you do to encourage the abscess to dry up and heal? ","answer":"Soak the foot (Epsom salts & warm water or iodine solution) OR pack the hoof (Animalintex, Ichthammol, etc.) 		accept either general or specific treatments"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4948 medium HIH755-1","question":"Racehorses & endurance horses are sometimes maintained at a BCS score of less than 5, yet they are healthy.  Why would you NOT want to maintain a highly competitive horse at a higher BCS score?","answer":"The horse would be carrying extra, unnecessary weight"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4949 medium FCH407","question":"In general, what does the suffix ï¿½emiaï¿½ describe?","answer":"In the blood                         "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4950 medium HIH435-2","question":"What happens with displacement colic?","answer":"Part of the intestines has moved to an abnormal position 
(examples are left dorsal colon displacement & right dorsal colon displacement ï¿½ not necessary to give this part)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4951 medium TH191","question":"Overuse of anti-inflammatory drugs & stress may cause what problem for the horse?","answer":"Gastric ulcers"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4952 medium HIH440-6","question":"Why are ointments less effective in warm weather?","answer":"Heat will cause them to melt & to escape from wound"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4953 medium DET211","question":"What is the chemical name for the anti-inflammatory drug "Bute"?","answer":"Phenylbutazone"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4954 medium DET211","question":"What is the common name for the drug Phenylbutazone?","answer":"Bute"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4955 medium DET169","question":"What is another name for a benign fatty tumor?","answer":"Lipoma"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4956 medium INT204-2","question":"Name 2 health problems that can be created by moldy or dusty hay.","answer":"Colic, heaves, allergies"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4957 medium DET117","question":"2 part question:  What are galls & what is the result if left untreated?","answer":"Abrasions or sores caused by the saddle or harness; untreated, may result in white hair spots"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4958 medium TH706-7","question":"What is stocking up?","answer":"Swelling of the lower legs after horses stand for long periods (fluid accumulates below the knees & hocks)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4959 medium HIH1380-1","question":"What is the name of the test being described?  Forcibly flexing a joint for 30 - 60 seconds, then jogging the horse?","answer":"Flexion test"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4960 medium HIH425-2","question":"In reference to horse health, what does CRT stand for?","answer":"Capillary refill time"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4961 medium HIH440-2","question":"Name a substance that can be applied topically to control bleeding.","answer":"Silver nitrate"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4962 medium FCH211/HIH410-1","question":"What is anhidrosis?","answer":"Inability to sweat"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4963 medium DET46","question":"What is the term for a localized thickening of the outer layer of the skin due to repeated friction or pressure?","answer":"Callus"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4964 medium HIH790-1","question":"For an obese horse, weight loss should occur gradually over several months.  What amount of weight loss in pounds OR what change in the body condition score is recommended in one month?","answer":"Approximately 50 pounds or one body condition score      "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4965 medium TH111","question":"What is pulmonary hemorrhage?","answer":"Bleeding in the lungs		"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4966 medium TH276","question":"What is cystitis?","answer":"Infection/inflammation of the bladder "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4967 medium HIH435-1","question":"What is incarceration colic?","answer":"When a section of intestine gets trapped within the abdominal cavity
(examples are epiploic foramen entrapment & mesenteric rent entrapment)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4968 medium DET15","question":"What is the medical term for any variation from the normal heart rate?","answer":"Arrhythmia"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4969 medium FCH294/HIHvarious","question":"What can be fed daily in order to reduce sand-induced diarrhea or colic?","answer":"Psyllium"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4970 medium CAHA58","question":"What causes the "lub-dub" sound of the healthy heart?","answer":"Rush of blood & closing of heart valves	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4971 medium DET27","question":"What is the term for a tumor that is not malignant?","answer":"Benign  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4972 medium FCH34","question":"What is hypothyroidism?","answer":"Low thyroid;     addtl info - can be a result of low iodine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4973 medium HIH425-2","question":"A partial or complete blockage in the esophagus will cause a horse to do what?","answer":"Regurgitate food or saliva from nostrils    (not be able to swallow food, water, or saliva)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4974 medium DET189","question":"What procedure is being described?  Anesthetic injections are given to numb certain parts of the body.  This is used to diagnose the location of lameness or to facilitate standing surgeries.","answer":"Nerve block	 (also accept local anesthesia)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4975 medium DET240","question":"What is the name of a common skin condition of the horse that can resemble an ulcerated wart & may be caused by a virus?","answer":"Sarcoid"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4976 medium DET12","question":"What is the name of the medication that's used to counteract a poison?","answer":"Antidote"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4977 medium TH611","question":"Name a possible cause of choke.","answer":"Bolting food/greedy eating, bad teeth, lack of water"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4978 medium FCH258/HIH","question":"What is considered the major cause of death in foals less than 8 months old?","answer":"Pneumonia"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4979 medium HIH465-2","question":"What is a sarcoid?","answer":"Type of skin tumor in horses"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4980 medium HIH465-3","question":"Name an area where sarcoids occur.","answer":"Eyelids, ears, head, legs, sheath		(do not need to give all)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4981 medium HIH465-3","question":"What is believed to be the cause of sarcoids?","answer":"Virus, but exact cause is unknown (BPV or bovine papilloma virus)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4982 medium HIH465-3","question":"What is immunotherapy?","answer":"Stimulating the immune system to react to tumors & cause them to regress; 
Additional info -- also used for allergic diseases (allergy shots)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4983 medium HIH465-3","question":"What is a corneal ulcer?","answer":"Corneal abrasion or tear 	
(additional info -- caused by trauma to the cornea; may lead to infection & blindness)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4984 medium DET63","question":"What do you call the type of bone fracture that breaks the skin?","answer":"Compound fracture"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4985 medium HIH660-1","question":"What type of bacteria is considered the most common cause of infectious enterocolitis in adult horses?","answer":"Salmonella"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4986 medium HIH, FCH, etc.","question":"A soluble-fiber, bulk agent such as Metamucil or Psyllium would be administered to a horse with diarrhea that is a result of what type of ingestion?","answer":"Sand ingestion"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4987 medium HIH425-2","question":"A horseï¿½s body condition or degree of fat cover can be affected by many things.  Name 2.","answer":"Food availability/diet, reproductive activities, weather changes, performance/working activity, management practices"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4988 medium HIH410-1","question":"How soon should a horse with heat exhaustion respond to cooling efforts?","answer":"10 - 15 minutes	 (additional info -- will appear very tired, but willing to eat & drink)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4989 medium HIH425-2","question":"Name a sign of choke.","answer":"Coughing, lump in neck, food/fluid may come out of mouth or nose, horse may be unable to swallow saliva, food, or water "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4990 medium FCH380","question":"What is the term for a condition of increased sensitivity to a specific protein, which may result in a rash, hives, sneezing or respiratory difficulties?","answer":"Allergy"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4991 medium HIH440-1","question":"Why is drainage encouraged with a puncture wound?","answer":"To remove pus & debris OR so wound will heal from inside out   (accept either)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4992 medium HIH440-3","question":"2 part question:  What is a penetrating wound & how should you treat it?","answer":"A wound that penetrates a body cavity or organ Treat as an EMERGENCYï¿½call vet & cover wound with sterile gauze)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4993 medium HIH450-4","question":"Why is impaction colic more common in winter?","answer":"Horse not drinking enough water "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4994 medium HIH785-1","question":"Name a cause of starvation in horses.","answer":"Unintentional neglect, intentional neglect, abandoned, ignorance of horse care, economic hardship of owner"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4995 medium HIH785-2","question":"When a horse loses more than 50% of his body weight, what is the prognosis for recovery?","answer":"Very poor"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4996 medium HIH785-3","question":"What is the best approach for rehabilitating a starved horse?","answer":"Feed small, frequent meals of high quality alfalfa for 1st 10 days, then increase hay amounts slowly to free choice.  Grain not recommended until horse is near normal weight"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4997 medium HIH785-3","question":"How much time is generally required to get a starved horse back to normal body weight?","answer":"3 - 5 months"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4998 medium HIH790-2","question":"Name 2 ways to increase exercise for horses with chronic lameness.","answer":"Turn out into large paddock/pasture, provide companion, locate feed & water sources far apart, hand walk, swimming"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"4999 medium HIH425-2","question":"How do you test capillary refill time?","answer":"Press thumb on gums for a few seconds and then remove.  Gum should return to normal pink color within 1-2 seconds"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5000 medium HIH790-3","question":"Referring to overweight horses, how much can a horse safely lose per month?","answer":"50 pounds"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5001 medium HIH445-1","question":"Why is vaccinating your horse after he's been exposed to a disease not very effective?","answer":"Seldom gives horse enough time to build immunity"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5002 medium TH611","question":"What is choke?","answer":"Partial or complete blockage of the esophagus "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5003 medium DET100 ","question":"What is the correct medical terminology used to describe the humane or painless death of a horse through the action of a person (usually a veterinarian)? ","answer":"Euthanasia   (also accept ï¿½put downï¿½)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5004 medium ES193","question":"What does the term "biosecurity" mean?","answer":"Protecting living things from infectious agents"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5005 medium FCH392","question":"Small swellings or welts on the skin that appear suddenly & are caused by an allergic reaction are called what?","answer":"Hives"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5006 medium HIH445-7","question":"You should vaccinate your mare for Tetanus, WEE, EEE & Influenza approximately how long before foaling in order to build antibodies that'll be transferred to the foal?","answer":"30 days"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5007 medium FCH362","question":"What is the term for a partial or complete blockage of the esophagus causing an inability to swallow?","answer":"Choke		"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5008 medium HIH445-2 new","question":"The American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA) divides vaccinations into 2 categories.  What are they?","answer":"Core & risk-based"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5009 medium FCH399","question":"An excessive reaction of the skin to sunlight is called what?","answer":"Photosensitivity"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5010 medium HIH445-5new","question":"How many types of West Nile vaccines are there?","answer":"3"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5011 medium FCH210","question":"What kind of fluid should you give a horse suffering from heat cramps?","answer":"Electrolyte solution (water with electrolytes)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5012 medium HIH780-1","question":"What is another term for the degree of fat cover on your horseï¿½s body?   ","answer":"Body condition  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5013 medium DET51","question":"What term refers to a horse that's fallen or is lying down too close to a wall or fence to get up without assistance?","answer":"Cast"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5014 medium TH104","question":"What do you call the spasmodic muscle contraction that produces heat in cold weather?","answer":"Shivering"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5015 medium FCH380","question":"What is the term for a localized collection of pus in the body tissue which is often accompanied by swelling & inflammation?","answer":"Abscess"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5016 medium HIH445-2new","question":"According to the American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA), vaccinations that protect from diseases that are endemic to a region, with potential public health significance, required by law, highly infectious and/or pose a risk of severe disease are called what general type of vaccine?","answer":"Core vaccines"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5017 medium FCH405/DET89","question":"What term describes an accumulation of abnormally large amounts of fluid in the horse's body tissue?","answer":"Edema 	(additional info -- stocking up is edema of the lower legs)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5018 medium HIH851-4","question":"How can you evaluate back or loin soreness?","answer":"Use	thumb & forefinger on each side of withers.  Apply gentle pressure & move down the back.  If sore, horse will drop back away from pressure in that area			"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5019 medium HIH851-2","question":"What is the body condition score of a horse whose topline is level & whose ribs can be felt, but not seen?","answer":"Five"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5020 medium HIH975-1","question":"What is the normal temperature for a newborn foal?","answer":"99 ï¿½ 101.5 degrees		(accept any number in range)   "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5021 medium HIH820-2","question":"Where is the greatest amount of electrolytes lost?","answer":"Sweat"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5022 medium HIH451-8","question":"A method of assessing a horse's body condition by visually appraising or physically feeling fat cover in several areas is called what?","answer":"Body condition scoring"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5023 medium CAHA5/TH129/FCH199","question":"How does sweating cool the horse's body?","answer":"Sweat is evaporated from the horseï¿½s body & cools the horse."},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5024 medium HIH975-1","question":"What is the normal heart rate for a foal?","answer":"80 ï¿½ 120 beats per minute			(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5025 medium TH307","question":"What is anemia?","answer":"Deficiency of red blood cells"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5026 medium HIH635,435-2","question":"What is a common culprit in the development of gas colic?","answer":"Overeating grain"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5027 medium TH306","question":"What is the muscle disorder that can appear in horses under regular heavy exercise that are not worked for a few days, yet still remain on full feed?  It can also occur in out-of-condition horses that have been worked too hard.","answer":"Monday Morning Sickness or Tying Up or Azorturia (also accept black water disease or extertional rhabdomyolysis)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5028 medium TH306","question":"Why should you reduce the grain intake of a horse on non-work days?","answer":"Horse can tie up (Monday Morning Sickness or Azoturia) (also accept black water disease or extertional rhabdomyolysis)	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5029 medium HIH975-1","question":"Giving only one number, what is the normal respiratory rate of a foal?","answer":"20 - 40 breaths per minute		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5030 medium HIH635,435-2","question":"Which type of colic is caused by a blockage in the intestinal tract?","answer":"Impaction"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5031 medium HIH440-2","question":"What is silver nitrate?","answer":"Chemical used to stop bleeding 	(also used as an antiseptic)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5032 medium HIH425-1","question":"Respiration rate should always be lower than what?","answer":"Heart rate"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5033 medium CAHA62/ES163","question":"Where would you measure a digital pulse?","answer":"Artery in foot OR back of pastern/just above pastern joint	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5034 medium TH110","question":"What is the term for an infection localized in the lungs?","answer":"Pneumonia"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5035 medium HIH455-3","question":"How can you help keep a puncture wound open while it's healing?","answer":"Soak in warm water & Epsom salts	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5036 medium CAHA22/FCH397","question":"What is the term for cutting the digital nerve to relieve pain?","answer":"Nerving or neurectomy"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5037 medium HIH1160-1,2","question":"Why should you be especially careful of how much tension you apply to a leg bandage?","answer":"Too loose, bandage can fall off & allow the wound to get contaminated; too tight, bandage can restrict blood flow to the area & cause tissue damage"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5038 medium HIH1160-1","question":"Most medically indicated bandages have how many layers?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5039 medium HIH1160-1","question":"What is one purpose of the secondary bandage layer?","answer":"Absorbs fluids from wound OR provides padding"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5040 medium HIH1160-2","question":"Why should leg bandages be wrapped in a spiral fashion from the front to back (pulling across the front of the leg rather than the back)?","answer":"To minimize the risk of uneven tension on the back of the leg and/or damage to the tendons, nerves, & blood vessels	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5041 medium FCH304","question":"What is a spasm?","answer":"Sudden involuntary contractions of a muscle or group of muscles"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5042 medium HIH440-3","question":"In reference to a wound, what is meant by the term "golden period"?","answer":"Elapsed time from injury to closure (after which, suturing a wound would do little good)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5043 medium FCH381","question":"An antibiotic is used to control or eliminate what?","answer":"Bacterial infection"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5044 medium FCH405","question":"Where is a subcutaneous shot administered?","answer":"Under the skin"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5045 medium FCH387","question":"What is the term for higher than normal amounts of water in the feces or for an animal defecating too frequently?","answer":"Diarrhea		"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5046 medium HIH425-1","question":"A respiratory rate higher than the pulse rate is known as what?","answer":"Inversion"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5047 medium HIH210-5","question":"What is a pre-purchase exam?","answer":"Exam made by a veterinarian to determine overall soundness & health of a horse prior to a sale transaction"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5048 medium TH610","question":"When can a horse with a fractured limb be moved?","answer":"After a splint has been applied OR after evaluation by vet"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5049 hard HIH440-5","question":"Your horse has been kicked by another horse & has a contusion.  The trauma is sufficient to break blood vessels, resulting in an abnormal pocketing, & collecting of blood in body tissue.  What is this called?","answer":"Hematoma	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5050 medium DET240","question":"What is the common term for diarrhea in foals?						","answer":"Scours"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5051 medium FCH259/DET240","question":"2 part question:  What is scours & when during a horse's life does it usually occur?","answer":"Watery diarrhea; occurs in foals under 6 months old"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5052 medium HIH445","question":"You are the veterinarian treating a horse with West Nile.  The horseï¿½s owner wants to know why youï¿½re not treating the horse with antibiotics.   Explain why you arenï¿½t","answer":"West Nile is a viral disease & antibiotics are used to treat bacterial diseases"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5053 medium FCH290","question":"It is painful for your horse to eat due to lesions in his mouth.  Identify one change you can make to your horseï¿½s diet that would decrease the pain associated with eating.","answer":"Provide green grass, feed a mash by adding water to 	a complete pelleted feed, alfalfa pellets, meal or bran                  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5054 medium DET167, 118, 138, etc				","question":"In general, what does the suffix ï¿½itisï¿½ indicate?","answer":"Inflammation                    "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5055 medium FCH296","question":"What type of forage would be most appropriate for a horse with renal failure?","answer":"Grass forage    (lower in protein, phosphorus and calcium)      "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5056 medium HIH405-5","question":"A pituitary tumor may cause what syndrome associated with heavy hair growth?","answer":"Cushings                         "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5057 medium DET10","question":"What is the contributing factor to the condition known as anaphylaxis?","answer":"Severe allergy                "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5058 medium HIH435a-1","question":"Identify 2 types of colic in regards to the placement of the small intestine","answer":"Displacement, telescoping (intussuception) or twisting (volvulus)     "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5059 medium DET168","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½leukoï¿½ refer to?","answer":"White blood cells                "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5061 medium HIH795-2","question":"Intense exercise correlates with an increased incidence of EGUS.  What is EGUS?","answer":"Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome             "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5122 medium DET12","question":"What substance is produced in the body in response to an allergen?","answer":"Histamine         "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5123 medium HIH440-3","question":"You are the veterinarian on call & are examining a horse that sustained a laceration to the front lower leg sometime in the past 12 hours.  There is no active bleeding from the wound.  What would be the main reason to NOT suture the wound?","answer":"Suturing may increase the risk of infection due to elapsed time since injury (without the wound being properly cleaned)              "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5124 medium DET221","question":"What is the use of a prophylactic medication?","answer":"To prevent illness or disease             "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5125 medium TH167, DET183","question":"Identify 2 other terms for the condition commonly referred to as mud fever","answer":"Grease, grease heel, scratches, cracked heel           "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5126 medium BEG115-1L","question":"You are the conditioning veterinarian judge for an endurance trail ride.  What condition would these vital signs indicate?  Temperature 102 degrees, heart rate 80 bpm & respiration 100 breaths per minute","answer":"Inversion    (respiratory rate higher than pulse rate)            "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5127 medium DET23","question":"What is the name for the radiopaque dye material given to a horse by mouth to outline the digestive tract on radiographs (X-rays)?","answer":"Barium				"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"medium","number":"5128 medium DET3            ","question":"What is the correct term for the medication referred to by the slang term ï¿½Aceï¿½?","answer":"Acetyl promazine    (acepromazine)               "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5129 hard DET85","question":"What are you doing if you are "drenching" a horse?","answer":"Giving liquid medication to the horse by pouring it down its throat from a bottle"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5130 hard DET235","question":"What is the correct term for a thick, multi-layer bandage that includes wood or metal splints & is used to restrain & support an injured leg?","answer":"Robert Jones bandage"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5134 hard DET17","question":"What medication is used to treat bradycardia?","answer":"Atropine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5135 hard DET91","question":"What is an embolism?	","answer":"The lodgment of a foreign particle (such as an air bubble or blood clot) in the circulatory system"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5136 hard DET17","question":"What is an astringent?","answer":"Drug that causes constriction or contraction of tissues & decrease secretions
(additional info -- examples ï¿½tannic acid, alum, zinc oxide)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5137 hard DET10","question":"Your horse has gone into anaphylactic shock. What is this?","answer":"An acute, massive, often fatal allergic reaction	 (additional info -- treated with a shot of epinephrine) "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5138 hard HIH425-2","question":"What would a brownish-green urine color indicate?","answer":"Jaundice, azotoria, tying-up, Monday morning sickness or disease"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5139 hard DET40","question":"What is the general term for a drug that causes the air passages of the lungs to widen?","answer":"Bronchodilator"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5140 hard DET228","question":"Rain rot is a bacterial infection of the skin where the hair separates from the skin at the roots & sloughs off in sections.  This is often confused with rain scald which is caused by an infection with what organism?","answer":"Fungus			"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5141 hard HIH851-4","question":"If you were able to check the heart rate of your horse on a prolonged gallop, how high would you expect it to be?","answer":"200 - 250 beats per minute 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5142 hard FCH339","question":"There are no specific treatments for some poisonings, but horses are usually given activated charcoal & a saline laxative by stomach tube.  What is the reason for giving these medications?","answer":"To prevent further absorption of the toxin OR activated charcoal binds with the toxin & the saline laxative speeds the passage of toxins through the digestive tract"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5143 hard TH62","question":"Where are 2 places on the horse's head where the pulse can easily be felt using your fingers?","answer":"Under the jaw & just below eye	    (facial artery & transverse facial artery)  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5144 hard CAHA60","question":"What is verminous colic?","answer":"Colic caused by worms"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5145 hard DET107","question":"What is the reason for not treating fibular fractures unless bone fragments need to be surgically removed?","answer":"Tibia acts as a splint & no lameness is involved"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5146 hard DET155","question":"What is the term for passage of a tube into either the trachea or the esophagus?","answer":"Intubation"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5147 hard TH594","question":"What term is used to describe a slower than normal heartbeat?","answer":"Bradycardia"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5148 hard DET228","question":"What is the common name for a painful, infectious skin inflammation that causes the hair coat to separate from the skin at the roots, forming painful crusts & sloughing off in sections?","answer":"Rain rot"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5149 hard DET268","question":"What is the common name for synchronous diaphragmatic flutters?","answer":"Thumps"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5150 hard HIH860-3","question":"Equine sweat is hypertonic.  What does this mean?","answer":"Contains a significant amount of salts"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5151 hard DET34","question":"What is a bolus?","answer":"Rounded mass of food or medicine given orally"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5152 hard FCH388","question":"Define epistaxis.","answer":"Bleeding from the nose   (nosebleed)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5153 hard DET43","question":"What is a caruncle?","answer":"Small, fleshy outgrowth"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5154 hard HIH810-2","question":"What is the most common treatment for exercise induced pulmonary hemorrhage (EIPH)?","answer":"Lasix   (also accept Furosemide)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5155 hard HIH635-2","question":"Why is the pelvic flexure in the colon a common site of impaction?","answer":"It's where the large colon narrows in diameter & makes a tight, upward hairpin turn"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5156 hard HIH635-4","question":"How long does it generally take for the results of treatment for intestinal impaction to occur?","answer":"24 - 72 hours		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5157 hard FCH408","question":"What is the proper name for a small sac or blister containing fluid?","answer":"Vesicle, vesicular or cyst"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5158 hard FCH213","question":"What 2 internal parts are associated with thumps?","answer":"Diaphragm & heart"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5159 hard DET255","question":"When used properly, what is the purpose of a steroid?","answer":"Control inflammation or suppress allergic reaction"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5161 hard TH306","question":"What is the name of the condition where there is an unusually high level of fat in the blood?","answer":"Hyperlipemia 	(also accept hyperlipidemia)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5162 hard TH517","question":"What is the condition in which cerebrospinal fluid accumulates, causing the head to enlarge & the central nervous system to be abnormal?","answer":"Hydrocephalus"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5163 hard TH163","question":"What is the purpose of a neurectomy?","answer":"Eliminate pain reception from a body part"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5164 hard TH115-16","question":"What do the letters ECG stand for?","answer":"Electrocardiogram"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5165 hard DET4","question":"What is an adhesion?","answer":"Sticking together of 2 structures that normally move freely from each other"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5166 hard FCH387","question":"What is the general term for inflammation of the skin?","answer":"Dermatitis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5167 hard TH610","question":"What is the term for removal of foreign material & damaged or dead tissue from a wound?","answer":"Debridement    (deh-BREED-ment)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5168 hard HIH440-6","question":"Give one example why you would use a hot poultice on your horse.","answer":"Increase blood supply to the injured area or draw out infection from abscess/puncture wound"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5169 hard TH256","question":"Why would the urine of horses fed legume hay smell stronger than the urine of horses fed grass hay?","answer":"Legume hay has more protein so more nitrogen is excreted in the urine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5170 hard TH269","question":"What is the condition score for the horse being described?  There is slight fat cover over the ribs, but they're easily seen.  The hook bones appear rounded, but are visible.  The tailhead is prominent & the withers, shoulder & neck are accentuated","answer":"Condition score 3"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5171 hard TH104","question":"Shivering is what type of involuntary physiological response?","answer":"Spasmodic muscle contraction"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5172 hard HIH425-2/CAHA68","question":"2 part question:  How many times a day do horses urinate & how much urine do they produce?","answer":"5 - 7 times daily; 	produce from 4 - 7 quarts"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5173 hard FCH381","question":"What is the term for a chemical substance that inhibits or destroys bacteria or other micro-organisms & is  used primarily in the treatment of infectious diseases?","answer":"Antibiotic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5174 hard DET32","question":"2 part question:  Medically speaking, what is a block & why would one be used?","answer":"Anesthetic injection used to numb certain parts of the body; used to detect the location of lameness & for standing surgeries"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5175 hard DET22","question":"What is the name for the syringe-like device used to give large pills to horses?","answer":"Balling gun"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5176 hard TH110","question":"What part of the lungs is damaged when a horse has pulmonary emphysema?","answer":"Alveoli"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5177 hard DET10","question":"What is the term used for an acute, massive, often fatal allergic reaction?","answer":"Anaphylactic shock"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5178 hard DET4","question":"What medication is being described?  This medication may be used to treat severe asthma or anaphylactic  reactions.  It causes contraction of capillaries & arteries by stimulating the sympathetic nervous system.  It  causes an increase in the heart rate & blood pressure.","answer":"Adrenalin or epinephrine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5179 hard TH269","question":"What is the body condition score for the horse being described?  Prominent crease down the back, difficult to feel ribs, fat around tailhead very soft, area behind shoulder filled noticeable thickening of neck, fat deposited along withers & inner buttocks","answer":"BCS score 8"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5180 hard HIH470-1","question":"2 part question:  Name an advantage & disadvantage of using a barbituate overdose for euthanasia","answer":"Advantage - speed of action, minimal discomfort for horse;    disadvantage - requires IV, so horse must be restrained"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5181 hard HIH435-1","question":"What is volvulus or torsion colic?","answer":"When the intestines twist	 (additional info -- can stop blood supply & cause necrosis of the intestine)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5182 hard DET137","question":"Hemiparesis is ï¿½weaknessï¿½ on one side of the body. What does the term hemiplegia describe?","answer":"ï¿½Paralysisï¿½ on one side of the body"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5183 hard HIH795-2","question":"What is Equine Gastric Ulcer Syndrome?","answer":"Ulcers of the horseï¿½s stomach 
(additional info -- may be caused by stress, stomach acid, bacteria, parasites, or feeding intermittently)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5184 hard TH306","question":"Why do horses that "tie up" sometimes have dark-colored or coffee-colored urine?","answer":"Myoglobin is released from damaged muscle & is incorporated into the urine (breakdown of muscle tissue)
Accept either"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5185 hard HIH795-2","question":"The development of equine gastric ulcer syndrome has been linked with intense exercise.  In what breed is it most prevalent?","answer":"Thoroughbred	   (additional info -- 91% of those in training & 100% of those currently racing)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5186 hard HIH795-2","question":"Allowing a horse free-choice hay while recovering from gastric ulcers does what?","answer":"Keeps the gastric pH from becoming highly acidic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5187 hard DET p. 36, 169					","question":"What is the term for a liquid medication that is applied to the horseï¿½s legs after exercise to prevent swelling & to reduce soreness?","answer":"Brace, liniment, or astringent		(accept any)	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5188 hard DET137","question":"What is the difference between hemiparesis and hemiplegia?","answer":"Hemiparesis is ï¿½weaknessï¿½ on one side of the body;    hemiplegia is ï¿½paralysisï¿½ on one side of the body"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5189 hard DET74	","question":"What is the proper name for the procedure that is used in the treatment of sarcoid lesions and results in the destruction of tissue by the application of extreme cold? ","answer":"Cryosurgery "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5190 hard DET165","question":"If you are using a lavage to treat a woundï¿½What are you doing? ","answer":"Washing the wound with a stream of fluid "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5191 hard DET72","question":"What is the name of the aluminum or wooden device worn around the neck of a horse to prevent it from chewing at sores, blankets or bandages?","answer":"Neck cradle or cradle"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5192 hard HIH445-1","question":"Define vaccination.  ","answer":"Artificially stimulating immunity in an animal without actually giving it the disease"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5193 hard FCH308","question":"The equine liver will function at near optimal levels until approximately what percent of it is destroyed?","answer":"80 %	 (accept numbers between 70 to 80 %)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5194 hard TH610","question":"How would you keep a horse with a broken leg on the ground until the vet arrives?","answer":"Sitting on its neck & applying pressure on the head"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5195 hard HIH445-1/DET281","question":"What is a vaccine?","answer":"Substance that stimulates an animal to produce antibodies against certain diseases
(additional info --- vaccines use live/ weakened micro-organisms, killed micro-organisms, or the toxins or proteins of micro-organisms)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5196 hard HS56","question":"What would you call the lodgment of a foreign particle - such as a blood clot or air bubble - in the circulatory system?","answer":"Embolism"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5197 hard HS37","question":"What is a bacterin vaccine?","answer":"Substance made of killed bacteria that is given to an animal to stimulate immunity"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5198 hard HS47/DET20","question":"What is the name of the immune stimulating product that's made from killed bacteria?","answer":"Bacterin"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5199 hard DET81","question":"Give 2 medical properties or uses for Dimethyl Sulfoxide (DMSO)","answer":"Anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, analgesic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5200 hard HIH445-13","question":"Why is the anthrax vaccine not readily available in the US?","answer":"The disease is not very common & has only occurred in certain areas "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5201 hard HIH445-2","question":"What is the difference between a tetanus anti-toxin & a tetanus toxoid vaccine?","answer":"Anti-toxin -- gives immediate short-term protection
(additional info -- usually given in cases where the immunization status of the animal is unknown);
Toxoid - gives long term protection	  	 (additional info -- usually given annually)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5202 hard TH12","question":"What do you call the occupational field that emphasizes conditioning, measuring fitness & improving rehabilitation techniques of the horse?","answer":"Equine Sports Medicine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5203 hard DET266","question":"What is the correct name of the vaccine used in horses for prolonged protection against tetanus?","answer":"Tetanus toxoid		 (additional info -- tetanus antitoxin is temporary protection)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5204 hard TH594","question":"What is tachycardia?","answer":"Rapid heart rate"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5205 hard HIH640-2","question":"What type of medications are Flunixin (floo-NIX-in) meglumine (MEG-glue-mean), Ketoprofen (kee-toe-PRO-fen), & Phenylbutazone (feen-ill-BUTE-ah-zone)?  ","answer":"NSAID (Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs)   "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5206 hard DET92","question":"What is the name for the medical instrument used in the examination of the interior of a hollow organ such as the stomach?","answer":"Endoscope"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5207 hard FCH408","question":"Describe Wobbler's Syndrome.","answer":"Uncoordination of the back legs (generally in growing horses) caused by compression of the cervical spinal cord"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5208 hard FCH381","question":"What is the medical term for the condition when a horse becomes uncoordinated & staggers due to a disease or injury of the brain or spinal cord?","answer":"Ataxia"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5209 hard FCH383","question":"What is the common term for measuring the hematocrit or percent of red blood cells?","answer":"Blood count"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5210 hard FCH392","question":"What is hematocrit?","answer":"The percent of the blood that's red blood cells"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5211 hard FCH213","question":"Movements of the flank in sync with the heartbeat - indicating an electrolyte imbalance - are commonly called what?","answer":"Thumps (diaphragmatic flutter)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5212 hard FCH277","question":"Most developmental orthopedic disease conditions are due to the failure of what?","answer":"Growing cartilage to be properly converted to bone"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5213 hard HIH435-1","question":"What is intussusception?","answer":"When the intestines ï¿½telescopeï¿½ 	(additional info -- usually occurs in the small intestines of young horses)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5214 hard BEG104","question":"Under what conditions is the horse's cooling ability significantly reduced to the point where it can be fatal if the horse is stressed?","answer":"When the sum of the temperature & relative humidity is greater than 180  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5215 hard HIH445-13","question":"If you use the nasal Strangles vaccine, why should you NOT give other injectable vaccines at the same time?","answer":"The live bacteria in the Strangles vaccine will form abscesses at the injection site"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5216 hard FCH394","question":"What is an ion?","answer":"Atom with an electrical charge"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5217 hard FCH397","question":"What is necrosis?","answer":"Death of cells or body tissue while animal is still alive"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5218 hard TH273","question":"Why do thumps often occur in horses during endurance rides?","answer":"Decreased blood level of potassium"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5219 hard FCH387","question":"What part of the horse would be inflamed if it had desmitis?","answer":"Ligament"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5220 hard DET98","question":"Adrenaline is a hormone secreted by the central portion of the adrenal gland that acts primarily as a stimulant. Give another name for adrenaline.","answer":"Epinephrine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5221 hard FCH388","question":"What is an inflammation of the endometrium called?","answer":"Endometritis (in-doe-mee-TRITE-is)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5222 hard FCH253","question":"What do you call a liquid introduced into the intestine by way of the anus?","answer":"Enema"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5223 hard TH265","question":"What is osteochondritis (ahs-tee-oh-con-DRYT-is)?","answer":"Improper maturation of cartilage to bone 	
(additional info -- affects the cartilage & subchondral bone of joints)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5224 hard TH111","question":"2 part ï¿½ What is exercise induced pulmonary hemorrhage & what causes it?","answer":"Bleeding from the nose after physical exertion; caused by bursting of small blood vessels in the lungs"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5225 hard HIH445-13","question":"Who developed an Anthrax vaccine in 1881?","answer":"Louis Pasteur"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5226 hard FCH209","question":"What does the drug Lasix treat in racehorses?","answer":"Exercise induced pulmonary hemorrhage OR bleeding from nose "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5227 hard TH105","question":"The vocal cords are 2 muscles that project across the lower part of the larynx.  Paralysis on one or both of the muscles results in a condition known as what?","answer":"Roaring	"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5228 hard DET91","question":"Endocarditis is an inflammation or infection of the lining of what organ?","answer":"Heart"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5229 hard DET221","question":"What term describes a preparation that contains no medication & is administered in order to simulate treatment such as in a research study?","answer":"Placebo"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5230 hard DET16","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½periï¿½ describe?				","answer":"Around "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5231 hard DET178,198,240","question":"In general, what does the suffix ï¿½omaï¿½ describe?       ","answer":"Tumor (also accept cancer or neoplasm)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5232 hard DET79","question":"In general, what does the prefix ï¿½desmoï¿½ indicate?","answer":"Ligament                  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5233 hard (medium)				TH111","question":"You do the math --- If the cardiac output is 35 liters & the heart rate is 35 beats per minute, what is the stroke volume?","answer":"1 liter                     "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5234 hard DET13","question":"In general, what is the expected effect of an antipyretic medication?            ","answer":"Fever reduction     (also accept increases heat loss; reduces heat production)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5235 hard ES163","question":"Blood is pulled from the peripheral circulation to the internal vital organs in a horse with shock.  How would this physiological process affect the capillary refill time?","answer":"Delayed or slower             "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5236 hard HIH460-4","question":"What does the abbreviation PSSM indicate?","answer":"Polysaccharide Storage Myopathy         "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5237 hard DET2","question":"What is the correct term for the medication referred to by the abbreviation DMSO?","answer":"Dimethyl sulfoxide         "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"hard","number":"5238 hard HIH795-2","question":"Horses with Equine Metabolic Syndrome can be differentiated from other obese horses by what characteristic regional adiposity (fat deposits)?","answer":"Fat deposits located in the crest of the neck & tail head    (only need to give one location)     "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5239 bonus HIH795","question":"Name 3 disorders of the horse that are affected by nutritional management.","answer":"Colic, laminitis, gastric ulcer syndrome, Equine Metabolic Syndrome, Cushingï¿½s disease, developmental orthopedic disease/DOD, hyperkalemic periodic paralysis/HYPP, exertional rhabdomyolysis/tying up, recurrent airway obstruction/heaves"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5241 bonus FCH259/HIH975-11","question":"Name 3 causes of foal diarrhea.","answer":"Stress,  diet/nutritional causes,  parasites (threadworms, strongyles, ascarids),  sand ingestion, foal heat,
Bacteria (E. coli, salmonella, clostridium, rhodococcus equi),  infections, combined immunodeficiency,  zootonic disease
Virus (rotavirus, coronavirus, adenovirus),  secondary to treatment for meconium impaction,
feeding errors/schedules (orphan foals),  gastric ulcers,  lactose intolerance,  physical enteritis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5242 bonus HIH851-10","question":"Equine swimming pools have become popular for conditioning horses.  Name 3 ways in which swimming helps horses build condition","answer":"Improves cardiovascular health, increases respiratory function, increases muscle tone, decreases stress on feet & legs"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5243 bonus HIH465-3","question":"Name 3 of the categories of sarcoids.","answer":"Occult, verrucous, nodular, fibroblastic, mixed"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5244 bonus HIH465-2","question":"Name 3 treatments for a horse with squamous cell carcinoma.","answer":"Surgical removal, chemotherapy, laser, freezing, radiation, combination of these "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5245 bonus HIH465-2","question":"Name 3 of the most common eye problems in the horse.","answer":"Blocked tear duct, eyelid laceration, sarcoid, squamous cell carcinoma, moon blindness"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5246 bonus HIH465-3","question":"2 part question:  All corneal ulcers should be considered emergencies.  Describe the difference between a simple & a complicated corneal ulcer & the main treatment for each.","answer":"Simple is superficial & not infected; treat with topical antibiotics & pain meds; 
Complicated is deep & infected; treat with antibiotics & pain meds, may require surgery"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5247 bonus HIH465-2","question":"What are 3 common signs of eye disease in the horse?","answer":"Color change, redness, cloudiness, squinting, tearing, discharge, decreased vision, blindness, closing eye"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5248 bonus HIH950-8, 975-4","question":"Pneumonia is the major cause of mortality in foals.  Name 3 factors that predispose foals to pneumonia.","answer":"Dust, poor sanitation, fluctuations in temperature, overcrowding, extremes of temperature/humidity, poor ventilation, parasites, poor nutrition, stress/overcrowding/weaning, etc., prematurity, foal didn't receive colostrum, secondary to other infections (example influenza), hereditary diseases (example combined immunodeficiency), failure to vaccinate mare, failure of immunity (no colostrum or antibodies havenï¿½t developed yet)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5249 bonus HIH440-4","question":"Name 3 types of closed wounds.","answer":"Contusion, hematoma, sprain, torn muscle, torn ligament, torn tendon, torn cartilage"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5250 bonus HIH410-1","question":"Name 3 tissues of the horse that can be damaged in open wounds.","answer":"Skin, muscle, nerves, blood vessels, tendons, bones, internal organs"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5251 bonus HIH795-2","question":"Name 3 ways you can treat Equine Metabolic Syndrome.  ","answer":"Exercise horse, maintain body condition (don't let horse get fat!), feed rations low in sugar & starch, feed high forage diet, test hay for sugar content or soak for at least an hour before feeding, limit pasture high in fructans"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5252 bonus HIH470-1","question":"What are the only 3 acceptable methods of euthanasia for a horse?","answer":"Overdose of barbiturates, gunshot, captive bolt"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5253 bonus HIH470-1","question":"Name 3 criteria for considering euthanasia.  ","answer":"Horse's condition causes unnecessary pain or suffering; horseï¿½s condition is incurable; horse is a danger to himself or handlers; horse requires pain medication for the rest of its life; horse may get down & be unable to get up; horse cannot keep an adequate body condition; owner cannot afford treatments that may keep horse comfortable for the duration of its life"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5254 bonus HIH795-2","question":"Name 3 risk factors for gastric ulcers.","answer":"Intense exercise, stall confinement, stress"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5255 bonus HIH790-1","question":"Horses with a high body fat percentage are at greater risk for what 3 things?","answer":"Heat stress, laminitis, hyperlipidemia, decreased athletic performance, poor reproductive performance"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5256 bonus HIH425-2","question":"When examining a horse, what 3 things would you evaluate when looking at the mucous membranes?","answer":"Color, moistness, capillary refill time"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5257 bonus HIH435-2","question":"Name 3 things that a horse owner can easily check that will help indicate the seriousness of colic.","answer":"Temperature, pulse, respiratory rate, mucous membranes, capillary refill time, gut sounds"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5258 bonus HIH425-1,2","question":"What are 4 of the basic vital signs of the horse?","answer":"Temperature, pulse, respiration, capillary refill time, mucous membrane color, skin pliability"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5259 bonus H3-19/DET154,258,204","question":"2 part question:  Name 3 types of injections & the location where they're given.","answer":"Subcutaneous (SubQ)ï¿½under the skin;
Intramuscular or IMï¿½in the muscle;
Intravenous or IVï¿½directly into the bloodstream;
Intradermal ï¿½ into the skin; intra-articular ï¿½ into a joint"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5260 bonus HIH435a-4","question":"Gas colic may be helped by walking the horse.  However, in more severe colic cases, it's better to save the horse's energy.  What are 4 signs that would indicate NOT walking the colicking horse?","answer":"Pulse keeps increasing or higher than 55 bpm, rare or no gut sounds, horse is depressed or irrational, horse has clammy ears or extremities"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5261 bonus HIH440-5","question":"Name 3 symptoms common to horses who have survived an electric shock.","answer":"Dazed or unconscious, slow/labored or gasping breathing, weak or slow pulse, eyes dilated or constricted, convulsions, paralysis"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5262 bonus HIH410-1","question":"Give 3 signs of heat stroke in the horse.","answer":"Rapid breathing, weakness, incoordination, refusal to work, depressed, unwilling to drink, poor gut sounds, high heart rate, high respiratory rate"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5263 bonus HIH1150-2,440-5","question":"Name 3 items found in an equine first aid kit.","answer":"Antiseptic cleansing agent, open weave/Telfa type adhesive bandages, bandage scissors, straight scissors (to cut tape, etc.), practical cotton, sheet cottons, leg wraps/quilted cotton, twitch, elasticon tape, eye wash, antiseptic soap, bute, sterile water, thermometer, pad & pencil, vet's phone number, vet wrap, stethoscope, eye ointment, coppertox, epsom salts, watch with second hand, hand towels, syringe, electrolytes, saline solution, first aid ointment, etc.		Accept any reasonable answer"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5265 bonus HIH435,635","question":"Name 3 common treatments for colic.","answer":"Surgery, mineral oil/stool softener, using stomach tube to release gas, IV fluids, pain relievers, anti-inflammatory drugs/bute, feeding psyllium for sand colic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5266 bonus HIH435,635","question":"Name 2 types of colic that require surgery.  ","answer":"Incarceration, displacement, torsion (twists), intussusception "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5267 bonus HIH435,635,795-1","question":"What are 3 causes of colic?","answer":"Moldy feed, overfeeding, sudden diet change, letting overheated horse gorge on cold water, riding hard after full feeding, twisted/telescoped intestine, blockage of intestine, enterolith, excessive parasites, sand,  high grain diet, dehydration"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5268 bonus HIH435,635","question":"Name 3 symptoms of colic.","answer":"Pawing, rolling, turning head to side, stomping with back feet, kicking or biting at flanks, excessive sweating, wanting to lie down, depression, increased or decreased gut sounds, bloating, increased or decreased heart rate, change in manure appearance or lack of defecation, grinding teeth, laying on back"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5269 bonus HIH435,635","question":"Name 3 types of colic.","answer":"Spasmodic, impaction, Displacement, incarceration, volvulus/torsion, intussusception, sand colic, gas colic, ulcers"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5270 bonus FCH116","question":"Name 3 things that can cause urticaria, welts, hives or protein bumps.  ","answer":"Foods, medications, inhaled pollens, insect bites, parasites, vaccines, chemicals"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5271 bonus HIH440-6","question":"Give 3 uses for a poultice.","answer":"Increase blood supply to area, draw out infection, encourage abscess to open, decrease inflammation"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5272 bonus HIH440-4","question":"Name 3 factors that may affect the healing of a wound.","answer":"Infection, blood supply to wound, associated soft tissue damage, skin temperature, availability for loose connective tissue to allow wound closure, age, hormonal/cardiac/liver/kidney abnormality, systemic disorders or deficiencies of protein/Vitamin A/Vitamin C/zinc"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5273 bonus HIH 950-10","question":"Identify 3 vaccinations that a foal should receive by the age of 6 months.","answer":"Tetanus (toxoid), Rhinopneumonitis, Influenza, Rabies, EEE, WEE, West Nile 
(also accept Botulism on farms where disease has been documented)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5274 bonus TH609","question":"Name 3 of the most dangerous locations for bleeding.  ","answer":"Neck, chest, forelegs, trunk, & hind legs (jugular vein, carotid artery, subclavian arteries & vein, aorta, femoral arteries & vein, digital arteries)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5275 bonus FCH272/HIH445-7	","question":"By what age should Tetanus, WEE, EEE, & West Nile vaccines be given to 1) a foal from a vaccinated mare & 2) a foal from an unvaccinated mare?","answer":"By 6 months for foals from vaccinated mares; by 3-4 months for foals from unvaccinated mares"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5276 bonus FCH301","question":"Name 3 causes of slobbering or excessive salivation ","answer":"Choke, sharp points on the teeth, poorly fitted bits, inappropriately used bits, infectious diseases of the mouth (vesicular stomatitis), horses bedded on wood shavings containing bitter weed, drugs, old toothless horses  some types of forage can cause slobbering (red clover)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5277 bonus HIH795-2","question":"Name 3 uses of horses that increase the incidence of gastric ulcers.","answer":"Racing, endurance, & showing"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5278 bonus HIH 445-2 new","question":"The AVMA lists 5 vaccinations in the "core" group.  Name 3. ","answer":"Tetanus, West Nile, EEE (Eastern Equine Encephalomyelitis), WEE (Western Equine Encephalomyelitis), Rabies"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5279 bonus HIH various","question":"Give 3 reasons why a gelding would be excessively overweight other than hormonal reasons.","answer":"Grass fat/unrestricted grazing, inadequate exercise, intentionally overfed to mask undesirable traits if being shown/sold, unintentionally overfed, dominant horse in feeding situation"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5280 bonus HIH425-2","question":"2 part question -- The color of a horse's urine can indicate health problems.  Name 3 of these problems & the accompanying urine color.","answer":"Red ï¿½bleeding in urinary tract; 
Brownish greenï¿½jaundice or liver problems;
Dark brown or coffee coloredï¿½azorturia or tying up"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5281 bonus HIH140-1","question":"Name 3 ways to determine a horse's weight.","answer":"Livestock scales, weight tape, visual estimation/guessing  "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5282 bonus HIH410-1/BEG104-2L/ES155","question":"Name 3 factors that can cause temperature variations in the individual horse.","answer":"Age, sex, time of day, rain or snow, wind, outside temperature, disease, level/intensity of activity,  stress/anxiety"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5283 bonus HIH441-5,410-2","question":"Describe 3 things you can do for an overheated horse.","answer":"#1 - call the vet!  Until vet arrives - spray/hose down with water, put horse in shade or cool stall, use fans, put ice on head or topline, give a few swallows of water"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5284 bonus TH113","question":"Name 3 factors that affect the horse's heart rate.","answer":"Exercise level, pain, disease, level of excitement, fever, temperature, humidity, stroke volume, cardiac output"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5285 bonus HIH1150-2","question":"Give 2 reasons why you would take your horse's feed & water buckets with you when you travel.","answer":"Familiar containers reduce stress, reduces risk of disease from contaminated mangers, water tanks, etc"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5286 bonus FCH260-61 HIH975-11","question":"Give3 clinical signs that a foal has a gastric ulcer.","answer":"Depression, grinding teeth, colic, diarrhea, poor body condition, pot-belly appearance, laying on back, poor appetite/, decreased nursing excessive salivation, froth around lips, "},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5287 bonus FCH403","question":"Name 3 symptoms of shock.","answer":"Loss of color of mucous membranes, decreased temperature of extremities, feeble or rapid pulse, decreased or shallow breathing, restlessness, anxiety, loss of blood volume/pressure, inability to stand, sometimes unconscious"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5288 bonus CAHA62","question":"Name 3 places where a horse's pulse can be felt using your fingers.","answer":"Under jaw, below eye, below hock, medial side of pastern, hind leg outside cannon bone, along fetlock next to deep digital flexor tendon, front leg inside just below knee, base of tail, behind elbow
Also accepted - specific arteries -- facial, transverse facial, lateral dorsal metatarsal, digital, metacarpal"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5289 bonus HIH1160","question":"Name 3 general types of bandages.","answer":"Support, shipping, first aid"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5290 bonus HIH1160-1","question":"Name a material used for each of the 3 bandage layers","answer":"Primary/contact layerï¿½Telfa pad (or similar), release pad, gauze pad, etc.;
Secondary layerï¿½sheet cotton, roll cotton, quilted leg wraps;
Outer/tertiary layerï¿½vet wrap, Elasticon"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5292 bonus HIH1160-1/440-4","question":"Name 3 purposes of bandaging.","answer":"Support, keep wound clean, protect from infection/dirt/insects, protect from further trauma, absorbs drainage, travel protection, immobilization, control bleeding, reduce swelling, keeps medication on wound"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5293 bonus TH/HIH/various","question":"Name 3 things that can cause skin & hair problems in horses.","answer":"Nutritional deficiencies, infections, trauma, sunburn, parasites, allergies, freezing, chemical irritants"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5294 bonus INT1203-2L","question":"In reference to ï¿½Body Condition Scoreï¿½, name 3 of the body sites that are evaluated.","answer":"Neck, withers, back, tail head, behind the shoulder at fore rib, ribs at mid-barrel"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5295 bonus FCH245,3,4","question":"Name 3 paths of physiological water loss from a horseï¿½s body.","answer":"Urine, sweat, feces, respiration"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5296 bonus TH611","question":"Name 3 symptoms of tying up.","answer":"Horse is reluctant to move, stiff all over, sweating, painful breathing, muscle tremors, dark urine"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5297 bonus TH594","question":"Name 3 signs of inflammation.","answer":"Heat, pain, swelling, redness"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5298 bonus FCH308/HIH/TH/DET","question":"Name 3 possible causes of anemia.","answer":"Blood loss, increased destruction of red blood cells, decreased production of red blood cells by bone marrow, infection, chronic disease, dietary deficiency, toxins, lack of iron, parasites, incompatible blood types"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5299 bonus FCH214","question":"Fatigue or exhaustion may result from a deficit of what 2 things?","answer":"Energy, water, electrolytes"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5300 bonus HS37,45-46","question":"What are 3 ways you can help prevent infectious diseases in horses?","answer":"Avoid contact with sick animals, cleanliness, disinfect boots when going from one farm to another, provide boot dip for visitors to farm, wash hands before/after touching animals, disposable boots, remove manure from trailer, disinfect trailer between uses, isolate new horses at least 14 days before introducing to herd, don't use same needle to vaccinate different horses	 (accept any reasonable answers)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5301 bonus HS46","question":"If horses are confined & can't exercise, what are 3 things that could happen?","answer":"Lose muscle tone, become stiff or lame, digestive system won't function as effectively, stocking up, become nervous, develop stable vices, gain weight"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5302 bonus HS45","question":"What are 3 good reasons why you should be concerned with maintaining the proper health of your horse?","answer":"It's your responsibility to protect your horse from injury or illness, if your horse is ill, you can't use him, if your horse needs treatment, it costs you money & time"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5303 bonus HIH410","question":"Name 3 problems that can occur when working an out of condition horse.","answer":"Laminitis or founder, heat exhaustion, exhaustion, heart attack, stroke, lameness, tying up, muscle soreness	 (accept any reasonable answers)"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5304 bonus HIH120","question":"According to the Horse Industry Handbook, what are 3 things you need to do in order to keep your horse in year-round good health?","answer":"Feed properly, take care of feet, exercise, deworm, provide shelter, provide water, immunize/vaccinate"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5305 bonus HS45","question":"Name 3 problems that can be caused by overfeeding horses.","answer":"Fat, founder, become temporarily infertile, aggravates respiratory problems, colic"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5306 bonus HIH450-6","question":"Give 3 visual signs of old age in the horse.","answer":"Gray hairs around eyes/muzzle, deep depressions above the eyes, swayback, drooping lower lip, harder to keep weight on horse, angle of incisor teeth, stiffness in legs/joints, coarser hair coat, Galwayne's groove"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5307 bonus HIH440-1","question":"Name 4 types of open wounds.","answer":"Incisions, lacerations/tears, punctures, abrasions, penetrating wounds"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5308 bonus HIH410","question":"Name 3 causes of hyperthermia in horses.","answer":"Hot weather, high humidity, poor stable ventilation, prolonged exposure to direct sunlight, overwork, transportation, obesity"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5309 bonus HIH410","question":"Name 3 precautions you can take to avoid overheating in horses.","answer":"Remove blankets/sheets, use fans, make sure there's ventilation for stabled horses, strenuous work only during cooler times of day/cooler seasons, water available at all times, shade available, salt available, use electrolytes, clip long hair, transport during cool times of day"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5310 bonus HIH440-1","question":"What are 3 common causes of horse wounds?","answer":"Kicks, bites, falls, colliding with objects, trauma, lacerations from fencing"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5311 bonus HIH425-1","question":"Name 3 things to consider when evaluating the general healthiness of a horse.","answer":"Temperature, pulse rate, respiration rate, body fluids (urine, feces), mucous membranes, hoof condition, behaviors, body condition score, weight, movement, feeding habits, coat condition"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"5312 bonus HIH1160-1","question":"Identify three indications or reasons for the use of bandages.         ","answer":"Protection from trauma (shipping/travel wraps)
To absorb exudates
To control hemorrhage (bleeding)
To exert pressure which can prevent/reduce edema
To support an injured limb
To protect a wound from environmental contamination/infection
To aid in removal of necrotic tissue/for debridement
To provide comfort"},
{"category":"HEALTH & SANITATION","level":"bonus","number":"7149 bonus HIH440-5","question":"Name 3 common conditions or management practices that can result in injury to the horse.","answer":"Barns/stalls/fences/gates either too small or not designed properly for horses or in poor repair; improper building materials (poor quality wood, barb wire, hog wire, etc.); uncapped steel posts; sharp edges on waterers/feeders, etc.; lack of or improper bedding; protruding nails, bolts, etc.; misc. equipment or junk in pasture; overcrowding; allowing aggressive horses in group situations; lack of feeder space in group situations; using wire to hang buckets/feeders; improper tying	 (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5313 easy HH4/TH4/ES5","question":"On what continent did Equus originate?	","answer":"North America"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5314 easy HS5/H2-7","question":"What does Eohippus mean?","answer":"Dawn horse"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5315 easy HS4/ES9","question":"How tall was Eohippus?","answer":"About 12 inches"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5316 easy ES9","question":"What was the original ancestor of the modern horse?","answer":"Eohippus  "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5317 easy TH4/HS4","question":"What proof do we have of what ancient horses were like?	","answer":"Fossils"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5318 easy HS5/TH7","question":"How did horses return to North America during the 1500ï¿½s?","answer":"Spanish explorers"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5319 easy HS4/TH6","question":"What animal has played a significant role in warfare since ancient times?","answer":"Horse"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5320 easy HS5","question":"The Greek word "eos" means dawn.  What does the Anglo-Saxon word "hors" mean?","answer":"Swiftness"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5321 easy HS4/TH4","question":"What was the final stage of development of the horse?","answer":"Equus"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5322 easy HS5/ES9","question":"How tall was Mesohippus?","answer":"24 inches"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5323 easy HS4/ES9","question":"What is the second stage in the horse's evolution?","answer":"Mesohippus"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5324 easy TH4/HS4","question":"When Equus died out in North America, how did some of the population survive?","answer":"Crossed a land bridge between Alaska & Siberia (Russia)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5325 easy TH6/HS4","question":"Name one of the horse's greatest contributions to human history.  ","answer":"Use in war, transportation, beast of burden/draft animal       (accept any)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5326 easy TH9","question":"What caused the decline of draft horse use?","answer":"Invention of the combustible engine OR it was replaced by tractor    (accept either)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"easy","number":"5327 easy ES7","question":"Identify the 2 land masses that were once connected by the Bering Land Bridge","answer":"Alaska & Siberia/Russia                    "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5328 medium TH13","question":"Warmblooded animals that give milk & have hair fall into what zoological class?","answer":"Mammalia"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5329 medium HS5","question":"What language does the term "Eohippus" come from?","answer":"Greek"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5330 medium HS5","question":"Which toe of Mesohippus became the foot of Equus?","answer":"Middle toe  "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5331 medium HIH163B-1","question":"Which individual is credited with bringing the first spotted horses to North America?","answer":"Cortez"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5332 medium TH4","question":"What is the Greek word for horse?","answer":"Hippus"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5333 medium HS4","question":"Which toe of Mesohippus was largest?","answer":"Middle one"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5334 medium HS4","question":"How many toes did Mesohippus have?","answer":"Three on each foot    	 (additional info -- middle toe largest)	"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5335 medium HS4","question":"Geologists suggest our modern horse began his history how long ago?","answer":"55 - 60 million years ago (58 million years ago)  	(accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5336 medium TH7","question":"Where were horses first domesticated?","answer":"Asia & Europe"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5337 medium TH7","question":"2 part question:   When did horses return to North America & who brought them?","answer":"16th century (1500ï¿½s),   Spaniards"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5338 medium HS2","question":"2 part question:  The word ï¿½horsï¿½ comes from what language group & what does it mean?","answer":"Anglo-Saxon;    swiftness  "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5339 medium TH13","question":"What is Latin for the genus & species of horse?","answer":"Equus caballus"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5340 medium HS4","question":"What type of environment was Eohippus most suited for?","answer":"Forested & swampy"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5341 medium TH6","question":"Domestication of the horse had spread to almost every area of Europe, Asia & North Africa by what date?    ","answer":"1000 BC   "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5342 medium TH9","question":"What is one reason why horses were not widely used in Puritan New England?","answer":"Hilly/rocky fields were better suited for oxen OR Puritan ethic discouraged the expense & frivolity of keeping riding horses"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5343 medium TH9","question":"2 part question:  Who first imported the draft breeds to America & why?","answer":"Farmers in New York & Pennsylvania; they needed heavier horses to haul & plow"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5344 medium TH6","question":"What ABILITY of the horse had the greatest significance in building civilization?","answer":"Its ability to carry & pull loads OR ability to serve as draft animal for work and/or transportation  "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5345 medium TH4","question":"During what time period did Equus migrate over the land bridges to Asia?","answer":"Ice Age 	(additional info -- approximately 1 million years ago)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"medium","number":"5346 medium TH5","question":"Although the precise date of domestication of the horse remains unknown, what serves as the first record of man's dependence on the horse?  These records date back to the most ancient of times.","answer":"Cave drawings/paintings"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5347 hard TH4","question":"In regards to the history of the horse, what event took place during the Pleistocene epoch in North America?","answer":"Horse became extinct in North America"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5348 hard ES9","question":"How many toes did Merychippus have?","answer":"3"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5349 hard ES9","question":"Describe the difference between the front legs of Mesohippus & Merychippus.","answer":"Mesohippus - all 3 toes touched the ground;       Merychippus - only the middle toe touched the ground"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5350 hard ES9","question":"How tall was Merychippus?","answer":"About the size of a Shetland Pony"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5351 hard ES9","question":"How tall was Pliohippus?","answer":"About the size of a pony"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5352 hard TH13","question":"In the zoological classification, what phylum does the horse belong to?","answer":"Chordata"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5353 hard HS4","question":"2 part question:  How many toes did Eohippus have on his front feet & how many on his back feet?","answer":"Front foot ï¿½ 4;     back foot ï¿½ 3 "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5354 hard TH5","question":"The appearance of man in North America during the Paleolithic era coincided with the disappearance of the horse from the continent.  What early use of the horse by man could have contributed to this?","answer":"Use of the horse as food"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5355 hard TH13","question":"In reference to zoological classification, the horse is classified as belonging to the phylum "chordata".  What is the basis for this classification?","answer":"Animals with a backbone     (animals with notochords or spinal cords)"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5357 hard ES9","question":"What ancestral horse was the first to exhibit only one toe on each foot?","answer":"Pliohippus"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"hard","number":"5358 hard ES15","question":"In the zoological classification, what is the order the horse would be included in?","answer":"Perissodactyla                             "},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5359 bonus TH5","question":"Early wild horses showed great adaptability in the environments where they lived.  Name 2 of those environments.","answer":"Steppes, forests, deserts, tundra"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5360 bonus TH5","question":"The horse's early development was affected by wide variations in several things.  Name 2.","answer":"Altitude, climate, soil, forage"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5361 bonus TH6","question":"Name 2 of the earliest areas of the horse's domestication.","answer":"China & Mesopotamia"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5362 bonus TH7,8","question":"How did the use of the horse differ between the Plains & the East Coast Indians?","answer":"Plains Indians- used to hunt for food, pack animals, war;    East Coast - used for pack animals"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5363 bonus TH6-10/HIH various","question":"Give 4 general uses of the horse throughout time.","answer":"Food, pack animals, transportation, war, pleasure, recreation, sports, agriculture, showing, rodeo, etc"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5364 bonus TH4","question":"Name 3 other animals that became extinct from North America about the same time as the horse (during the Pleistocene era).","answer":"Rhinoceros, saber-toothed tiger, mastodon, camel, elephant"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5365 bonus TH4","question":"Give 3 reasons that are thought to be the cause of the horse's extinction in North & South America during the Pleistocene era.","answer":"Disease, depletion of food sources, insects, early human intervention, sudden climate change, parasites, failure to adapt to environment"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5366 bonus HS4/ES9","question":"Timelineï¿½The evolution of the horse began approximately 75 million years ago with the ï¿½Prehorseï¿½.  Put the following five major forms of the horse in the correct order beginning with the most ancient form and ending with the present    ï¿½ Merychippusï¿½ Pliohippusï¿½ Equusï¿½ Mesohippusï¿½   Eohippus","answer":"Eohippusï¿½Mesohippusï¿½Merychippusï¿½Pliohippusï¿½Equus"},
{"category":"HISTORY","level":"bonus","number":"5367 bonus TH4","question":"Name 3 continents where fossil remains of horses have been found.","answer":"Asia, Europe, Africa, North America, South America"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5368 easy HH10/TH152/CAHA4","question":"What part of the horse needs to be deep & fairly thick with good V muscling?","answer":"Chest  "},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5369 easy HH14","question":"What is the key to success in giving oral reasons?","answer":"Practice"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5370 easy HH15","question":"Where should your hands be while you're delivering a set of oral reasons?","answer":"Behind your back"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5371 easy HH14","question":"How are horses usually numbered in a judging class?","answer":"1 - 4,    left to right"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5372 easy HH14","question":"What is most important in giving oral reasons?","answer":"Accuracy"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5373 easy HH14","question":"What is the maximum time for giving oral reasons?","answer":"Two minutes"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5374 easy HIH230-1","question":"When horse judging, besides having a knowledge of anatomy, you should also be able to recognize what?","answer":"Unsoundnesses, blemishes, or conformation faults      (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5375 easy HH14","question":"At what distance should one stand from an oral reasons judge while delivering a set of oral reasons?","answer":"About 6 - 10 feet	(accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5376 easy HH14","question":"When is the best time to take notes at a judging class?","answer":"When the class is in front of you      (during the class)"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5377 easy HH14","question":"In a horse judging contest, should you prepare your notes before or after making your final placing?","answer":"Before"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5378 easy HH14","question":"According to the Horses & Horsemanship manual, how does one develop the art of horse judging?","answer":"Study & practice"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5379 easy HH9/TH133","question":"In judging, how do you determine if a horse has balance?","answer":"Forequarters & hindquarters appear to be nearly equal size & development OR proportionally as long as it's tall	(accept either)"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5380 easy HH15","question":"In judging contests, should one make the placing mostly on essential characteristics, less essential characteristics or both?","answer":"Mostly on essential characteristics"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5381 easy HH14","question":"In reference to horse judging, what determines how easy your reasons are to follow?","answer":"How you organize them    (they should be logical & clear)"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5382 easy HH16","question":"In judging, when should you omit a difference in pairs from your reasons?","answer":"When it's minor or when it leaves room for doubt"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5383 easy HIH220-1","question":"When determining the quality of a horse's conformation, to what do you compare it?","answer":"Ideal horse for the breed"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5384 easy HIH220-6","question":"Other than its intended use, what is the most important characteristic in equine selection?","answer":"Balance"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5385 easy HH14","question":"What is necessary for one to properly place a class & give good reasons?","answer":"Accurate observations OR knowing what you're looking at"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5386 easy HIH230-1","question":"What is the main factor to consider in evaluating the seriousness of a leg conformation fault?","answer":"How it affects the travel and/or durability of the horse"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5387 easy HH15-16","question":"Under what conditions should you switch a pair when judging?","answer":"Only on less essential characteristics"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5388 easy HIH220-1","question":"In a halter class, what is the judge looking for?","answer":"A horse that resembles the ideal for the breed  (conformation)"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"easy","number":"5389 easy HIH220-5/TH132","question":"What is the single most important factor when selecting a horse?","answer":"Intended use"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"medium","number":"5390 medium HH15","question":"How is the phrase ï¿½I grantï¿½ used in horse judging oral reasons?","answer":"Used to explain a desirable feature of a less desirable horse in a judging class  "},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"medium","number":"5391 medium HH14","question":"When judging a horse, from what position would you view the length & width of the gaskin muscle?","answer":"Rear"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"medium","number":"5392 medium HH9","question":"A horse that doesn't fit the general description of the ideal saddle horse is said to be what?","answer":"Off type"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"medium","number":"5393 medium HH14","question":"Name 2 things you check for when judging the horse at the trot.","answer":"Straightness of action, ease/smoothness of action, lameness	"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"medium","number":"5394 medium HH16","question":"What do the following terms have in common ï¿½long hip, sloping shoulder, straight legs & deep girth?","answer":"They are all essentials in judging"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"bonus","number":"5395 bonus DET129","question":"Name 3 things horses shown at Halter Class are judged on.","answer":"Type, conformation, quality, substance (muscling or condition), soundness (way of going), sex characteristics, possibly color/pattern, balance"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"bonus","number":"5396 bonus HH14-16","question":"When judging a quality class of mules, what 2 things should be considered?","answer":"What the mules will be used for & the ideal animal for that purpose "},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"bonus","number":"5397 bonus HIH220-1","question":"Name 3 ways horses are viewed in a judging class.","answer":"Left side view, front view, right side view, hind view, at the walk, at the trot"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"bonus","number":"5398 bonus HIH220-1","question":"Name 3 important points in giving a good set of oral reasons.","answer":"Accuracy, presentation, mental picture of the class, use proper terms"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"bonus","number":"5399 bonus HH16","question":"When giving oral reasons, name 3 terms to describe a desirable walk.","answer":"Straight, smooth, well-balanced, good stride, quick, elastic"},
{"category":"HORSE JUDGING","level":"bonus","number":"5400 bonus HH16","question":"When judging, name 3 things to look for when viewing the front of the horse from a distance.","answer":"Shape/expression of head, size/setting of ears, width of chest, muscling of arm/forearm/chest, set of front legs, alignment of knee & cannon"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5401 easy HIH415-6","question":"During what time of the year are adult bot flies most active?","answer":"Late summer to early fall"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5402 easy HIH430-1","question":"If you see a rough hair coat on a horse, what would you suspect the problem is?","answer":"Worms    (parasites)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5403 easy HIH430-6","question":"In reference to parasites, what can happen if a pasture is overgrazed?","answer":"Pasture can become a serious source of parasite infections   (horse can get worms)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5404 easy HIH430-6","question":"Ideally, horses should be rotated to fresh pasture every 2 weeks.  Why?","answer":"To allow the pasture time to re-grow OR to reduce parasite infestation  "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5405 easy HIH430-6/TH606","question":"Why should you never feed your horse on the ground?","answer":"Horse can get parasites OR horse can eat sand & can develop colic"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5406 easy HIH430-7","question":"Why should you rotate or alternate chemical deworming products?","answer":"Worms can develop resistance"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5407 easy HIH110-5","question":"What is it called when you give medication to decrease the number of internal parasites in the horse?","answer":"Deworming or worming"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5408 easy HIH430-4","question":"How can you remove bot eggs?","answer":"Scrape them off"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5409 easy HIH415-5,430-3","question":"What insect does the adult bot fly look like?","answer":"Honeybee"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5410 easy HIH430","question":"What general type of horse is very susceptible to internal parasites?","answer":"Young, thin, old, or horses in poor condition		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5411 easy HIH430-2/TH649-50","question":"What cycle of a parasite must be broken to decrease the number of parasites in horses?","answer":"Life cycle"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5412 easy HIH430-3/FCH158","question":"What parasite causes a horse to rub his rump against posts, trees or other objects?  ","answer":"Pinworms, mites, or lice 	(do not need to give all)	"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5413 easy HIH430-1/HS35","question":"Internal parasites are particularly harmful to foals & young horses up to what age?","answer":"18 months - 2 years 		(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5414 easy HIH430-1,2","question":"Generally speaking, what age horses are ascarid infections restricted to?","answer":"Young horses 	(generally less than 18 months)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5415 easy HIH430-4,5","question":"What age horses are affected by strongyles & bots?","answer":"All ages"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5416 easy HIH430-2","question":"What may happen if horses are de-wormed too frequently?","answer":"Parasites may develop resistance"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5417 easy HIH430-1/TH630","question":"What is the most common cause attributed to coughing, pot bellies & rough hair coats in young horses?","answer":"Worms (specifically ascarids or roundworms)  	 (accept either general or specific answer)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5418 easy HIH430-3","question":"Where on the horse do bot eggs hatch?","answer":"In the horseï¿½s mouth"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5419 easy HIH430-6,730-9","question":"How does dragging pastures kill internal parasites?","answer":"Exposes them to the sun"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5420 easy HIH430-3/TH640","question":"What is the most obvious clinical sign of pinworm infestation?","answer":"Rubbed tail/rump OR bare patches on tailhead/buttocks      (accept either)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5421 easy HIH430-1/TH644-66","question":"2 part question:  When worming, what stage of the worm's life cycle do you particularly want to destroy & why?","answer":"Adult;   so they can't lay eggs"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5422 easy HIH430-7","question":"What times of year is it most important to deworm horses?","answer":"Spring & Fall"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5423 easy HIH430","question":"How can you evaluate the effectiveness  of dewormers?","answer":"Have vet do a fecal egg count"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5424 easy HIH430-3","question":"Historically, only young horses were susceptible to pinworms, but for some unknown reason, they are now found in what age groups?","answer":"All ages"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5425 easy HIH430-4","question":"What causes bot eggs to hatch?","answer":"Warmth & moisture from the horseï¿½s tongue "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5426 easy HIH430-10","question":"What is the main principle for how frequently to worm your horse?","answer":"Deworm as infrequently as possible, but as often as necessary    (also accept as recommended by your vet)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5427 easy HIH430","question":"Which is more important in parasite control, treatment or prevention?","answer":"Prevention"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5428 easy HIH430/HS56/TH647","question":"How often should horses be ï¿½wormedï¿½?","answer":"As recommended by your vet OR 2 times a year in the spring & fall OR 4 times a year OR every 2 months OR daily with certain types of wormers"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5429 easy HS43/HIH430","question":"Which internal parasite of the horse spends its adult life outside of the horse?","answer":"Bots"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5430 easy HS43/HIH430","question":"Name the fly that hovers about the horse, then quickly darts toward the animal & glues individual eggs to the hair in a matter of seconds?","answer":"Bot fly"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"easy","number":"5431 easy TH640","question":"What color are pinworms?","answer":"White"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5432 medium DET106,213,224,156","question":"Fenbendazole, Piperazine, Pyrantel and Ivermectin are examples of what type of medication? ","answer":"Anthelminitic    (de-wormer) "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5433 medium FCH161","question":"Name the wormer available in alfalfa-flavored pellets which is designed to be fed on a daily basis.","answer":"Strongid C"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5434 medium HIH430-6","question":"What is the most common form of anti-parasitic compound for horses?","answer":"Paste"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5435 medium TH623","question":"Define larvae.","answer":"The immature, worm-like form of certain parasites"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5436 medium HIH430-4","question":"Tapeworms infect horses through which intermediate host?","answer":"Mites 	(specifically oribatid mite)		accept either general or specific"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5437 medium HIH430-6","question":"How does mowing & harrowing a pasture help control parasites?","answer":"Breaks up the manure deposits & exposes larvae to sun which kills them"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5438 medium TH588","question":"Where in the horseï¿½s digestive system would you find bot larvae attached?","answer":"Stomach"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5439 medium HIH430-5","question":"Which internal parasite is the most significant & most common?","answer":"Strongyle"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5440 medium HIH415-5,430-3","question":"How do bot fly larvae usually get into the horse's mouth?","answer":"Horse bites/licks at areas where eggs are laid which stimulates hatching of the eggs"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5441 medium HIH415-5,430-3","question":"How many species of bot fly are there?","answer":"At least 3"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5442 medium HIH430","question":"In the 5 stage cycle of the life cycle of a parasite, what happens in stage 1?","answer":"Eggs passed out to pasture"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5443 medium HIH430","question":"At what stage in an internal parasite's life cycle does it become infective?","answer":"Stage 2   (larvae)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5444 medium HIH430-5","question":"What is the main damage caused by pinworms?","answer":"Irritation to the anal region causing tail rubbing"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5445 medium HIH430-5","question":"What forms as a result of the bloodworms migrating in the arteries?","answer":"Blood clots"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5446 medium HIH430-1","question":"Which specific internal parasite is most common in young horses?","answer":"Ascarids (also accept roundworms, nematodes, or Parascaris equorum)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5447 medium HIH430-6","question":"What is an anthelmintic?","answer":"De-wormer		 (wormer)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5448 medium HIH430","question":"What is a fecal egg count?","answer":"Lab procedure used to determine the number of parasite eggs in a fecal sample"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5449 medium HS44","question":"When the horse licks or bites itself, where the bot fly eggs are attached, what does this do?","answer":"Stimulates hatching"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5450 medium HIH430-1","question":"Why are horses older than 18 months not commonly infected with ascarids?","answer":"They develop immunity after being exposed early in life"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5451 medium HIH430-2","question":"Most foals infected with threadworms don't show any symptoms.  For those that do, what is the main symptom?","answer":"Diarrhea"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5475 medium HIH430-4","question":"Tapeworms cluster in the cecum.  The presence of large numbers of tapeworms may result in what?","answer":"Intestinal blockage & colic"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5476 medium HIH430-6","question":"No deworming schedule fits every horse.  Name 2 reasons why.","answer":"Local parasite resistance, fecal egg count of horse, age of horse, health of the horse, number of horses on farm, climate  "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5477 medium HIH430-7","question":"Parasite control programs should target which specific internal parasite that is the most common & is the most problematic.","answer":"Strongyles		(specifically small strongyles)			accept either general or specific"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5479 medium HIH430-7","question":"Effective de-wormers should be able to reduce the number of eggs shed by how much?","answer":"At least 90% 	  (additional info -- below 80% usually indicates resistance)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5480 medium HIH430-8","question":"In customizing an internal parasite control program, what is the first & most important step?","answer":"Determine which drugs are still effective "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5481 medium HS45","question":"How long are most strongyles?","answer":"Less than an inch"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5482 medium HIH430-4","question":"What is another name for strongyles?","answer":"Bloodworms"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5483 medium HIH430-1","question":"Where do ascarid larvae develop into mature worms?","answer":"Small intestine"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5484 medium HIH430-2,3 975-14","question":"Which type of worm affects foals almost exclusively, causing diarrhea, dehydration & weight loss?","answer":"Threadworms     (strongyloides or Strongyloides westeri)	   accept either general or specific"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5485 medium HIH430-2","question":"The more mature ascarids are, the more they are susceptible to what?","answer":"De-worming agents"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5486 medium HIH430-6","question":"What is a disadvantage to harrowing or dragging your pasture in the fall?","answer":"Leaves it uniformly contaminated until the following spring   "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"medium","number":"5487 medium HIH430-7","question":"Why is it necessary to know which de-worming agent is effective with which internal parasite?","answer":"They differ in their effectiveness OR some worms are resistant to some dewormers"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5488 hard FCH159","question":"What type of parasite usually only occurs in horses that are grazed in pastures with donkeys?","answer":"Lungworms"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5489 hard HIH415-5","question":"How long does the mature bot fly take to emerge from the pupa case?","answer":"1 - 2 months				accept either"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5490 hard HIH430-9","question":"Approximately what percent of horses in a herd are able to maintain relatively low numbers of strongyles without any deworming?","answer":"50%"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5491 hard HIH430-9","question":"As a rule of thumb, about 20% of the horses in any herd are responsible for what percent of internal parasite egg production?","answer":"80%"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5492 hard HIH430-1","question":"Name 3 internal parasites of horses.","answer":"Strongyles/bloodworms, ascarids/roundworms/nematodes, strongyloides/threadworms, pinworms, bots, tapeworms  "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5493 hard HIH430-3","question":"Where may pinworm eggs be found?","answer":"Around horseï¿½s anus, pasture, feces, bedding, feeding areas, water	 (only need to name one)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5494 hard HIH430-1","question":"Which internal parasite's eggs are very resistant to the outside environment & may survive as long as a decade?","answer":"Ascarid"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5495 hard HIH430-3","question":"How long does it take for the bot egg to mature in the stomach?","answer":"Approximately 8 months"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5496 hard HIH430-3","question":"During what seasons do bots detach themselves from the stomach wall & are passed outside in the feces?","answer":"Spring & summer"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5497 hard TH623-29","question":"At what stage of development do large & small strongyles have marked differences?","answer":"4th stage"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5498 hard TH630","question":"Describe stage 5 of the ascarid life cycle.","answer":"Develop into mature worms & begin egg production"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5499 hard HIH430-9","question":"The tendency of some horses to harbor large numbers of internal parasites & therefore shed large egg amounts is due to what?","answer":"Genetic trait"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5500 hard HIH430-7","question":"What is ï¿½tubingï¿½ a horse?","answer":"Inserting a nasogastric tube to release gas or to give medications such as wormers or medicines for colic"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5501 hard HIH430-1","question":"How do ascarid larvae get out of the lungs to the small intestine?","answer":"Coughed up & then swallowed"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5502 hard HIH430-8","question":"How can you totally eradicate large strongyles from a closed herd?","answer":"Use 1 larvicidal treatment every 6 months.  Since the life cycle is approximately 6 - 8 months, all will be eradicated within 18 months in a closed herd"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5503 hard HIH430/TH623-35","question":"What happens in stage 4 in the life cycle of an internal parasite?","answer":"Migration of immature worms through the horse's tissues"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5504 hard HIH430-5","question":"What internal parasite causes damage to the arterial walls?","answer":"Strongyles OR bloodworms OR Strongylus vulgaris"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5505 hard HIH430-8","question":"Small strongyles are almost universally resistant to what drug class?","answer":"Benzimidazoles     (also accept pyrantel)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5506 hard HIH430-1","question":"Where do ascarid larvae go after penetrating the stomach wall?","answer":"Into the bloodstream where they migrate to the liver & lungs"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5507 hard TH617","question":"What is a nematode?","answer":"Another name for a roundworm OR ascarid OR Parascaris equorum"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5508 hard HIH430-8","question":"Besides incorporating ERP (egg reappearance period) into your parasite control program, the refugia needs to be kept as large as possible - why?","answer":"The resistant genes will be diluted by susceptible ones"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5509 hard TH630/HIH430","question":"How long are ascarids?","answer":"5 - 15 inches		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5510 hard TH645","question":"What skin problem of horses is a possible result of the internal parasite Habronema?","answer":"Summer sores (dermatitis granulose)		accept either"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5511 hard HIH975-14	HIH430","question":"How long is the life cycle of the ascarid?","answer":"2-3 months	(10-12 weeks)		accept either"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5512 hard TH630","question":"What is the common name for Parascaris equorum?","answer":"Ascarid OR roundworm OR nematode"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5513 hard HIH415-5","question":"A large infestation of bots can cause paralysis of what part of the alimentary canal?","answer":"Esophagus"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5514 hard HS45","question":"Where do pinworms mature?","answer":"In the large intestine"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5515 hard TH623","question":"What blood vessel is damaged by Strongylus vulgaris?","answer":"Cranial mesenteric artery"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5516 hard HIH430-2","question":"How are foals infected with strongyloides or threadworms?","answer":"Ingest larvae in mare's milk OR ingestion or penetrating skin by free-living larvae in pastures, paddocks, etc."},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5517 hard INT200-3L","question":"What color are the eggs of the nose bot fly?","answer":"Black"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5518 hard HIH430-8","question":"In reference to parasite control, what is "refugia"?","answer":"Parasite population that hasn't been exposed to de-wormers"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5519 hard TH405","question":"What causes summer sores?","answer":"Stomach worm larvae in the skin OR Habronema"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5520 hard FCH159","question":"Horses infected with lungworms have generally been exposed to what animal?","answer":"Donkey"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5521 hard FCH157","question":"Name 2 organs where you might find Parascaris equorum as either adults or larvae?","answer":"Small intestine, lungs, liver"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5522 hard HS43","question":"How many eggs does the female bot fly lay?","answer":"About 500"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5523 hard FCH158","question":"What is the genus of this parasite?  Adult horses rarely have clinical problems.  They primarily affect nursing foals.  The small, thread-like adult worms in the small intestine can cause diarrhea & un-thriftiness.","answer":"Strongyloides"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5524 hard HIH430-5","question":"What is the scientific name of the following parasite?  Life cycle takes 6 - 7 months with the adult ending up in the large intestine.  The larvae migrate to the anterior mesenteric artery & may cause problems within the digestive tract by forming clots.  They are the most dangerous of the 3 large strongyles.","answer":"Strongylus vulgaris"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5525 hard HIH430-1","question":"Why might a horse showing pulmonary symptoms of ascarids have a negative fecal count?","answer":"These symptoms are associated with immature worms, not egg-laying adults"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5526 hard HIH430-1","question":"How many eggs can a female ascarid lay per day?","answer":"200,000"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5527 hard HIH430-4","question":"What drug is 100% effective against tapeworms?","answer":"Praziquantel 	(found in Equimax, Quest Plus, & Zimectrin Gold)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5528 hard HIH430-5","question":"Environmental conditions are critical to the transmission of strongyles.  Eggs will only hatch & develop into infective larvae at what temperature?","answer":"45 - 85 degrees		 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5540 hard HIH430-7","question":"What is anthelmintic resistance?","answer":"Ability of a worm to survive a dose of an anthelmintic  (wormer) which previously had  been effective"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5542 hard HIH430-4","question":"The orbatid mite is the intermediate host for which internal parasite?","answer":"Tapeworm                "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5543 hard HIH430-4","question":"Praziquantel & pyrantel pamoate are both effective for the control of tapeworms.  How does the dosage of pyrantel paomate need to be altered when treating tapeworms?","answer":"Give twice the standard dose                "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"5544 hard FCH157","question":"What type of parasite may result in coughing, fever & nasal discharge ï¿½ which is commonly referred to as a ï¿½summer coldï¿½ - in foals?","answer":"Roundworms   (parascaris equorum)    "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"hard","number":"7148 hard HIH430-7","question":"What is ERP or egg reappearance period?","answer":"The time interval between treatment & resumption of significant number of eggs"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"BONUS","number":"5546 BONUS ES188/HIH430-3","question":"Horses can be grouped into low, medium & high "contaminators" according to their fecal egg counts.  Give the approximate egg count for each group.","answer":"Low - counts below 200
Medium - counts between 200 - 500
High - counts above 500"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"BONUS","number":"5547 BONUS ES189/HIH430-2","question":"Describe 3 life cycle stages of ascarids/roundworms.","answer":"Life cycle is about 3 months; eggs are passed out in feces to pasture; eggs become infective; eggs are swallowed by animal; larvae hatch in intestinal tract; larvae migrate through blood stream to liver & lungs; larvae are coughed up & swallowed; worms mature & reproduce in the small intestines"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5548 bonus HIH430-9","question":"Customizing your internal parasite control program will reduce your cost & diminish resistance in parasites.  Give the general recommended worming schedule for low, medium & high "contaminators".","answer":"Low contaminators (fecal egg counts less than 200)ï¿½use minimum schedule (2 times a year in spring & 
fall);
Medium contaminators (fecal egg counts 200-500)ï¿½ use minimum schedule plus one additional treatment
during the main transmission season (OR 3 times a year);
High contaminators (fecal egg counts above 500)ï¿½ use the same measures as the moderate group with
another additional treatment during the main transmission season  (OR 4 times a year)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5549 bonus HIH430","question":"Name 3 signs or effects of internal parasite infestation.","answer":"Rough coat, pot belly, un-thriftiness, slow growth, depression, weight loss, tail rubbing, colic, diarrhea, death
Decreased work efficiency, poor ultilization of feed, intermittent lameness, bacterial/fungal disease,  colic, chronic cough, bronchitis, blood clots, digestive irritation, intestinal blockage,  retarded growth, , pneumonia,"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5550 bonus HIH430","question":"Name 2 types of internal parasites that affect horses of all ages.","answer":"Strongyles, bots, tapeworms, pinworms"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5551 bonus HIH430","question":"Out of the 150 types of internal parasites known to infect horses, what are the 5 most significant ones?","answer":"Ascarids, strongyles, pinworms, bots, tapeworms  "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5552 bonus HIH430-8","question":"What are 2 practices that should be used to assist in controlling internal parasite infestations?","answer":"Good sanitation, fecal egg count, appropriate use of anthelmintics/DEWORMER "},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5553 bonus HIH430-5,6,7","question":"No deworming schedule fits all horses.   List 3 factors that would influence your deworming program.","answer":"Climate, humidity, rainfall, season, concentration of horses, size of pasture, age of horses, parasite infection history, travel of horses out of facility, fecal egg count"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5554 bonus HIH415-5,430-4","question":"Name 3 areas on the horse where the bot fly lays her eggs.","answer":"Legs, shoulders, flank, mane, belly, chin, under jaw, nose, chest, neck"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5555 bonus TH628","question":"Give the scientific name for 3 of the following 4 types of parasites:  large pinworms, bloodworms, roundworms, threadworms","answer":"Oxyuris equi (large pinworms), 		Strongylus vulgaris (bloodworms), 
Parascaris equorum (roundworms), 		Strongyloides westeri (threadworms)"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5556 bonus HIH430-8","question":"Explain how you would determine which drugs are still effective against the internal parasites on your premises.","answer":"Approximately 4 months from last worming, collect fecal sample from 10% of the herd & do a fecal egg count.  Then treat horse with drug of interest & 2 weeks later, do a second fecal egg count.  The results are compared to see how effective the drug is.  A decrease of 90% is considered effective.  80% & below indicate resistance"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5557 bonus HIH430-9","question":"Describe 3 life stage cycles of strongyles/bloodworms.","answer":"Life cycle is 8-11 months; eggs are passed out in feces to pasture; 2 larval stages outside the horse; 3rd larval stage ingested by horse; 4th larval stage leaves large intestine & migrates to the cranial mesenteric artery; worms  mature & reproduce in the large intestines"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5558 bonus FCH155","question":"What are the scientific names for the three types of large strongyles?","answer":"Strongylus vulgaris, Strongylus edentatus, Strongylus equinis	"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5560 bonus HIH430-7","question":"Generally what is the egg reappearance period for the following drug classes:  a) Piperazine, Benzimidazole & Pyrantel, b) Ivermectin, & c) Moxidectin","answer":"a) 4 weeks or less,     b) 6 - 8 weeks,     c) 10 - 12 weeks"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5561 bonus HIH430-6","question":"Give 3 generic wormer names.","answer":"Ivermectin, Pyrantel (pamoate & tartrate), Fenbendazole, Oxibendazole, Moxidectin, Praziquantel, Piperazine"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5562 bonus HIH430-6","question":"Give 3 examples of purge deworming.","answer":"Paste, stomach tube, using feed as carrier"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5563 bonus HIH430","question":"Name 3 internal parasites that are more common in young horses or foals than in mature horses.","answer":"Ascarids, pinworms, threadworms"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5564 bonus ADV300-3L","question":"2 part question:  There are 3 types of Gastrophilus or horse bot flies.  Give either their common name or scientific name & identify one area on the horse where they deposit their eggs.","answer":"Gastrophilus intestinalis/common bot fly ï¿½ legs, chest, neck, stomach, flanks	
Gastrophilus nasalis/throat bot fly ï¿½under jaw, throat
Gastrophilus hemorrhoidalis/nose bot fly ï¿½upper & lower lips"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5565 bonus TH630/HIH975-14","question":"Give 3 examples of damage that ascarids can do to a horse.","answer":"Chronic enteritis, disruption of digestive system/absorption of nutrients, malnutrition, pulmonary problems, destructive migrating through liver/lungs, peritonitis, intestinal obstruction/rupture etc"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"bonus","number":"5566 bonus HIH430","question":"Name 3 management practices, not including worming,  that have been found to be effective in reducing parasite (both external & internal) numbers.","answer":"Don't feed on ground, remove manure, re-bed stalls regularly, compost manure, don't let grass grow in small exercise lots, rotate pastures, drag pastures, avoid overcrowding, clean water sources, don't use non-composted manure on pastures, deworm new horses before bringing home, don't graze pastures below 3", use fecal egg counts, eliminate mosquito breeding areas, use fly control products, fence off wetlands, remove bot eggs, deworm before grazing clean pastures, rest pastures"},
{"category":"INTERNAL PARASITES","level":"BONUS","number":"5567 BONUS ES188/HIH430-5","question":"Describe 3 stages of the life cycle of common bots (Gastrophilus intestinalais).","answer":"Life cycle is 9-12 months; female bot fly lays eggs on horse; horse bites or licks eggs; eggs hatch in mouth; 1st larval stage migrates through tissues; 2nd larval stage; 3rd larval stage attaches to the wall of the stomach; bot larvae are passed out in feces; pupae in soil; adult flies"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5568 easy H4-31	","question":"What should a rider never use for balance when learning to jump?","answer":"The reins "},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5569 easy H4-31","question":"What is another name for the jumping position?","answer":"Two point"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5570 easy HH20","question":"A good seat for jumping is not developed by strength in gripping or hanging on the reins, but by what?","answer":"Balance"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5571 easy HH54/DET52","question":"What are cavaletti?","answer":"Raised jumps made of poles on the ground OR poles on the ground which are properly spaced"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5572 easy H4-31","question":"For the jumping position, in what direction should the rider be looking?","answer":"Straight ahead OR between the horse's ears"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5573 easy H4-31	","question":"When learning to jump, in order to give security to the rider & freedom for the horse, what length should the stirrup leathers be?","answer":"Medium OR 1-2 holes shorter than the flat length"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5574 easy DET52","question":"What is the name of the small wooden rails a horse is worked over to encourage him to lengthen his stride?","answer":"Cavaletti"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5575 easy DET253","question":"What is a spread jump?","answer":"Jump with width to it   (example:  oxer)"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5576 easy DET231","question":"What is the term for a horse stopping in front of or passing a jump without jumping it?","answer":"Refusal"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"easy","number":"5577 easy DET145","question":"What is the name of the class in which the horse is required to jump 2 fences & then is shown on the rail?","answer":"Hunter Hack"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5578 medium DET62","question":"In show jumping, a ï¿½combination obstacleï¿½ consists of two or more separate jumps that are numbered and lettered. For example 4A and 4B would be used to designate the two jumps in a combination. If you are judging this class, would the  jumps 4A and 4B each receive a score or would they be judged as one obstacle? ","answer":"Judged as one obstacle "},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5580 medium DET p. 24 ","question":"What term refers to the desirable arc a horseï¿½s body makes as it goes over a jump?","answer":"Bascule"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5582 medium DET62","question":"If a horse refuses the second element of a combination, what must the rider do when making a second approach to the jump?","answer":"Take both jumps again"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5583 medium H4-31","question":"What is the purpose of the two point position?","answer":"To adjust the rider's balance to match the horse during jumping and/or galloping"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5584 medium DET23","question":"What is the name for a drop jump that is a solid earthen ramp or wall?","answer":"Bank jump"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5585 medium DET54","question":"What is the term used when a horse rushes into a fence while jumping?","answer":"Charging"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5586 medium H4-31","question":"In referring to "legs" in hunt seat equitation, what part of the leg is used as an aid?","answer":"Between the knee & ankle OR calf"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5587 medium DET4","question":"Charging refers to the behavior of a horse that suddenly attacks or savages a person or another horse.  What does charging refer to in jumping events?","answer":"Rushing into a fence"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5588 medium DET62","question":"In jumping, what is the type of jump that has 2 fences set within 24 feet of each other?","answer":"In & out or combination jump"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"medium","number":"5589 medium DET58","question":"In show jumping, what is meant when a competitor has a clear round?","answer":"Round is completed without jumping or time faults"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"hard","number":"5590 hard DET63","question":"In a Conformation Hunter Class, what percent of the class is judged on performance?","answer":"60%"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"hard","number":"5591 hard DET4","question":""Against the clock" is a term used in which equestrian discipline where the winner is determined by the fastest time & fewest faults?","answer":"Show jumping"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"hard","number":"5592 hard DET145","question":"How are hunter classes judged?","answer":"Horse is judged on even hunting pace, manners & jumping style together with faults earned on the course"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"hard","number":"5593 hard DET150","question":"Referring to show jumping, what is an "element"?","answer":"One jump in a combination"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"hard","number":"5594 hard DET24","question":"Define the term "bascule".","answer":"Desirable arc a horseï¿½s body makes as it goes over a jump"},
{"category":"JUMPING","level":"bonus","number":"5595 bonus DET52","question":"What are 3 things that cavaletti work teaches a horse?","answer":"Rhythm, balance, agility, lengthen stride, improve balance, loosen up/strengthen muscles"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5598 easy HIHvarious","question":"Give two definitions of the term ï¿½throatlatchï¿½.","answer":"Part of the horseï¿½distinct space between the head & neck; part of the bridleï¿½strap that goes around the horseï¿½s throatlatch area & keeps the bridle from slipping over the horseï¿½s head"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5599 easy H1-35","question":"Where is a Thoroughbred race horse tattooed?","answer":"Inside of lip"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5600 easy HIH1355-1","question":"Name 2 things about the horse being sold or purchased that you will find listed on a bill of sale or sales contract.","answer":"Breed, sex, color, markings, registered name, barn name, registration number, age"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5601 easy HIH110-2","question":"In choosing a horse or pony for a young child, what is more important than the animal's size?","answer":"Disposition/temperament"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5602 easy HH47/DET176","question":"What is a maverick?","answer":"An unbranded stray"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5603 easy HH46","question":"What is it called when an animal is roped by the forefeet?","answer":"Fore-footing"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5604 easy HS2","question":"The horse, although not the fastest animal, possesses great what?	","answer":"Endurance"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5605 easy HH39","question":"Why do horses have hair in their ears?","answer":"To prevent dirt or insects from entering the ear"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5606 easy HIH1900-1","question":"What is the oldest non-formal youth development organization in the US?","answer":"4-H"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5607 easy H1-34-35/TH809","question":"Name 2 types of brands.","answer":"Hot brand, freeze brand, lip tattoo, microchip"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5608 easy H4-27","question":"What are mild bucking motions called?","answer":"Crow hops"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5609 easy HH54","question":"What is a cowboy proverb about kicking a horse?","answer":""Kicking never gets you nowhere, less'n you're a mule""},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5610 easy HIH420-1","question":"How does a horse's coat keep him warm in winter?","answer":"Traps heat between the hair fibers"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5611 easy HH4/TH809","question":"What is a brand?","answer":"Mark of identification"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5612 easy HIH210-1","question":"What famous quote about horses is attributed to Will Rogers?","answer":""The outside of a horse is good for the inside of a man""},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5613 easy H4-27","question":"What are crow hops?","answer":"Mild bucking "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5614 easy H1-34/TH809","question":"What is the name of the branding method that uses extreme cold rather than heat?","answer":"Freeze branding"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5615 easy HH40","question":"A collection of saddle horses at a roundup from which are chosen those used for the day is called what?","answer":"Remuda"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5616 easy HS4","question":"Referring to horses, what is a cavy?","answer":"Collection of horses"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5617 easy H1-34","question":"What is the term that means "of, or pertaining to the horse"?","answer":"Equine"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5618 easy HIH1900-1","question":"When did the horse & pony program become part of the 4H organization?","answer":"1960s"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5619 easy HIHvarious","question":"Horse ownership is very expensive.  Name the thing that will usually cost the most in a given year?","answer":"Feed   (hay/grain)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5620 easy H1-35/TH42","question":"What is one of the oldest methods of identification for horses?","answer":"Hot branding"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5621 easy HIH420-1","question":"What causes horses to grow their winter coat?","answer":"Shorter length of daylight"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5622 easy INT222","question":"What is the main reason people own horses in the US?","answer":"Pleasure"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5623 easy H5-34","question":"What is the name of a military division that's mounted on horseback for fighting?","answer":"Cavalry"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5624 easy HIH110-3","question":"What is meant by the term "full board"?","answer":"Stable where horse is kept will take care of all your horse's needs"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5625 easy HIH110-3","question":"What is the term for the service when a boarding stable takes care of all your horse's needs?","answer":"Full board"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5626 easy HIH120-1","question":"Where are most working horses in the US found?","answer":"Cattle ranches"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5627 easy HIH210-3","question":"What are the 2 primary expenses of horse owners?","answer":"Feed & board   (also accept vet & farrier)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5628 easy HIH210-1","question":"What age horses are generally preferred for novice or first time owners?","answer":"Older	 (5 years of age or older)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5630 easy DET140","question":"What is the term meaning "study of the horse"?","answer":"Hippology"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5631 easy DET176","question":"A mascot is a companion animal for horses.  Name 2 of the most common mascots.","answer":"Goat, pony, dog, cat"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5632 easy DET217","question":"Define the term "ponying".","answer":"Leading one horse while riding another"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5633 easy DET140","question":"What does ï¿½hippologyï¿½ mean?","answer":"Study of the horse"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5634 easy TH132","question":"NOT referring to conformation, what is the single most important factor in selecting a horse?","answer":"Purpose OR what you're going to use it for"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5635 easy TH809","question":"Which type of branding was developed for the Thoroughbred race horse as a means of identification?","answer":"Lip tattoo"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5636 easy TH129","question":"How often does a horse shed its hair?","answer":"Twice a year"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5637 easy DET259","question":"What is a ï¿½sunfisherï¿½?","answer":"Bucking horse that twists his body in the air"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"easy","number":"5638 easy DET207","question":"What is the name of the winged horse of Greek mythology?","answer":"Pegasus"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5639 medium HIH1340-1","question":"The type of insurance that provides coverage for almost all causes of death - including those related to illness or injury - is called what?","answer":"Full mortality"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5640 medium HIH130-1","question":"When was the Cooperative Extension Service established?","answer":"1914	 (additional info -- by the Smith Lever Act)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5641 medium DET5","question":"What do the initials AHC stand for?","answer":"American Horse Council"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5642 medium DET19","question":"What is the name for the metal rod on which the wheels of a carriage turn?","answer":"Axle"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5644 medium TH266","question":"Generally, growing horses attain 90% of their adult height by what age?    ","answer":"1 year          "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5645 medium HIH130-1","question":"2 part question:  How & why was the Cooperative Extension Service established?","answer":"By the Smith-Lever Act in 1914 as a way to distribute new research information to the states"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5646 medium HIH1355-1","question":"Referring to leasing a horse, what is the difference between a lessor & a lessee?","answer":"Lessorï¿½one who owns the horse; 	Lesseeï¿½one who's leasing it"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5647 medium HIH1340-3","question":"What specific type of insurance would you need to purchase in order to insure your horse against death from sickness, injuries, disease or old age?","answer":"Full mortality or all risks mortality		accept either"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5648 medium HIH130-1","question":"What was the name of the government act that established the Cooperative Extension Service in 1914?","answer":"Smith - Lever Act"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5649 medium HIH320-6","question":"What 2 factors of the horse's life are influenced by light?","answer":"Shedding & estrous cycle"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5650 medium DET52","question":"In regards to equine business, what does the Latin expression "caveat emptor" refer to?","answer":"Let the buyer beware"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5651 medium HIH450-1","question":"What are 2 reasons horses live longer today than in the past?","answer":"Aren't ridden/used as hard, generally receive better care"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5652 medium HIH1360-2	","question":"To be considered a business rather than a hobby by the IRS, how many years must a horse business make a profit?","answer":"2 out of every 7 years"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5653 medium TH36,179,728HIH/HH","question":"What are 2 definitions of forging as applied to horses?","answer":"Shaping of iron, striking forefoot with hindfoot"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5654 medium TH7","question":"The horse has no equal as a draft animal. Even today, tractors, automobiles & trucks are rated in what manner reflecting on the horse?","answer":"They are compared in terms of ï¿½Horsepower "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5655 medium DET234","question":"To ride a horse to his absolute limit so that he's exhausted & unable to go farther is called what?","answer":"Ride him into the ground"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5656 medium DET151","question":"What does the term ï¿½Indian brokeï¿½ mean?				","answer":"The horse is trained to accept being mounted from either side"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5657 medium HIH1940-2","question":"What organization reviews and updates the Horse Industry Handbook and Youth Leaders Manual reference books?                               ","answer":"American Youth Horse Council (AYHC)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5658 medium ES115","question":"You do the mathï¿½ Approximately 75 percent of a horses total body	weight is made up of water.  If your horse weighs 1000 pounds, how much of this total weight is water?","answer":"750 pounds                           "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5659 medium TH139","question":"You do the mathï¿½.A horse that is 66 inches tall would be considered to be how many hands tall?","answer":"16.2  hands tall                       "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"medium","number":"5661 medium DET74","question":"What type of knot is used on the end of a rope to keep it from unraveling?","answer":"Crown knot                         "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5662 hard DET pg 130","question":"What does the slang term ï¿½hat rackï¿½ mean when used in describing a horse?","answer":"An emaciated or very thin horse"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5663 hard DET52","question":"What term refers to the mythological creature that had a head, torso and arms of a man and the body and legs of a horse? ","answer":"Centaur "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5664 hard HIH1340-1","question":"What is a FLT insurance policy?","answer":"Policy that covers injury or death that results from fire, lightning or transportation"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5665 hard DET140","question":"What does the term "hippophile" describe?","answer":"Horse lover"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5666 hard HIH1340-1","question":"What are the 2 general types of mortality insurance?","answer":"Full Mortality/All Risks & Specified/Named Peril"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5667 hard HIH1330","question":"Most equine insurance policies require you to do what if your horse is injured, ill or lame?","answer":"Immediately notify the company"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5668 hard HIH1340-3","question":"What type of insurance offers coverage in the event that an insured horse suffers from a physical condition that makes it totally & permanently unable to fulfill its intended use?","answer":"Loss of use"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5669 hard HIH450-1","question":"What percentage of horses in this country are aged?","answer":"20%"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5670 hard HIH1340-2","question":"As the owner of a horse boarding or training operation, what type of insurance do you need to carry to protect you from situations where you may be held responsible for bodily injury or property damage?","answer":"Liability"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5671 hard DET43","question":"What is another name for an auction ring?","answer":"Sale ring or bull pen"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5672 hard FCH181","question":"REM or deep sleep occurs only when horses are in what position?","answer":"Lying down with muzzle touching the ground"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5673 hard HIH175-1","question":"What is PMU?","answer":"Pregnant Mare Urine	 (additional info -- source of hormones used in estrogen replacement therapy)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5674 hard DET205","question":"What is the name for the process of heating a food material - usually a liquid - to a specific temperature for a specific length of time for the purpose of destroying bacteria?","answer":"Pasteurization"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5675 hard HIH1380","question":"What does it mean when you say a horse is syndicated?","answer":"Horse is owned by a group of people who each own shares in it"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5676 hard DET41","question":"What is the term for a cowboy from the far Western US who follows the horsemanship techniques of the old California vaqueros?","answer":"Buckaroo"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5677 hard TH809","question":"How does freeze branding a gray horse differ from freeze branding a chestnut horse?","answer":"New hair growth after freeze branding comes in white.  When branding a gray horse, the iron is applied long enough to kill the root, thus preventing new growth so brand can be seen"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5678 hard HIH1340-5","question":"What type of insurance covers the insured against bodily injury or property damage as well as provides for legal defense in actions alleging negligence?","answer":"Liability"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5679 hard TH177","question":"If you were reading a freeze brand, what symbol would identify the animal as unregistered or grade?","answer":"The letter E"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5680 hard TH8","question":"How did George Carlin document the impressive riding skills of the Plains Indians?","answer":"Paintings"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5681 hard DET161","question":"What does the term "knacker" refer to?","answer":"Person who buys & slaughters horses OR buys carcasses	 (additional info -- generally for pet food)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5682 hard DET221","question":"What marking is described as a muscular depression of unknown origin, is usually seen on the neck and sometimes seen on the shoulder?                              ","answer":"Prophetï¿½s thumb"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5684 hard TH810","question":"When using the Y-Tex Corporation system for freeze branding, the alpha character is used to identify what?","answer":"Breed of horse   (or ï¿½Eï¿½ is grade or unregistered)                      "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"hard","number":"5685 hard HIH910-8/ADV304-2L, 327-2L","question":"Identify 2 general physiological processes in the horse that are affected by the length of daylight","answer":"Hair coat, estrous cycle/female reproduction, male reproduction/testosterone production/sperm production                   "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5686 bonus HIH210-6","question":"If you are thinking of buying a horse, what are 3 things you should consider in deciding whether or not be become a horse owner?","answer":"They are expensive to buy/keep, you must be willing to devote time on regular basis, you must be willing to pass up other activities"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5687 bonus DET127","question":"Give 3 definitions of the term "hackï¿½.","answer":"Horse ridden to a hunt meet, a pleasure ride, a riding horse for hire"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5688 bonus DET37","question":"Give 3 locations where horses are branded.","answer":"Cheek, neck, shoulder, hip"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5689 bonus TH20","question":"Name 3 ways to identify  a horse by its physical appearance.","answer":"Brands, chestnuts, coat color, coat pattern, markings, scars, cowlicks, hair whorls, muscular dimples/defects, etc.	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5690 bonus HIH210-5","question":"Name 3 questions you should ask the owner before buying a horse.","answer":"Why are you selling?  Is horse easy to clip/bathe?  Is horse easy to handle while being trimmed/shod, wormed, etc?  How much/what type training has horse had?  What aids/cues are used to make horse perform?  Does horse have any unusual quirks, etc.	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5691 bonus TH810","question":"2 part question:   You have just purchased a bay Arabian mare.  Under her mane is a white band with numerous characters composed of bars & angles.  What type of brand is this & what do the characters signify?","answer":"Freeze brand - each symbol represents a number - the entire brand gives the year the horse was born & its registry number"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5692 bonus TH804","question":"Identifying horses & other livestock has always been a problem for owners.  If an identification system is to be successful, the identifying marks must have several characteristics.  Name 3","answer":"Visible from a distance, permanent, painless, unalterable, inexpensive, easy to apply, non-damaging, adaptable to data retrieval  "},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5693 bonus ADV338","question":"Name 4 equine-related careers where workers do NOT work hands-on with live horses.","answer":"Cooperative extension personnel, Dept of Agriculture, breed association, horse council, show/race announcer, feed industry, show organizer, equine insurance, equine lawyer, tack store, judge, barn builder, equine appraiser, etc.	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5694 bonus FCH398","question":"In reference to the horse world, give 3 definitions of the term "maiden".","answer":"Horse that's never won a race, rider/horse that's never won a ribbon, mare that's never been pregnant/had a foal"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5695 bonus HIH110-3","question":"In addition to the purchase price, name 3 essential purchases (other than hay & grain) that a new horse owner would need to make.","answer":"Halter, lead rope, bridle, saddle, water/feed buckets, fly spray, saddle blanket/pad, grooming tools/brushes, helmet, harness ,etc.	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5696 bonus HIH210-1/TH132","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered in order to select the most appropriate horse for your needs & desires.","answer":"Age of rider, experience of rider, age of horse, horse's level of training, cost, horse/rider combination, breed/breed type, management experience, color, registered or grade, purpose/ intended use, temperament, budget, etc.	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5697 bonus HIH110-4","question":"What are 3 advantages to leasing a horse?","answer":"May satisfy desire to ride & costs less than owning, good way to determine if interest is serious before buying, good way to see if horse is compatible/what you expected"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5698 bonus HIH110-2","question":"Name 3 life skills that children may develop as a result of horse ownership","answer":"Responsibility, teamwork, self-confidence, sportsmanship, self-discipline, social skills, greater coordination/strength/agility, healthy competitive nature"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5699 bonus HIH1340-4","question":"What are the only four US states without Equine Activity Liability Laws?","answer":"California, Maryland, Nevada & New York"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5700 bonus HIH1355","question":"Name 3 types of equine-related contracts.","answer":"Breeding, sales, sales agency agreement, partnership, syndication, boarding, release of liability/waiver, hauling agreement, lease, training, etc		(accept any reasonable answer)	"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5701 bonus HIH184-1/TH63-64/DET60","question":"Cob or cobby are terms used in the horse industry.  Give 3 examples of how you might use these terms","answer":"Cob-tailedï¿½English custom of docking the tail; 
Cob-tail classï¿½one of 2 classes Hackney ponies are divided into for show;
Cobï¿½type of horse (short-legged with bone/substance of heavyweight hunter);
COBï¿½form of feed  (corn, oats, barley mix);
Cobbyï¿½description of a close coupled & stoutly built horse;
Welsh Cobï¿½division of the Welsh Pony"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5702 bonus TH80","question":"In order to register your horse or identify it on a Coggins test paper, you must provide a description that will distinguish it from other horses.  Other than color & markings, what are 4 other visual means of horse identification?","answer":"Muscular dimples/defects, scars, cowlicks, hair whorls, lip tattoo, brands, chestnut patterns, blemishes, sex, height, etc.	(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"MISCELLANEOUS","level":"bonus","number":"5703 bonus DET215","question":"Name 3 ways the term "points" can be used in relation to horses & the horse industry","answer":"Sharp edges on teeth, coloring of mane/tail & legs, values for winning or placing at shows,
On anEnglish saddle - the part of pommel arch that extends below the stirrup bar, lower part of tapaderas,
Team in back of leaders in an 8 horse hitch,
Type of race (point to point), p
Pointing -extension of stride with little flexion, standing position where one of front legs is extended ahead of
the other/sore foot put in front to take weight off it"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5704 easy BEG118-1L","question":"When your horse is carrying a pack load down a steep grade, what piece of rigging other than the cinch needs to be adjusted and pulled tighter?","answer":"Breeching"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5705 easy HIH1125-1","question":"Traditional pack saddles come in 2 styles.  Name them.","answer":"Crossbuck/sawbuck & Decker"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5706 easy HIH1125-1","question":"What does the term "mantied" mean?","answer":"Placed in a canvas cover"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5707 easy BEG118-1L","question":"When comparing the crossbuck & Decker saddles, which is better suited to a sling load that's mantied?","answer":"Decker"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5709 easy HIH1125-1","question":"What type of rigging does a crossbuck or sawbuck saddle have?","answer":"Double"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5710 easy HIH1125-3","question":"What is a manta or mantee?","answer":"Canvas used to cover load when packing"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5711 easy HIH1125-3","question":"A piece of canvas which is used to cover your pack load is called what?","answer":"Manta or mantee"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5712 easy HIH1125-1","question":"How many cinches are on a Decker pack saddle?","answer":"One"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5713 easy HIH1125-3","question":"What is a lash rope used for?","answer":"To tie the load onto the pack saddle"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5714 easy HIH1125-2","question":"Which piece of equipment is used to keep a pack saddle from sliding backwards?","answer":"Breast collar"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5715 easy HIH1125/BEG118-1L","question":"What is the purpose of the crupper on a pack saddle?","answer":"To keep the saddle from sliding forward OR to help keep the pack load centered"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5716 easy HIH1125-3","question":"If you are using a stock saddle for packing, what piece of equipment that goes around the base of the tail & attaches to the saddle would you use to help keep the pack load centered?","answer":"Crupper"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5717 easy HIH1125-3","question":"What is the name for the piece of equipment that's used to carry supplies on a pack trip?","answer":"Panniers"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5718 easy HIH1125-3","question":"Name 2 pieces of equipment that you can use to help stabilize a load on a pack horse.","answer":"Breeching, breast collar, crupper"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5719 easy HIH1125-3","question":"What item of pack equipment could contain shelves or double as a small table?","answer":"Panniers	"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5720 easy HIH1125-1","question":"What must be balanced & centered on your pack animal?","answer":"The load or pack"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5721 easy HIHvarious/HH","question":"Name a good way to restrain a pack horse.","answer":"Hobbles, picket line, high line"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5722 easy HIH1125-1","question":"What is the use of a sawbuck saddle?","answer":"Packing"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5723 easy HIH1125-1	","question":"What is a pannier?","answer":"Container used for carrying supplies while packing"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5724 easy HIH1125-1","question":"When securing the entire balanced load to the pack animal, what is the most important factor?","answer":"The hitch"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5725 easy HIH1125-1","question":"What is the purpose of a pack saddle's breeching?","answer":"To prevent the saddle from sliding forward when going downhill"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5726 easy HIH1125-1","question":"Which pack saddle has a single cinch?","answer":"Decker"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"easy","number":"5727 easy HIH1125-1","question":"Which pack saddle has a double-rigged cinch?","answer":"Crossbuck or sawbuck   "},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"medium","number":"5728 medium HIH1125-1","question":"What type of pack saddle is described as a centerfire-rigged, single cinch saddle with a half breed?","answer":"Decker"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"medium","number":"5729 medium HIH1125-1","question":"Single, double, half, Arizona & diamond are terms referring to what?","answer":"Pack hitches"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"medium","number":"5730 medium HIH1125-5","question":"What is a half-inch rope of soft, twisted nylon 45-50 feet in length that's used to secure the entire load on a pack saddle?","answer":"Lash rope"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"medium","number":"5731 medium BEG118-1L","question":"Why is a horse or mule with little or no withers undesirable as a pack animal?","answer":"Because the saddle wonï¿½t fit well & will cause sores."},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5732 hard HIH1125-1","question":"What is the purpose of a quarter strap in packing?","answer":"Reduce cinch sores"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5733 hard HIH1125-2","question":"On a sawbuck or crossbuck saddle, where is sheepskin lining added for more protection & comfort?","answer":"Blades"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5734 hard HIH1125-2","question":"In choosing a packhorse, what kind of withers are best?","answer":"Medium high"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5735 hard HIH1125-5","question":"In securing your pack before hitting the trail, what are the last 2 items you need?","answer":"Lash cinch & lash rope"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5736 hard HIH1125-1","question":"2 part question:   In reference to packing, describe a half-breed & explain how it's used.","answer":"Heavy canvas pad with wooden bars at the bottom used over a Decker saddle; provides extra padding & holds the pack away from the animal's sides"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5737 hard HIH1125-2","question":"Why is it important to keep a pack saddle from sliding backwards?","answer":"So it doesn't rest on the horse's kidneys or lumbar region"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5738 hard HIH1125/BEG118-1","question":"Why is a traditional McClellan saddle a reasonably effective packsaddle?","answer":"Lightweight & has plenty of rings & straps to tie thing onto"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5739 hard HIH1125-1","question":"Extra-long crossbucks are used for what purpose?","answer":"They hold the pack away from the animal's sides"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5740 hard HIH1125-1","question":"When referring to packing, what is the purpose of the "half-breed"?","answer":"To hold packs away from the animal's sides OR to provide extra padding"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5741 hard HIH1125-1","question":"What is another name for a basket or barrel hitch?","answer":"Sling hitch"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"hard","number":"5742 hard HIH1125-1","question":"Over what location on a stock saddle would panniers fit?","answer":"Cantle & swells"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"bonus","number":"5743 bonus HIH1125-2","question":"2 part question:  In regards to withers, what type of conformation is undesirable in a packhorse & why?","answer":"Little or no withers ï¿½ allows saddle to turn & rub/creates sores OR withers that are too highï¿½they're        harder to fit & more prone to sores "},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"bonus","number":"5744 bonus HIH1125-1","question":"Name 3 types of saddles that can be used in packing.","answer":"Decker, crossbuck/sawbuck, McClellan, Western or stock"},
{"category":"PACKING","level":"bonus","number":"5745 bonus HIH1125-1","question":"Name 4 hitches used in packing.","answer":"Squaw hitch, 1/2 diamond, double diamond, triple diamond, one-man diamond, box hitch, Arizona, square, sling, basket, barrel"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5746 easy FCH39/HIH930-3","question":"What is foal heat?	","answer":"Mare's first heat after foaling    (addtl info ï¿½ 7-15 days after foaling)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5747 easy HIH920-5","question":"You do the mathï¿½ A mare that was bred on May 20th should foal in what month the next year?","answer":"April"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5748 easy HIH970-3/TH422","question":"In a normal birth, which legs appear first?","answer":"Front"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5749 easy HIH975-6","question":"Why is creep feeding of foals recommended when foals are 30-60 days old?","answer":"Mareï¿½s milk production declines "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5750 easy HIH 450-2/DET p. 171				","question":"What is a long yearling?","answer":"A horse more than 1 year old but not yet 2 years old"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5751 easy HS22/TH384 DET7","question":"What does alter mean?","answer":"To castrate or geld a horse"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5752 easy HIH980-1/TH387/HS23","question":"What is the term used when a male horse has retained one or both testicles in his body cavity?","answer":"Ridgling or cryptorchid"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5753 easy HIH950-4old  DET77","question":"The mother of a horse is called what?","answer":"Dam"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5754 easy TH537/HS18/DET246","question":"The father of a horse is called what?","answer":"Sire"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5756 easy HS26/TH431-32DET258","question":"What do you call the charge for breeding services rendered by a stallion?","answer":"Stud fee"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5757 easy FCH389/TH322/HS22/DET107","question":"What is the term for an immature female horse?","answer":"Filly"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5758 easy HS23/DET234","question":"What is a ridgling?","answer":"A male horse that has retained one or both testicles in his body cavity"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5759 easy FCH385/HS22/DET62","question":"The correct term to use when describing a male foal is what?","answer":"Colt"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5760 easy HIH342/H3-34/DET175","question":"What is a mare?","answer":"Mature female horse OR female horse 4 years old & older   "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5761 easy HS22/FCH385/DET62","question":"What is a colt?","answer":"Male foal (immature male horse)  "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5762 easy HIH975-6","question":"A foal is normally weaned at what age?","answer":"4 - 6 months	  	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5763 easy TH930/HS24/DET288","question":"What is a weanling?","answer":"A weaned foal or foal that's been taken away from its mother"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5764 easy HS22/DET111","question":"What is a foal?","answer":"Colt or filly under one year old      (a baby horse)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5765 easy HIH930-4","question":"How long is the gestation period for horses?","answer":"Approximately 11 months OR 335-340 days  		 (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5766 easy HIH910-1/DET258","question":"What do you call an unaltered male horse?","answer":"Stallion (stud)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5767 easy HIH110-5/FCH390","question":"What is a gelding?","answer":"A castrated male horse"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5768 easy HIH110-5","question":"An altered or castrated male horse is called what?","answer":"Gelding"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5769 easy HIH970-2","question":"What is colostrum?","answer":"The first milk a mare produces after the birth of the foal"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5770 easy HH56/DET120","question":"What is the breeding term for the offspring of a sire?","answer":"Get			"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5771 easy HH58 DET258","question":"What is the slang term for a horse breeding establishment?","answer":"Stud	     (stud farm)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5772 easy HH56/DET220","question":"What is the breeding term for the offspring of a dam?","answer":"Produce			"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5773 easy HIH930-1/FCH382","question":"What is a barren mare?","answer":"A mare that's not in foal but who was bred    (mare that's been bred, but isn't pregnant)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5774 easy HH12","question":"Define sex characteristic.","answer":"Masculinity in the stallion & femininity in the mare"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5775 easy TH323/ADV336-1L/HIH940-1","question":"What is the term for the stallion that is used to determine if a mare is receptive to breeding?","answer":"Teaser"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5776 easy HIH920-5/930-4","question":"The length of time (usually 11 months) for the development of the foal from the time of breeding until birth is called what?","answer":"Pregnancy or gestation period"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5777 easy HIH920-4","question":"What do the ovaries produce?","answer":"Eggs   (also accept estrogen and progesterone)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5778 easy TH781/ DET258","question":"A barn where stallions are kept for breeding is called what?","answer":"Stud barn or stallion barn"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5779 easy HIH930-1/DET174","question":"What term refers to a mare that has never been bred","answer":"Maiden               "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5780 easy HIH930-1","question":"What is a maiden mare?","answer":"Mare that's never been bred"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5781 easy DET152 HIH930-1","question":"What does the term ï¿½in foalï¿½ mean? ","answer":"The mare is pregnant "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5782 easy BEG112-2/HIH970-3","question":"During what time period are most foals born?","answer":"Night     (11 pm ï¿½ 4 am ï¿½ accept either general or specific)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5783 easy HIH920-5, 930-4","question":"In months, what is the gestation period of the Rangerbred?","answer":"11 months	"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5784 easy HIH930-1","question":"What does the term "open mare" refer to?","answer":"Mare that is currently not pregnant   (not bred this season)	"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5785 easy TH323/HIH920-5","question":"How long is the estrous cycle of the mare?","answer":"21 - 23 days              (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5786 easy HIH781-1","question":"A nursing foal's nutrient requirements exceed those provided by the dam's milk within how many months?","answer":"Two"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5787 easy H2-35/FCH234/DET163","question":"What is lactating?","answer":"Producing milk"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5788 easy HIH980-1/TH387","question":"What is another name for a ridgling?","answer":"Cryptorchid"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5789 easy HIH930-1","question":"What do you call a mare that was bred, but didn't produce a foal?","answer":"Barren"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5790 easy HS24/TH326/HIH920-5","question":"What is the average length of estrus (heat period)?","answer":"6 days"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5791 easy HS24/TH361","question":"At what age are most mares capable of reproduction?","answer":"Three"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5792 easy HS23","question":"At what age can you start using a stallion for breeding purposes?","answer":"Two	  	 (additional info -- only for limited breeding)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5793 easy HS24/TH322/HIH920-5","question":"What is another name for heat?","answer":"Estrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5794 easy HIH930-2","question":"Other than hormones, what can be used to bring mares into heat earlier than the normal breeding season?","answer":"Artificial lights"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5795 easy HIH940-1","question":"What is a common method used to determine if a mare is in heat?","answer":"Teasing"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5796 easy H2-35/FCH234/DET163","question":"Lactation means the production of what?","answer":"Milk		"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5797 easy HIH970-5","question":"Normal foals will nurse for the first time within how many hours of birth?","answer":"2 ï¿½ 3		  	(accept either)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5798 easy HS22/TH384/DET119","question":"What does it mean to geld?","answer":"Castrate a male horse"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5799 easy HIH970-2	","question":"What is the nutritious, high-protein first milk for the foal called?","answer":"Colostrum"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5800 easy HIH781-1old","question":"How much weight will a foal typically gain per day during the first 3 months?","answer":"2.25 - 3 pounds per day		  	(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5801 easy HIH920-4","question":"Of all of our domestic animals, which animal has the lowest reproductive efficiency?","answer":"Horse"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5802 easy HH46/DET107","question":"What is a colt or filly under one year of age called?","answer":"Foal"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5803 easy BEG112/HIH970-4/975-2","question":"Why should you treat the naval stump of a newborn foal with chlorohexidine?","answer":"To prevent bacteria from entering the body through it"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5804 easy HIH930-1","question":"What is the slang term for a mare that's nursing a foal?","answer":"Wet mare"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5805 easy FCH400","question":"What is the slang term for a gelding that shows stallion-like aggressive behavior?","answer":"Proud cut, rig, false rig (accept any)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5806 easy HIH930-1","question":"What is a ï¿½wet mareï¿½?","answer":"Mare that's nursing a foal"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5807 easy HIH930-1","question":"What do you call a mare which is kept for breeding & producing young?","answer":"Broodmare        "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5808 easy HIH920-5","question":"Which domestic animal has the longest heat period?","answer":"Mare   (horse)     "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"easy","number":"5809 easy HIH975-4","question":"Other than bottle feeding, name a way to feed an orphan foal","answer":"Bucket, nurse mare, nurse goat              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5810 medium HIH970-5/975-2","question":"What care should be given to the navel stump of a newborn foal?","answer":"Apply mild iodine solution (7%) OR 1% povidone  OR 0.5% solution of chlorohexidine to prevent bacteria from entering body  (addtl info   chlorohexidine  right after birth & for first 3 days is the recommended ï¿½ iodine can cause delayed healing, killed tissue"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5811 medium FCH235/TH323/ HIH920-6","question":"What event triggers the end of estrus or heat - usually within 24- 48 hours?","answer":"Ovulation"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5812 medium HIH920-3","question":"What is the name for the structure in the abdomen that's multi-layered, hollow, Y-shaped & is suspended by the broad ligaments?","answer":"Uterus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5813 medium HIH920-5/FCH235","question":"Frequent urination & eversion of the vulva or winking will occur during what phase of the mare's reproductive cycle?","answer":"Estrus or heat"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5815 medium FCH245/HIH970-4","question":"What can be done to delay foaling until the veterinarian arrives if there is an indication of abnormal presentation of the foal?","answer":"Walk the mare and keep her standing"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5816 medium HIH975-3","question":"What is the name of the first feces that the foal excretes?","answer":"Meconium"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5817 medium TH340","question":"How do nutrients get from the mare to the fetus after it's attached to the uterus?","answer":"Through the placenta 	(additional info -- via the umbilical cord)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5818 medium TH340 HIH970-5","question":"What is the correct name for the membranous organ referred to as the afterbirth?","answer":"Placenta"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5841 medium CAHA71","question":"In comparison to the horse, how is the length of the estrous cycle of donkeys and ponies different?","answer":"Estrous cycles are longer 	(additional info -- usually 25 days instead of 19-22 days)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5842 medium DET280/HIH920-3","question":"What is the reproductive organ that holds the fetus from conception to birth?","answer":"Uterus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5843 medium TH321/HIH910-3","question":"What is the muscle that is a physical barrier between vagina & uterus ","answer":"Cervix"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5844 medium TH432","question":"What does "return privilege in season" mean?","answer":"You may bring your mare back until she's in foal for that breeding season only.  A second fee will be charged after the current season if the mare is returned"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5845 medium TH323/HIH920-5","question":"What word means without estrus?","answer":"Anestrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5846 medium TH319/DET106","question":"What is the process of the uniting of the sperm & egg?","answer":"Fertilization"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5847 medium TH427/DET62/HIH975-3","question":"Colostrum is especially important to the foal because it contains what 2 things?","answer":"Antibodies (proteins) that protect the foal from infection & laxatives (fats) that help foal pass meconium "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5848 medium TH271/HIH930-6","question":"When does the most rapid period of fetal growth take place?","answer":"During the last 3-4 months of pregnancy"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5849 medium HS25","question":"How are identical twins produced?","answer":"A single fertilized egg (zygote) divides & produces offspring with identical genetic makeup  "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5850 medium TH346/HIH930,940 DET278","question":"What technique of pregnancy diagnosis is the easiest &the most accurate.  It can detect pregnancy as early as 2 weeks after conception?","answer":"Ultrasound"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5851 medium TH128","question":"What is the primary sex organ of the mare?","answer":"Ovary"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5852 medium HIH920-3","question":"What is the largest part of the female reproductive system?","answer":"Uterus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5853 medium TH318/HIH920-4","question":"How many follicles are on an ovary?","answer":"Hundreds"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5854 medium TH361","question":"Puberty - or the capacity to produce sex cells - occurs in the stallion at approximately what age?","answer":"One year"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5855 medium HS22/HIH920-3","question":"What is the unborn animal called as it develops in the uterus?","answer":"Fetus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5856 medium TH361/HIH980-2","question":"What hormone does the testicle produce?","answer":"Testosterone	 (also estrogen)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5857 medium TH128 HIH980-1","question":"What is the primary sex organ of the stallion?","answer":"Testes (testicle)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5858 medium TH355/HIH980-4","question":"As compared to body temperature, should the temperature of the scrotum & testicles be higher, lower or the same?","answer":"Lower"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5859 medium TH355/HIH980-2","question":"What is the sack-like pouch that suspends the testicles outside the male animal?","answer":"Scrotum"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5860 medium TH128	HIH920-4","question":"What is an ovary?","answer":"A female reproductive organ that produces eggs & sex hormones (estrogen & progesterone)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5861 medium TH323/HIH920-5","question":"What is the term for the rhythmic opening & closing of the labia as exhibited in mares?","answer":"Winking"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5862 medium HIH975-4","question":"About how long does it take for a foal's immune system to become functional & produce significant levels of antibodies?","answer":"2 - 4 months            (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5863 medium TH322","question":"What is the average age of puberty in the mare?","answer":"12 - 15 months            (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5864 medium TH427/HIH975-4","question":"How long does the mare produce colostrum?","answer":"Up to 48 hours after birth of the foal (foal absorbs antibodies from colostrum for 36 hours)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5865 medium HIH920-6","question":"What does FSH cause in the mare?","answer":"Follicle growth"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5866 medium DET258","question":"What are 2 meanings of the term ï¿½studï¿½?","answer":"A stallion & an establishment at which horses are kept for breeding purposes"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5867 medium FCH235","question":"What is a silent heat?","answer":"Ovulation without outward signs of estrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5868 medium INT226-2L HIH920-4","question":"Name the tube which carries the egg from the ovary to the uterus?","answer":"Oviduct or Fallopian tube"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5869 medium TH376/HIH950-1","question":"What do the initials AI stand for?","answer":"Artificial insemination"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5870 medium CAHA73/DET285","question":"Parturition is another name for what?","answer":"Birth"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5871 medium TH346 HIH930/940","question":"What is a common method of diagnosing pregnancy in the mare?","answer":"Ultrasound or rectal palpation               (accept either)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5872 medium TH323/HIH920-5","question":"During what season would a mare be naturally in anestrus?","answer":"Winter"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5873 medium CAHA73 HIH970-4","question":"Within a few days of birth, what begins to form on the mare's teats?","answer":"Wax"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5874 medium TH427/HIH970-4","question":"What is the VERY FIRST step in taking care of a foal immediately after birth?","answer":"Remove anything from foal's nostrils that might restrict breathing"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5875 medium HIH930-1","question":"What is the difference between a barren mare & an open mare?","answer":"Barren ï¿½ not pregnant, but was bred; 
Open ï¿½ not pregnant, but was NOT bred this season (has had foals in the past)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5876 medium TH409/HIH940-3","question":"What is the most important environmental cue in inducing estrus in mares?","answer":"Light"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5877 medium TH425/DET38","question":"Delivery in which the foal's rump or hind feet are presented first in the birth canal is called what?","answer":"Breech birth"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5878 medium DET205","question":"What is the correct medical terminology for giving birth?","answer":"Parturition              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5879 medium TH339 DET100","question":"What is the hormone responsible for the mare's outward sexual behavior?","answer":"Estrogen   (specifically estradiol)           Accept either general or specific answer"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5880 medium TH427 HIH975-4 HIH950-3-4","question":"The foalï¿½s digestive tract permits absorption of the colostrum antibodies for approximately how long?","answer":"36 hours"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5881 medium TH127/DET221","question":"What does the hormone prolactin do?","answer":"Initiates lactation"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5882 medium TH425/DET1","question":"What is the expulsion of the fetus before the time of normal foaling called?","answer":"Abortion"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5883 medium TH400","question":"What does the term "proud cut" refer to?","answer":"A gelding that shows stallion-like behavior"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5884 medium TH323 HIH920-5","question":"What is the name of the long period between breeding seasons when the ovaries are inactive?","answer":"Anestrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5885 medium TH362/HIH980-3","question":"Where in the stallion is sperm produced?","answer":"Testes/testicles (more specifically in the seminiferous tubules)     Accept either general or specific"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5886 medium TH365/HIH980-3","question":"What is the general term for the substance emitted by a stallion during the breeding of a mare?","answer":"Semen or seminal fluid"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5887 medium CAHA73/FCH246/HIH970-5","question":"What is the last event to occur in the mare's labor?","answer":"Expulsion of the placenta (afterbirth)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5888 medium HIH920-5","question":"At what part of a mare's estrous cycle is she NOT responsive to the stallion?","answer":"Diestrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5889 medium TH428/HIH975-6","question":"What is a nurse mare?","answer":"A lactating mare known for her foster mother qualities -- she will accept a strange/orphan foal & let it nurse"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5890 medium CAHA5/HIH980-5","question":"What is the term for the black, waxy substance that can build up in a horse's sheath?","answer":"Smegma"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5891 medium TH781/DET39","question":"What is a breeding shed?","answer":"Specialized building where mares are bred"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5892 medium HIH940-1, 920-3-5","question":"Name a major cause of infertility in mares? ","answer":"Uterine infections/endometriosis  or  Human management"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5893 medium HIH930-6","question":"Why would you want to deworm your pregnant mare 30 days before her foaling date?","answer":"to decrease passage of parasite eggs to foal    "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5894 medium TH343 HIH930-4","question":"On average, how many days longer are colts carried than mares?","answer":"2 - 7 days             (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5895 medium HIH920-6/ADV326-3","question":"What hormone does the maturing follicle on the ovary release to stimulate the sexual behavior of mares during heat?","answer":"Estrogen"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5896 medium TH417/HIH970-2, 940-3","question":"How long before birth will pregnant mare's teats begin to wax?","answer":"1 ï¿½ 6 days               (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5897 medium HIH990-1","question":"Handling breeding stallions should focus on what?","answer":"Using the least amount of restraint necessary to ensure safety            "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5898 medium HIH920-5","question":"What is the difference between estrus & diestrus?","answer":"Estrus - period during which mare is receptive to stallion & encourages mating
Diestrus - period during which mare is not receptive to stallion & will resist him"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5899 medium TH340/DET278","question":"Between what 2 structures is the umbilical cord?","answer":"Fetus & placenta"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5900 medium HIH920-5","question":"The mare's estrous cycle is divided into 2 distinct phases.  What are they?","answer":"Estrus & diestrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5901 medium TH327","question":"When a mare ovulates, but fails to show behavioral signs of estrus, this is called what?","answer":"Silent heat"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5902 medium FCH245/ HIH970-3","question":"In the pregnant mare, the first stages of foaling can often mimic what condition?","answer":"Colic"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5903 medium CAHA5a/HIH980-3","question":"2 part question :   What is smegma & where is it found?","answer":"Waxy substance that builds up in a horse's sheath"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5904 medium HIH920-3, 940-1","question":"When during the estrous cycle is conception rate the highest in mares?","answer":"At the end of estrus (1 - 2 days prior to ovulation) OR foal heat"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5905 medium TH428/HIH975-6","question":"What is the term used for a lactating mare that takes care of an orphaned foal as her own?","answer":"Nurse mare	"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5906 medium TH319/HIH920-4","question":"Where do the sperm & egg unite?","answer":"Oviducts or fallopian tubes        (accept either)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5907 medium TH337 HIH920-5","question":"What is the hormone called that caused follicle growth?","answer":"FSH     (follicle stimulating hormone)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5908 medium TH326/ HIH920-5/FCH235","question":"What term describes when a mare undergoes multiple estrous cycles only during a specific part of the year?","answer":"Seasonally polyestrous    "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5909 medium TH317 HIH920-4","question":"2 part question: What are the size & the shape of the ovaries?","answer":"2 - 3 inches long, bean shaped"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5910 medium TH317 HIH920-4","question":"What is the scientific name for the egg?","answer":"Ovum	 (additional info -- ova is plural)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5911 medium TH781/DET39","question":"What is the name for the specialized building where mares are bred?","answer":"Breeding shed"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5912 medium HIH930-2","question":"Reproductive ability in the mare decreases after what age?","answer":"15	(accept any number within 15-18 range) "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5913 medium DET97","question":"What does the term "entire" refer to?","answer":"Stallion"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5914 medium BEG112 HIH970-5, 975-2","question":"In the newborn foal the navel stump is a site that allows easy access for the invasion of what microorganism into the body?","answer":"Bacteria	"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5915 medium DET176/FCH234","question":"What is mastitis?","answer":"Inflammation/infection of the udder"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5916 medium CAHA69","question":"In mare's milk, which is higher -- milk fat or lactose?","answer":"Lactose"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5917 medium TH393 HIH940-3","question":"What type of lights makes a photo-stimulation effective?","answer":"Regular bulbs on a timer OR fluorescent bulbs		 (accept either)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5918 medium FCH250 HIH970-5","question":"After birth, when a mare passes the placenta, what should you do with it?","answer":"Examine it to make sure it's all there"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5919 medium TH355 HIH980-1","question":"What is the main function of the scrotum?","answer":"Encloses testicles OR controls the temperature of the testicles (accept either)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5920 medium HIH1380-1,2","question":"What breeding policy involves payment of the stud fee when the mare is pronounced in foal at a 42 day exam?","answer":"Guaranteed in foal"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5921 medium HIH970-4","question":"Name a cause of dystocia or difficulty foaling","answer":"Abnormal presentation, foal too large for mareï¿½s pelvis, twins, ï¿½red bagï¿½
(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5922 medium TH340 HIH960-3","question":"Approximately how many days does it take for the fertilized ovum to migrate to the uterus?","answer":"4 - 6              (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5924 medium DET100 HIH920-5","question":"During what stage of the mare's estrous cycle is she receptive to the stallion?","answer":"Estrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5925 medium HIH1380-1","question":"What breeding policy involves payment in advance of the entire price for the season with the payment non-refundable?","answer":"No guarantee"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5926 medium TH423 HIH970-5","question":"How soon after birth should a mare pass her placenta?","answer":"3 hours"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5927 medium CAHA74 HIH980-4","question":"How does the scrotum regulate testicular temperature?","answer":"Raising or lowering the testicles close to or away from the body"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5928 medium DET222","question":"What is the term for the change that occurs in an animal that results in the animal being able to produce sex cells?","answer":"Puberty"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5929 medium FCH44","question":"Lactating mares have an increased need for water due to what?","answer":"Milk production"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5930 medium TH430 HIH975-7","question":"When weaning a foal from the mare, why is it recommended to reduce the mare's food?","answer":"To help the drying up process"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5931 medium TH245","question":"What percent of mare's milk is water?","answer":"90%"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5932 medium HIH421, 970-5","question":"What happens in the 3rd stage of labor?","answer":"Expulsion of the placenta (afterbirth)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5933 medium DET92/HIH920-3","question":"Define endometrium","answer":"Inner Lining of the uterus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5935 medium FCH395 HIH975-3","question":"What is the meconium?","answer":"First manure passed by the foal  OR  dark green/brown/black tarry stools formed prior to birth - normally begin to pass 1/2 hour to 6 hours after birth"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5936 medium FCH234 DET176","question":"What is the term for a bacterial infection of the udder?","answer":"Mastitis"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5937 medium HIH940-2","question":"When using the system for scoring of behavioral estrus in mares, what behavior is seen in a mare scoring 1?","answer":"Mare isn't aggressive towards stallion OR looks away/isn't interested"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5938 medium HIH940-5old","question":"A normal foal weighs what percent of the mare's body weight at birth?","answer":"9 - 10% 		(accept either)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5940 medium HIH1380","question":"When the breeder guarantees a live foal, what must that foal do to fulfill the guarantee?","answer":"Stand & suck"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5941 medium DET298","question":"What is a zygote?","answer":"Fertilized egg"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5943 medium INT227-2 HIH980-1","question":"Which structure of the horse is responsible for maintaining proper temperature for sperm production?","answer":"Scrotum"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5944 medium FCH240","question":"What general type of equine has the lowest incidence of twin pregnancies?","answer":"Ponies"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5945 medium TH323-36 HIH920-5","question":"What is meant by the term ï¿½seasonally polyestrousï¿½?","answer":"Mare undergoes multiple estrous cycles only during certain times of the year"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5946 medium FCH273","question":"In general, what type of horse is often used as a nurse mare 	because they produce more milk?","answer":"Draft or draft-cross mares                                         "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5947 medium HIH975-7","question":"When weaning a foal, why would you want to keep it in familiar surroundings?","answer":"Minimize stress, decrease exposure to disease                "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5948 medium HIH920-5","question":"Give 2 ways that humans contribute to poor reproductive performance","answer":"Attempting to breed mares outside their natural reproductive season
Selecting stallions/mares for their performance/pedigree/beauty instead of their reproductive efficiency"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5949 medium HIH970-1","question":"If a mare must be moved to another facility before foaling, why should you do it no later than 3-4 weeks prior to the expected foaling date?","answer":"To allow her to acclimate to the new area/people/reduce stress            "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"medium","number":"5950 medium HIH970-2","question":"How long before foaling does colostrum develop?                  ","answer":"2-3 weeks"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5951 hard DET91  HIH960","question":"This type of breeding is not accepted by all breed associations.   It is the process of recovering a fertilized egg from the uterus of one mare and transferring it to the uterus of another for gestation. What is this type of breeding? ","answer":"Embryo transfer "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5952 hard HS16 HIH920-6","question":"What hormone regulates testosterone in the stallion?","answer":"LH   (luteinizing hormone)		Accept either"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5953 hard HIH782-5, 975-5","question":"On average, how much milk in pounds is a light horse mare capable of producing per day?","answer":"23 - 29 pounds 		(accept any number within this range) also accept 2-3% of her body weight per day  HIH975-5) "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5954 hard TH424","question":"When a foal is in the transverse ventral presentation for delivery, what part of the foalï¿½s body is lodged against the pelvis of the mare and preventing the delivery of the foal?","answer":"The foalï¿½s back"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5955 hard TH358 HIH980-2","question":"What is the vas deferens?","answer":"Tube that carries sperm from the epididymis to the urethra in the male"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5956 hard TH365 HIH980-5","question":"What is the definition of semen?","answer":"Sperm mixed with fluids from the accessory glands"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5957 hard TH127/HIH920-3, 940-4","question":"What does the hormone progesterone do?","answer":"Encourages glandular development, encourages greater muscle tone in myometrium
Steroid hormone that keeps mare out of estrus & helps to maintain pregnancy in early stages"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5958 hard TH358 HIH980-2","question":"What is the tube that carries sperm from the epididymis to the urethra?","answer":"Vas deferens"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5959 hard HIH970-4","question":"During the second stage of labor, you notice the appearance of a red, velvety bulb at the vulva which looks like a basketball. This is commonly referred to as a ï¿½red bagï¿½. What does this indicate?","answer":"Premature placental separation
(This is an emergency requiring immediate rupture of this membrane to expedite delivery of the foal)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5960 hard TH358 HIH980-2","question":"What is the tube through which both semen & urine pass through the male's penis?","answer":"Urethra"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5961 hard TH128 HIH920-1","question":"2 part question -- What is the birth canal & what organs does it consist of?","answer":"Organs through which the unborn animal passes at birth.  Consists of cervix & vagina"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5962 hard TH319/HIH920-4","question":"What is the funnel-like membrane which surrounds the ovary & catches the egg when it's released?","answer":"Infundibulum"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5963 hard CAHA72","question":"What does the urachus do?","answer":"Takes urine away from the foal during pregnancy"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5964 hard TH362 HIH980-3","question":"Where, specifically, does sperm production take place?","answer":"Seminiferous tubules"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5965 hard HIH920-4, 980-4","question":"What is the function of the cremaster muscle?","answer":"Raises & lowers the scrotum"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5966 hard HIH980-4","question":"What is the name for the major muscle that raises & lowers the scrotum?","answer":"Cremaster"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5967 hard TH321/HIH920-1","question":"Into what organ in the mare does a stallion deposit sperm during mating?  The foal also passes through this during birth ","answer":"Vagina"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5968 hard TH340 HIH980-4","question":"Why are the testicles suspended outside the body cavity?","answer":"Because the scrotal temperature is several degrees cooler than that of the body cavity which is necessary for normal development of the sperm"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5970 hard TH361 HIH980-1","question":"The glands located along the urethra of the male produce fluids which nourish & preserve the sperm.  What are these glands called?","answer":"Accessory glands"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5971 hard TH319 HIH920-3","question":"Define corpus luteum.","answer":"A solid mass that forms on the ovary after ovulation; produces the hormone progesterone that helps maintain pregnancy"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5972 hard TH358 HIH980-4","question":"What is the main function of the epididymis?","answer":"To store sperm	 (additional info -- where they undergo maturation)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5973 hard TH128","question":"Define reproductive organs","answer":"Special organs that produce sex cells & carry out the process of reproduction"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5974 hard TH339 DET100","question":"Hormones that stimulate the development & maintenance of feminine sexual characteristics are called what?","answer":"Estrogenic hormones  OR  Estrogens"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5975 hard TH317-18 HIH920-4","question":"Define follicle","answer":"Bubble-like structure on the ovary which contains the egg"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5976 hard TH319 HIH920-4","question":"Define ovulation","answer":"Time when the follicle bursts & the egg is released"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5977 hard DET213/CAHA72-73/TH340,127/HIH970","question":"What is the placenta?","answer":"Membrane/organ that attaches the fetus to the uterus & transports nutrients & wastes between the uterus & fetus 	(additional info -- via the umbilical cord)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5978 hard HIH950-2old","question":"What does agalactic mean?","answer":"Without milk"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5979 hard HIH940-4","question":"Regumate is the synthetic form of which hormone?","answer":"Progestrone"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5980 hard HIH940-3","question":"What ratio of daylight to darkness seems to bring mares into heat?","answer":"16 hours of daylight to 4 hours of darkness   OR 4:1      Accept either"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5981 hard FCH237/HIH930-2, 940-3","question":"Use of an artificial lighting program to induce early estrous cycling and ovulation should include 16 hours of light each day and begin how long before the desired breeding season?","answer":"2 to 3 months		 (accept anything within this range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5982 hard TH319/HIH920-3","question":"What is the infundibulum?","answer":"Funnel-like membrane that surrounds the ovary & catches the egg"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5983 hard HIH980-3","question":"What is spermatogenesis?","answer":"Process of producing sperm cells"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5984 hard TH339/HIH920-6/CAHA71","question":"What does a lutenizing hormone do?","answer":"Causes ovulation & initiates the formation of the corpus luteum"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5985 hard TH423/DET87/HIH970-4","question":"What is dystocia?","answer":"Difficulty in giving birth    (foaling problems)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5986 hard HIH920-3","question":"What is the main purpose of the myometrium?","answer":"Responsible for the contractions that expel the foal at birth"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5987 hard HIH920-6","question":"In response to GnRH release from the hypothalmus, what structure releases FSH & LH?","answer":"Pituitary gland"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5988 hard TH422/DET200","question":"Give 2 reasons for injecting a mare with oxytocin","answer":"Help with delivery of foal, stimulate milk let down"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5989 hard ADV327-1 HIH980-2","question":"The Sertoli cells located in the seminiferous tubules of the stallion's testes stimulate spermatogenesis in the stallion.  What hormone from the pituitary gland controls the Sertoli cells?","answer":"FSH (follicle stimulating hormone)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5990 hard TH344/HIH940-4","question":"What does PMSG stand for?","answer":"Pregnant mare serum gonadotropin"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5991 hard HIH920-6, 940-4/CAHA71","question":"What hormone released by the uterus if the mare isn't pregnant is responsible for the regression of the corpus luteum & the return of the mare cycling?","answer":"Prostaglandin"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5992 hard TH427 HIH975-4","question":"What is the protein in colostrum that provides the foal with temporary immunity against infectious diseases?","answer":"Immunoglobulin (antibodies)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5993 hard CAHA71","question":"When during the estrous cycle does ovulation usually occur?","answer":"24 - 28 hours before end of estrus           (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5994 hard FCH239","question":"2 part question:  What substances in the urine & in the blood are used to test for pregnancy & what specifically are they tested for?  ","answer":"Urineï¿½estrogen; 	blood --PMSG (pregnant mare serum gonadotropin)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5995 hard TH376 HIH930-3","question":"Name the operation performed on mares where the upper part of the vulva is stitched to reduce infection?","answer":"Caslicks"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5996 hard HIH920-4","question":"What organ is responsible for the production of estrogen & progesterone?","answer":"Ovary"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5997 hard TH396","question":"How long can sperm cells survive in the female reproductive tract?","answer":"48 -72 hours"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5998 hard HIH 940-5old				","question":"You do the mathï¿½ A newborn foal normally weighs 9-10% of the mareï¿½s body weight.  What would be the approximate weight of a foal if the mare weighs 1200 pounds?","answer":"Approximately 108 to 120 pounds		 (accept anything within this range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"5999 hard HIH920-6","question":"Once the follicle has ruptured & released the ova, the luteal phase begins.  The corpus luteum begins to form & is responsible for the release of what hormone?","answer":"Progesterone"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6000 hard TH341/CAHA72 HIH920-3","question":"What is the name of the innermost membrane of the fetal placenta that forms the water bag for the developing fetus?","answer":"Amnion"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6001 hard CAHA72","question":"What is the name of the hard disc-like structure found in the placental fluids after birth?","answer":"Hippomane"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6002 hard ADV327-2 HIH980-3","question":"What structures in the testes serve as the location for spermatogenesis?","answer":"Seminiferous tubules"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6003 hard HIH930-2","question":"What is the purpose of a Caslick's operation?","answer":"To seal the vulva  OR  to prevent air/debris from being sucked into reproductive tract of the mare"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6004 hard CAHA5","question":"What do the sebaceous glands in the prepuce of a stallion produce?","answer":"Smegma"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6005 hard TH358/HIH980-3/DET97","question":"In what part of the stallion's reproductive tract do sperm undergo modifications or maturation?","answer":"Epididymis"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6006 hard TH338 HIH920-6","question":"What 2 hormones increase just before ovulation in the mare?","answer":"Estrogen & Lutenizing Hormone/LH"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6007 hard HIH980-1","question":"2 part question:  What is a bilateral cryptorchid stallion & explaining your answer, can they be used for breeding?","answer":"Stallion that's retained both testicles in the body cavity.  No, they canï¿½t be used for breeding because they're infertile 	(additional info -- due to suppressed spermatogenesis)  "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6008 hard HIH920-4","question":"What is the function of the cilia in the oviducts?","answer":"Transporting the ovum/egg down the oviduct & moving sperm in opposite direction"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6009 hard HIH980-2","question":"What is the primary hormone that's produced & secreted by the Leydig cells in the testes?","answer":"Testosterone"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6010 hard HIH920-3","question":"Which layer of the mare's uterus is responsible for the powerful contractions which expel the foal at birth?","answer":"Myometrium (middle layer)        Accept either"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6011 hard HIH980-2","question":"Leydig cells in the stallion are responsible for the production of what 2 hormones?","answer":"Testosterone & estrogen"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6012 hard TH127/HIH920-3","question":"What hormone causes the cervix of the mare to become relaxed during estrus?","answer":"Estrogen"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6013 hard ADV327 HIH980-2","question":"What is the primary purpose of FSH in the stallion?","answer":"Stimulates production of sperm"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6014 hard TH387 HIH990-4","question":"How is it determined that a stallion has ejaculated while breeding a mare?","answer":"Tail flagging"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6015 hard TH360 HIH990-5 ","question":"The vesicular gland is responsible for adding what to the semen?","answer":"Gel fraction"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6016 hard TH340 DET200","question":"What hormone is responsible for both milk let-down & contractions during parturition?","answer":"Oxytocin"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6017 hard HIH920-3","question":"Name the 2 tough sheet-like structures by which the uterus is suspended within the body cavity?","answer":"Broad ligaments"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6018 hard TH339 HIH920-6","question":"What are the 2 ovarian hormones that control the mare's estrous cycle?","answer":"Estrogen & progesterone"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6019 hard HIH920-6","question":"Which hormone do the luteal cells within the corpus luteum secrete?","answer":"Progesterone"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6020 hard TH595 HIH970-4","question":"Give a good reason for not breaking the foal's umbilical cord too soon after birth?","answer":"Foal would be deprived of about 30% of the blood that flows from mare to her foal immediately after birth"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6021 hard TH411/HIH960-1","question":"Define embryo transfer","answer":"Transfer of fertilized egg from a donor mare to another recipient mare who carries it to term"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6022 hard HIH990-2","question":"When collecting semen from a stallion for use in artificial insemination, what is the most common method?","answer":"Using an artificial vagina   (use a jump mare or breeding phantom/dummy)         "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6023 hard HIH920-5","question":"During which stage of a mare's reproductive cycle will she exhibit eversion of the vulva?","answer":"Estrus"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6024 hard ADV327-1 HIH980-2","question":"Which hormone stimulates spermatogenesis or the production of sperm in the stallion?","answer":"FSH"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6025 hard TH340 DET10, 56","question":"The amnion, allantois, & chorion comprise what structure?","answer":"Placenta"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6026 hard ADV327-1 HIH980-3","question":"The process of the production of sperm cells is called what?","answer":"Spermatogenesis"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6027 hard TH343-44","question":"The gestation period of a mare carrying a horse foal is approximately how many days shorter than it would be if she were carrying a mule foal?","answer":"10 days"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6028 hard TH218","question":"Lactation increases the energy requirements of a mare above maintenance by what percentage?	","answer":"50 - 70%                (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6029 hard FCH247","question":"Pandiculation is an indication of the well-being of a foal & usually occurs within 4 hours after birth.  What is pandiculation?","answer":"Stretching                      "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6030 hard HIH940-4","question":"A ï¿½red bag deliveryï¿½ is most commonly observed in mares that have grazed on what type of pasture?","answer":"Fescue            "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6031 hard CAHA332","question":"What term describes plant toxins that cross the placental barrier during pregnancy & cause defects in the foal?","answer":"Teratogenic               "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6032 hard HIH980-3","question":"Mares are often placed under lights to bring them into heat earlier.  Why would you want to place a stallion under lights?","answer":"Increase testicular activity              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6033 hard HIH910-3","question":"Weakening of the broad ligaments can cause a downward tilting of the uterus & can predispose a mare to uterine infections & infertility.  Other than injury & illness, identify 2 things that would contribute to the weakening of these ligaments?","answer":"Age of mare, number of pregnancies the mare has had            "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6034 hard TH240,247)","question":"In what specific area of the uterus does the fertilized egg attach & the fetus develop in a normal horse pregnancy?","answer":"Uterine horn                      "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6035 hard HIH930-4","question":"Ovulation will usually occur within how many days after the discontinuation of treatment with Regumate?","answer":"Approximately 12 days              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6036 hard HIH920-4","question":"You recently purchased a new stallion for your breeding program.  The previous owner stated that the stallion had a respiratory illness accompanied by a high fever 30 days ago.  What impact would this have on the stallionï¿½s fertility?","answer":"Would expect a lower sperm count for 65 days after the illness         "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6037 hard TH368","question":"Which 2 criteria used to evaluate semen are NOT affected by the length of day or season of year?","answer":"Morphology & motility                "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6038 hard TH429","question":"What is the slang term for a foal thatï¿½s born with septicemia & is semi-comatose?","answer":"Sleeper or sleeper foal         "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6039 hard HIH920-4","question":"What is the national average for live foal births in human-controlled breeding operations?","answer":"50 ï¿½ 60%              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6040 hard HIH920-5","question":"What is the average for live foal births in feral horse populations?","answer":"80-90%             "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6041 hard HIH930-3","question":"What is short-cycling a mare?","answer":"Giving hormones to return mare to heat before their next natural cycle     "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6042 hard HIH930-6","question":"What has been one of the most important advances in commercial horse breeding?","answer":"The practice of AI (artificial insemination)    "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6043 hard HIH950-1","question":"AI is accepted in most breed associations.  Name a breed that requires live cover breeding","answer":"Thoroughbred             "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6044 hard HIH950","question":"Name a cause of colic in newborn foals                   ","answer":"Meconium impaction, gastric ulcer, enteritis, inguinal hernia, lethal white syndrome"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"hard","number":"6045 hard ADV336/HIH940-4","question":"Prostaglandin, human chorionic gonadotropin & progesterone (Regumate) are 3 hormones that can be used to do what?","answer":"Manipulate estrus in mares"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6046 bonus FCH240","question":"The most common cause of spontaneous abortion is placental or uterine infections.  Prior to the current widespread use of ultrasound, what accounted for about 25% of abortions & was considered to be the second most common cause?","answer":"Twinning              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6047 bonus HIH1380-24/HIH920-3","question":"Name 3 distinct layers of the uterus.","answer":"Endometrium, myometrium, serosa"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6048 bonus ADV336-2/HIH940-2","question":"When scoring the behavioral estrus in mares, give 3 examples of behavior that would indicate a score of 4","answer":"Mare shows intense interest in stallion, turning hindquarters to him, leaning towards him, exhibits continuous winking & urination, squats, tail lifting, calling"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6049 bonus HIH445-3, 930-5","question":"Name 3 booster vaccinations should the broodmare receive 4 - 6 weeks before foaling?","answer":"Tetanus, rhinopneumonitis, flu  change to - tetanus, WEE/EEE, influenza, West Nile, rabies"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6050 bonus H3-34/HIH910-1","question":"Give 3 negative aspects of breeding your horse.","answer":"Years before foal can be ridden, might not be able to sell foal, foal might not inherit desirable characteristics, pregnancy or birth complications, mare or foal could die during foaling, might not be able to use mare during pregnancy/lactation, expenses such as stud fee, mare care, medical expense, ï¿½foal proofingï¿½ facility, etc.     Accept any reasonable answers"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6051 bonus H3-9","question":"Give 3 positive aspects of breeding your horse.","answer":"Good learning experience, can imprint/train foal, can plan mating to produce type of offspring you want, possible income from sale of foal or pregnant mare"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6052 bonus HIH930-1","question":"Give 3 of the 5 reproductive classifications of mares.","answer":"Pregnant, open, barren, maiden, wet/lactating/nursing"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6053 bonus FCH230/HIH930-1","question":"2 part question:  Reproductively, name 3 ways mares can be classified & explain each classification.","answer":"Barrenï¿½mare that's been bred, but isn't pregnant; 
In foal/pregnantï¿½pregnant mare; a mare which will foal in the current or following year
Wet/lactatingï¿½nursing a foal;
Maidenï¿½never been bred;  (or mare that has never delivered a foal)
Openï¿½currently not in foal (hasn't been bred this season, but has produced foal in previous seasons)
HIH definition simpler ï¿½ ï¿½mare not pregnant in the current yearï¿½"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6054 bonus TH365 HIH990-6","question":"Name 3 of the criteria used to evaluate stallion semen.","answer":"Concentration, motility/movement, volume, morphology, appearance"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6055 bonus INT226-2/ADV326 HIH920-5","question":"Name 3 behaviors of a mare in diestrus towards a stallion.","answer":"Biting, kicking, striking, squealing, tail switching, ignoring/disinterested"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6056 bonus TH374 HIH980","question":"Give 3 causes of infertility in the stallion.","answer":"Poor health, poor nutrition, anxiety, masturbation, unnecessary rough handling, scared by aggressive mares, injury, worry, improper management, overuse as a teaser, overbreeding, pain"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6057 bonus TH339 HIH920-6","question":"What are the 3 principal estrogenic hormones?","answer":"Estradiol, estrone, estriol"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6058 bonus TH375/HIH910-2","question":"You have recently opened a Quarter Horse breeding operation.  You think you've found the ideal stallion for your program.  His conformation is nearly flawless.  However, there are other considerations when purchasing a stallion -- Name 3 other considerations.","answer":"Semen evaluation, weight (over or under), cardiovascular system, reproductive tract palpation, temperament/manners,  condition of respiratory tract, record of settling mares, general health, hindleg soundness, arthritis, parasite infestation, colic frequency, libido evaluation, melanomas, genetic problems, unsoundness, "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6059 bonus TH323 HIH920-5","question":"Name 3 signs of estrus in the mare.","answer":"Frequent urination, flexed pelvis/squatting, winking, elevated tail, acceptance of stallion"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6060 bonus TH374/HIH920-5","question":"Name3 general causes of infertility in either a mare or stallion.","answer":"Infection, hormonal disturbance/imbalance, nutritional factors, anatomical problems, age, psychological, mechanical, management factors"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6061 bonus TH341 DET","question":"Name the 3 membranes of the placenta.","answer":"Amnion, allantois, chorion"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6062 bonus TH346 HIH930,940","question":"What are 3 methods that can be used to determine if a mare is pregnant?","answer":"Blood test for PMSG after 45 days, palpation, failure to come into heat, ultrasound"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6063 bonus TH425-27HIH","question":"Name 3 causes of equine abortion","answer":"Infectious:  acute infections, chronic infections, bacterial infections, viral infections, fungal infections, non-infectious:  fetus in the uterine body instead of uterine horn, endometrial fibrosis, strangulation of umbilical cord, fetal abnormalities, trauma, twins, fetal malnutrition, problems with placenta, drugs, plants, hormone imbalance, nutritional deficiencies"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6064 bonus HIH920-1/TH128","question":"Name 3 parts of the reproductive tract of the mare.","answer":"Ovaries, oviducts/fallopian tubes, uterus, cervix, vagina, vulva"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6065 bonus TH128 HIH980-1","question":"Name 3 parts of the stallion's reproductive tract.","answer":"Testicle, scrotum, epididymis, vas deferens, urethra, penis"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6066 bonus HS22 DET","question":"Name 3 terms that mean the removal of testicles in a horse.","answer":"Alter, geld, castrate"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6067 bonus TH385 HIH","question":"Give 3 advantages of castration.","answer":"Geldings are safer for novice horsemen, geldings are easier to care for, geldings are easier to transport, geldings are less prone to injuries, can keep several geldings together, can keep geldings with mares, prevents accidental pregnancy"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6068 bonus TH363 HIH980-3","question":"Name the 3 parts of the sperm cell","answer":"Head, midpiece, tail"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6071 bonus HIH950-8","question":"Premature separation of the placenta during parturition resulting in hypoxia is a known cause for neonatal maladjustment syndrome.  Identify 3 terms used to describe these foals as they progress through the stages of this disorder","answer":"Wanderer, dummy, convulsive or barker foal                   "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6072 bonus TH424","question":"A broodmare whose foal is in a ï¿½flexed capriï¿½ position would need what problem corrected to enable normal vaginal delivery?","answer":"Knees are bent, so foal would need repositioned & front legs straightened into normal presentation for delivery                         "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6073 bonus HS22 DET111,107,62","question":"What are the terms used for a baby horse, a baby female horse, a baby male horse?","answer":"Baby horse is a foal, baby female horse is a filly, & baby male horse is a colt"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6074 bonus FCH237","question":"In regards to the stallion, identify 4 advantages for artificial insemination versus live cover breeding","answer":"Prevent spread of venereal disease
Able to breed injured/crippled stallions that are unable to mount a mare
Eliminates injury to stallion from nervous, aggressive or shy mares
Able to breed more mares per season
Able to impregnate a mare located far away by shipping semen"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6075 bonus FCH237","question":"What are the 4 methods used to breed mares?","answer":"Pasture breeding, hand breeding, artificial insemination, embryo transfer        "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6076 bonus FCH251","question":"Describe 3 methods that can be used to help establish an effective airway for a foal thatï¿½s not breathing after delivery","answer":"Clear & remove membranes from over nostrils
Place foal on sternum (head outstretched with rear end elevated)
Gently remove fluids from nostrils with fingers
Tickle inside of nose to induce sneezing
Suction fluids from mouth using bulb syringe
Rub with towels"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6077 bonus HIH930-4","question":"Give 3 physical signs of immaturity in a newborn foal","answer":"Underweight, silky hair, floppy ears, weakness, poor suckle reflex, illness/septicemia      "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6078 bonus HIH930-4","question":"Give 3 factors affecting gestation length           ","answer":"Time of year (late winter/early spring may foal 5-10 days later), fetal sex, maternal nutrition, environmental stress, ingestion of toxins (fescue)"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6079 bonus HIH950-1","question":"Name 3 advantages of AI     (artificial insemination)           ","answer":"breed to large pool of stallions no matter where located geographically ï¿½ potential to improve genetics in their herd w/o shipping mare to stud, potential injuries/risks associated w/transportation eliminated, health risks due to disease transmission reduced, mares susceptible to uterine infections more likely to conceive, stallions can breed to more mares"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6080 bonus HIH950-1","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of AI   (artificial insemination)    ","answer":"initial costs to stallion owner, need skilled staff, costs of shipping (usually overnight), mare must be examined ï¿½ timing of heat & ordering, need good communication between mare/stallion owners, must be ordered in advance"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6081 bonus HIH960-2","question":"Name 3 reasons why embryo transfer might be used         ","answer":"Obtain foals from mares w/o withdrawing them from competition, produce more than one foal from a valuable mare within same year, obtain foals from young, cycling mares that lack mental and/or physical maturity, provide economic benefit to owner, improving productivity of fertile mares w/lesser genetic potential by using them for surrogates"},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6082 bonus HIH975-3","question":"Name 3 symptoms of meconium impactions in newborn foals","answer":"Depression, not interested in nursing, flagging tail, increased heart rate/tachycardia, increased respiration rate/tachypnea, abdominal distension              "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6083 bonus HIH990-1","question":"What are 3 reasons for doing a semen evaluation?","answer":"Monitor stallionï¿½s semen quality, estimate the number of mares that could be bred, maximizing use of single time breeding, shipping cooled semen, freezing semen for later use, quality control    "},
{"category":"REPRODUCTION","level":"bonus","number":"6084 bonus TH360   HIH980-1","question":"What are the 3 accessory glands located along the urethra in the stallion?","answer":"Prostate, seminal vesicles/vesicular glands, Cowper's/bulbourethral glands"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6085 easy HH52","question":"Why should you tie your horse far away from strange horses?","answer":"They might fight"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6086 easy HH53","question":"When riding your horse on paved roads, what gait should you use?","answer":"Walk"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6087 easy HH53","question":"Why should horses on a picket line not be too close to each other?","answer":"They might fight"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6088 easy H1-27","question":"Never tie a horse at a level below what point of the horse?","answer":"Withers /shoulder"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6089 easy HH53","question":"Which gait should you use when riding on rough ground or in sand, mud, ice or snow?","answer":"Walk (let him pick his own way as there is danger or slipping or falling)	"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6090 easy HH52	","question":"What is the safest way to lead a horse through a narrow opening or gate?","answer":"Step through first & move to one side to avoid being crowded"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6091 easy HH52","question":"If your horse resists while you are trying to lead it, what should you NOT do?","answer":"Don't get in front & try to pull him"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6092 easy HH53","question":"While riding, what should you do if your horse becomes frightened & tries to run away?","answer":"Turn him in a circle & tighten the circle till he stops OR use pulley rein or one rein halt"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6093 easy TH822/HIH340-4","question":"In case of an emergency what two pieces of equipment should be outside every horseï¿½s stall?","answer":"Halter and lead"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6094 easy H1-25","question":"What is the recommended knot for tying a halter rope to a fixed object?  	","answer":"Quick release  "},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6095 easy HH51","question":"If you have to work around a horseï¿½s hindquarters, why is it important to stay close?","answer":"If the horse kicks, you wonï¿½t get the full impact of the kick"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6096 easy HIH340-1/TH754","question":"What tragic event involving barns or equine facilities can be caused by human carelessness and lack of safety knowledge? ï¿½","answer":"Barn fires"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6097 easy HH52","question":"What should you never do with a lead rope or reins?","answer":"Never wrap them around your hand, wrist, or body"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6099 easy HH53","question":"Why should you speak to your horse when approaching it from the rear?","answer":""},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6100 easy HH52","question":"When going up & down hills, you should always use which gait?","answer":"Walk	"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6101 easy HH53","question":"Why should you recheck the cinch just before mounting the horse?","answer":"Because the cinch often loosens after you walk your horse around"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6102 easy HH51","question":"Why is it important to learn & practice safety rules?","answer":"So theyï¿½ll become habits & will keep you safe"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6103 easy HH52","question":"When your horse is tied, what should you always do before removing the halter?","answer":"Untie the horse 	(additional info -- so if the horse pulls back you wonï¿½t get hurt)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6104 easy H4-19","question":"What should you do as a safety precaution if your horse is known to kick?","answer":"Put a red ribbon in its tail"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6105 easy HIH1220-1","question":"Why should you never approach a horse directly from behind?","answer":"He can't see directly behind himself & you might get kicked"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6106 easy HH52","question":"What direction should you turn the horse when leading it?","answer":"Away from you OR to the right	 (additional info -- so you donï¿½t get stepped on)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6107 easy HH53","question":"After adjusting the saddle & before you mount, what should you do?","answer":"Re-check the cinch  "},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6108 easy HH53","question":"In using a double-rigged saddle, which cinch should you buckle first?","answer":"Front"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6109 easy HH52","question":"What is the only thing you should tie your horse with?","answer":"Halter rope/lead rope"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6110 easy HH51","question":"Where should you place your hand first when petting your horse?","answer":"Neck or shoulder"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6111 easy HIH340-4","question":"Why should you keep a halter & lead rope by each stall?","answer":"In case of emergency	 (additional info -- so you can lead horse out quickly)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6112 easy HH53","question":"Which cinch should you loosen first when unsaddling a double-rigged saddle?","answer":"Back"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6113 easy HH52","question":"When working on a horse, what position is considered the safest for you to be in?","answer":"As near shoulder as possible		
(additional info -- so you can stay away from the mouth & the hind legs)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6115 easy HH52","question":"You should never tie a horse with what?","answer":"Bridle/reins"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6116 easy HH54","question":"Why shouldn't you run past other horses & riders?","answer":"It will make the other horses want to run & someone could get hurt"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6117 easy HH51","question":"Always do what when approaching your horse?","answer":"Speak to him"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6118 easy HH51","question":"Disregarding simple safety rules in handling horses can result in what?","answer":"Serious injury"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6119 easy HIH340-2","question":"Give 2 fire safety rules for barns.","answer":"No smoking, no flammable substances, store vehicles & machinery elsewhere, fire extinguishers available, no kerosene or portable heaters, automatic fire sprinklers, smoke alarms, inside water supply with hose, exterior stall doors, space between buildings exit doors marked, barn aisles clear, keep cobwebs/dust off electrical fixtures, manure piles at least 20ï¿½ away from barn, keep weeds/brush/trash picked up from around barn, fire hose/buckets available		(accept any reasonable answer)		"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6120 easy BEG113-2/HIH340-4","question":"Why should smoking NEVER be allowed in a barn?","answer":"It could cause a fire"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6121 easy H1-25","question":"What kind of knot is recommended when tying a rope around a horse's neck?","answer":"Bowline	 (additional info -- because it wonï¿½t slip & choke the horse)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6122 easy HH54","question":"What should you tell someone who's going to ride your horse?","answer":"Tell them what to expect"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6123 easy H1-27","question":"What is the safest way to comb a horseï¿½s tail?","answer":"Stand off to the side & bring the tail around to you"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6124 easy HH51","question":"Horses kept in tie stalls must be taught to do what before you walk in beside them?","answer":"Move over	 (additional info -- so youï¿½re not crowded against the wall)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6125 easy HH52","question":"If your horse rears up while you are leading it, what should you do?","answer":"Release the hand nearest the halter so you can stay on the ground"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6126 easy H4-16","question":"Describe how the halter lead rope should be held.","answer":"Right hand holds the lead rope near the halter.  Left hand holds the excess lead either folded in figure 8 "},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6127 easy HIH710-5","question":"When using a hay net for feeding horses, why should it be tied at approximately eye level of the horse?","answer":"SAFETY ï¿½ so horse canï¿½t get foot caught in it"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6128 easy HH53","question":"When riding, if an obstacle frightens your horse, what should you do?","answer":"Steady him/give him time to overcome his fear then ride by the obstacle"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6129 easy HH53","question":"Why is it important to keep your horse under control & to keep a secure seat?","answer":"Horses are easily frightened    (also accept so you wonï¿½t fall off)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6130 easy HIH340/TH781			","question":"For fire safety, a building for hay storage should be located at least how many feet from any other structures?","answer":"At least 100 feet away"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6131 easy HH21","question":"Why is it a good safety practice to face the rear of the horse when mounting?","answer":"Easier to keep your balance OR easier to control horse"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6132 easy H1-25","question":"What are 2 basic knots every horseperson should know?","answer":"Quick release, bowline, square knot, half hitch, double half hitch"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6133 easy HH51","question":"When catching a horse, what area of the horse should you walk towards?","answer":"Neck or shoulders"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6134 easy HH54","question":"If a rider should fall from the horse when jumping, what should be done?","answer":"DONï¿½T move him;   CALL 911 if heï¿½s injured"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6135 easy H1-25","question":"What type of knot would you use when you need a loop that won't slip or tighten?","answer":"Bowline"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6136 easy HH52","question":"Why should you never tie a horse with the reins?","answer":"He may pull back, break the reins, or injure his mouth 	(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6137 easy HH53","question":"When saddling, if you drop the saddle down too quickly or hard, what may happen?","answer":"Might scare the horse or hurt his back"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6138 easy HH52","question":"What is the safest way to turn your horse loose in a pasture or stall?","answer":"Lead horse completely through gate/door.  Turn him to face direction from which you just came, then remove the halter/bridle
(additional info -- never let him bolt away from you because itï¿½s a bad habit & you might get kicked)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6139 easy HH52","question":"What is the safest position from which to lead a horse?","answer":"Between his head & shoulder "},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6140 easy HH53","question":"When riding a young or green horse, what's the safest way to cross a paved road?","answer":"Dismount & lead him across"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6141 easy HH54","question":"What part of the horse's body should you NEVER strike or kick?","answer":"Head or legs		 (additional info -- they injure more easily than the rest of the body)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6142 easy HH37/TH719-20","question":"Why should a hoof pick only be used from heel to toe?","answer":"Safety!  If used the opposite way, it could slip & gouge handler or horse"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6143 easy HH53","question":"On what side of the road should you ride?","answer":"With traffic OR side required by state law"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6144 easy HH52","question":"In using a double-rigged saddle, which cinch should you buckle last?","answer":"Rear			"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6145 easy HIH340-1","question":"Most barn fires occur in which seasons?","answer":"Summer & winter"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6146 easy TH821","question":"During a fire, what's the best thing to do to get your horse out of a barn?","answer":"Blindfold him"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6147 easy BEG107-2/TH775/HIH320","question":"Why is electrical wiring in a barn is always run in conduits?","answer":"To protect the horse from getting shocked  add: to keep horses from chewing on it
(additional info -- conduits are coverings for electrical wires & are often made out of metal)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6148 easy HH53","question":"Why should you never mount or dismount near fences, barns, or overhanging projections?","answer":"You may get hurt"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6149 easy HIH340-2","question":"How often should a fire extinguisher be checked?					","answer":"Yearly"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"easy","number":"6150 easy HIH320-9","question":"Why is it recommended that hay be stored in a different building from the horses?","answer":"Fire safety   (possibly respiratory issues)              "},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"medium","number":"6151 medium HIH340-1old, 340-4new","question":"Where should fire extinguishers be hung in a barn?","answer":"Should be hanging at all exterior doorways, in middle of long aisles & next to electrical panel box      
Also accept at least 75 feet apart"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"medium","number":"6152 medium HIH340-2old","question":"What is a critical, but often overlooked, item of a barn escape plan?","answer":"Providing for a holding area at a distance from the barn that's big enough to hold all the horses"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6153 bonus HH53","question":"Name the 3 times you should check your cinch.","answer":"After saddling, after walking a few steps, after mounting & riding a short distance"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6154 bonus TH759/HH/HIH/CCS","question":"You should check your pasture or turnout area for unsafe conditions.  Name 3.","answer":"Old machinery/junk, broken fence, loose wire, broken boards, nails, poisonous plants, etc
Accept any reasonable answer"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6155 bonus H4-19-21/HH53","question":"Name 3 safety precautions for riding in a group.","answer":"Don't rush past other riders who're going slower, keep a safe distance between horses, cross roads together, ride on same side of road, most experienced rider in lead, least experienced riders in middle of group, wait for everyone to be mounted before you ride off, no practical jokes, warn other riders of obstacles, if possible take cell phone, if horse kicks - put red ribbon in tail, pay attention      
(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6159 bonus H1-25","question":"What are 3 features of a good knot?","answer":"Easy to tie, strong, holds firmly, easy to untie if used for livestock"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6160 bonus HIH320, 340/BEG320","question":"When building a barn, what are 3 safety features you should incorporate?","answer":"Adequate ventilation, electrical outlets in safe/convenient locations, windows in proper location, alley width, stall door width, stall size, stall doors hung safely, no obstacles blocking air ventilation, adequate lighting, waterers in safe/convenient locations, inside temperature at comfortable level
use flame retardant or fire resistant materials, install smoke detectors, fire alarms, sprinkler systems, etc"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6161 bonus HIH340","question":"Give 3 safety features for barn electrical systems.","answer":"Conform to national electrical code, panel boxes in dry/dust-free area, switch boxes have dust/watertight covers, corrosive resistant/weather proofed, wires in conduits, appliances grounded/UL approved,  thermostats on water heaters, heat lamps not close to hay/bedding, no portable heaters, light bulbs in dust free covers, inspect equipment regularly, outlets/wires/lights out of horse's reach, utility shutoffs prominently marked ,  lightning rods on barns"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6162 bonus HIH340-1","question":"Name 3 things that cause winter fires","answer":"Appliances/portable heaters, rodents/horses chewing through wires, dust/cobwebs on electrical surfaces, smoking, etc		(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6163 bonus H4-21","question":"When trail riding in a group with riders & horses of varying experience, describe the riding order - experience wise - that' s the most safe.","answer":"Most experienced in lead, least experienced in middle, strong rider bringing up rear"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6164 bonus HIH340-2-old","question":"Give 3 basic steps of a barn escape plan.","answer":"Escape plan posted in barn, fire drills, firefighters/emergency personnel trained in horse handling/behavior, horses accustomed to simulated smoke/emergency situations, necessary equipment & knowledge of how to use, never lock stall doors, fire dept phone # posted, have supply of towels/burlap bags for blindfolds			
6165	(bonus)				HIH340-1
Q:  Name 3 highly flammable materials found in barns/stabling areas
A:  Hay, straw, bedding (esp. sawdust/shredded newspaper), cobwebs, dust, grain dust, horse blankets, paint, fertilizer, pesticides & herbicides"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6165 bonus HIH340-1","question":"Name 3 highly flammable materials found in barns/stabling areas 		","answer":"Hay, straw, bedding (esp. sawdust/shredded newspaper), cobwebs, dust, grain dust, horse blankets, paint, fertilizer, pesticides & herbicides"},
{"category":"SAFETY","level":"bonus","number":"6167 bonus HIH340-2","question":"An ignition source is something that can cause an accelerant or flammable material to ignite or smoke.  Name 3 common ignition sources				","answer":"Cigarettes, matches, sparks, motors, heaters, electrical appliances, fence chargers, electrical fixtures/wires, batteries, broken glass, chemicals"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6168 easy TH766/HIH330-4","question":"In order to reduce maintenance & the chance of injury, what device is used to keep horses off the fence?","answer":"Hot wire or electric wire"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6169 easy TH412/HIH940-3 HIH350-1/970-2","question":"Why is straw preferred over shavings as bedding for a foaling stall?","answer":"Shavings can stick wet foal, irritate eyes/mucous membranes, potentially interfere w/breathing   (accept any ï¿½ do not need to give all)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6170 easy HIH320-3","question":"What is the minimum height for a stall wall?","answer":"Eight feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6171 easy BEG107-3/HIH320-7","question":"Name one reason not to store hay above horse stalls.","answer":"Dust, mold, fire hazard"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6172 easy HIH360-2","question":"How far should a manure storage area be from a drinking water well?","answer":"At least 100 feet        Accept answers between 100 ï¿½ 150 feet
Addtl info - HIH365-2 (update) says 150 feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6173 easy HIH320-7","question":"What is the main purpose of a cupola on a barn roof?","answer":"Ventilation"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6174 easy HIH320-3-old","question":"What is the minimum size recommended for a box stall?","answer":"10 feet x 10 feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6175 easy HIH320-3old/BEG107-2/TH778","question":"What is the most popular box stall size?","answer":"12 feet x 12 feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6176 easy HIH320-3/BEG107-2/TH779","question":"Name a disadvantage to wood floors in stalls.","answer":"Slippery when wet, attracts rodents, difficult to clean, harbor odors"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6177 easy H3-25/TH754/HIH320","question":"When planning a horse facility, what should be the main consideration?","answer":"Safety"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6178 easy HIH330-4/TH765-66","question":"Name a disadvantage of electric fencing.","answer":"Not very visible, shorts out easily, horse can be injured on the T posts"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6179 easy HIH330-5/TH766","question":"What is the biggest disadvantage of PVC or vinyl fencing?","answer":"Expensive 	(additional info -- 2 times the cost of board)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6180 easy HIH320-4","question":"What is one of the most desirable materials for building a stall?","answer":"Wood"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6181 easy HIH320-5","question":"What is the major purpose of a stall door?","answer":"To keep the horse safely in the stall       (also accept to let the horse into the stall)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6182 easy HIH350-1","question":"What is one of the most popular kinds of bedding?","answer":"Straw or shavings 		(also accept sawdust)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6183 easy HIH210-3/350-1","question":"What is a general term for material used to cover a stall floor to provide comfort & absorb moisture?","answer":"Bedding"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6184 easy HIH210-3","question":"Which is generally higher for horses purchase price or maintenance costs?","answer":"Maintenance cost"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6185 easy HIH320-7","question":"The temperature inside a barn should be no more than 5 degrees above what?","answer":"Outside temperature     "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6186 easy HIH320-8","question":"If you store hay above stalls, how much space must be left between the hay & walls for air passage?","answer":"At least 12 inches"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6187 easy HIH320-3","question":"What size should a stallion stall be?","answer":"14 feet x 14 feet     or  minimum of 12 x 14 feet  "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6188 easy HIH320-3","question":"In order to resist pawing, how thick should rubber mats used as stall flooring be?","answer":"At least 5/8 inch thick   (updated 2014 HIH info)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6189 easy H3-23/TH757/HIH360-4","question":"What happens to your pasture if you put horses in the pasture during very wet weather?","answer":"Turf damage"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6190 easy HIH365-6","question":"What do you call an unwanted or out-of-place plant?","answer":"Weed"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6191 easy BEG104/FCH181","question":"To what direction should the open side of a 3-sided shelter face?","answer":"Away from prevailing winds OR towards warm winter sun"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6192 easy HIH110-5/HIH350-1","question":"What is bedding?","answer":"Material used to cover the stall floor to provide comfort for horse & absorb moisture"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6193 easy HIH330-4/TH761","question":"What type of fence is strongly discouraged for use with horses?	","answer":"Barbed wire or mesh with large holes  or  high tensile wire   (2014 HIH update info)	 
(additional info -- horse is more likely to get injured)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6194 easy HIH330-2/TH762","question":"2 part question:  On what side of the post should fence boards be nailed & why?","answer":"Inside; so horse can't knock boards off		"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6195 easy HIH730-2","question":"What do weeds & brush in a pasture often indicate?","answer":"Pasture has been poorly managed, overgrazed or inadequately fertilized	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6196 easy HIH320-6","question":"Which type of barn lighting - incandescent or fluorescent - is more energy efficient?","answer":"Fluorescent    (additional info ï¿½ 4 times more efficient)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6197 easy HIH320-5","question":"What type of stall door is the safest & easiest to use around horses?","answer":"Sliding"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6198 easy HIH320-6","question":"What horse health problem can a poorly ventilated or drafty barn cause?","answer":"Pneumonia or other respiratory problems such as heaves"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6199 easy HIH350-1","question":"What is one of the first things to look for when choosing bedding?","answer":"Absorbency"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6200 easy HIH350-1/TH417/FCH243","question":"What is the ideal bedding for a foaling stall?","answer":"Straw	 (additional info -- shavings or sawdust can get stuck in the newbornï¿½s nostrils)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6201 easy HIH950-5/FCH268-69/TH263","question":"What is the name of the structure that allows foals to eat without interference from the mare?","answer":"Creep feeder"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6202 easy HIH320-6 old/TH777","question":"When building a stall, should the stall door be placed to swing in toward the stall or swing out toward the aisle?","answer":"Swing out"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6203 easy HS39","question":"Referring to pastures, what is carrying capacity?","answer":"Number of animals that a habitat can support"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6204 easy HIH740-5","question":"Give a reason why it's important to identify which weeds are present in your pasture.","answer":"So you can use the right product to control them OR so you can identify if any are poisonous"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6205 easy TH770-71/HIH/HH/CCS","question":"What can you do to prevent mud holes around gates, water tanks, & feeding areas?","answer":"Fill them with gravel  "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6206 easy HIH330-1","question":"How high should the outside pasture fence be?","answer":"Minimum of 5 feet OR several inches above the horseï¿½s withers  "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6207 easy HIH360-1","question":"Name one thing that can cause ground water contamination.","answer":"Improperly constructed wells, fuel spills, pesticides, fertilizer, manure   (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6209 easy TH275/HIH365-2","question":"What is the purpose of screening or dragging your pastures to spread out manure piles?","answer":"To reduce parasites  "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6210 easy HIH710-5","question":"What is the main factor to consider when storing hay?","answer":"Protecting it from moisture or other things that can damage the hay"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6211 easy HIH365-1","question":"How is manure usually managed in a pasture?","answer":"Spread	 (additional info ï¿½ usually with a harrow)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6212 easy HIH365-6","question":"In general, how often should a pasture be re-seeded?","answer":"Every 3 - 5 years 	(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6213 easy HIH740-5","question":"What is the most cost-effective method of weed control?","answer":"Prevention OR maintain healthy pasture grasses that can compete with weeds."},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6214 easy HIH740-5","question":"If weeds become a persistent problem, what can you use to control them?","answer":"Herbicides or weed killer"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6215 easy HIH740-5","question":"Bare areas in a pasture provide a perfect environment for what to grow?","answer":"Weeds"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6216 easy HIH740-5","question":"When using herbicides to control weeds, it's important to do what?","answer":"Follow the directions"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6217 easy HIH740-5","question":"If you turn too many horses out in a small pasture & allow it to be overgrazed, what will happen to the pasture?  ","answer":"It will become an exercise lot(dry lot)   (it wonï¿½t have enough forage to provide adequate nutrition)  "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6218 easy HIH330-4","question":"What is a characteristic of wire mesh, high tensile wire, & electric fences that can result in injury to horses confined by them?","answer":"They're hard for the horse to see"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6219 easy H3-27/DET183","question":"What is meant by the term "mucking out"?	","answer":"Cleaning a stall	(also accept stripping, picking out the stall, etc.) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6220 easy TH764/HIH330-3","question":"Other than hot wire, what is the most common kind of wire fencing for horses?","answer":"Woven wire or stock wire"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6221 easy FCH105/HIH730-8,735-2","question":"What is rotational grazing?","answer":"Letting horses graze one pasture for a while, then moving them to another & letting the first area rest"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6222 easy HIH360-3,4","question":"In regards to pasture management, name 2 circumstances when you should keep horses off the pasture?","answer":"During pesticide spraying, during fertilizing, to reduce overgrazing, when there is fresh/lush pasture, during winter, when soil is wet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6223 easy HIH930-5","question":"Why should you keep pregnant mares separate from non-pregnant ones?","answer":"For proper feeding & management OR so they wonï¿½t get hurt"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6225 easy DET p.183/H3-27	","question":"What term refers to the process of cleaning out a horse stall by removing the manure & soiled bedding? ","answer":"Mucking out (also accept stripping, picking out the stall, or any reasonable answer) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6226 easy TH773/HIH320","question":"Give a reason why horse barns must be well ventilated.","answer":"Prevent condensation, prevent odor buildup, decrease humidity, improve air quality, help prevent pneumonia or respiratory problems  "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6227 easy FCH188","question":"Giving only one number, the horse is most comfortable at what temperature?","answer":"18 - 59 degrees   (accept any number within range)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6228 easy TH777-78/HIH320-3","question":"There are 2 main kinds of horse stalls.  What are they?","answer":"Box & tie"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6229 easy FCH103","question":"Name 2 purposes of pastures.","answer":"Provide feed; provide room to exercise"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6230 easy HIH365-3","question":"How many bins would you need for composting the manure produced by 2 - 5 horses?","answer":"Two"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6231 easy HIH330-3","question":"Give one reason for putting a 6 inch wide board at the top of a wire fence?","answer":"To allow the horse to see the fence better OR to prevent damage to the horse & the fence.
OR prevents them from pushing it down/causing it to sag"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6232 easy TH771/HIH330","question":"Why shouldn't galvanized iron or aluminum gates be used for horse facilities?","answer":"Bend & break easily"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6233 easy TH784","question":"What is a mechanical device that leads horses in a circle at a slow walk to cool them down after training or exercise?","answer":"Hot walker"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6234 easy TH771/HIH330-6","question":"How wide should a horse pasture gate be?","answer":"5 - 14 feet	 (accept any answer within this range) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6235 easy TH775/HIH-4","question":"How wide should barn aisles be?","answer":"Wide enough for 2 horses to pass safely (about 9 feet) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6236 easy TH820","question":"With regards to fire safety, what is a common problem in stall construction?","answer":"That there's only one door"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6237 easy HIH320-2","question":"Name a disadvantage of clay floors in stalls                      ","answer":"Holes form easily"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6238 easy HIH320-2","question":"What is an advantage of a larger sized stall?			","answer":"Easier to keep clean, more room for horse to move, may help alleviate some vices"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6239 easy HIH330-2","question":"Which type wood fence posts are stronger ï¿½ round or square?      ","answer":"Round"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6240 easy HIH330-5","question":"What is a disadvantage of rubber fencing?				","answer":"Sags easily, some horses pull at edges & swallow pieces, availability, cost"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6241 easy HIH330-2","question":"When comparing the absorbency of types of bedding, which 	of the following would be the most absorbent?  Shredded newspaper, straw or pinewood sawdust             ","answer":"Shredded newspaper"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6242 easy TH768 HIH350-5","question":"What type of fence is low maintenance and has the longest life expectancy?","answer":"PVC/Vinyl                            "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6243 easy HIH320-2-4","question":"Ideally, each stall in a barn should have what for ventilation?","answer":"Window                "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6244 easy TH764","question":"What type of wire fencing is inexpensive but never appropriate for equine fencing due to the high incidence of injuries?","answer":"Barbed wire                              "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"easy","number":"6245 easy HIH320-5","question":"What is a major concern when using a hose & bucket to water your horse during the winter?","answer":"Making sure it doesnï¿½t freeze                   "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6246 medium HIH320-2-4","question":"Name a problem with using ï¿½greenï¿½ oak for partitions, windows or doors when building stalls","answer":"It will shrink/twist as it dries                    "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6247 medium FCH105-6/HIH735-2","question":"In the eastern US, rotational grazing can double the amount of forage you can generate from the same size pasture.  Each area should be grazed for 10 - 14 days & then allowed to rest for how long?","answer":"One month OR until grass grows to at least 3 inches high"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6248 medium FCH183/HIH320","question":"It's January & you are looking at a new boarding facility for your horse.  It's clean, comfortable, & warm in the barn.  What might the problem be with this barn if you see condensation dripping from parts of the ceiling & there is a significant ammonia odor?","answer":"Poor ventilation"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6249 medium FCH105","question":"In good pasture management, in order to maximize re-growth of pasture & minimize weed invasion, what should be prevented?","answer":"Over grazing"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6250 medium HIH350-1","question":"You are trying to decide between straw & wood shavings for bedding for your 10 horse boarding facility.  Straw is cheaper, but why would it be more economical to use shavings?","answer":"Shavings are less labor intensive OR they pay for their extra cost by savings in labor expense"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6251 medium HIH350-5","question":"Give 2 advantages of using high tensile vinyl fencing.","answer":"Safe, strong, durable, low maintenance, longevity, cost effective"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6252 medium TH766/HIH330-3","question":"You have just finished installing a beautiful white painted fence around your pasture, but you have a problem.  Your horses are fighting over the fence & leaning into & over it.  What can you do to keep the horses off the fence?","answer":"Install electric/hot wire on the top board on each side of the fence"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6253 medium HIH320-1","question":"What 2 environmental conditions in barns or other shelters have proven to be the most detrimental to a horse's health?","answer":"High moisture & temperature extremes (too hot/cold)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6254 hard INT207/HIH320-4","question":"2 part question:  When constructing a horse stall, what spacing should be used for the partition bars & why?","answer":"3 ï¿½ to 4 inches spacing so that the horseï¿½s foot canï¿½t get stuck between them
(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6255 medium TH417,780 HIH320-3","question":"How big should a foaling stall be?","answer":"12 feet x 14 feet minimum (also accept 12 x 16, 16 x 16, 16 x 20)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6256 medium TH755/HIH320,330","question":"What is the most limiting factor of new barn & fence construction?","answer":"Cost"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6257 medium TH763/HIH330-2","question":"What kind of wood is best for fence posts?","answer":"Black locust, cedar, osage orange, or western juniper 	(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6258 medium TH763-64/HIH330-3","question":"What are the 2 types of wire mesh openings?","answer":"Diamond & rectangular"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6259 medium HIH740-5","question":"How does rotational grazing increase pasture productivity?","answer":"Allows time for pasture to re-grow (replace leaf tissue & replenish carbohydrate levels)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6260 medium TH771 HIH320-1","question":"The biggest mistake in most barns is that they are built for human comfort, not for equine health. What is the primary fault found in these barns?","answer":"Poor ventilation"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6261 medium HIH365-1","question":"The US horse industry uses 2 types of feed management systems.  One is grazing full time.  What is the other?","answer":"Confined feeding   (feeding hay or grain in a stall or paddock)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6262 medium HIH330-3","question":"Besides a sight board, what else can you add to a wire fence to keep horses from leaning on it & stretching it","answer":"A board in the middle of fence    "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6263 medium TH771/HIH330-6","question":"How wide should a horse pasture gate be?","answer":"5 - 16 feet	 (accept any answer within this range) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6364 medium HIH740-5","question":"Horses are spot grazers.  What does this mean?","answer":"Horses choose to graze in preferred areas in pastures & on specific forage species/types of plants"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6265 medium TH762/HIH330-2","question":"What size boards should you use for a wood fence?","answer":"1 x 6 OR 1 x 8     (1ï¿½ thick by 6ï¿½ or 8ï¿½ wide) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6266 medium TH784","question":"What is the minimum size for a training arena?","answer":"60 x 100 feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6267 medium TH784","question":"What is the minimum size for an arena used for shows or for the public?","answer":"120 x 100 feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6268 medium INT204-2","question":"Why may putting a blanket on a horse with a winter coat actually make the horse colder rather than warmer?","answer":"Winter coat traps body heat between the hair; putting blanket on may compress the insulating hair eliminating the air layer & reducing the horse's natural protection against the cold"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6269 medium FCH398","question":"Give 2 meanings of the word paddock.","answer":"Small fenced area smaller than a pasture & larger than a run; area where race horses are saddled & viewed before a race "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6270 medium FCH387/HIH","question":"What is a dry lot?","answer":"Paddock or exercise area without growing edible plants"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6271 medium TH274-75","question":"What are 2 benefits to keeping your pastures clipped or mowed?","answer":"Prevents plants from becoming too mature, helps maintain balance of grasses & legumes, controls weeds, helps spread manure"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6272 medium HIH365-2","question":"What is the method of managing manure called that results in a desirable dry end product?","answer":"Composting"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6273 medium BEG107 HIH320-6","question":"In the stable, adequate ventilation is necessary to reduce the presence of air contaminants.  Name 2 examples of air contaminants.","answer":"Dust, mold, irritating gasses (such as ammonia or methane), airborne bacteria, microscopic debris "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6274 medium HIH330-2","question":"Wooden fence posts should be at least what diameter?","answer":"4 inches"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6275 medium HIH350-1","question":"2 part question:  When using wood shavings for bedding, what specific wood should be avoided & why?","answer":"Black walnut;  it can cause laminitis or founder"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6276 medium FCH185","question":"2 part question:  Which type of wood is least preferred for horse fences & why?","answer":"Soft pines or firs; weak in strength, horses like to chew it"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6277 medium HIH320-6","question":"2 part question:  What is the minimum height for an indoor arena & why is a higher ceiling more desirable?","answer":"14 feet minimum; the higher the ceiling, the better lit the arena will be
(additional info - fewer shadows)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6278 medium TH779/HIH365-1,367-1","question":"On average, how many tons of manure does the average horse produce in one year?","answer":"9 tons     (interesting info ï¿½ enough to FILL a 12 x 12 foot stall)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6279 medium FCH181","question":"What is the ideal stall size for a draft horse?","answer":"14 feet x 14 feet"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6280 medium FCH149","question":"If the hay rack is too high for the horse eating from it, what are 2 problems that may occur?","answer":"Hay may get into the horse's eyes & horse may inhale dust
(additional info -- which could lead to respiratory problems)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6282 medium HIH320-5","question":"What should be considered in the construction of interior stall walls?","answer":"Smooth, rugged materials free from any projections that can injure the horse"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6283 medium HIH320-3","question":"How should the stall partitions be placed so the horse's legs can't get caught under them?","answer":"Flush with or slightly below the floor"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6284 medium HIH320-7	","question":"You do the mathï¿½Following the rule of thumb recommendation for adequate ventilation in a barn, a barn with 8 stalls would require how much ridge ventilation?","answer":"At least 8 feet of ridge ventilation (1 foot per stall)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6285 medium FCH106","question":"What method is used to determine how much fertilizer your pasture needs in order to maintain it in top condition?","answer":"Soil test"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6286 medium TH770","question":"What is the most popular base floor material for a box stall?","answer":"Hard-packed clay       "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6287 medium HIH365-6","question":"What is the advantage to rotating horses with cattle or sheep in a pasture?","answer":"Breaks the parasite life cycle"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6288 medium BEG107 HIH320-7","question":"You do the mathï¿½. If it's 70 degrees outside, what should the maximum air temperature inside the barn be in order to insure adequate air exchange?","answer":"75 degrees"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6289 medium DET288","question":"A wash rack is a specific area for washing horses.  What are 2 things that are important in its construction?","answer":"Good footing when wet & adequate drainage"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6290 medium HIH320-8","question":"Barns constructed with aluminum or steel can be hot in summer & cold in winter unless what 2 things are done?","answer":"Make sure there's adequate insulation & ventilation"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6291 medium FCH 323/HIH350-1","question":"What is the most common symptom in horses that have been stabled on hardwood shavings that contain black walnut?                                      ","answer":"Lameness due to laminitis   (accept lameness or laminitis)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6292 medium HIH320-1","question":"2 part question:  What is the barn condition that's most detrimental to a horse's health & why?","answer":"Extreme temperatures with high humidity; harms respiratory system & allows inhalation of pathogens"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6293 medium TH768/HIH330-3","question":"What type of horse fence has the shortest life expectancy?","answer":"Board OR post & rail 	(only need to give one)        Also accept ï¿½plasticï¿½  (HIH ref)    "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6294 medium TH772","question":"As opposed to keeping horses in separate stalls, name one disadvantage of using open front shelters or run-in sheds for several horses.","answer":"Unable to monitor diet of each individual horse, unable to monitor the amount of exercise of each horse, increased risk of injuries"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6295 medium HIH365-1","question":"When properly composted, manure can be used for what?","answer":"Fertilizer or soil conditioner"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6296 medium HIH1100-12/HIH320","question":"In addition to keeping a horse in the stall, give 2 other functions of a stall guard?","answer":"Allows for more air circulation; allows horse to hang its head over/out of the stall "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6297 medium HIH740-5","question":"Since new weeds often fill in the spaces left after herbicides are used, it's important to do what?","answer":"Correct the conditions that created the weed problem OR over-seed pasture when necessary"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6298 medium HIH710-8","question":"Why can foals & growing horses usually be fed in groups with little problem?","answer":"Dominance hierarchies or pecking orders have not yet become strongly established."},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6299 medium HIH330-6/TH771","question":"What is the minimal width of a gate that will be used to move equipment in & out of a pasture?","answer":"12 - 16 feet 		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6300 medium HIH 365-2","question":"2 part question:  Besides dragging your pasture, name two ways you can get better manure distribution in the pasture & avoid concentration of manure in isolated spots of the pastures. ","answer":"Move feeding troughs periodically, have several watering facilities available, split pastures, rotate pastures "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6301 medium FCH199","question":"Yearly fertilizer applications should be applied to pasture at what time of year?","answer":"Approximately 1-3 months before the beginning of the growing season"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6302 medium HIH360-4","question":"What is the primary cause of runoff on horse farms?","answer":"Overgrazing"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6303 medium HIH360-4","question":"What two things will become a problem when 10% or more of the soil is exposed as a result of overgrazing? ","answer":"Weeds & erosion "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6304 medium HIH420-1, 360-1","question":"2 part question:  Name two goals of a water quality management plan.","answer":"To reduce runoff; protect ground water from contamination"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6305 medium HIH365-6","question":"On what type of land is it suitable to spread uncomposted manure?","answer":"Crop land OR other un-grazed, vegetated areas "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6306 medium HIH365-6","question":"How many times a year should pastures be mowed & chain harrowed or dragged to break up manure piles & expose parasite eggs to the elements? ","answer":"2 - 4 times per year 		(accept any number within this range) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6307 medium HIH365-3","question":"When using a 2 bin composting system, how long is it before the composted manure in the first bin is ready to use? ","answer":"2 - 4 months		 (accept any number within this range) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6308 medium TH766/HIH330-4","question":"When fencing  horse pastures, what is the most effective way to use an electric fence?","answer":"In conjunction with another fence; use the electric fence at the top of the fence to keep the horses off of the other fence"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6309 medium HIH320-7","question":"Adequate ventilation of a stable area is defined as how many air changes per hour?","answer":"4 ï¿½ 8 changes per hour		(accept any number in range)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6310 medium HIH320-7","question":"What structure is commonly found on a barn roof & functions to properly ventilate the barn?","answer":"Cupola OR ridge vents"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6311 medium HIH360-3","question":"How often should a manure pile be turned for aeration for optimum composting?","answer":"Every 10 days"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6312 medium HIH320-2-4","question":"2 part:  Name 1 advantage & 1 disadvantage to using concrete or concrete blocks when building stalls","answer":"Advantage ï¿½ easy to paint, easy to keep clean
Disadvantage ï¿½ can cause injury to horse if it hits it, must be reinforced so it wonï¿½t fall, more expensive"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6313 medium HIH320-3","question":"What type of stall floor material has many of the same disadvantages as concrete?       ","answer":"Asphalt"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6314 medium HIH320-3","question":"Why should wood floors in stalls be at least 2ï¿½ thick?			","answer":"So they donï¿½t decay easily"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6315 medium HIH320-4","question":"When using wire mesh as a stall front, why should the holes by 2 x 2 inches or smaller & why?","answer":"So horses canï¿½t catch foot in it ï¿½ A foalï¿½s foot can be as small as 2ï¿½ wide	"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6316 medium HIH320-4","question":"Why should you use treated lumber for the bottom boards of stall partitions?	","answer":"To prevent rotting"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6317 medium HIH320-5","question":"What is a good management practice to use when watering your horse with a bucket?","answer":"Empty at least once a day, cleaned every 2-3 days   (addtl info ï¿½ empty/clean every day if any illness in barn)						
6318	(medium)				HIH320-7
Q:  Keeping air temperature in barn at no more than 5 degrees above outside temperature will provide air quality horse needs, but may be inconvenient for who?
A - The handlers"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6319 medium HIH330-2","question":"Why should fence boards for corrals & small paddocks be at least 2ï¿½ thick?		","answer":"Horses have more difficulty in stopping in small area & more likely to run into fence"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6320 medium HIH330-3","question":"Give 2 reasons the bottom board on a fence should be approx.. 12ï¿½ above the ground level","answer":"For mowing, to prevent foals from rolling under it                   "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6321 medium HIH330-3","question":"If possible, pastures should have rounded corners for safety.  What is a big problem with square corners in pastures?						","answer":"One horse can trap another"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6322 medium HIH367-2","question":"What is ï¿½compost teaï¿½?					","answer":"Soak compost in water so the nutrients leach into the water"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6323 medium TH770","question":"When comparing the life expectancy of untreated wood fence posts, which of the following types of wood would last the longest?   White oak, black locust or yellow poplar","answer":"Black locust                              "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6324 medium ES195","question":"When introducing new horses into a herdï¿½ bio-securityï¿½ measures would include isolating the new horses for a minimum of how many days?","answer":"Minimum of 14 days                        "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6325 medium TH767","question":"What type of electric fence is considered to be safer because it is more visible and less injurious to the horse?","answer":"Electric tape"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"medium","number":"6326 medium HIH320-2","question":"You are an equine construction specialist & are preparing a site for a new barn.  In regards to topography, what would be your recommendation for grading the soil to facilitate proper drainage & prevent erosion?","answer":"Slope of 2 ï¿½ 6%         "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6327 hard HIH330-4","question":"Name a disadvantages of using electric tape for fencing       ","answer":"Wind can catch it & cause wear/stretching/loosening, premature breaking, "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6328 hard HIH730-3","question":"When during the year should the last application of nitrogen be applied to the pasture?","answer":"Late summer   "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6329 hard HIH330-3","question":"2 part question:  What is the best & safest wire for horse fencing & why?","answer":"Five diamond V mesh    (or rectangular or square mesh with small openings);
The close weave/small openings prevent horseï¿½s foot from getting caught"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6330 hard HIH330-1","question":"Why should the top of a corral or paddock fence be about eye level of the horseï¿½s head in a natural position?   ","answer":"To discourage fighting over the fence or so horse canï¿½t hang head over fence (might cause wire fence to sag down)       Accept either"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6331 hard HIH360-1","question":"What is used as the standard test for bacteriological safety of water?","answer":"Fecal coliform counts"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6332 hard HIH360-3","question":"Name 2 management practices that one must consider when maintaining pasture for ground cover & to provide quality nutrition for horses.","answer":"Pasture appropriate for the location; grass varieties that will thrive with the soil & climate"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6333 hard HIH320-7","question":"What is the rule of thumb ventilation guide?","answer":"One foot of ridge ventilation for each horse or stall in the barn"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6334 hard HIH365-5","question":"What happens if too much composted manure/bedding is added to the surface of a riding arena? ","answer":"It can hold excess moisture and cause horses to slip and fall (also accept excessive dust and odor) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6335 hard HIH360-3","question":"Composting stall waste for 1 to 2 months reduces the volume of waste by what percentage? ","answer":"40-70 percent     (accept any number within this range) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6336 hard TH763/HIH330-3","question":"If not properly installed, what can happen with post & rail fencing?","answer":"The rails can slip out of the posts"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6337 hard TH779","question":"Name a general type of horse is commonly housed in a tie stall?","answer":"Draft, hack, carriage, livery 		(only need to give one)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6338 hard HIH360-3","question":"Drainage from a three-sided run-in shed to an absorption pit or grass waterway should have what percent of slope?","answer":"2%   "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6339 hard HIH360-4","question":"If the soil test indicates, what would you apply to a pasture to improve forage growth & raise the pH of soil? ","answer":"Lime "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6340 hard TH771/HIH320-8","question":"What are 2 factors to be considered when buying building materials for barns?","answer":"Cost, attractiveness, fire resistance, durability, maintenance, safety"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6341 hard FCH322","question":"What type of shavings range in color from coffee brown to purplish black?","answer":"Black walnut"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6342 hard FCH193","question":"What substance helps to reduce the ammonia level in stalls?","answer":"Hydrated lime	 (lime)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6344 hard HIH740-5","question":"Fertilizing & liming are 2 important components of the management of what?","answer":"Pastures"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6345 hard FCH7","question":"2 part question:  What does TDS stand for & what does it indicate about water quality?","answer":"Total dissolved solids; high TDS indicate water that may be contaminated, be unfit for consumption, or have high salinity 	(don't need to give all) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6346 hard HIH380-3			","question":"Who is the following quote attributed to ï¿½ ï¿½Good fences make good neighborsï¿½?","answer":"Robert Frost"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6347 hard HIH 365-2","question":"2 part question:  Name two of the three factors that must be optimum for the microbes when composting manure.","answer":"Temperature, moisture, & carbon: nitrogen ratio "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6348 hard HIH310-1","question":"When planning a horse facility there are many things to consider that are part of the natural environment. What term describes the shape & the slope of the land? ","answer":"Topography"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6349 hard HIH360-1","question":"When talking about the management of horse facilities, what do the initials BMP stand for?","answer":"Best Management Practices"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6350 hard HIH360-3","question":"Why is properly composted manure & bedding safe to spread on pastures without worry about the spread of parasites, pathogenic bacteria, or weed seeds?","answer":"Composted manure will reach a temperature that will destroy these problems."},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6351 hard HIH360-4","question":"What is the purpose of a buffer strip in watercourse management? ","answer":"It filters horse waste & soil from the runoff water; slows the water down for better absorption 
(only need to give one answer)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6352 hard HIH320-1","question":"Horses can do well in almost any environment if what 2 conditions are met?     ","answer":"Humidity held to comfortable level, Good ventilation"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6353 hard HIH320-3","question":"When properly applied, what type of stall floor material will be as hard as concrete, but without concreteï¿½s disadvantages?			","answer":"Limestone dust"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6354 hard HIH320-5, 920-3","question":"Name one advantage & one disadvantage with hinged double doors on stalls		","answer":"Advantage ï¿½ top door can be left open which allows horse to stick his head out, ventilation, more light, 
Disadvantage ï¿½ Tend to sag, possibility that one door may not be closed tightly"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"hard","number":"6355 hard HIH320-6","question":"When building a barn, what is a common mistake regarding the installation of electrical outlets?","answer":"Not providing enough              (should have at least one double outlet for every 2 stalls)    "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6358 bonus HIH365-2-3","question":"Name 2 of the 3 recommended methods for manure management.","answer":"Compost (remove & compost); stockpile (remove & store in piles); land application (remove daily & spread on cropland)		"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6359 bonus HIH 365-5","question":"Name 3 specific microorganisms that may be transmitted between horses & humans through fecal material.","answer":"E. Coli; Giardia; Salmonella"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6360 bonus BEG107-2L/HIH320-2-3","question":"Horses that are kept in stalls for any length of time depend on a good stall floor for comfort & safety.  Name 3 factors you would look for in choosing flooring material for your horse.","answer":"Durable, non-slip, absorbent, easy to clean, resistant to pawing, expense/cost, amount of bedding required, availability, non-toxic		"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6361 bonus HIH350-1","question":"What are 3 factors that should be considered when selecting the appropriate bedding for your horse's stall?","answer":"Absorbency, dust content, availability, non-toxic, easily disposable, cost, unpalatable, specific use (example foaling stall)  etc"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6364 bonus TH759/HIH330","question":"Give 3 general features of a good horse fence.","answer":"Strong, high, tight, highly visible, safe"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6365 bonus HIH320-2-3","question":"Name 3 of the more commonly used materials for stall floors.","answer":"Clay, clay & sand mix, limestone dust, wood, concrete, asphalt, rubber mats"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6366 bonus HIH350-1","question":"Give 2 advantages & 2 disadvantages of using straw for bedding.","answer":"Advantages:  highly absorbent, attractive, relatively dust-free, doesn't stick to newborn foal, doesn't clog foal's airway, comfortable
Disadvantages:  horses eat it, highly combustible, dusty, cost, large volume of debris, labor intensive for cleaning, needs large amount of storage room, difficult to dispose of, availability, if wet, then not as absorbent & could mold"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6367 bonus HIH320-1-2","question":"Name 3 functions of housing for horses.","answer":"Provide for welfare of horse, provide for safety/comfort/health of handlers, make efficient use of labor, cost effective, shelter, confinement"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6368 bonus HIH330-3","question":"Give 3 examples of wire fencing.","answer":"Diamond mesh/5 diamond V mesh, woven wire, stock wire, high tensile wire, barbed wire, barbless wire, electric fence/hot wire     add:  high tensile polymer, polywire, braided electric tape"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6369 bonus HIH330/TH761-70","question":"Name 3 types of fencing for horses.","answer":"Board, post & rail, pipe/panels, PVC/vinyl, chain link (used for small pens/paddocks), cable, rubber, electric/hot wire, barbless wire,  high tensile polymer, stock wire, 5 diamond V mesh  add:  polywire, braided electric tape, polyethylene coated lumber, pipe & cable      (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6370 bonus TH770 HIH330-4","question":"What are 3 disadvantages of metal fence posts?","answer":"Not attractive, bend, rust, can injure horse"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6371 bonus TH772-73","question":"Name 3 advantages of an open front shelter.","answer":"Inexpensive, no daily stall cleaning, less labor, well ventilated, fires not likely to start, less space & bedding required, horses have room to move"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6372 bonus TH772","question":"Name 3 features you would want in an open front shelter.","answer":"Face away from prevailing winds, minimum 20' deep, opening wide enough for all horses to safely run out, roof slopes away from opening, built on high ground"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6373 bonus HIH330-1-2/TH761","question":"Name 3 advantages of a wood board fence","answer":"Attractive, rugged, safe, easily seen by horse, good for rolling land"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6374 bonus HIH330-1-2/TH761","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of a wood board fence.","answer":"Expensive, can be chewed, can splinter, break or rot"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6375 bonus HIH330-3/TH762-63","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of a post & rail fence.","answer":"More expensive than boards, posts tend to split, doesn't hold up well"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6376 bonus HIH310","question":"Name 3 natural features that would be considered as part of an ï¿½environmental analysisï¿½ before establishing a new horse facility. ","answer":"Topography/slope of land, drainage, prevailing winds, solar radiation, precipitation, vegetation, soil characteristics, available water"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6377 bonus HIH350","question":"Name 3 requirements of a good winter pasture.","answer":"3-sided shelter or natural windbreak, water source that won't freeze,  place free from mud/wind where horses can be fed"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6378 bonus TH816-19/HIH","question":"Name 3 steps of good pasture management.  ","answer":"Soil test (to see how much lime/fertilizer is needed), don't overgraze, rotate pastures, clip/mow pastures, scatter manure piles, keep pasture free from mechanical hazards/junk, keep free of poisonous plants, keep horses off pasture in extremely wet weather                     (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6379 bonus TH753","question":"When planning a horse facility, there are several items which need to be considered before construction.   Name 3","answer":"Purpose of facility, number/breed of animals to be housed, room for future expansion, regulatory requirements/zoning laws, staying within budget/costs, how barn layout facilitates the day to day activities, geographic location/environmental factors "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6380 bonus HIH330-2","question":"Board fencing is expensive, but practical for several things.  Name 3.","answer":"Stallion paddocks, sale pens, show pens, turn-out areas, arenas, creating good looking effect for front paddocks & along driveways to barns"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6381 bonus TH779/HIH320-3","question":"Name 2 advantages & 2 disadvantages to concrete floors.","answer":"Advantages:  drains quickly if properly sloped, doesn't collect urine, rat-hole proof,  easy to clean/sanitize  
Disadvantages:  cold, hard, needs more bedding, slippery, can have poor drainage, associated with leg
problems"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6382 bonus HIH350-1","question":"Name 3 types of bedding","answer":"Straw, shavings, cornstalks, sawdust, shredded newspaper,"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6383 bonus HIH710-2","question":"Name 3 specific microorganisms that can contaminate water.","answer":"Salmonella, E. coli, Leptospira; Cryptosporidium, Giardia; blue-green algae
(NOTE ï¿½ general types are bacteria, protozoa & algae, but question is asking for specific types"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6384 bonus TH284,774/HIH320","question":"Name 3 disadvantages of an automatic waterer.","answer":"Initial expense, malfunction, horses may play with it, neglect/not cleaned regularly, excessive water intake when horse is hot, no way to monitor water intake, electric shock"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6385 bonus TH762/HIH330-","question":"Name 2 types of wood that are suitable for fencing.","answer":"Oak, cypress, hemlock, yellow pine, cedar, western larch"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6386 bonus HIH1100-4","question":"Give 3 questions that a horse owner must answer when deciding to keep a horse at home.","answer":"Do you have the space?  Do zoning laws permit horses?  Do you have at least 1-2 acres suitably fenced?  Do you have some type of shelter or money to build one?  Do you have source of hay & storage room?  Can you/family member regularly feed & water horse?  Do you have time to clean daily?  Where/how will you store manure?  Where/how will you dispose of stockpiled manure?  Do you have time/experience to manage horse at home?                            (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6387 bonus HIH330-6/TH770","question":"Name 2 places where a gate should NOT be placed in a pasture.","answer":"Corner of fence line, low or wet areas, area with unsuitable terrain or footing	"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6388 bonus HIH740-5","question":"Horses are spot grazers.  Give 3 results of repeated grazing in the same area.","answer":"Carbohydrate reserves of plants depleted, plants unable to grow new leaves, plants eliminated from the pasture"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6389 bonus HIH740-1","question":"Identify 3 advantages of maintaining horses on a well-managed pasture         ","answer":"Reduces required supplemental feed (hay and/or grain)
Recycles nutrients from manure			Exercise
Reduces frequency of respiratory disease		Maintains gastrointestinal health
Aesthetically pleasing				Increases grazing capacity
Enhances water quality				Socialization
Decreases erosion"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6390 bonus DET/HIH/FCH","question":"Name 3 poisonous trees found in North America.","answer":"Black locust, black chestnut, chokecherry/wild black cherry, elderberry, horse chestnut/buckeye, oak, red maple, black walnut"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6391 bonus TH770/HIH330-6","question":"What are 3 considerations when installing a paddock gate?","answer":"Location ï¿½ not in a corner, not in a low, wet area; size ï¿½ is it just for horse traffic or machinery too; durability/material ï¿½ is it safe for horses. Should be level with top of fence,  handler should be able to unlatch/open/shut/refasten with one hand (leaves other hand free to hold lead rope/bucket)		(accept either general or specific)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6392 bonus HIH360-4","question":"Erosion of your pastures is affected by what 3 environmental or topographical factors? ","answer":"Soil type, slope of the land, amount of rain or snowfall (precipitation), vegetative cover "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6393 bonus HIH360-4","question":"What are 3 techniques for reducing runoff? ","answer":"Divert clean runoff water away from barns, paddocks, manure storage areas, & exercise areas; reduce the length of slopes on pastures with the use of terraces & water bars; plant grass in drainage ditches to slow down runoff water; plant a vegetative buffer strip at least 10 ft. wide between steep slopes and waterways "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6394 bonus HIH360-5","question":"What are 3 ways that streams and river banks can be protected from trampling, destruction of vegetation and contamination? ","answer":"Fence off streams and river banks 
Do not allow horses to graze near the edges of streams or rivers
Use trees or shrubs as natural buffers
Use electric fencing to control access to streams or rivers
Use gravity flow or pumped water to fill watering tanks instead of using rivers or streams as an accessible water source
Do not spray pesticides or herbicides near the stream
Never dump pesticides into storm drains, septic tanks or sewers
Rinse pesticide containers out and properly dispose of the containers"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6395 bonus HIH120-3","question":"Your horse is a living animal that depends upon you for its basic needs. Name 3 basic needs that have to be provided. ","answer":"Food, water, safe space, shelter, hoof care, health (shots, worming) "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6396 bonus HIH/HH/CCS/FCH180","question":"A complete set of records should be kept on every horse. Name 3 pieces of information that should be kept.","answer":"Name, Registration #, breed, identification (color/markings/sex/tattoo/brand/height/weight), training, performance record, parentage, boarding (location/cost/date, etc.), breeding, reproduction, feeding (types, amount, supplements), foaling date (any problems), foot care, growth rate, health records (vaccinations, deworming, illness, castration, injury, dental, etc.)		accept any reasonable answer"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6397 bonus HIH360-1","question":"In regards to watercourse management, what are 3 purposes of increasing the vegetative cover in drainage ditches or in buffer strips between steep slopes & waterways?","answer":"Slows down runoff water, increases absorption of runoff water, filters animal waste, filters soil out, helps prevent soil erosion"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6398 bonus HIH 350-1","question":"Give 2 advantages & 2 disadvantages of using sawdust or wood shavings for bedding.","answer":"Advantages:  less volume for disposal, easier disposal, seldom eaten by horses, less labor intensive to 
clean, less combustible, less odor
Disadvantages:  more expensive, may be dusty, may cause respiratory problems (if dusty), be cautious of
black walnut shavings, may require additional storage space, needs to be stored indoors or in a
protected area (when itï¿½s wet itï¿½s non-absorbent & it takes a long time to dry)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6399 bonus HIH440-5","question":"Name 3 common conditions or management practices that can result in injury to the horse.","answer":"Barns/stalls/fences/gates either too small or not designed properly for horses or in poor repair; improper building materials (poor quality wood, barb wire, hog wire, etc.); uncapped steel posts; sharp edges on waterers or feeders; lack of or improper bedding; protruding nails, bolts, etc.; misc. equipment or junk in pasture; overcrowding; allowing aggressive horses in group situations; lack of feeder space in group situations; using wire to hang buckets/feeders; improper tying	 (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6400 bonus HIH320-5","question":"Name the 3 general types  of stall doors                   ","answer":"Half wood & half bars/mesh, full wood, full mesh"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6401 bonus HIH320-8","question":"Wood is the best all-around building material for barns.  Name 3 advantages of using wood","answer":"Strong, attractive, good insulator, easier to install ventilation system		"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6402 bonus HIH320-8","question":"If you canï¿½t remove barb wire from pasture fencing, name 3 ways to help make it safer for horses   ","answer":"Sight board on top, move bottom wires up at least 12ï¿½ from ground to reduce risk of lower leg injury, electric wire 4-6 inches inside top of fence to keep horses off, remove extremely bossy horses from pasture, keep same horses in each group (no new/strange ones), asap replace all barbed wire   "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6403 bonus HIH367-2","question":"Name 3 ways you can use compost at home				","answer":"Flower/vegetable gardens, new planting areas, surface mulch, lawn topdressing, potting mix, compost ï¿½teaï¿½ spreading on pastures"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6404 bonus HIH350-1","question":"Name 3 things that bedding  does					","answer":"Bedding encourages horse to lie down/rest, cushions horseï¿½s feet/legs, soaks up urine/moisture"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6405 bonus HIH350-1","question":"Name 3 advantages to using recycled newsprint for bedding		","answer":"Pollen free & lest dust than straw/shavings   Very absorbent, softer & more comfortable than either shavings or straw"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6406 bonus HIH380-2","question":"Give 3 key components of a Manure Management Plan (MMP)		","answer":"Considerations of stocking, density of horses, amount of manure produced, knowledge of levels of nutrients in manure, appropriate manure storage & manure management (land application, hauling off site, etc), soil testing & records of activities"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6408 bonus HIH610-3","question":"Your job at a breeding farm is management of the pregnant broodmares.  Identify three management practices you follow in regards to herd management to prevent an abortion storm.            ","answer":"Isolate all new arrivals for at least 21 days  Keep pregnant mares separated from weanlings and other horses
Do not mix maiden mares with older mares   Divide pregnant mares into small groups by the stage of pregnancy
Keep mares in group until all in group have foaled  Maintain all pregnant mares on vaccination program
If pregnant mares are moved off the farm and later return ï¿½ do not reintroduce them into the original group
If a foster mare is introduced do not place her in a group with other mares"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6409 bonus ES194","question":"In regards to biosecurity, identify 3 ways to diminish the possibility of transferring infective agents with your boots","answer":"Disinfect boots using a spray disinfectant
Disposable boots or boot covers
Disinfect boots with a boot dip
Change boots (between farms, between clean & dirty areas, etc)"},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6410 bonus HIH330-3","question":"Name 3 things that should be considered when installing a wire fence","answer":"Sight board, board in middle (keeps horses from leaning on/stretching fence), wire attached on inside of post, should be 10 gauge or heavier      (accept other reasonable answers)    "},
{"category":"STABLE & PASTURE MANAGEMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6411 bonus HIH367-1","question":"Name 3 things to consider when determining the quality of compost","answer":"pH, nutrient content, organic matter content, moisture content, particle size              "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6412 easy HH33","question":"Name one thing a poor fitting saddle causes.","answer":"Sores, saddle rolling during mounting/dismounting, saddle slipping/sliding during use, horse bucking, horse head tossing, cinchiness"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6413 easy HH27","question":"What are hobbles?","answer":"Straps fastened to the front legs of a horse to prevent him from straying	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6414 easy HIH1100-12","question":"Which type martingale has rings through which the reins pass?","answer":"Running"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6415 easy HIH1100-10	","question":"The upper end of a standing martingale connects to what part of the bridle?","answer":"Cavesson or noseband"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6416 easy HH34","question":"Why should you clean your tack after use?","answer":"To remove dirt or sweat"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6417 easy HH34","question":"What practice can add to the use & life of any leather article?","answer":"Regular cleaning"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6418 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What bit is capable of acting as two bits in one mouthpiece?   With two sets of reins, you have both snaffle & curb action?","answer":"Pelham	 (do not accept Kimberwicke which only uses one set of reins)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6419 easy HH34","question":"What is the main problem with stiff or dried out leather tack?	","answer":"It's brittle & will crack easily"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6420 easy HH30","question":"What kind of bit is a Tom Thumb?","answer":"Jointed curb"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6421 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Define port.","answer":"The part of the bit mouthpiece that curves up over the tongue OR the bump in the middle of the mouthpiece of a curb bit		"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6422 easy HH29","question":"What is a snaffle key bit?","answer":"Snaffle bit with small metal pieces dangling from the center     (additional info -- used in training colts)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6423 easy HH30","question":"How should a horse respond to a curb bit?","answer":"By flexing at the poll"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6424 easy HH31","question":"How can you remove rust spots from a bit?","answer":"Use steel wool"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6425 easy HIH1100-5","question":"What was the original purpose of the horn on a Western saddle?","answer":"To hold roped calves/cows (dally)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6426 easy HH34","question":"Which type saddle does not necessarily require a saddle pad?","answer":"English"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6427 easy H4-35/FCH395","question":"A strap or rope 25-30 feet long that's used to circle or work a horse is called what?","answer":"Longe line	  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6428 easy HH34","question":"What is the purpose of splint boots?","answer":"To protect or support the splint &/or cannon bones"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6429 easy HH34","question":"What type boots protect the back of the rear fetlocks from abrasions during sliding movements?","answer":"Skid boots or sliding boots"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6430 easy HIH1125-3","question":"Which piece of tack is used to keep the saddle from slipping forward when going downhill?","answer":"Breeching  OR crupper"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6431 easy HIH1125-3","question":"Which piece of tack is used to keep the saddle from sliding backward when going uphill?","answer":"Breast collar  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6432 easy HIH1100-1","question":"Give 2 general purposes of whips & crops.","answer":"Giving cues, punishment, appointments"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6433 easy HIH1100-4","question":"Fender, D-ring, skirt & front jockey are all parts of what?","answer":"Western saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6434 easy HIH1100-2,4","question":"The rider sits in the deepest part of the saddle between what 2 parts?","answer":"Pommel & cantle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6435 easy HIH1125-3,1100","question":"What type of saddle would most likely be used with a double-rigged cinch?","answer":"Pack saddle (sawbuck or cross buck) OR roping saddle (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6436 easy HIH1100-3","question":"What part of the Western saddle should you consider first when fitting your horse?","answer":"Tree"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6437 easy HH29","question":"What is the term for a girth-like band passed over the horse's back & around the belly?  Itï¿½s used along with a bridle in ground training horses.","answer":"Surcingle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6439 easy HIH1100-3","question":"Where on a horse should the girth of an English saddle be?","answer":"Heartgirth area OR belly area directly behind the front legs"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6440 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What part of a bit enables it to be classified as a leverage bit?","answer":"Shanks"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6441 easy HIH1100-8","question":"Describe a non-leverage bit.","answer":"Bit without shanks   		(example:  a snaffle bit)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6442 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What is the name for the flexible quirt that's attached to California-style reins?","answer":"Romal"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6443 easy HIH1100-5","question":"A TRUE Navajo saddle blanket is made from what material?","answer":"Wool"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6444 easy HH34","question":"What are 2 meanings of the term "jockey"?","answer":"Person who rides racehorses;  small flaps on each side of the saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6445 easy HH54","question":"For safety, what MUST a rider wear while jumping?","answer":"Helmet	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6446 easy HH29","question":"What is a mecate?","answer":"Lead rope on a hackamore"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6447 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Name 2 types of hackamores.","answer":"Bosal, mechanical, side pull"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6448 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What 2 bits does the double bridle use?","answer":"Snaffle/Bridoon & curb/Weymouth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6449 easy HIH1100-3","question":"Where are most Western saddles produced?","answer":"United States"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6450 easy HIH1100-10","question":"If a bit is too wide & slides back & forth, what results?","answer":"Lack of control OR confusing rein signals OR can hurt horseï¿½s mouth		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6451 easy HIH1100-4","question":"The primary goal of the pleasure saddle is what?","answer":"Comfort"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6452 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Which curb bit is considered to be the most severe Western curb bit?","answer":"Spade"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6453 easy BEG108","question":"What is the name of the strap commonly seen on a Western bridle but not on a simple English bridle?","answer":"Curb strap or curb chain"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6454 easy HIH1100-5","question":"What type saddle would you use with a Navajo blanket?","answer":"Western or stock saddle				"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6455 easy HH27/DET141","question":"What is the name for the eye formed on the end of the lariat through which the rope is passed to form a loop?","answer":"Honda	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6456 easy HIH1100-10","question":"2 part question:  What is the part of the bit mouthpiece that curves up over the tongue & what is its purpose?","answer":"Port; purpose ï¿½ relieves tongue pressure OR  applies pressure to roof of mouth	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6457 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What part of the bridle keeps the crownpiece from sliding down the horse's neck?","answer":"Browband	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6458 easy HIH1100-8/BEG108-3L","question":"Besides the mouth, name two other places where a ï¿½leverageï¿½ bit applies pressure.","answer":"Poll; under chin/curb groove"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6459 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the basic purpose of a martingale?","answer":"To keep a horse's head in a desired position"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6460 easy HIH1100-16","question":"What type of blanket assists your horse in drying off after a workout?","answer":"Cooler or mesh sheet"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6461 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What are the 3 main parts of the bridle?","answer":"Reins, bit, headstall"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6462 easy HH27","question":"Why is a breakaway stirrup important to a beginning rider?","answer":"Allows for quick/easy release if rider falls"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6463 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the basic principle of a hackamore?","answer":"Horse learns to respond to pressure on his nose & under chin"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6464 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the most common material used in making bits?","answer":"Stainless steel"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6465 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Which material, when used in a bit, increases salivation?","answer":"Copper   (also accept sweet iron)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6466 easy HIH1100-1","question":"Which English saddle has a padded knee roll to provide more security when riding?","answer":"All purpose (also accept forward seat, hunt seat, jumping, or dressage saddle) "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6467 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the English term for a tie-down?","answer":"Standing martingale"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6468 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Which bit is more severe ï¿½ an egg-butt with a mouthpiece as thick as your pinkie or a D-ring with a mouthpiece as thick as your thumb?","answer":"Eggbutt with the thinner mouthpiece"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6469 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What is the purpose of a browband?","answer":"To keep the bridle from sliding down the horse's neck"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6470 easy HIH1100-8","question":"Describe roping reins.","answer":"Reins that are one continuous strap	      (additional info -- so the rider doesnï¿½t drop the reins while roping)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6471 easy HIH1100-5","question":"What is the name for a colorful woven blanket made of wool that's used with a Western saddle?","answer":"Navajo"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6472 easy HIH1100-16","question":"What type of sheet would be used to keep flies away from your horse?","answer":"Mesh"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6473 easy HIH1100-5","question":"What is the purpose of a back cinch on a roping saddle?","answer":"To keep the saddle from flipping up when roping/dallying "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6474 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What type of reins is a romal attached to?","answer":"California or closed"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6475 easy HH34","question":"Name 2 products commonly used to keep leather soft & pliable.","answer":"Leather oil such as neats foot oil, saddle soap, leather conditioner such as Lexol"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6476 easy H5-35","question":"What is the name for the restraining device that's put around a horse's upper lip to make him stand still?","answer":"Twitch"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6477 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What common piece of tack does the term "jaquima" refer to?","answer":"Bosal or hackamore           "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6478 easy HIH1100-2,4","question":"What is the term for the wide piece of leather on an English saddle that's similar to the fender on a Western saddle?","answer":"Flap"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6479 easy HH29","question":"What is Spanish for lasso?","answer":"Reata"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6480 easy HIH1100-8-10","question":"What is a curb chain?","answer":"Chain strap attached to a curb bit	 (additional info -- applies pressure to underside of horse's jaw)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6481 easy HH32","question":"A forward seat saddle places the rider's weight over what part of the horse?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6482 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What is the function of a cavesson?","answer":"To keep the horse's mouth closed"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6483 easy HIH1100-1","question":"Name at least 3 items you'll see at a tack shop.","answer":"Saddle, bridle, blanket, halter, brushes, saddle blanket/pad, lead rope, medicines, hoofpick, apparel
(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6484 easy HIH1100-16","question":"Referring to outerwear for your horse, what is the purpose of a horse blanket?","answer":"To keep the horse warm in cold weather   (also - keeps him from getting dirty)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6485 easy HH29","question":"What are rowels?","answer":"Toothed wheels on spurs"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6486 easy HIH1100-4","question":"What do you call the front part of the Western saddle that the horn sits on?","answer":"Pommel       (also accept swells or fork)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6487 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the Western version of a standing martingale?","answer":"Tiedown"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6488 easy HH29","question":"What is the name for the cover on a stirrup?","answer":"Tapadera"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6489 easy HIH1100-1","question":"What does it mean to tack up?","answer":"Put on saddle & bridle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6490 easy HH29/DET287","question":"What is a war bridle?","answer":"An emergency bridle made of rope OR a ï¿½come alongï¿½ which is made of stiff rope & is used for leading unruly horses by exerting pressure on the poll"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6491 easy HH29","question":"Referring to saddles, what is a tree?","answer":"Frame of the saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6492 easy H4-35/FCH395","question":"How long should a longe line be?","answer":"About 30 feet	 (accept answers between 25-30 feet)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6493 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Define shank.","answer":"The part of the bit from the mouthpiece down"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6494 easy HH29","question":"What are the toothed wheels on spurs called?","answer":"Rowels		"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6495 easy H4-35/H1-35/HH29","question":"What is a ropeï¿½often made of rawhideï¿½with a running noose that's used for catching cattle?","answer":"Lariat OR lasso"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6496 easy HIH1100-10","question":"A strap running from the girth between the front legs to the bridle is called what?","answer":"Martingale OR tiedown"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6497 easy HIH1100-4","question":"What are the wide pieces of leather along the stirrup leather on a Western saddle called?","answer":"Fenders"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6498 easy HIH1100-4","question":"Where is the cantle of the saddle located?","answer":"Back of the saddle, just behind the seat"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6499 easy HIH1100-3","question":"What do you call the wide cord girth used on Western saddles?","answer":"Cinch"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6500 easy HH20/DET54","question":"What are chaps?","answer":"Seatless overalls 
(additional info -- usually made of leather used to protect the legs, keep legs warm, & used for show)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6501 easy H4-25","question":"What piece of equipment ï¿½other than the longe line & halter ï¿½ might you need when teaching a foal to lunge?","answer":"Whip"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6502 easy HIH1100-10/HH31","question":"What kind of bridle is most often used in saddle seat classes?","answer":"Weymouth OR double bridle    (also accept full bridle)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6503 easy HH34","question":"Under what condition should leather & rope halters be stored?","answer":"Dry place"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6504 easy HIH1100-10/DET35","question":"What is a bosal?","answer":"Noseband on a hackamore	 (additional info -- often made of rawhide) "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6505 easy HH27","question":"A strap fastening the front legs of a horse together so that he can't stray is called what?","answer":"Hobbles"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6506 easy HH31","question":"On the Western saddle, what are the D rings?","answer":"Rings that hold the cinch straps	 (additional info -- billet on off side & latigo on near side)  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6507 easy HIH1100-4/H4-34","question":"What is the fork of a saddle?","answer":"Fork (or swells or pommel) is the front, raised part of a Western saddle that supports the saddle horn OR 
part of the swells of a Western saddle that makes up the gullet"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6508 easy HIH1100-3","question":"A saddle should have a spread in its tree to fit comfortably on what part of your horse?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6509 easy HIH1100-3","question":"What is a cinch?","answer":"Girth used on a Western saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6510 easy HIH1100-3","question":"What is the term for the raised back of the saddle behind the seat?","answer":"Cantle					"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6511 easy HIH1100-4","question":"Referring to saddles, what are fenders?","answer":"Wide pieces of leather along the stirrup leathers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6512 easy HH29","question":"What is a tapadera?","answer":"Stirrup cover	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6513 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What kind of bridle uses 2 bits?","answer":"Weymouth OR double bridle (also accept full bridle)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6514 easy HIH1100-9","question":"What are cheekpieces?","answer":"Side pieces of the bridle	 (or sidepieces of  bit)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6515 easy HIH1100-9","question":"What is the browband?","answer":"Part of the bridle that goes across the head above the eyes	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6516 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What do you call the leather bridle straps without the bit & reins?","answer":"Headstall"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6517 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What is the portion of the bit from the mouthpiece down?","answer":"Shank"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6518 easy HH29/DET287","question":"What is an emergency bridle made of rope called?","answer":"War bridle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6519 easy HIH1100-8","question":"When the bridle is correctly adjusted, the bit will rest on what part of the horse's mouth?","answer":"Bars   (also accept interdental space)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6520 easy HH34","question":"Where is leather tack most likely to fail?","answer":"Around buckles, bends & attachments"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6521 easy HH34","question":"What one thing should never be done to leather, no matter how wet it gets?","answer":"Never place it near heat"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6522 easy HIH1100-8","question":"In general, how do bits operate?","answer":"By applying pressure to certain parts of the mouth or head"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6523 easy HIH1100-9","question":"What do you call the strap that goes around the horse's forehead?","answer":"Browband"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6524 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What is the most important part of the bridle?","answer":"The bit"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6525 easy HIH1100-8","question":"How can you tell if the bit's adjusted correctly?","answer":"There should be 1-2 wrinkles on each side at lip corners"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6526 easy HIH1100-8","question":"Name 2 areas to which a non-leverage bit (like a snaffle) applies pressure.","answer":"Corners of mouth, tongue, bars		"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6527 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What part of the bridle keeps the horse from rubbing it off?","answer":"Throatlatch"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6528 easy HIH1100-1","question":"Of the hunt seat saddle types, which one is most popular for trail riding?","answer":"All purpose"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6529 easy HIH1100-9","question":"What is the piece of the bridle behind the horse's ears called?","answer":"Crownpiece"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6530 easy HIH1100-2","question":"What are billets?","answer":"Straps used to tighten the girth on an English saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6531 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is another name for an English double bridle?","answer":"Weymouth    (also accept full bridle)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6532 easy HIH1100-2","question":"Where is the pommel on an English saddle?","answer":"Slightly raised part on the front of the saddle (in front of the seat)     (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6533 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the braided rawhide or rope noseband on a hackamore called?","answer":"Bosal"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6534 easy HH20","question":"What is the purpose of chaps? ","answer":"Protection from cuts, protection from cold, showing		 (only need to give one) "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6535 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What do you call the noseband on an English bridle?","answer":"Cavesson"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6536 easy HIH1100-16","question":"What advantage do web, laced, or rubber reins have over plain reins?","answer":"More secure grip, not slippery when wet	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6537 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What is the most commonly used type of Western reins?","answer":"Split"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6538 easy HIH1100-13","question":"Where do most saddle fitting problems occur?","answer":"Withers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6539 easy HIH1100-7,9","question":"Name the part of the bridle that's found on an English bridle, but not on most Western ones.","answer":"Noseband or cavesson	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6540 easy HIH1100-2","question":"How many billets are usually found on an English saddle?","answer":"Three		"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6541 easy HIH1100-8","question":"In addition to ropers, what other type of rider would you see using roping reins?","answer":"Gymkhana/games OR barrel racers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6542 easy HIH1100-1","question":"What is the general term for all of the leather equipment used to ride and/or drive a horse?","answer":"Tack"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6543 easy HIH1100-8","question":"On a Western bridle, on what side of the horse does the throatlatch buckle?","answer":"Left"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6544 easy HIH1100-8","question":"The corner of the horse's mouth should have how many wrinkles with a properly fitted egg-butt snaffle bit?","answer":"One or two	(accept either)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6545 easy HIH1100-3","question":"What is the difference between an Arabian tree & a Quarter Horse tree?","answer":"Arabian tree is wider "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6546 easy HH27","question":"A saddle pad cut to fit the shape of the saddle sometimes has a large colorful roll around the edges.  This roll is called what?","answer":"Corona"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6547 easy HIH1100-3","question":"What does a safety stirrup do?","answer":"In the event of a fall, a heavy rubber band releases which lets the rider's foot come free of the stirrup"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6548 easy HIH1100-8","question":"Describe a slip ear headstall.","answer":"Small loop is added to the crownpiece to go around the ear"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6549 easy HH32","question":"Which type of saddle was originally developed for ranch work?","answer":"Western or stock"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6550 easy HIH1100-1","question":"What is another name for a saddle seat saddle?","answer":"Cut back, Park, or Lane Fox		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6551 easy HIH1100-1","question":"What is another name for a hunt seat saddle?","answer":"Forward seat, close contact, or jumping	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6552 easy HIH1100-3","question":"By placing 2 fingers between your horse's withers & the fork of the saddle, you are checking for what?","answer":"Proper fit"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6553 easy HH27","question":"A Western saddle with the cinch hung from the center is called what?","answer":"Center-fire"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6554 easy HH29/DET259","question":"What is a surcingle?","answer":"Broad strap around the horse's girth      (additional info - may be used with bridle for ground training)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6555 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Which martingale needs "stops" added to each rein to prevent the rings from interfering with the bit?","answer":"Running"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6556 easy HH27","question":"What is a center-fire?","answer":"Western saddle with cinch hung from the center	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6557 easy HIH1100-4","question":"Referring to a saddle, what is a jockey?","answer":"Small flaps on the side of the saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6558 easy HH29","question":"What is a chin chain made of flat, large links called?","answer":"Polo chain"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6559 easy HH29","question":"What is the lead rope on a hackamore called?","answer":"Mecate (meh-COT-ay)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6560 easy DET165","question":"What is the Spanish term for a cinch strap?                      ","answer":"Latigo"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6561 easy DET239","question":"2 part question:  What type of saddle would have saddle strings & what are they used for?","answer":"Western/stock; used for tying things to the saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6562 easy DET86","question":"What is the purpose of a dropped noseband?","answer":"Prevents a horse from opening its mouth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6563 easy DET32/FCH382","question":"What is the purpose of blinkers on a bridle?","answer":"To keep the horse looking forward OR to prevent the horse from looking to the side "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6564 easy HIH1100-6","question":"What is the main function of a headstall?","answer":"To hold the bit in place"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6565 easy HIH1100-8","question":"Why are roping reins one continuous strap?","answer":"To prevent losing or dropping the reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6566 easy HIH1100-2","question":"What material are most English saddles made of?","answer":"Leather"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6567 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Why is copper sometimes used in bit mouthpieces?","answer":"Increases salivation or makes mouth more responsive"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6568 easy HIH1100-4","question":"Which part of the Western saddle is used for tying equipment to the saddle?","answer":"Lace strings or saddle strings"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6569 easy HIH1100-14","question":"For what purpose is glycerin soap used?","answer":"Cleaning tack"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6570 easy HH29/DET188","question":"What is Neatsfoot oil?","answer":"Oil used for conditioning, softening or preserving leather   (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6571 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the Spanish word for hackamore?","answer":"Jaquima   (HA-kee-ma)	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6572 easy HIH1100-4","question":"What are the small flaps on the side of the saddle called?","answer":"Jockey or jockey skirt          "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6573 easy HH29","question":"What is a reata?","answer":"Spanish word for lasso (also accept rope)      "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6574 easy HIH1100-10","question":"Name the 2 most common types of martingales. ","answer":"Running & standing "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6575 easy HH28","question":"What influences the severity of a bosal?","answer":"The stiffness"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6576 easy HH27","question":"What do you call a combination of bridle, harness pad, & crupper?","answer":"Bitting rig"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6577 easy HH28","question":"What do you call the part of the reins passing between thumb & fingers & out the top of the hand?","answer":"Bight"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6578 easy H4-7,17","question":"What is the main purpose of a saddle?","answer":"To distribute the rider's weight over the horse's back   (also gives rider a sense of security)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6579 easy HH28","question":"What is the special knot on a hackamore called that exerts pressure at the rear of the jaw?","answer":"Heel knot         (DET106 defines a ï¿½fiadorï¿½ as the cord throatlatch on a hackamore ï¿½ NOT the knot)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6580 easy HH28","question":"Name one of the pressure points on a mechanical hackamore.","answer":"Underside of horse's jaw, over the bridge of the nose, poll"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6581 easy -				HH34","question":"In order to take proper care of leather, you should always do what 2 things?","answer":"Keep it dry, keep it clean, keep it oiled/conditioned"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6582 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What is a bridoon?","answer":"Snaffle bit used on a double bridle OR another name for snaffle bit"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6583 easy HIH1100-8","question":"What do you call the type of Western rein that's one continuous strap?  This type helps prevent dropping or losing a rein","answer":"Roping reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6584 easy HIH1100-3","question":"How can a saddle pinch your horse?","answer":"Riding too high on sides of withers	 (not fitting properly)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6585 easy HIH1125-3","question":"What is the strap that goes around the base of the animal's tail & attaches to the saddle?  It's used to keep the saddle centered & is best suited for use on a stock saddle","answer":"Crupper"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6586 easy HIH1100-3","question":"Which English saddle uses a longer stirrup?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6587 easy HIH1100-2","question":"What is a sweat flap?","answer":"Small flap of an English saddle under the flap      (the flap between the billets & the horse)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6588 easy HIH1100","question":"What is the first step in selecting a saddle?","answer":"Deciding which style of riding you prefer"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6589 easy HIH1100-8	","question":"The severity of a snaffle bit comes from what?","answer":"Thickness of the mouthpiece		 (additional info -- thinner is more severe)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6590 easy HIH1100-8","question":"When using the terms D-ring, round, or full-cheek, you are referring to what?","answer":"Snaffle bits"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6591 easy HIH1100-8","question":"A rider's pull on the reins of a snaffle causes what kind of pressure?","answer":"Direct"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6592 easy HH31","question":"What is the basic foundation of all stock saddles?","answer":"Tree"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6593 easy HIH1100-8","question":"When shanks are added to a bit, what is created?","answer":"Leverage"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6594 easy HIH1100-10","question":"What is the name for the small ring snaffle that, combined with a curb bit, makes up a Weymouth or double bridle?","answer":"Bridoon"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6595 easy DET84/HH/HIH","question":"What is a double-rigged saddle?","answer":"Saddle with 2 cinches"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6596 easy HIH1100-10","question":"How tight should the halter chinstrap be?","answer":"You should be able to put a couple of fingers between the halter & muzzle OR with enough room to prevent binding the face & tight enough to prevent a foot from being caught"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6597 easy HH23","question":"What should you do if you find a strap that's thin from wear or torn?","answer":"Replace it ASAP"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6598 easy HIH1100-3","question":"Give 2 advantages of a synthetic saddle.","answer":"Less expensive, lightweight, easy to take care of"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6599 easy HIH1100-16","question":"In the winter, what type of blanket should be used to keep your horse's hair from growing too long?","answer":"Heavy one"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6600 easy HH25","question":"What part of the saddle must be fitted to the rider?","answer":"The seat    (also accept stirrups)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6601 easy HH25","question":"On an English saddle, the billets attach what to the saddle?","answer":"Girth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6602 easy HH26","question":"What is the most common bit used for Thoroughbred race horses?","answer":"Snaffle					"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6603 easy HH34","question":"What part of the anatomy do bell boots protect?","answer":"Back of the front coronary band OR coronet band & hoof  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"easy","number":"6605 easy HH34","question":"What is another name for bell boots?","answer":"Overreach boots	"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6606 medium HIH1100-3","question":"Which English saddle is designed to give the rider optimum leg contact with the horse?","answer":"Dressage"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6607 medium HH33","question":"How is the length of a stock saddle measured?","answer":"From base of horn to top of cantle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6608 medium HIH1100-8","question":"What is another name given to reins connected to each other with a romal?","answer":"California reins or closed reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6609 medium HH26","question":"Name 2 types of bits that might be used when driving horses.","answer":"Half-cheek snaffle, Liverpool bit, bar bit, plain snaffle (O ring, D ring, egg-butt, etc.)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6610 medium HIH1100-10","question":"Which bit is similar to a snaffle -except it has slots on top of the rings for attaching the headstall & hooks for attaching the curb chain?","answer":"Kimberwicke"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6611 medium DET29","question":"What do you call the deviceï¿½normally made of metal or rubber ï¿½that attaches to the headstall & is used to regulate the position of the horse's head & to help control the pace & direction of the horse?","answer":"Bit"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6612 medium HIH1100-10","question":"What does the term "mullen mouth" mean?","answer":"Bit mouthpiece that has a slight bow or curve"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6613 medium HH29","question":"What does the term "slick" mean when referring to saddles?","answer":"Describes the shape of the fork on a Western saddle (forks or swells that are narrow at the top & are wide at the bottom)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6614 medium HH32","question":"What is the effect of stirrups that are set too far back?","answer":"Rider is thrown into the pommel or fork"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6615 medium HH33","question":"Where do you measure the width of the withers?","answer":"Two inches below the top of withers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6616 medium HH33","question":"Where do you measure the width of a saddle tree?","answer":"Across the bottom of the gullet"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6617 medium DET p. 287","question":"What type of bridle is often made of stiff lariat rope & is used in leading unruly horses by exerting pressure on the poll.  It is sometimes called a ï¿½come-alongï¿½. ","answer":"War bridle  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6618 medium DET76,256","question":"Explain the difference between a standing & a running martingale.","answer":"Standing martingale attaches to the back of the noseband; running martingale has a Y shaped strap with rings on the ends that reins pass through"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6619 medium HIH1100-10","question":"Why is a snaffle called a direct-action bit?  ","answer":"Reins attach directly to rings on the mouthpiece which causes a direct pulling action"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6620 medium HIH1100-4","question":"What basic part of the bridle serves as a secondary means of communication as well as allowing you to manipulate the bit?","answer":"Reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6621 medium FCH382/DET32","question":"What are blinders or blinkers?","answer":"Solid pieces attached to the headstall alongside each eye so the horse can't see to the side without turning its head		 (additional info -- keeps horse looking forward)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6622 medium HIH1100-14","question":"How does leather conditioner work?","answer":"Puts back vital oils"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6623 medium HIH1100-3","question":"2 part question:  You are looking to purchase an English saddle for your 6' father who wants to trail ride.  There is a 14" all-purpose saddle advertised in the local paper.  Will this saddle be adequate for your father?  Explain your answer.","answer":"No; the all-purpose type will work BUT the saddle is too small ï¿½ an adult that size would need a 16 - 18 inch saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6624 medium HIH1100-3","question":"From what 2 points do you measure to determine the size of an English saddle?","answer":"From the saddle nail to the mid-point of the cantle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6625 medium HIH1100-10","question":"What is the "never rust" material used in making bits?","answer":"Stainless steel or solid nickel"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6626 medium BEG108","question":"In reference to an English saddle, what is the name for the channel that runs down the center of the underside of the saddle?","answer":"Gullet"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6627 medium HIH1100-6","question":"Name a type of martingale that attaches to the reins.","answer":"Running, Irish, or German		 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6628 medium DET272","question":"In driving, what are the parts of the harness that run from the collar to the singletree?","answer":"Traces"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6629 medium HIH1100-10","question":"Which mouthpiece material is very lightweight, brittle, & may cause the horse's mouth to be dry?","answer":"Aluminum"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6630 medium HIH1100-1","question":"2 part question:  Where would you find a latigo & what is its purpose?","answer":"On a Western saddle; it's the strap that's used to tie the cinch knot"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6631 medium HIH1100-9","question":"Referring to an English saddle, what is the collective term for stirrup leathers, stirrup irons & girth?","answer":"Fittings"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6632 medium HIH1100-3","question":"In reference to tack, define the word "fittings".","answer":"Stirrup leathers, stirrup irons, & girth for English saddles"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6633 medium HIH1100-12","question":"What piece of equipment needs to be used with a running martingale to prevent the martingale from interfering with the bit?","answer":"Rein stops"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6634 medium HIH1100-6","question":"What type of reins are covered with a pebbled surface on the handgrip portions & are used in racing to provide a secure grip?","answer":"Rubber reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6635 medium TH659","question":"Why is it a good idea to switch stirrup leathers on an English saddle from side to side on a regular basis?","answer":"Mounting causes leather to stretch making them uneven"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6636 medium DET38","question":"What part of the harness helps the horse hold back the vehicle when there is no brake?","answer":"Breeching   (also accept pole strap, thimbles, shaft cups)			"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6637 medium DET72","question":"Referring to bits, what is a cricket?","answer":"The attachment on a bit's port that spins when the horse moves its tongue"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6638 medium HIH1100-8","question":"What is the difference between a slip ear & a split ear bridle?","answer":"Slip ear ï¿½ piece added to the crownpiece that can be slid to either side allowing ear to pass through; 
Slit earï¿½crownpiece is split allowing ear to pass through"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6639 medium DET25","question":"In reference to tack & equipment, what is a bat?","answer":"Short, flat riding whip"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6640 medium HIH1100-3","question":"What measurement is necessary to have a properly fitted girth?","answer":"Heartgirth   (from girth buckle to girth buckle)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6641 medium DET72","question":"What is the name of the attachment on the port of a curb bit that will spin in the horse's mouth as it moves its tongue?","answer":"Cricket or roller"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6642 medium HIH1100-3","question":"What kind of saddle would you select for a thick-withered English horse?","answer":"English saddle with wide tree"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6643 medium DET94","question":"What is the name of the specific part of the headstall that holds the bit up in the horse's mouth?","answer":"Cheek piece "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6644 medium DET29","question":"What is the name for the rubber or leather ring that lies between the horse's cheek & the bit that prevents rubbing or pinching of the skin?","answer":"Bit guard"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6645 medium H4-17","question":"A felt saddle with a wood frame was created around 200 BC by whom?","answer":"Asian horsemen"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6646 medium DET26","question":"What is the name of the protective boots that fit over the coronet band & bulbs of the heel?","answer":"Bell boots or overreach boots"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6647 medium DET55","question":"What is the specific name of the type of western chaps that extend slightly beyond the knee, but do not cover the riderï¿½s shins?","answer":"Chinks   (do not accept half chaps which cover the ankle & shin)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6648 medium HIH1100-5","question":"What kind of saddle would you select for a Western horse with low, thick withers?","answer":"Western saddle with Quarter Horse or Arabian tree OR Western saddle with wide tree"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6649 medium HIH1125-1","question":"The McClellan saddle is single-rigged.  What does this mean?","answer":"Only has one cinch/girth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6650 medium HIH1100-6","question":"Give 2 uses of a mesh sheet.","answer":"Aids in cooling out, keeps flies away"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6651 medium DET207/HIH1100-10","question":"What bit is being described?  This bit uses 2 sets of reins.  It's a one piece bit that functions like both a snaffle & a curb combined in one mouthpiece.  One set of reins is attached to the rings & works like a snaffle & one set attaches to the shanks to provide leveraged action","answer":"Pelham"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6652 medium DET48,49","question":"In general, what is the main design difference between a cart & a carriage?","answer":"Cart has 2 wheels & carriage has 4 wheels"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6653 medium DET270","question":"What bit is being described?  This bit is sometimes called a ï¿½cowboy snaffleï¿½.  It's a curb bit with short, straight, swivel shanks & a broken mouthpiece","answer":"Tom Thumb"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6654 medium HIH1100-16","question":"The lighter weight blanket is specifically used for what 2 purposes?","answer":"Shipping, turnout"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6655 medium HIH1100-11","question":"What is the term for the type of solid bit mouthpiece that has a slight bow in the middle instead of a port?","answer":"Mullen mouth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6656 medium HIH1100-5","question":"What type of saddle would you select for a horse used for roping?","answer":"Full double-rigged roping saddle  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6657 medium DET265","question":"Terrets are rings on the harness of driving horses.  What passes through these rings?","answer":"Reins or lines"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6658 medium HIH1100-8","question":"2 part question:   The width of a snaffle bit is very important.  Explain what can happen from a) a bit that's too narrow & b) bit that's too wide  ","answer":"Too narrow ï¿½ pinching;    too wide - loss of control"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6659 medium HH23/HIH","question":"Give two definitions of the term "girth".","answer":"Measure of the circumference of the horse's body back of the withers;
Leather, canvas or corded piece that goes around the body of a horse to hold the saddle on"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6660 medium BEG108-3L","question":"What type of martingale allows the rider to maintain contact with the bit at all times?","answer":"Running martingale"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6661 medium HIH1100-6","question":"The term cavesson means 2 different pieces of equipment.  What are they?","answer":"Noseband on an English bridle; stiff headstall used for longe line training"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6662 medium HH34","question":"Why is a stable a poor place to store leather?","answer":"Temperature, dampness, rodents, ammonia from urine/manure"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6663 medium DET25,26/HIH1100","question":"Name 2 types of bars found on tack.","answer":"Stirrup bar, bars of saddle tree, bar mouthpiece"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6664 medium DET57","question":"What is the common name for the 4-in-hand knot that's tied the same as a knot on a man's tie & is used to secure a saddle in place when a buckle isn't used?","answer":"Cinch knot"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6665 medium DET40","question":"What is the term for a bit with a hinge in the middle of the mouthpiece?","answer":"Broken bit or jointed bit	 (do NOT accept curb or snaffle; both can have solid or broken mouthpieces)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6666 medium HIH1100-7","question":"To what part of the English bridle's headstall does the throatlatch attach?","answer":"Crownpiece"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6667 medium HIH1100-1","question":"Close contact & all purpose are both examples of what type of English saddle?","answer":"Forward seat or hunt seat"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6668 medium DET pg 202","question":"A pad with a cinchï¿½which may include stirrupsï¿½used for exercising the horse is called what?","answer":"Bareback pad, pad saddle, or exercise saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6669 medium HIH1100-10","question":"What is the difference between a bosal hackamore & a mechanical hackamore?","answer":"Bosal ï¿½ has a braided rawhide or rope noseband with a knot-like arrangement under the horse's jaw; 
Mechanical ï¿½ has metal shanks & a curb strap"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6670 medium DET85,89","question":"What is the main difference in the design of a D-ring & an egg butt snaffle? ","answer":"Shape of the rings"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6671 medium IDET 161, HIH 1100-9","question":"The Kimberwicke bit is considered a leverage bit.  How is it different from a typical leverage bit like a curb bit?","answer":"No shanks"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6673 medium HH31","question":"What is a Liverpool bit?","answer":"Curb bit commonly used for driving		 (additional info -- has several rein attachment slots)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6674 medium HH27","question":"Why would you use a bitting rig?","answer":"To teach a horse to flex at the poll"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6675 medium HIH1100-3","question":"How much room should there be on each side of the widest part of a rider's foot in an English stirrup?","answer":"1/4 inch"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6676 medium DET109","question":"What noseband is a cross between a cavesson and a 	figure eight noseband?","answer":"Flash noseband                              "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6677 medium HIH1100-1","question":"A saddle seat saddle is often referred to as a ï¿½cut backï¿½ saddle.  The head of the saddle is cut back to accommodate what characteristic conformation aspect of the breeds that are most often shown in the saddle seat division?                                         ","answer":"High-withers    (also accept anything that describes the high head and neck carriage)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6678 medium DET196","question":"What does the term open bridle describe?                        ","answer":"A bridle without blinders or blinkers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6679 medium HIH1100-1","question":"What is the main purpose of the close contact saddle?","answer":"Jumping                       "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"medium","number":"6680 medium HIH1100-10","question":"A bradoon & a curb are typically used with what type of bridle?		","answer":"Full or Weymouth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6681 hard DET67","question":"Where would you find a ï¿½stabilizerï¿½ or ï¿½roperï¿½sï¿½ bar?","answer":"On a bit, connecting the shanks where the rein loops are attached."},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6682 hard HIH1100-3","question":"You do the mathï¿½..There should be ï¿½ï¿½ of room on each side of the hunt seat riderï¿½s foot when itï¿½s in the stirrup.  The total width of the stirrup tread should be how much wider than the width of the boot?","answer":"ï¿½ inch   "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6683 hard HIH1100-3","question":"Define the term "saddle nail".","answer":"Rivet on the front side of the skirt near pommel on English saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6684 hard HIH1100-3","question":"What does an adult-size English saddle seat measure?","answer":"16 - 18 inches	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6685 hard HIH1100-3","question":"What does a youth-sized English saddle seat measure?","answer":"12 - 16 inches	 (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6686 hard HIH1100-1","question":"In English riding, what saddle is used to ride "on the flat" just behind the center of your horse?","answer":"Saddle seat       (also accept:  park, cut-back or Lane Fox)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6687 hard HIH1100-10","question":"What is the name of the soft, apple-flavored, rubber mouthpiece that's very gentle & non-allergenic?","answer":"Happy Mouth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6688 hard DET129","question":"What is the proper term for the steel or wooden arms that are fitted to the collar of a harness?","answer":"Hames"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6689 hard DET p. 172","question":"What is the term for the person who makes the metal parts of tack such as bits, curb chains, & stirrup irons?","answer":"Lorimer"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6690 hard HIH1100-12","question":"What does a breastplate have that a breast collar may not have?","answer":"Neck strap"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6691 hard HIH1100-10","question":"What equipment should always be treated as a means to an end, used only when needed & then only as long as needed?","answer":"Martingales & draw reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6692 hard HH30","question":"2 part question:  Which general type curb bit produces the most discomfort for the horse & why?","answer":"Jointed mouth ï¿½ it affects all the pressure points & creates a nutcracker action on bars & tongue"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6693 hard HIH1100-10","question":"What are the unique components of a Weymouth bridle?","answer":"Two bits   (snaffle/bridoon & curb/Weymouth) "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6694 hard HH28","question":"What is a heel knot?","answer":"Ball on bottom of bosal  "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6695 hard HH30","question":"Brace, roller, & a high port are all parts of what bit?","answer":"Spade bit"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6696 hard HH32,34","question":"What do we mean when we refer to the rigging of a saddle?","answer":"Location where cinch is attached to saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6697 hard TH658","question":"Which of the following types of Western saddle riggings would accommodate only one cinch ï¿½ centerfire, full, or 3/4?","answer":"Centerfire"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6698 hard HIH1100-12","question":"What is the purpose of an anti-sweat sheet?","answer":"To wick moisture away from horse's body after a heavy workout"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6699 hard BEG108-1","question":"What type of English saddle is specially designed with a flat seat, forward short flaps & no extra knee roll?","answer":"Close contact   "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6700 hard HIH1100-4","question":"Where on a Western saddle would you find the hobble strap?","answer":"At bottom of fender above the stirrup 	(additional info -- keeps the stirrup from falling off)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6701 hard HIH1100-16","question":"What is the use of a half sheet?","answer":"Used for warmth when exercising horses outdoors in cold weather"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6702 hard HIH1100-10","question":"2 part question:  On a Pelham bridle, which rein functions as the snaffle & which as the curb?","answer":"Upper rein is the snaffle & lower one is the curb"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6703 hard HIH1100-5","question":"What type of saddle am I describing?  This lightweight saddle gives the rider a straight leg position & a deep seat for security & balance.  The tall horn gives the rider something to grab onto during the turns.  The skirts are often rounded.","answer":"Barrel racing saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6704 hard HIH1100-10","question":"What is the name for the strap that holds the snaffle bit in a double bridle?","answer":"Bradoon carrier"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6705 hard HIH1100-11","question":"What type horse was the cut-back saddle developed for?","answer":"High withered OR horse with more front end action & high head carriage (example Saddlebred)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6706 hard HIH1100-4","question":"What type of saddle am I describing?  This saddle has high thigh rolls located near the front of the saddle which keeps the rider firmly in place.  It usually has no horn & is popular with trail riders","answer":"Australian, Outback, or Poley	 (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6707 hard HIH1100-2","question":"Where would you find the twist on an English saddle?","answer":"Top of saddle at junction of the seat & pommel"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6708 hard HIH1100-12/DET38","question":"How does an English breast collar differ from a Western breast collar?","answer":"English breast collar has a neck strap to help hold it up "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6709 hard HIH1100-6","question":"What is the biggest problem with foam saddle pads?","answer":"They don't breathe  (donï¿½t allow sweat to evaporate)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6710 hard HIH1100-2","question":"What part of an English saddle rests on the horse's back?","answer":"Panel"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6711 hard HIH1100-16","question":"What is the term for the type of sheet that's used during outdoor exercise in cold weather?  It runs from the withers to the hindquarters","answer":"Half sheet"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6712 hard HH27","question":"On an English double bridle, what does the lip strap do?","answer":"Positions the curb chain"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6713 hard DET13","question":"What is the name for a bit, used in conjunction with a halter, that has 3 small ringsï¿½2 for the cheek pieces & one for a lead rein?  It's used to help control horses that rear.","answer":"Anti-rearing bit or Chifney"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6714 hard DET95","question":"On an English saddle, what part is located between the panels?","answer":"Gullet"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6715 hard DET47","question":"On the Western saddle, what is the term for the outside back of the cantle?","answer":"Cantle drop or Cheyenne roll"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6716 hard HIH1100-1","question":"Why is a forward seat saddle versatile?","answer":"Allows rider to be in balance with horse whether riding on flat, jumping, or doing a combination of flat riding & jumping"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6717 hard DET120","question":"Which martingale combines the action of both the snaffle rein & a draw rein?","answer":"German martingale"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6718 hard HIH1100-1","question":"What English girth style reduces chaffing of your horse's elbows?","answer":"Elastic & contour leather"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6719 hard DET14,77,81,123,207","question":"Referring to tack, what is being described by the following terms:  pelican, gourd, appleton, dinner plate & dally?","answer":"Types of saddle horns"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6720 hard DET54","question":"Explain the difference between batwing & shotgun chaps.","answer":"Batwing ï¿½ flared;   shotgun ï¿½ fit close to leg "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6721 hard HIH1100-10","question":"Although it is described as German silver, a bit made from this material is not made from silver and is actually a combination of 3 different metals. Name one of the metals. ","answer":"Copper, nickel, & stainless steel"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6722 hard HIH1100-3","question":"What fitting is being described by the terms string, elasticï¿½end, contour, threefold, & balding?","answer":"Girths"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6723 hard HIH1100-6","question":"Name one advantage of web reins.","answer":"Won't stretch, rot, or crack; offer more grip than plain leather"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"hard","number":"6725 hard DET231","question":"What type of reins are fastened to the girth & then passed through the rings of the snaffle bit into the rider's hands?","answer":"Draw reins"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6726 bonus HH34","question":"Name 3 things you should inspect leather for (especially when buying used tack).","answer":"Cracked, stiff or dried out, thin or worn, broken stitching, stretched out or enlarged holes 
(accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6727 bonus HIH1100-1","question":"Name 3 types of Western saddles.","answer":"Pleasure/Trail, Endurance, Reining, Roping, Cutting, Barrel Racing, Equitation, Gymkhana"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6728 bonus HH25","question":"Name 3 parts of an English saddle that are NOT found on a Western saddle.","answer":"Stirrup iron, stirrup bar, flap, sweat flap"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6729 bonus HH32","question":"Name 3 types of rigging & one of their uses.","answer":"Full double ï¿½ roping, packing 
7/8 or 3/4 double ï¿½ reining, cutting, pleasure;
In skirtï¿½pleasure, trail;
Centerfire--packing, bucking saddle"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6730 bonus HIH1100-1","question":"What are the 3 saddle types in the hunt or forward seat category?","answer":"All purpose, close contact, dressage"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6731 bonus HIH1100-10","question":"Name 3 different materials used to make bit mouthpieces.  ","answer":"Stainless steel, German silver, solid nickel, copper, aluminum, rubber, vulcanite, brass, leather, Happy Mouth, sweet iron"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6732 bonus HIH1100-16","question":"Name 3 different types of outwear for your horse.","answer":"Turnout blanket, turnout sheet, cooler, mesh sheet, stable blanket, stable sheet (also accept blanket, sheet, cooler, sleazie, hood) "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6733 bonus HIH1100-6","question":"Name 3 types of English reins.","answer":"Laced, plain, web, rubber"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6734 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"Name 3 areas to which a hackamore applies pressure.","answer":"Nose, chin, face, poll, jaw, cheeks"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6735 bonus HH33","question":"Name 3 things that could happen when a poor fitting saddle is used on a horse.","answer":"Sores, rolls on mounting/dismounting, slips/slides during use, horse bucking, horse head tossing, cinchiness"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6736 bonus HIH1100-2,4","question":"Name the 3 parts of an English saddle & a Western saddle that are the same.","answer":"Pommel, cantle, skirt, seat"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6737 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"Name 3 areas where a bit or bridle applies pressure.  ","answer":"Corners of mouth, bars, tongue, roof of mouth, curb groove, nose, poll"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6738 bonus HIH1100","question":"Name 3 bits.","answer":"Weymouth, Pelham, Walking horse, snaffle, hackamore, Liverpool, bar, spade, Kimberwicke, roper curved cheek, half cheek snaffle, full cheek snaffle, Tom Thumb  (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6739 bonus HIH1100-3","question":"List 3 types of girths used in English riding.","answer":"String, elastic-end, contour leather, 3 fold leather, Balding, leather (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6740 bonus HIH1100-1","question":"Name 2 kinds of saddles that roughly fit under the heading of English saddles.","answer":"Racing & polo"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6741 bonus HH33","question":"Besides fitting a horse at the withers, name 3 conformation factors that contribute to saddle fit.","answer":"Length of back, slope of shoulder, muscling, spring of rib cage"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6742 bonus HIH1100-5","question":"Name 3 different materials that English saddle pads are made of.","answer":"Sheepskin, hair, foam, imitation sheepskin, felt, therapeutic"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6746 bonus HIH1100-6","question":"What are 2 events where you would commonly use rubber reins?","answer":"Racing, cross country/eventing, jumping, steeplechase"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6747 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"Describe the following Western headstalls:   split ear, slip ear, & conventional.","answer":"Split ear has a slit in the crownpiece for the ear; slip ear has a small loop added to crownpiece for the ear; conventional has a brow band"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6749 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"Leverage bits cause pressure to be applied to the poll & under the chin.  Tell what pieces of the bridle cause this pressure.","answer":"Poll ï¿½ crownpiece; 	under chinï¿½curb strap or chin strap "},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6750 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"Name 2 purposes of the port on a curb bit.","answer":"Relieves pressure on tongue & applies pressure to roof of mouth"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6751 bonus HH33","question":"Name 3 factors that might contribute to a saddle resting on the horse's withers instead of clearing them.","answer":"Fork of saddle too wide, saddle tree too wide, withers too high, withers too narrow, combination of these"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6752 bonus HIH1100-5","question":"Name 3 functions of a saddle pad.","answer":"Protect horse's back, absorb sweat, protect saddle, help saddle fit better, absorb shock"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6753 bonus HIH1100-3","question":"What are 3 criteria for selecting a saddle.","answer":"Must fit the horse, should fit the rider, should not interfere with performance or ability of horse, be appropriate for desired riding style"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6754 bonus HH29","question":"Name 3 factors affecting the severity of a bit.","answer":"Diameter of mouthpiece, type of mouthpiece, amount of leverage, position of horse's head (example - nose up or flexed at poll)"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6755 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"What are the 3 pressure points affected by a snaffle bit?","answer":"Corners of mouth, bars, tongue"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6756 bonus HIH1100-8","question":"Explain the differences between a snaffle bit, a curb bit, & a hackamore. ","answer":"Snaffle has no shanks (reins attach directly to rings on the mouthpiece ï¿½ no leverage)
Curb has shanks (that cause leverage)
Hackamore has no mouthpiece."},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6757 bonus HIH1100-5,6","question":"Name 3 materials used to make Western saddle pads","answer":"Wool, cotton, sheepskin, synthetic fibers"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6758 bonus HIH1100-1","question":"Give 3 names for the type of saddle used for saddle seat riding","answer":"Park, cut back, saddle seat, Lane Fox"},
{"category":"TACK & EQUIPMENT","level":"bonus","number":"6759 bonus HIH1100-1,5","question":"Name 3 types of saddles.","answer":"Western/stock, English, Australian, dressage, saddle seat, forward seat, racing, polo"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"1 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"What do you call the third set of incisors, those closest to the interdental space? ","answer":"Corners  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"2 easy BEG105/HS15 ","question":"What is the interdental space?  ","answer":"Gum space between incisors and premolars/molars "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"3 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"The second set of incisors is called what? ","answer":"Intermediates  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"4 easy CAHA48/HIH405-1/HS12 ","question":"Where in the mouth are the canine teeth located? ","answer":"Bars or interdental space 	(space between the incisors and the premolars/molars) "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"5 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"How can you estimate a horse's age?","answer":"By its teeth 		
(also accept specific info such as appearance, cups, wear, eruption, slant/angle, and Galvayneï¿½s groove)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"6 easy HH49 ","question":"If you looked in a horse's mouth and noticed that the top incisors were evenly worn off, what vice might you suspect this horse has? ","answer":"Cribbing  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"7 easy HS16/TH92 ","question":"Excluding wolf teeth, how many teeth does a mature female horse have? ","answer":"36 		(additional info:  12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"8 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"What are the first centrally located incisors called? ","answer":"Centrals  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"9 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"Define molars. ","answer":"Rear grinding teeth    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"10 easy HIH405-2 ","question":"Filing off the sharp edges of a horse's teeth is known as what? ","answer":"Floating  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"11 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"What teeth does a male horse have that a mare seldom has? ","answer":"Canine teeth    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"12 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"What is another name for the horse's rear grinding teeth? ","answer":"Molars  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"13 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"Which teeth are used for cutting grass? ","answer":"Incisors  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"14 easy HIH405-1240-1/HS16/CAHA48 ","question":"In horses, which type of teeth erupt only as permanent teeth? ","answer":"Molars, canines, wolf teeth		 (accept any)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"15 easy TH92-93/HS15 ","question":"Age of the horse can best be estimated by examining what things about their teeth? ","answer":"Wear and slant of incisors  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"16 easy HIH240-3/DET11 ","question":"What is the angle of incidence? ","answer":"Angle at which the upper and lower incisors meet    (as viewed from the side/ profile)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"17 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"Referring to teeth, what is another name for a ï¿½tushï¿½? ","answer":"Canine tooth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"18 easy HIH240-3/HS14 ","question":"What is the term for the profile (side) view of the angle formed where the upper and lower incisors meet? ","answer":"Angle of incidence or angle of bite 	(accept either)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"19 easy HIH240-2/TH92 ","question":"How many teeth does a yearling have? ","answer":"24 		(additional info 12 incisors and 12 premolars) "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"20 easy CAHA48/HS14 ","question":"What is the part of the tooth located between the crown and the root at the surface of the gums?","answer":"Neck  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"21 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"Which teeth can be examined for wear and slant to best estimate the age of a horse? ","answer":"Incisors  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"22 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"What is meant by the term "full mouth"? ","answer":"Horse has a complete set of permanent teeth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"23 easy BEG105 ","question":"What do you call the gum space between the incisors and the premolars? ","answer":"Interdental space or bars	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"24 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"The hollow spaces on the wearing surfaces of the incisors are called what? ","answer":"Cups  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"25 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"Teeth that appear in the interdental space on the male horse at 5 years of age, sometimes referred to as ï¿½tushesï¿½, are called what? ","answer":"Canine teeth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"26 easy HIH405-2 ","question":"Referring to teeth, what is floating? ","answer":"Filing of rough or irregular teeth to give a smoother grinding surface 	     (accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"27 easy HIH405-2 ","question":"Which jaw of the horse is wider? ","answer":"Upper jaw or maxilla		 (accept either)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"28 easy HIH405-2 ","question":"How often is it recommended to float teeth? ","answer":"Once yearly or as recommended by your vet  	(accept either)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"29 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"What do you call a horse whose biting surfaces of the upper and lower incisors are smooth? ","answer":"Smooth mouthed 		(additional info:  occurs at 10-12 years of age)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"30 easy HIH240-2 ","question":"What term refers to the amount of use seen on the biting surfaces of the incisors? ","answer":"Wear    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"31 easy HIH405-1/FCH396/TH92/DET180/INT205-2L ","question":"What is another name for a temporary or non-permanent tooth? ","answer":"Milk tooth, baby tooth, or deciduous tooth		 (accept any)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"32 easy INT205-2L/FCH396/TH92 ","question":"What is a milk tooth? ","answer":"Temporary tooth, baby tooth, or deciduous tooth		 (accept any)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"33 easy HS14 ","question":"How do you ask a horse to open its mouth? ","answer":"Put 1-2 fingers in the corner of his mouth (bars or interdental space) and apply pressure if needed"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"34 easy CAHA48/HS15 ","question":"The teeth just in front of the upper premolars are called what? ","answer":"Wolf teeth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"35 easy INT205-1 ","question":"What is the proper name for a horse's front teeth? ","answer":"Incisors  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"36 easy CAHA48/HS16 ","question":"Canine teeth are USUALLY NOT present in which sex of the horse?","answer":"Mare    (female)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"37 easy FCH400/HS14 ","question":"What is the term for a horse that has all of its permanent teeth? ","answer":"Full mouthed	 (additional info:  usually occurs around 5 years of age)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"38 easy HIH405-1 ","question":"Your horse eats with his head sideways or spills much of his grain from his mouth.  What should be checked? ","answer":"His teeth   "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"39 easy H2-34,35      HIH405-2","question":"Sharp protrusions that develop on the molars due to uneven wear are called what? ","answer":"Hooks or points  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"40 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"An adult male horse with no wolf teeth will usually have how many total teeth? ","answer":"40 		(additional info 12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars, 4 canines)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"41 easy HIH405-1 ","question":"A bit that hits the horse's wolf teeth may cause the horse to do what? ","answer":"Throw its head"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"42 easy HIH405-1 ","question":"In the horse's upper jaw, how many wolf teeth MAY be present? ","answer":"None, one, or two 		(accept any)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"43 easy HIH405-1 ","question":"In the horse's lower jaw, how many wolf teeth are NORMALLY found? ","answer":"None   "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"44 easy HIH415-1 ","question":"What is the best way to prevent dental problems in your horse? ","answer":"Routine care       (regular dental check-ups)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"45 easy HIH405-3 ","question":"What practice can prevent an unopposed tooth from becoming too tall or too long? ","answer":"Floating  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"46 easy HIH405-2 ","question":"Sharp edges on the teeth may cause damage to what part of the horse? ","answer":"Tongue and/or cheek  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"47 easy HIH420-3 ","question":"Large particles of food or un-chewed kernels of grain in the horse's manure may indicate a need for what? ","answer":"Floating the teeth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"48 easy HIH420-3 ","question":"Why would NOT taking care of a horse's mouth add to the expense of keeping a horse? ","answer":"More feed will be needed to maintain the horse in good condition"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"49 easy HIH240-1 ","question":"How many incisors does a foal have? ","answer":"12 (twelve)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"50 easy HIH405-1 ","question":"Sharp edges on the teeth cause the horse to do what? ","answer":"Chew food slowly, waste food, lose weight, rear, buck, toss head	 (accept any)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"51 easy HIH240-3/CAHA48 ","question":"What is the neck of the tooth? ","answer":"The part between the crown and the root       (the part located at the surface of the gum)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"52 easy HIH240-3 ","question":"What is the top part of a tooth, the part that protrudes above the gum? ","answer":"Crown  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"53 easy CAHA48/HIH240-3 ","question":"What is the crown of the tooth? ","answer":"The top of the tooth that protrudes above the gum  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"54 easy HIH405 ","question":"What are the 2 movements of the jaw? ","answer":"Vertical and lateral OR up and down and sideways"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"55 easy HIH1100-8/CAHA48 ","question":"The bit rests on what part of the horse's mouth? ","answer":"Bars or interdental space	 (accept either)    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"56 easy CAHA41 ","question":"All of the horse's lower teeth are located in which bone? ","answer":"Mandible    (lower jawbone)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"easy","number":"57 easy DET110","question":"What is the term for the rasp that is used to float a horseï¿½s teeth?","answer":"Float     (also accept dental float)              "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"58 medium INT205-2,CAHA48 ","question":"As the cups on the horseï¿½s incisors disappear, what starts to form first as a narrow elongated yellow mark? ","answer":"Dental star  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"59 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"How do you examine a horse's molar teeth? ","answer":"Grasp the tongue with right hand and the lower lip with left hand.  The mouth will open for examination of the teeth. "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"60 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"By what age are the temporary central incisors evident? ","answer":"By 8 days 		(accept any number between birth to 8 days of age)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"61 medium HIH240-3 ","question":"Most horses have a well-developed dovetail notch by what age? ","answer":"7 (seven)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"62 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"How do you examine a horse's incisor teeth? ","answer":"Hold the halter near the chin with one hand and roll the lips back with the other hand"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"63 medium HIH240-3 ","question":"Which teeth have a dental star? ","answer":"Permanent incisors  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"64 medium HIH240-2/405-1 ","question":"The foal's temporary premolar teeth appear by what age? ","answer":"2 weeks  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"65 medium HIH240-3 ","question":"2 part question:  What is ï¿½smooth mouthï¿½ and when does it occur? ","answer":"When the cups on the incisors have smoothed out; occurs at 10-12 years of age
(accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"66 medium TH93 ","question":"At what age do the cups start disappearing? ","answer":"6 (six)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"67 medium TH92 ","question":"What is the proper name for the foal's baby teeth? ","answer":"Deciduous or temporary teeth"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"68 medium HIH405-2 ","question":"What causes a long or tall tooth to occur in the horse's mouth? ","answer":"A missing tooth leaves an unopposed space that lets the tooth grow longer"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"69 medium CAHA48/HIH405-1 ","question":"On what side of a horse's tooth do points develop? ","answer":"Cheek side             (also accept outside of upper cheek teeth & inside of lower cheek)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"70 medium BEG105-2/HIH240-4 ","question":"At what age does Galvayne's Groove appear? ","answer":"10 (ten)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"71 medium TH93 ","question":"How does the shape of the chewing surfaces of the teeth change as the horse ages? ","answer":"Changes from oval to triangular   "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"72 medium CAHA48 ","question":"At the age of 20, what is the shape of a horse's permanent central incisor? ","answer":"Triangular  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"73 medium ES215 ","question":"2 part question:  How many premolars and how many molars does an adult horse have? ","answer":"12 premolars, 12 molars  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"74 medium HIH405-2 ","question":"Retention of deciduous teeth (caps) is most commonly seen in which teeth? ","answer":"Premolars  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"75 medium HIH405-1 	","question":"Which teeth are present at birth or erupt during the first week of life? ","answer":"Deciduous central incisors"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"76 medium INT205-1 ","question":"By what age does a horse generally have all teeth erupted and thus is considered full mouthed? ","answer":"5 (five)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"77 medium HIH240-2 ","question":"A young horse 8 months old would have 24 deciduous teeth.  What type of teeth does the young horse NOT have that it will develop later as permanent teeth? ","answer":"Molars          (also accept canines)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"78 medium TH93 ","question":"Under what living conditions would a horse's teeth make him appear older than he actually is? ","answer":"When kept on sandy, soil pastures          (Addtl  info: sand tends to wear down the teeth at a faster than normal rate)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"79 medium TH92 HIH405-1","question":"At what age do the permanent intermediate incisors erupt? ","answer":"3 ï¿½ to 4 years         (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"80 medium TH92/HIH405-1 ","question":"At what age do permanent corner incisors erupt? ","answer":"4 ï¿½ to 5 years         (accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"81 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"Name 2 types of teeth in the male horse that never occur as deciduous teeth.  They are only found as permanent teeth. ","answer":"Molars, wolf teeth, canine teeth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"82 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"How many incisors do horses have in each of their upper and lower jaws? ","answer":"6 in each jaw"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"83 medium HIH240-3 ","question":"Referring to teeth, what are cups? ","answer":"Hollow spaces on the wearing surfaces of the incisors"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"84 medium HIH240-2 ","question":"What are canine teeth? ","answer":"Teeth that appear in the interdental space of the male horse at 5 years of age
(additional info: some mares may also have small canines)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"85 medium HIH405-1/HS15 ","question":"When do the corner deciduous incisors erupt? ","answer":"By 8 months            (accept any number within 6-9 months)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"86 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"How many premolars does a foal of either sex have? ","answer":"12  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"87 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"At what age do the permanent centrals erupt? ","answer":"2 ï¿½ years  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"88 medium HIH405-1/TH92 ","question":"In determining the age of a horse by its teeth, you would know the horse was 4 ï¿½ to 5 years of age if it had just gained which permanent incisors? ","answer":"Corners         (corner incisors)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"89 medium FCH387 ","question":"On what teeth are dental stars first evident? ","answer":"Central incisors       (centrals)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"90 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"At what age does the last set of the horse's molars erupt? ","answer":"3 ï¿½ to 4 years           (accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"91 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"At what age does the first set of the horse's molars erupt? ","answer":"1 year  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"92 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"What can be caused by foreign bodies being wedged between the teeth or lodged in the tongue? ","answer":"Excessive salivation OR spillage of feed from mouth "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"93 medium HIH405-2 ","question":"Which teeth are continuously erupting and wearing? ","answer":"Cheek teeth      (premolars and molars)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"94 medium HIH405-3 ","question":"Name a cause of an infected tooth in the horse. ","answer":"Trapped or decomposing food, jaw fracture, periodontal disease"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"95 medium HIH405-4 	","question":"What percent of horses have some degree of overbite? ","answer":"30 - 60%             (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"96 medium HIH405-4 ","question":"Which teeth in middle aged and, in older male horses are often tall and/or sharp? ","answer":"Canines  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"97 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"At what age have all the milk teeth erupted? ","answer":"6 - 9 months          (accept any number within this range)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"98 medium HIH240-1 ","question":"If teeth are worn down, name one way you can estimate the age of the horse ","answer":"Eruption pattern, angle of bite/angle of incidence, shape of tooth, Galwayne's Groove, 
(cups would be hard to see if the teeth are worn down from other reasons)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"99 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"What can good dental care do for your horse? ","answer":"Extend life, improve health, improve performance       (accept any)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"100 medium FCH384 ","question":"Temporary teeth that fail to fall out when the permanent teeth erupt are called what? ","answer":"Caps    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"101 medium HIH405-1/HS15 ","question":"When do the intermediate deciduous incisors erupt? ","answer":"By 8 weeks          (accept any number within the 4-8 week range)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"102 medium HIH240-3 ","question":"In reference to teeth, how can you use cups to estimate age? ","answer":"Cups become smooth or wear down at different times
(additional info:  the upper ones are deeper than the lower ones so they don't wear evenly)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"103 medium HIH240-1/HS17 ","question":"Name 2 reasons why wolf teeth should be removed. ","answer":"Can cause pain and can cause interference with the bit    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"104 medium HIH405-1 ","question":"If wolf teeth are present, at what age do they erupt? ","answer":"5-6 months   (accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"medium","number":"105 medium HIH240-4		","question":"What would be the estimated age of a horse when the Galvayneï¿½s groove extends to the wearing surface of the corner upper incisor?","answer":"20              "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"106 hard HIH240-1 ","question":"Until what age can a horse be accurately identified by its teeth? ","answer":"10 - 14 years         (accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"107 hard HIH405-4 ","question":"What is a root canal in a horse called? ","answer":"Apicoectomy         (ay-pee-coh-ECT-o-mee)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"108 hard HIH240-2 ","question":"How are temporary teeth distinguished from permanent teeth? ","answer":"Temporary teeth are smaller, whiter, and have a distinct neck.  Permanent teeth are larger, stronger, and darker in color.  Younger horses will have distinct cups on their permanent incisors.  Older horses' incisors become more triangular.         (Donï¿½t need to give all)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"109 hard HIH240-2 ","question":"At what age are teeth very slanted, dental stars are larger, and teeth are triangular shaped? ","answer":"20 - 21 years 	(accept either)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"110 hard DET114 ","question":"What is the age of a horse that has all adult teeth present and Galwayne's Groove beginning to show at the gum edge of the upper corner incisors? ","answer":"9 ï¿½ 10 	(accept either)   "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"111 hard HS15/HIH240-3/INT205-1 ","question":"Explain the difference between full mouthed and smooth mouthed. ","answer":"Full mouthed means a horse has a complete set of permanent incisors     (occurs at 5); 
Smooth mouth means the cups have disappeared on both the upper and lower permanent incisors    (occurs at 10-12)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"112 hard DET48 ","question":"In reference to teeth, what are caps? ","answer":"Temporary teeth that fail to fall out when replaced by the permanent teeth"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"113 hard HIH240-4 ","question":"How can you use Galwayne's Groove to estimate age? ","answer":"Groove appears at the gum line at about 10 years of age, itï¿½s halfway down at age 15, all the way to wearing surface at 20, then begins to disappear and is gone by age 30   (addtl info ï¿½ appears on upper corner incisor)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"114 hard HIH240-3 ","question":"What is the angle of incidence in young horses? ","answer":"160 - 180 degrees 	(accept any number within this range)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"115 hard HIH240-1 ","question":"Under which age is a horse more closely identified by its teeth with its approximate age? ","answer":"10 (ten)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"116 hard HIH405-2 ","question":"2 part question:  Describe how the upper jaw teeth fit over the lower teeth and vice versa. ","answer":"Upper teeth extend over the lower ones on the outside; lower teeth extend on the inside of the upper ones"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"471 hard HIH405-2 ","question":"Describe the effect of teeth position on tooth wear. ","answer":"Position of the horse's teeth causes wear which creates sharp points on the outside of the upper teeth and on the inside of the lower ones"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"472 hard HIH240-3 ","question":"2 part question:  What is the cause of a dovetail notch and when does it usually appear? ","answer":"Surface of lower corners is not worn all the way to the back edges of the upper ones due to the angle of bite as the horse ages.  This leaves a notch on the upper corners at approximately 7 years of age.  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"473 hard HIH240-3  ","question":"What is Galwvayne's groove? ","answer":"A groove that appears at the gum edge of the upper corners at about 10 years of age"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"474 hard TH93 ","question":"By looking at a horseï¿½s teeth, how old is a horse whose Galvayneï¿½s groove is halfway down the upper corner incisor? ","answer":"15 (fifteen)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"475 hard HIH240-3 ","question":"The angle of incidence is approximately 160 - 180 degrees in young horses and becomes what angle in older ones? ","answer":"90 degrees  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"476 hard CAHA48 ","question":"At around 9 years of age, what marker on the grinding surface of the horse's tooth is revealed when the tooth is worn down to the pulp cavity? ","answer":"Dental star  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"477 hard HIH405-1 ","question":"Why are problems resulting from teeth discomfort common in horses between 2 ï¿½ to 4 ï¿½ years of age? ","answer":"All deciduous/baby incisors and premolars are shed and replaced with permanent teeth and 8 molars erupt and begin to wear during this time. 	(Accept any reasonable wording)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"478 hard HIH405-1 ","question":"Retention of which deciduous cheek teeth are more common? ","answer":"First 3 cheek teeth or premolars	 (accept either)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"479 hard HIH405-1 ","question":"Two year old horses might develop sharp points within 4-6 weeks of having their teeth floated.  Why?  ","answer":"Their deciduous premolars are still present and are softer than the permanent teeth"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"480 hard TH92 ","question":"In the dental formula, identify what the letters I, C, P, and M stand for.","answer":"Incisors, canines, premolars, molars     "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"481 hard HIH405-2 ","question":"What causes hooks on the horse's cheek teeth? ","answer":"If the teeth are out of position, the part of the tooth that is not in wear becomes longer or taller. 
(Also accept:  Upper teeth are slightly forward or towards the nose as compared to the lower ones.)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"482 hard HIH405-2 ","question":"In the horse's mouth, the upper cheek teeth are often positioned slightly forward, towards the nose, as compared to the lower ones.  What can this situation cause? ","answer":"Hooks 	(also accept long or tall teeth because the entire tooth is not in wear)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"483 hard HIH405-3 ","question":"Inflammation of the periodontium (the tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone) is called what? ","answer":"Periodontal disease  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"484 hard HIH405-3 ","question":"What is periodontal disease? ","answer":"Inflammation of the periodontium (the tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone) (also accept gum disease)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"485 hard HIH405-3 ","question":"What is the periodontium? ","answer":"The tissue that anchors the tooth to the bone    "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"486 hard TH92/CAHA49","question":"How old would a horse be that has the 1st and 2nd premolars 	in place?		 ","answer":"2 ï¿½ years old                "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"487 hard HIH405-2 ","question":"2 part question:  Describe how the upper jaw teeth fit over the lower teeth and vice versa. ","answer":"Upper teeth extend over the lower ones on the outside; lower teeth extend on the inside of the upper ones"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"hard","number":"488 hard HIH240-4 ","question":"What is ï¿½bishopingï¿½? ","answer":"The practice of trying to replace the cups on worn incisors to make the horse appear younger than its actual age OR altering the teeth to conceal the horse's age "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"489 bonus HIH240-1/HS15 		","question":"We know that a mature male horse has 40 teeth total.  How many of each type of teeth does he have? ","answer":"12 incisors, 12 premolars, 12 molars, and 4 canines"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"490 bonus HIH405-1 ","question":"At which age does the horse normally shed the following deciduous cheek teeth (premolars):   1st set, 2nd set, and 3rd set? ","answer":"1st setï¿½shortly after 2 ï¿½ years; 
2nd setï¿½before 3 years of age;
3rd setï¿½around 3 years 8 months"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"491 bonus HIH405, 240-1 ","question":"Name 3 factors that may affect the technique of aging a horse by its teeth and that may make the horse appear different than its actual age. ","answer":"Prolonged drought, parrot mouth, cribbing, grazing on sandy soil"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"492 bonus HS14	 		","question":"What are the 3 parts of a temporary tooth? ","answer":"Crown, neck, and root or fang"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"493 bonus TH920 ","question":"Timelineï¿½  The eruption and wear of the permanent teeth can be used to determine the age of a horse.  Organize the following four types of permanent teeth according to the age of eruption:  canines, 1st premolars (wolf teeth), 2nd molars, and 2nd set or intermediate incisors. ","answer":"1st premolars or wolf tooth (5-6 months);  
2nd molars (2 years);
2nd or intermediate incisors (3ï¿½ years);
canines (4-5 years)
(only need to give the correct order; do NOT need to give the age of eruption)"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"494 bonus HIH240-1/HS14 		","question":"There are incisors in each upper and lower jaw.  What are their names? ","answer":"Centrals, intermediates, and corners"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"495 bonus HIH405-1 		","question":"Name 3 signs that would indicate your horse needs to have his teeth checked. ","answer":"Slobbering, tilting head when chewing, difficulty chewing, dropping feed when eating, quidding or incomplete chewing, head tossing, bit chewing, tongue lolling/rolling, tail wringing, bucking, fussing with bit, refusing bit, weight loss 	 (accept any correct answer)  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"496 bonus HIH405-1 ","question":"In horses, the last 3 cheek teeth (molars) are present only as permanent teeth.  At what age do the molars erupt? ","answer":"1 year, 2 years, and 3 ï¿½ to 4 years  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"497 bonus HIH405-1 ","question":"There are 4 periods of tooth eruption and development by age.  Name 3. ","answer":"Birth ï¿½ 2 ï¿½; 2 ï¿½ ï¿½ 5; 5 ï¿½ 9; aged"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"498 bonus HIH405-1/HS15 		","question":"At what ages do the following permanent teeth erupt:  central, intermediate, and corner incisors? ","answer":"Centrals ï¿½ 2 ï¿½ years;   intermediates ï¿½ 3 ï¿½ years; corners ï¿½ 4 ï¿½ years  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"499 bonus HIH240-1/HS15 		","question":"Name 3 ways to estimate the age of a horse by its teeth.   ","answer":"Eruption pattern or occurrence of teeth; wear or disappearance of cups; slant or angle of incidence or bite; Galwayne's Groove; shape of the surface of the permanent teeth, dovetail notch, hooks "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"500 bonus HIH240-3 ","question":"In general, you can estimate a horse's age from 6 -11 years by the order in which the cups become smooth.  What is this order? ","answer":"Lower centrals, lower intermediates, lower corners, upper centrals, upper intermediates, upper corners"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"501 bonus HIH405-4 ","question":"Name 3 benefits of shortening and blunting the canine teeth. ","answer":"Easier insertion and removal of the bit, less chance of injury due to the horse catching a canine on an object, less chance of inflicting injury in fights, reduced risk of injury to people"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"502 bonus CAHA41","question":"The permanent upper & lower teeth are located in what 3 bones?","answer":"Maxilla, mandible & incisive bone         "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"503 bonus HIH405-3 ","question":"Give 3 signs that a horse has an infected tooth. ","answer":"Slow eating or chewing, progressive unthriftiness, quidding, shaking or tilting head, swelling of the face or jaw, nasal drainage or drainage tracks"},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"504 bonus HIH405-1 		","question":"Name 3 dental problems in horses. ","answer":"Retained baby teeth (caps), wolf teeth, hooks, points, malaligned teeth, infected teeth, long/tall teeth, long/tall canines, lost tooth, fractured/broken tooth  "},
{"category":"TEETH","level":"bonus","number":"505 bonus TH92/HS15		 ","question":"Give 3 other names for a foal's baby teeth. ","answer":"Temporary teeth, milk teeth, deciduous teeth"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6760 easy ADV301-1L/HIH1155-1 ","question":"Vehicles used to tow trailers must have a safe sturdy hitch.  The hitch should be attached to what part of your vehicle? ","answer":"Frame  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6761 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"What structure acts as a safety feature in that it will help prevent a horse from falling out of the trailer when the door is open? ","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain   "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6762 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"2 part question:  When would you commonly see a head bumper being used and why would one be used? ","answer":"During trailering or when leading a horse into barn with low ceilings or doorways; reasons:  tall horse, horse thatï¿½s a bad shipper, horse that tends to throw its head or rear during loading or unloading   "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6763 easy HIH1155 ","question":"When should you check the trailer hitch? ","answer":"Before leaving   (and at every stop)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6764 easy HIH1155-2 ","question":"How high should the ceiling of a horse trailer be? ","answer":"High enough to allow ample head room OR 10 inches higher than horse's head in a normal resting position  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6766 easy HIH1155-2 ","question":"When trailering your horse, what can you use on the floor to reduce concussion on your horse's legs? ","answer":"Rubber mats or shavings  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6767 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"When unloading a horse from a trailer, what should you do before you release the butt chain? ","answer":"Untie the horse  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6768 easy HIH1155-1 ","question":"When trailering horses, what is one of the most important things to check? ","answer":"The hitch  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6769 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"If you tie your horse in a trailer, what kind of knot should you use? ","answer":"Quick release (you could also use trailer ties with panic snaps)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6770 easy HIH1150-1 ","question":"Why should you NEVER undo the butt chain or bar before untying your horse? ","answer":"Horse might try to back out as soon as the trailer door is open"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6771 easy HIH1155-3 ","question":"Which type trailer is a favorite because of the ease of loading and unloading horses? ","answer":"Slant load  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6772 easy HIH1155-1 ","question":"Besides the hitch, what else is used to attach the trailer to the tow vehicle? ","answer":"Safety chains (also accept lights, brakes, stabilizer bars)  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6773 easy HIH1155-1 ","question":"What is the most important consideration when trailering a horse? ","answer":"Safety  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6774 easy HIH1150-2 ","question":"When trailering, some horses, like people, get sick from motion.  Name one thing you can do to prevent this.","answer":"Adjust the feeding schedule to avoid travelling when horse is full; feed smaller amounts more often if necessary; limit grain; give free choice hay; bran mash before travel; tube with oil"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6775 easy H3-31/BEG104 ","question":"When shipping one horse in a two horse straight load trailer, on which side should the horse be loaded? ","answer":"Left  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6777 easy HIH1155-1 ","question":"Which type trailer attaches to the truck bed? ","answer":"Gooseneck or 5th wheel (accept either)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6778 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"Leg wraps for shipping should extend from the knees and hocks downward past what part of the horse? ","answer":"Coronary band  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6779 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"What SPECIFIC areas of the horse's leg do shipping boots or wraps protect? ","answer":"From the knees and hocks downward past coronary band"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6780 easy HIH1155-3 ","question":"What part of a straight load trailer gives the horse something to brace on rather than the door? ","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain    (accept either)   "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6781 easy HIH1155-3 ","question":"Describe a slant load trailer. ","answer":"Horses ride side by side on a slant with dividers separating them"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6782 easy HIH1155-2 ","question":"How much room should there be on each side of a horse in a trailer stall? ","answer":"3 inches  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6783 easy HIH1155-3 ","question":"Which type of trailer is a safe and popular way to transport a mare and foal? ","answer":"Stock  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6784 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"Name a piece of tack that keeps a horse from injuring its head in a trailer. ","answer":"Head bumper  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6785 easy HIH1155-1 ","question":"What is one of the most common mistakes when teaching a horse to load in a trailer? ","answer":"Rushing   (not taking enough time)  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6786 easy HIH1150-3 ","question":"What GENERAL color trailers may cause profuse sweating or heat stroke in the summer? ","answer":"Dark  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6787 easy ADV301-2 ","question":"When trailering your horse long distances, it's recommended that you offer him water every 3-4 hours.  Since you can't carry enough water for the entire trip, how can you deal with the taste changes in the water? ","answer":"Use something to mask the taste (like lemonade, sports drinks/Gatorade, electrolyte solutions, soft drinks, Kool-Aid) (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6788 easy HIH1155-2 ","question":"How high above the normal resting position of your horse's head should the trailer ceiling be?","answer":"10 inches  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6791 easy HIH1155-1 ","question":"Why should you use safety chains on a horse trailer? ","answer":"To provide added safety (if the hitch comes loose, the truck and trailer will still be attached by the chains)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"easy","number":"6792 easy HIH1155-2","question":"Why should rubber mats be periodically removed from a horse trailer?","answer":"To check for rot or rust, to allow floors to dry, to prevent rot, to prevent corrosion of metal floors (only need to give one)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"medium","number":"6793 medium HIH1155-1 ","question":"How should gooseneck hitches be attached to the tow vehicle? ","answer":"To a ball in truck bed (also to frame underneath)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"medium","number":"6795 medium HIH1155-2 ","question":"If your horse is leaning against the divider in the horse trailer, ideally how many inches would there be between his other side and the trailer wall? ","answer":"6 inches   (should have 3 inches on each side when standing properly)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"medium","number":"6796 medium H3-31 ","question":"Ideally, what is the desirable rest to driving time in hours when trailering your horse? ","answer":"1 hour rest for every 3 hours driving  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"medium","number":"6797 medium HIHvarious ","question":"Besides a first aid kit, what is another important kit to have with you when travelling? ","answer":"Tool kit  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"medium","number":"6798 medium TH816 ","question":"In transporting horses, what can you do prevent trouble when hauling a mare and stallion together?","answer":"Rub Vicks Vapor Rub on their nostrils to prevent them from smelling each other (also accept keep them separated)"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"medium","number":"6799 medium HIH1150-3 ","question":"2 part question:  Name an advantage and a disadvantage of using a tail wrap during trailering. ","answer":"Advantage - keeps hair from rubbing on butt bar OR keeps tail clean; disadvantage - if put on too tight, may cut off circulation OR cause hair to fall out"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"hard","number":"6800 hard FCH407 ","question":"What is the ï¿½twenty-eight hour lawï¿½? ","answer":"Law in the U.S. that prohibits transporting livestock for a period of longer than 28 consecutive hours without unloading, feeding, watering and resting for at least 5 hours before resuming transportation."},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6801 bonus HIH1155-2 ","question":"What are the 3 types of braking systems for horse trailers? ","answer":"Hydraulic, electrical, impulse   "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6802 bonus ADV301 ","question":"Name 3 ways horses can ride in a horse trailer. ","answer":"Slant, head to head, head to tail, side by side, loose as in stock trailer    "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6803 bonus INT201 ","question":"Give 4 features of a horse trailer that provide added safety for the horse ","answer":"Butt bar or butt chain, chest or wall padding, screened windows, rubber mats, quick release ties (accept any reasonable answers) "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6804 bonus HIH1150-3 ","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment used to protect your horse when trailering. ","answer":"Leg wraps, shipping boots, tail wrap, head bumper, blanket, hock pads, knee pads, hobbles, bell boots "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6805 bonus HIH1155-2 ","question":"Name 3 things you should check on your trailer regularly. ","answer":"Hitch, lights, brakes, safety chains, floor boards, doors, tire wear, tire inflation, wheel bearings, no sharp projections (accept any reasonable answer)  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6806 bonus TH816                  ","question":"What 4 connections on your trailer should you always double check? ","answer":"Hitch, lights, brakes, safety chains  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6807 bonus TH816 ","question":"Name 3 driving practices you should follow when pulling a trailer.   ","answer":"Start and stop slowly, make turns slowly, drive defensively, check hitch, make sure doors are closed (accept any reasonable answer)   "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6808 bonus HIH1155-1 ","question":"Name 3 factors you should consider when choosing a vehicle to pull a trailer. ","answer":"Truck size, engine size, electrical system, single or double axle, ball size, type of hitch, tire size, braking system, towing capacity, cooling system, type/weight/length of trailer, weight capacity of truck, cost   "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6809 bonus HIH1155-3 ","question":"Give 3 advantages of a slant load trailer. ","answer":"Horses seem to ride easier, horses are more stable during turns, horses encounter less stress "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6810 bonus BEG101 ","question":"Name 3 areas you should measure on your horse in order to determine if the trailer stall space is adequate. ","answer":"Resting head height, width from stifle to stifle, length from chest to tail, total length from head to tail"},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6811 bonus HIH1150-2 ","question":"Name 3 documents you should carry with you when you travel across state or border lines with your horse. ","answer":"Current health certificate, proof of ownership, Coggins test, brand inspection, other documents required by your destination or border crossing  "},
{"category":"TRAILERING","level":"bonus","number":"6812 bonus HIH1155-2 ","question":"Name 3 types of horse trailers. ","answer":"Slant, stock, straight load, in-line, horse van, gooseneck "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6813 easy HIH851-4 ","question":"Name 2 things to do when warming up your horse. ","answer":"Walk, trot, lateral flexion, vertical flexion  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6814 easy HIH1240-3/TH665/ADV320-2L ","question":"What type of ï¿½reinforcementï¿½ is reward training? ","answer":"Positive  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6815 easy HH39/TH672 ","question":"When training a young foal to halter, why should you have short lessons repeated often? ","answer":"Young foals have short attention spans OR a limited capacity to absorb new things"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6816 easy HH41/H5-31 ","question":"When first teaching a horse to neck rein, why would you need to use 2 hands? ","answer":"One to pull (direct rein) and one to push (bearing rein)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6817 easy HH39 ","question":"How much time should a young foal be worked with each day? ","answer":"30 minutes or half hour  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6818 easy HIH851-9/FCH376 ","question":"How should you end each training session? ","answer":"On a positive note OR with a cool-down period    "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6819 easy H4-23/FCH395 ","question":"What is the procedure in which the horse travels around the handler in a large circle on a longe line? ","answer":"Longeing  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6848 easy H5-34 ","question":"What is a finished horse? ","answer":"One that's completely trained  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6849 easy HH40/FCH391 ","question":"What is a green horse? ","answer":"One with little training    "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6853 easy HIH950-1 ","question":"Using a rump rope can help teach a foal to do what? ","answer":"Lead  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6855 easy HH35 ","question":"Name 2 parts of a fitness program. ","answer":"Diet/nutrition and exercise "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6856 easy H4-25 ","question":"When longeing, where do you step to signal a horse to stop? ","answer":"Step forward   (towards the shoulder)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6857 easy HS7 ","question":"Why is the horseï¿½s power of association useful in training? ","answer":"They will try to do as asked to earn a reward or to avoid a punishment  (accept any reasonable wording) "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6858 easy H5-34 ","question":"The process of building up the horse's cardiovascular system, tendons, and ligaments is called what? ","answer":"Conditioning  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6859 easy HIH851-9 ","question":"How should a workout conclude? ","answer":"With a cool-down period OR light work that will gradually bring horse back to resting status (also accept on a positive note)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6860 easy HIH851-1 ","question":"What provides a good monitor of how horses respond to exercise? ","answer":"Heart rate or pulse (accept either)  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6861 easy TH672/HH39 ","question":"In training, how does a foal learn? ","answer":"By repetition  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6862 easy HIH950-4 ","question":"What is a tail rope? ","answer":"Cotton rope that's wrapped around foal's rear quarters to aid in teaching it to lead (rump rope) OR rope tied to the tail of an animal to get the animal to its feet or to restrain the tail"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6863 easy HH41 ","question":"What is the purpose of a warm-up? ","answer":"Loosen up horse's muscles"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6864 easy HIHvarious ","question":"Name 3 things that you should teach a foal. ","answer":"To lead, to be groomed, to be clipped, to have feet worked with, to load in the trailer (accept any reasonable answers)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6865 easy HIH851-9 ","question":"Once a horse becomes conditioned or fit, what is one of the biggest challenges for the trainer? ","answer":"Maintaining fitness  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6866 easy HIH851-9 ","question":"Approximately how long will a horse maintain CARDIOVASCULAR fitness after beginning a layoff? ","answer":"6 - 8 weeks (accept any number within this range) (additional info:  musculoskeletal fitness declines faster)  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6867 easy HIH851-1 ","question":"What is the result of overtraining for a specific event? ","answer":"Horse gets sour OR horse doesn't want to perform"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6868 easy DET125/H4-23 ","question":"What is ground training? ","answer":"Working the horse from the ground"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"easy","number":"6869 easy HH47 ","question":"Using a sack, saddle blanket, or tarp as part of gentling and training a colt is called what? ","answer":"Sacking out       "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6870 medium TH53/DET198","question":"What is the name given to a horse that can't be broken?","answer":"ï¿½Outlawï¿½"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6872 medium TH664/HIH1240/ADV320-2L ","question":"Give the common term for positive reinforcement. ","answer":"Reward Training  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6873 medium TH665 ","question":"What is the term used when a horse runs or bolts from an aversive stimulus? ","answer":"Escape  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6874 medium HIH21 ","question":"Explain the general steps youï¿½d use when teaching your horse to respond cues. ","answer":"Give your horse a cue, if he responds to the cue praise him and release the pressure; if he doesnï¿½t respond, give a stronger cue; end training sessions on positive notes; repeat process so the horse learns by repetition (accept any reasonable wording)     "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6875 medium TH663 ","question":"In training, communication with the horse seems to be through what 2 senses of the animal? ","answer":"Touch and hearing  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6876 medium DET273 ","question":"Teaching the horse what actions are expected in response to the handler's cues is called what? ","answer":"Training  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6877 medium TH668 ","question":"What is the ï¿½acquisition periodï¿½ of training? ","answer":"When the horse is learning a task   "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6878 medium HS7 ","question":"Define ï¿½power of associationï¿½.","answer":"The ability to link an action and a reaction OR the ability to link a stimulus and a response (accept any reasonable wording)  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6879 medium HIH1100-10 ","question":"Why is a hackamore used to start young horses in training? ","answer":"Provides control, but doesnï¿½t injure the mouth"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6880 medium HIH181D-1 ","question":"What system of training horses has its roots in classical Greek horsemanship and became recognized during the Renaissance when the great European riding masters developed it? ","answer":"Dressage  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6881 medium HIH1220 ","question":"All of the horse's physiological senses are important in training.  What is considered to be the most important of these senses for responding to training cues? ","answer":"Touch  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6882 medium HIH250-2 ","question":"When training horses, why should your cues be consistent? ","answer":"So you donï¿½t confuse the horse OR so heï¿½ll understand what is being asked"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6883 medium TH661 ","question":"What do you call a stimulus that naturally causes a response? ","answer":"train  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6884 medium HIH525-2 ","question":"What term is used to describe the process of desensitization of the foal to the farrier and to the routine handling and examination of the feet? ","answer":"Imprint training  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6885 medium TH661/HIH1240-1 ","question":"What do you call a response that's learned through practice? ","answer":"Conditioned response  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6886 medium HIH850-4 ","question":"The study of movement is called what? ","answer":"Biomechanics or kinesiology    (accept either)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"medium","number":"6887 medium FCH206","question":"How quickly a horseï¿½s heart rate decreases & returns to their resting heart rate is an indication of what?","answer":"Fitness of the horse   (accept any answer that indicates this)            "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6888 hard HIH850-1 ","question":"In the horse's muscles, the anaerobic breakdown of glucose during hard exercise is performed in the absence of adequate levels of what specific element? ","answer":"Oxygen  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6889 hard HIH755-1 ","question":"What frequently determines how a horse performs in extended competitions? ","answer":"How quickly it fatigues  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6890 hard TH413 ","question":"What term classifies the following devices:  knee strap, side sling, casting harness, nose twitch, hobbles, and breeding chute? ","answer":"Restraints  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6891 hard HIH1240-6 ","question":"In training terms, what does the term "trial" mean? ","answer":"Practice   "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6892 hard HIH851-8 -8 ","question":"In some facets of the horse industry, exercise is used for purposes other than improving a horseï¿½s endurance, speed, or athletic potential.  The main goal in fitting halter horses is what? ","answer":"To maximize muscular development OR to improve body tone "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6893 hard HIH851-7 ","question":"Proper use of what in the horse's diet actually increases the time before fatigue sets in during exercise or conditioning? ","answer":"Fat   "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6894 hard FCH203 ","question":"When referring to training, what does ï¿½LSDï¿½ mean? ","answer":"Long, slow distance   (conditioning program of increasing distance over an extended time)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6895 hard FCH389 ","question":"What does the term "fartlek" mean? ","answer":"Alternating periods of slow and fast work (additional info:  a type of training method that comes from the Swedish word meaning "speed play")  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6896 hard HIH851-6 ","question":"Overexertion of a muscle without adequate conditioning can lead to the depletion of what in the muscles?  ","answer":"Glycogen  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6897 hard HIH1220-1 ","question":"What is the difference between conditioned and unconditioned stimuli in horses? ","answer":"Conditioned - stimulus that causes a response after it's been learned through practice; unconditioned - stimulus that naturally causes a response with no practice"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6898 hard TH103 ","question":"How will training for short, intense performances change a horseï¿½s muscle physiology? ","answer":"Increases muscle mass and strength"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6899 hard HIH851-9 ","question":"After performing strenuous exercise, a cool down period is suggested to remove what by-product of metabolism from the muscles? ","answer":"Lactic acid  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6900 hard HIH851-9, 895-1 ","question":"A cool down period is essential after vigorous exercise to allow your horse to eliminate any accumulated lactic acid.  What will be the consequence for the next 24 - 48 hours if you do not do this? ","answer":"Sore muscles  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6901 hard HIH895-1 ","question":"Define aerobic. ","answer":"Breakdown of energy sources in the presence of oxygen  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6902 hard HIH895-1 ","question":"Define anaerobic. ","answer":"Breakdown of energy sources in the absence of oxygen  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6903 hard ADV320-1L ","question":"In reference to training, what is the correct term for the acts or movements a horse makes when given cues or stimuli? ","answer":"Responses  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6904 hard HIH895-1 ","question":"What is ï¿½anaerobic thresholdï¿½? ","answer":"Point where the body starts breaking down energy in the absence of oxygen   "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6905 hard HIH895-1			","question":"Sprinting & galloping can produce an oxygen deficit within skeletal muscles & result in what type of metabolism?","answer":"Anaerobic             "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6906 hard INT220  HIH1240-3 ","question":"In reference to trainingï¿½ punishment, escape, and avoidance are similar in what way? ","answer":"They all involve aversive (negative) stimuli "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6907 hard HIH1240-3/DET189, 218 ","question":"What is the difference between positive and negative reinforcement? ","answer":"Positive ï¿½ animal gets a reward for a correct behavior; negative ï¿½ animal does the right thing to avoid a negative stimulus    "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6908 hard TH669 ","question":"A schedule of reinforcement where not every response is reinforced is called what? ","answer":"Intermittent  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6909 hard TH669 ","question":"When cues are presented without reinforcement, a learned response will gradually diminish to the pre-training level.  What is this called? ","answer":"Extinction  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6910 hard TH665 ","question":"What is the aim of punishment? ","answer":"To weaken or eliminate an undesirable behavior"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"hard","number":"6911 hard DET154  ","question":"What type of activity is being described?  This type of conditioning increases both speed and endurance. The program improves respiration, circulation, and removal of waste products. The horse is alternately subjected to periods of exercise and periods of rest.  ","answer":"Interval training          "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6912 bonus TH664 ","question":"Name 3 types of rewards that can be used in training horses. ","answer":"Food, praise, stroking/petting, removal of pressure, pain or discomfort, discontinuing work, letting horse relax   "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6913 bonus HIH851-6 ","question":"Recovery heart rate can be helpful in determining fitness.  What are the 2 things you should be looking for?","answer":"Speed of recovery; how low the heart rate falls in a specific recovery time"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6914 bonus HIH851-3 ","question":"Name 3 causes of an elevated RESTING heart rate. ","answer":"Fear, stress, pain, illness  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6915 bonus HIH851-1 ","question":"Successful conditioning of the equine athlete is dependent on several factors.  Name 3. ","answer":"Genetics, training, age, soundness, feeding (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6916 bonus HIH1240-7 ","question":"Name 3 factors that are fundamental to the psychology of horse training. ","answer":"Stimuli or cues, responses, reinforcements  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6917 bonus TH/HH/HIHvarious ","question":"Name 3 methods of restraining a horse. ","answer":"Tying, chute, hobbles, high line, picket line, blindfolding, twitch, lifting foot, holding ear or tail (accept any reasonable answer)"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6918 bonus H4-25 ","question":"What 3 things can the handler do to lessen fear and excitement in nervous horses? ","answer":"Have a calm attitude, use a soft voice, use slow, easy movements "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6919 bonus H4-25 ","question":"What are the 4 voice commands you use when longeing? ","answer":"Walk, trot, canter, whoa  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6920 bonus H4-25 ","question":"Name 3 pieces of equipment you need to longe a horse. ","answer":"Halter or longeing cavesson, whip, longe line"},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6921 bonus H4-25 ","question":"What are 2 purposes of longeing? ","answer":"Letting your horse work off steam, training young horse, teaching horse to respect you  "},
{"category":"TRAINING","level":"bonus","number":"6924 bonus HIH851-3 ","question":"Prior to a work or exercise period, name 3 ways you can evaluate the fitness and soundness of your horse for training. ","answer":"Heart rate, temperature, respiratory rate, capillary refill time, visual observation at walk or trot, soreness or sensitivity of back or loin noted while grooming, soreness or lameness when flexion testing, soreness or lameness during warm-up ride  "},
 ]
}
